<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.679075+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474025</id><title>Integrated cytometry with machine learning applied to high-content imaging of human kidney tissue for in-situ cell classification and neighborhood analysis (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.679723+00:00</updated><author><name>Seth Winfree</name></author><author><name>Andrew T McNutt</name></author><author><name>Suraj Khochare</name></author><author><name>Tyler J Borgard</name></author><author><name>Daria Barwinska</name></author><author><name>Angela R Sabo</name></author><author><name>Michael J Ferkowicz</name></author><author><name>James C Williams</name></author><author><name>James E Lingeman</name></author><author><name>Connor J Gulbronson</name></author><author><name>Katherine J Kelly</name></author><author><name>Timothy A Sutton</name></author><author><name>Pierre C Dagher</name></author><author><name>Michael T Eadon</name></author><author><name>Kenneth W Dunn</name></author><author><name>Tarek M El-Achkar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human kidney is a complex organ with various cell types that are intricately organized to perform key physiological functions and maintain homeostasis. New imaging modalities such as mesoscale and highly multiplexed fluorescence microscopy are increasingly applied to human kidney tissue to create single cell resolution datasets that are both spatially large and multi-dimensional. These single cell resolution high-content imaging datasets have a great potential to uncover the complex spatial organization and cellular make-up of the human kidney. Tissue cytometry is a novel approach used for quantitative analysis of imaging data, but the scale and complexity of such datasets pose unique challenges for processing and analysis. We have developed the Volumetric Tissue Exploration and Analysis (VTEA) software, a unique tool that integrates image processing, segmentation and interactive cytometry analysis into a single framework on desktop computers. Supported by an extensible and open-source framework, VTEA's integrated pipeline now includes enhanced analytical tools, such as machine learning, data visualization, and neighborhood analyses for hyperdimensional large-scale imaging datasets. These novel capabilities enable the analysis of mesoscale two and three-dimensional multiplexed human kidney imaging datasets (such as CODEX and 3D confocal multiplexed fluorescence imaging). We demonstrate the utility of this approach in identifying cell subtypes in the kidney based on labels, spatial association and their microenvironment or neighborhood membership. VTEA provides integrated and intuitive approach to decipher the cellular and spatial complexity of the human kidney and complement other transcriptomics and epigenetic efforts to define the landscape of kidney cell types.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474025" rel="alternate" title="Integrated cytometry with machine learning applied to high-content imaging of human kidney tissue for in-situ cell classification and neighborhood analysis (10 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474488</id><title>Structural insights into the ion selectivity of the MgtE channel for Mg2+ over Ca2+ (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.680349+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinyu Teng</name></author><author><name>Danqi Sheng</name></author><author><name>Jin Wang</name></author><author><name>Ye Yu</name></author><author><name>Motoyuki Hattori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MgtE is a Mg2+-selective ion channel whose orthologs are widely distributed from prokaryotes to eukaryotes, including humans, and play an important role in the maintenance of cellular Mg2+ homeostasis. Previous functional analyses showed that MgtE transports divalent cations with high selectivity for Mg2+ over Ca2+. Whereas the high-resolution structure determination of the MgtE transmembrane (TM) domain in complex with Mg2+ ions revealed a Mg2+ recognition mechanism of MgtE, the previous Ca2+-bound structure of the MgtE TM domain was determined only at moderate resolution (3.2 angstrom resolution), which was insufficient to visualize the water molecules coordinated to Ca2+ ions. Thus, the structural basis of the ion selectivity of MgtE for Mg2+ over Ca2+ has remained unclear. Here, we showed that the metal-binding site of the MgtE TM domain binds to Mg2+ ~500-fold more strongly than Ca2+. We then determined the crystal structure of the MgtE TM domain in complex with Ca2+ ions at a higher resolution (2.5 angstrom resolution), allowing us to reveal hexahydrated Ca2+, which is similarly observed in the previously determined Mg2+-bound structure but with extended metal-oxygen bond lengths. Our structural, biochemical, and computational analyses provide mechanistic insights into the ion selectivity of MgtE for Mg2+ over Ca2+.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474488" rel="alternate" title="Structural insights into the ion selectivity of the MgtE channel for Mg2+ over Ca2+ (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474400</id><title>Extreme value analysis of intracellular cargo transport by motor proteins (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.680838+00:00</updated><author><name>Takuma Naoi</name></author><author><name>Yuki Kagawa</name></author><author><name>Kimiko Nagino</name></author><author><name>Shinsuke Niwa</name></author><author><name>Kumiko Hayashi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the long axon of a neuron, cargo transport between the cell body and terminal synaptic region are mainly supported by the motor proteins kinesin and dynein, which are nano-sized drivers. Synaptic materials packed as cargos are anterogradely transported to the synaptic region by kinesin, whereas materials accumulated at the axon terminals are returned to the cell body by dynein. Extreme value analysis, typically used for disaster prevention in our society, was applied to analyze the velocity of kinesin and dynein nanosized drivers to disclose their physical properties in living cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474400" rel="alternate" title="Extreme value analysis of intracellular cargo transport by motor proteins (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474482</id><title>Rheology of crossbridge ensembles (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.681354+00:00</updated><author><name>Khoi D Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Madhusudhan Venkadesan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How skeletal muscle responds to mechanical perturbations, its rheology, is important for animal movement control. The molecular machinery of myosin II-actin crossbridge cycling is a crucial part of muscle's rheological properties, and multiple models have been proposed for this mechanochemical process. But current understanding of the scale-connection from individual molecular motors to ensemble rheology is limited. Here we present computational and mathematical analyses of several different hypotheses of crossbridge dynamics, from 2-state to 5-state myosin II motor models, and show that an ensemble of actomyosin crossbridges exhibits surprisingly simple rheological behavior in all cases. The ensemble rheology is captured by a sum of at most three linear viscoelastic sub-processes, and as few as one for some crossbridge models. This simplification lends itself to computationally efficient phenomenological muscle models with experimentally measurable parameters, while still remaining grounded in crossbridge theory. However, the collapse of the ensemble behavior to few linear sub-processes identifies major limitations of crossbridge models that cannot be resolved by adding complexity to the crossbridge cycle and point to the roles of inter-crossbridge interactions and non-crossbridge elements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474482" rel="alternate" title="Rheology of crossbridge ensembles (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474479</id><title>Equivalence of the Transition Heat Capacities of Proteins and DNA (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.681718+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew W Eskew</name></author><author><name>Albert S Benight</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It has been reported for many globular proteins that the native heat capacity at 25°C, per gram, is the same. This has been interpreted to indicate that heat capacity is a fundamental property of native proteins that provides important information on molecular structure and stability. Heat capacities for both proteins and DNA has been suggested to be related to universal effects of hydration/solvation on native structures. Here we report on results from thermal denaturation analysis of two well-known proteins, human serum albumin and lysozyme, and a short DNA hairpin. The transition heat capacities at the Tm for the three molecules were quantitatively evaluated by differential scanning calorimetry. When normalized per gram rather than per mol the transition heat capacities were found to be precisely equivalent. This observation for the transition heat capacities of the proteins is consistent with previous reports. However, an identical transition heat capacity for DNA has not been reported and was unexpected. Further analysis of the collected data suggested a mass dependence of hydration effects on thermal denaturation that is preserved at the individual protein amino acid and DNA base levels. Equivalence of transition heat capacities suggests the possibility of a universal role of hydration effects on the thermal stability of both proteins and DNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474479" rel="alternate" title="Equivalence of the Transition Heat Capacities of Proteins and DNA (4 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474515</id><title>Exercise and the brain: a mechanical model for pulsation on flow of cerebrospinal fluid (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.681962+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael George Hale</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Ainsley Coles</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Exchange of molecules between cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and brain cells contributes to brain function and protection from dementia, but the route by which CSF is brought close enough to the neural tissue to be exchanged by extracellular diffusion is not clear. Exogenous molecules injected into CSF are carried along channels outside arteries and reach the basement lamina that surrounds the dense capillary network.  Transport of solutes by diffusion along the basement lamina, a gel of macromolcules about 100 nm thick, would be too slow; bulk flow in a static geometry would require unphysiologically high pressures. However, it is known that the pulsation of blood aids transport of CSF, and we hypothesized that this is because the pulsation intermittently squeezes the pericapillary lamina. In a primitive mimicry, we have tested whether intermittent squeezing increases flow through an agar gel. In all but one of 216 tests, pulsation caused a reversible increase, sometimes by a factor of 100 or more. The enhancement was greatest for frequencies 5-11 Hz  and, over the tested range of pressure heads (20 - 50 cmH2O), was greatest for the lowest pressure. The results suggest one reason why exercise slows the aging of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474515" rel="alternate" title="Exercise and the brain: a mechanical model for pulsation on flow of cerebrospinal fluid (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>