<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular physiology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.969807+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/physiology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467739</id><title>Transcription modulates chromatin dynamics and locus configuration sampling (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.970210+00:00</updated><author><name>Giada Forte</name></author><author><name>Adam Buckle</name></author><author><name>Shelagh Boyle</name></author><author><name>Davide Marenduzzo</name></author><author><name>Nick Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Chris A. Brackley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In living cells the 3D structure of gene loci is dynamic, but this is not revealed by 3C and FISH experiments in fixed samples, leaving a significant gap in our understanding. To overcome these limitations we applied the “highly predictive heteromorphic polymer” (HiP-HoP) model, validated by experiments, to determine chromatin fibre mobility at the &lt;italic&gt;Pax6&lt;/italic&gt; locus in three mouse cell lines with different transcription states. While transcriptional activity minimally affects the movement of 40 kbp regions, we observed that the motion of smaller 1 kbp regions depends strongly on local disruption to chromatin fibre structure marked by H3K27 acetylation. This also significantly influenced locus configuration dynamics by modulating promoter-enhancer loops associated with protein bridging. Importantly these simulations indicate that chromatin dynamics are sufficiently fast to sample all possible conformations of loci within minutes, generating wide dynamic variability of gene loci structure within single cells. Experiments inhibiting transcription change chromatin fibre structure subtly, yet we predict they should substantially affect mobility. This combination of simulation and experimental validation provide a novel insight and mechanistic model to explain how transcriptional activity influences chromatin structure and gene dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467739" rel="alternate" title="Transcription modulates chromatin dynamics and locus configuration sampling (23 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467973</id><title>Effective Cell Membrane Tension is Independent of Substrate Stiffness (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.970484+00:00</updated><author><name>Eva Kreysing</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Mc Hugh</name></author><author><name>Sarah K. Foster</name></author><author><name>Kurt Andresen</name></author><author><name>Ryan D. Greenhalgh</name></author><author><name>Eva K. Pillai</name></author><author><name>Andrea Dimitracopoulos</name></author><author><name>Ulrich F. Keyser</name></author><author><name>Kristian Franze</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most animal cells are surrounded by a cell membrane and an underlying actomyosin cortex. Both structures are linked with each other, and they are under tension. Membrane tension and cortical tension both influence many cellular processes, including cell migration, division, and endocytosis. However, while actomyosin tension is regulated by substrate stiffness, how membrane tension responds to mechanical substrate properties is currently poorly understood. Here, we probed the effective membrane tension of neurons and fibroblasts cultured on glass and polyacrylamide substrates of varying stiffness using optical tweezers. In contrast to actomyosin-based traction forces, both peak forces and steady state tether forces of cells cultured on hydrogels were independent of substrate stiffness and did not change after blocking myosin II activity using blebbistatin, indicating that tether and traction forces are not directly linked with each other. Peak forces on hydrogels were about twice as high in fibroblasts if compared to neurons, indicating stronger membrane-cortex adhesion in fibroblasts. Finally, tether forces were generally higher in cells cultured on hydrogels compared to cells cultured on glass, which we attribute to substrate-dependent alterations of the actomyosin cortex and an inverse relationship between tension along stress fibres and cortical tension. Our results provide new insights into the complex regulation of membrane tension, and they pave the way for a deeper understanding of biological processes instructed by it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467973" rel="alternate" title="Effective Cell Membrane Tension is Independent of Substrate Stiffness (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468222</id><title>Cells use molecular working memory to navigate in changing chemoattractant fields (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.970885+00:00</updated><author><name>Akhilesh Nandan</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Das</name></author><author><name>Robert Lott</name></author><author><name>Aneta Koseska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In order to migrate over large distances, cells within tissues and organisms rely on sensing local gradient cues. These cues however are multifarious, irregular or conflicting, changing both in time and space. Here we find that single cells utilize a molecular mechanism akin to a working memory, to generate persistent directional migration when signals are disrupted by temporally memorizing their position, while still remaining adaptive to spatial and temporal changes of the signal source. Using dynamical systems theory, we derive that these information processing capabilities are inherent for protein networks whose dynamics is maintained away from steady state through organization at criticality. We demonstrate experimentally using the Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) signaling network, that the memory is maintained in the prolonged activity of the receptor via a slow-escaping remnant, a dynamical ghost of the attractor of the polarized signaling state, that further results in memory in migration. As this state is metastable, it also enables continuous adaptation of the migration direction when the signals vary in space and time. We therefore show that cells implement real-time computations without stable-states to navigate in changing chemoattractant fields by memorizing position of disrupted signals while maintaining sensitivity to novel chemical cues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468222" rel="alternate" title="Cells use molecular working memory to navigate in changing chemoattractant fields (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468059</id><title>A small molecule stabilises the disordered native state of the Alzheimer’s Aβ peptide (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.971136+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Löhr</name></author><author><name>Kai Kohlhoff</name></author><author><name>Gabriella T. Heller</name></author><author><name>Carlo Camilloni</name></author><author><name>Michele Vendruscolo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The stabilisation of native states of proteins is a powerful drug discovery strategy. It is still unclear, however, whether this approach can be applied to intrinsically disordered proteins. Here we report a small molecule that stabilises the native state of the Aβ42 peptide, an intrinsically disordered protein fragment associated with Alzheimer’s disease. We show that this stabilisation takes place by a dynamic binding mechanism, in which both the small molecule and the Aβ42 peptide remain disordered. This disordered binding mechanism involves enthalpically favourable local π-stacking interactions coupled with entropically advantageous global effects. These results indicate that small molecules can stabilise disordered proteins in their native states through transient non-specific interactions that provide enthalpic gain while simultaneously increasing the conformational entropy of the proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468059" rel="alternate" title="A small molecule stabilises the disordered native state of the Alzheimer’s Aβ peptide (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467894</id><title>Improvement of muscle strength in a mouse model for congenital myopathy treated with HDAC and DNA methyltransferase inhibitors (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.971412+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexis Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Sofia Benucci</name></author><author><name>Urs Duthaler</name></author><author><name>Christoph Bachmann</name></author><author><name>Martina Franchini</name></author><author><name>Faiza Noreen</name></author><author><name>Laura Pietrangelo</name></author><author><name>Feliciano Protasi</name></author><author><name>Susan Treves</name></author><author><name>Francesco Zorzato</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To date there are no therapies for patients with congenital myopathies, muscle disorders causing poor quality of life of affected individuals. In approximately 30% of the cases, patients with congenital myopathies carry either dominant or recessive mutations in the &lt;italic&gt;RYR1&lt;/italic&gt; gene; recessive &lt;italic&gt;RYR1&lt;/italic&gt; mutations are accompanied by reduction of RyR1 expression and content in skeletal muscles and are associated with fiber hypotrophy and muscle weakness. Importantly, muscles of patients with recessive &lt;italic&gt;RYR1&lt;/italic&gt; mutations exhibit increased content of class II histone de-acetylases and of DNA genomic methylation. We recently created a mouse model knocked-in for the p.Q1970fsX16+p.A4329D RyR1 mutations, which are isogenic to those carried by a severely affected child suffering from a recessive form of RyR1-related multi-mini core disease. The phenotype of the RyR1 mutant mice recapitulates many aspects of the clinical picture of patients carrying recessive &lt;italic&gt;RYR1&lt;/italic&gt; mutations. We treated the compound heterozygous mice with a combination of two drugs targeting DNA methylases and class II histone de-acetylases. Here we show that treatment of the mutant mice with drugs targeting epigenetic enzymes improves muscle strength, RyR1 protein content and muscle ultrastructure. This study provides proof of concept for the pharmacological treatment of patients with congenital myopathies linked to recessive &lt;italic&gt;RYR1&lt;/italic&gt; mutations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467894" rel="alternate" title="Improvement of muscle strength in a mouse model for congenital myopathy treated with HDAC and DNA methyltransferase inhibitors (6 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468236</id><title>Differential regulation of degradation and immune pathways underlies adaptation of the ectosymbiotic nematode Laxus oneistus to oxic-anoxic interfaces (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.971599+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriela F Paredes</name></author><author><name>Tobias Viehboeck</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Markert</name></author><author><name>Michaela A Mausz</name></author><author><name>Yui Sato</name></author><author><name>Manuel Liebeke</name></author><author><name>Lena Koenig</name></author><author><name>Silvia Bulgheresi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Eukaryotes may experience oxygen deprivation under both physiological and pathological conditions. Because oxygen shortage leads to a reduction in cellular energy production, all eukaryotes studied so far conserve energy by suppressing their metabolism. However, the molecular physiology of animals that naturally and repeatedly experience anoxia is underexplored. One such animal is the marine nematode Laxus oneistus. It thrives, invariably coated by its sulfur-oxidizing symbiont Candidatus Thiosymbion oneisti, in anoxic sulfidic or hypoxic sand. Here, transcriptomics and proteomics showed that, whether in anoxia or not, L. oneistus mostly expressed genes involved in ubiquitination, energy generation, oxidative stress response, immune response, development, and translation. Importantly, ubiquitination genes were also upregulated when the nematode was subjected to anoxic sulfidic conditions, together with genes involved in autophagy, detoxification and ribosome biogenesis. We hypothesize that these degradation pathways were induced to recycle damaged cellular components (mitochondria) and misfolded proteins into nutrients. Remarkably, when L. oneistus was subjected to anoxic sulfidic conditions, lectin and mucin genes were also upregulated, potentially to promote the attachment of its thiotrophic symbiont. Furthermore, the nematode appeared to survive oxygen deprivation by using an alternative electron carrier (rhodoquinone) and acceptor (fumarate), to rewire the electron transfer chain. On the other hand, under hypoxia, genes involved in costly processes (e.g., amino acid biosynthesis, development, feeding, mating) were upregulated, together with the worm's Toll-like innate immunity pathway and several immune effectors (e.g., Bacterial Permeability Increasing proteins, fungicides). In conclusion, we hypothesize that, in anoxic sulfidic sand, L. oneistus upregulates degradation processes, rewires oxidative phosphorylation and by reinforces its coat of bacterial sulfur-oxidizers. In upper sand layers, instead, it appears to produce broad-range antimicrobials and to exploit oxygen for biosynthesis and development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.11.468236" rel="alternate" title="Differential regulation of degradation and immune pathways underlies adaptation of the ectosymbiotic nematode Laxus oneistus to oxic-anoxic interfaces (5 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467404</id><title>Microtubule Lattice Spacing Governs Cohesive Envelope Formation of Tau Family Proteins (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.971766+00:00</updated><author><name>Valerie Siahaan</name></author><author><name>Ruensern Tan</name></author><author><name>Tereza Humhalova</name></author><author><name>Lenka Libusova</name></author><author><name>Samuel E. Lacey</name></author><author><name>Tracy Tan</name></author><author><name>Mariah Dacy</name></author><author><name>Kassandra M. Ori-McKenney</name></author><author><name>Richard J. McKenney</name></author><author><name>Marcus Braun</name></author><author><name>Zdenek Lansky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tau is an intrinsically-disordered microtubule-associated protein (MAP) implicated in neurodegenerative disease. On microtubules, tau molecules segregate into two kinetically distinct phases, consisting of either independently diffusing molecules or interacting molecules that form cohesive “envelopes” around microtubules. Envelopes differentially regulate lattice accessibility for other MAPs, but the mechanism of envelope formation remains unclear. Here, we find that tau envelopes form cooperatively, locally altering the spacing of tubulin dimers within the microtubule lattice. Envelope formation compacted the underlying lattice, whereas lattice extension induced tau-envelope disassembly. Investigating other members of the tau-MAP family, we find MAP2 similarly forms envelopes governed by lattice-spacing, whereas MAP4 cannot. Envelopes differentially biased motor protein movement, suggesting that tau family members could spatially divide the microtubule surface into functionally distinct segments. We conclude that the interdependent allostery between lattice-spacing and cooperative envelope formation provides the molecular basis for spatial regulation of microtubule-based processes by tau and MAP2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467404" rel="alternate" title="Microtubule Lattice Spacing Governs Cohesive Envelope Formation of Tau Family Proteins (3 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467816</id><title>Circulating Microvesicle-Associated Inducible Nitric Oxide Synthase Is a Novel Therapeutic Target to Treat Sepsis: Current Status and Future Considerations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.971950+00:00</updated><author><name>Robert J Webber</name></author><author><name>Richard M Sweet</name></author><author><name>Douglas S Webber</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To determine if mitigating the harmful effects of circulating microvesicle-associated inducible nitric oxide (MV-A iNOS) &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; increases the survival of challenged mice in three different mouse models of sepsis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Design&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability of anti-MV-A iNOS monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) to rescue challenged mice was assessed using three different mouse models of sepsis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Setting&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vivarium of a research laboratory&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Subjects&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Balb/c mice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interventions: Mice were challenged with an LD&lt;sub&gt;80&lt;/sub&gt; dose of either lipopolysaccharide (LPS / endotoxin), TNFα, or MV-A iNOS and then treated at various times after the challenge with saline as control or with an anti-MV-A iNOS mAb as a potential immunotherapeutic to treat sepsis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Measurement and Main Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each group of mice was checked daily for survivors, and Kaplan-Meier survival curves were constructed. Five different murine anti-MV-A iNOS mAbs from our panel of 24 murine anti-MV-A iNOS mAbs (1) were found to rescue some of the challenged mice. All five murine mAbs were used to genetically engineer humanized anti-MV-A iNOS mAbs by inserting the murine complementarity-determining regions (CDRs) into a human IgG&lt;sub&gt;1,kappa&lt;/sub&gt; scaffold and expressing the humanized mAbs in CHO cells. Three humanized anti-MV-A iNOS mAbs were effective at rescuing mice from sepsis in three different animal models of sepsis. The effectiveness of the treatment was both time and dose dependent. Humanized anti-MV-A iNOS rHJ mAb could rescue up to 80% of the challenged animal if administered early and at a high dose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our conclusions are MV-A iNOS is a novel therapeutic target to treat sepsis; anti-MV-A iNOS mAbs can mitigate the harmful effects of MV-A iNOS; the neutralizing mAb’s efficacy is both time and dose dependent; and a specifically targeted immunotherapeutic for MV-A iNOS could potentially save tens-of-thousands of lives annually and could result in improved antibiotic stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467816" rel="alternate" title="Circulating Microvesicle-Associated Inducible Nitric Oxide Synthase Is a Novel Therapeutic Target to Treat Sepsis: Current Status and Future Considerations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Physiology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>