<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv biophysics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.450690+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biophysics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.444805</id><title>Nanofluidic chips for cryo-EM structure determination from picoliter sample volumes (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.450996+00:00</updated><author><name>Stefan T. Huber</name></author><author><name>Edin Sarajlic</name></author><author><name>Roeland Huijink</name></author><author><name>Felix Weis</name></author><author><name>Wiel H. Evers</name></author><author><name>Arjen J. Jakobi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cryogenic electron microscopy has become an essential tool for structure determination of biological macromolecules. In practice, the difficulty to reliably prepare samples with uniform ice thickness still represents a barrier for routine high-resolution imaging and limits the current throughput of the technique. We show that a nanofluidic sample support with well-defined geometry can be used to prepare cryo-EM specimens with reproducible ice thickness from picoliter sample volumes. The sample solution is contained in electron-transparent nanochannels that provide uniform thickness gradients without further optimisation and eliminate the potentially destructive air-water interface. We demonstrate the possibility to perform high-resolution structure determination with three standard protein specimens. Nanofabricated sample supports bear potential to automate the cryo-EM workflow, and to explore new frontiers for cryo-EM applications such as time-resolved imaging and high-throughput screening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.444805" rel="alternate" title="Nanofluidic chips for cryo-EM structure determination from picoliter sample volumes (36 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445507</id><title>The molecular mechanism of load adaptation by branched actin networks (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.451220+00:00</updated><author><name>Tai-De Li</name></author><author><name>Peter Bieling</name></author><author><name>Julian Weichsel</name></author><author><name>R. Dyche Mullins</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Fletcher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Branched actin networks are self-assembling molecular motors that move biological membranes and drive many important cellular processes. Load forces slow the growth and increase the density of these networks, but the molecular mechanisms governing this force response are not well understood. Here we use single-molecule imaging and AFM cantilever deflection to measure how applied forces affect each step in branched actin network assembly. Unexpectedly, force slows the rate of filament nucleation by promoting the interaction of nucleation promoting factors with actin filament ends, limiting branch formation. This inhibition is countered by an even larger force-induced drop in the rate of filament capping, resulting in a shift in the balance between nucleation and capping that increases network density. Remarkably, the force dependence of capping is identical to that of filament elongation because they require the same size gap to appear between the filament and load for insertion. These results provide direct evidence that Brownian Ratchets generate force and govern the load adaptation of branched actin networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445507" rel="alternate" title="The molecular mechanism of load adaptation by branched actin networks (23 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445501</id><title>Cholesterol Oxidation Modulates the Formation of Liquid-Ordered Domains in Model Membranes (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.451395+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul Smith</name></author><author><name>Peter G. Petrov</name></author><author><name>Christian D. Lorenz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;7-ketocholesterol (KChol) is one of the most cytotoxic oxysterols found in the plasma membrane, and increased levels of KChol are associated with numerous pathologies. It is thought to induce apoptosis via inactivation of the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt signaling pathway — a pathway that depends on lipid-rafts as signaling platforms. By means of coarse-grained molecular dynamics simulations, we demonstrate that KChol disrupts the liquid-liquid phase separation seen in an equimolar mixture of (dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine) DPPC, (dioleoylphosphatidylcholine) DOPC, and Cholesterol (Chol). This disruption occurs via two mechanisms: i) KChol adopts a wider range of orientations with the membrane, which disrupts the packing of neighboring lipids and ii) KChol has no preference for DPPC over DOPC, which is the main driving force for lateral demixing in DPPC/DOPC/Chol membranes. This provides a molecular description of the means by which KChol induces apoptosis, and illustrates that a single chemical substitution to cholesterol can have a profound impact on the lateral organization of lipid membranes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical TOC Entry&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="445501v2_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445501" rel="alternate" title="Cholesterol Oxidation Modulates the Formation of Liquid-Ordered Domains in Model Membranes (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446223</id><title>Amphiphilic proteins coassemble into multiphasic condensates and act as biomolecular surfactants (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.451554+00:00</updated><author><name>Fleurie M Kelley</name></author><author><name>Bruna Favetta</name></author><author><name>Roshan M Regy</name></author><author><name>Jeetain Mittal</name></author><author><name>Benjamin S Schuster</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells contain membraneless compartments that assemble due to liquid-liquid phase separation, including biomolecular condensates with complex morphologies. For instance, certain condensates are surrounded by a film of distinct composition, such as Ape1 condensates coated by a layer of Atg19, required for selective autophagy in yeast. Other condensates are multiphasic, with nested liquid phases of distinct compositions and functions, such as in the case of ribosome biogenesis in the nucleolus. The size and structure of such condensates must be regulated for proper biological function. We leveraged a bio-inspired approach to discover how amphiphilic, surfactant-like proteins may contribute to the structure and size regulation of biomolecular condensates. We designed and examined families of amphiphilic proteins comprising one phase-separating domain and one non-phase separating domain. In particular, these proteins contain the soluble structured domain glutathione S-transferase (GST) or maltose binding protein (MBP), fused to the intrinsically disordered RGG domain from P granule protein LAF-1. When one amphiphilic protein is mixed in vitro with RGG-RGG, the proteins assemble into enveloped condensates, with RGG-RGG at the core, and the amphiphilic protein forming the surface film layer. Importantly, we found that MBP-based amphiphiles are surfactants and control droplet size, with increasing surfactant concentration resulting in smaller droplet radii. In contrast, GST-based amphiphiles at increased concentrations co-assemble with RGG-RGG into multiphasic structures. We propose a mechanism for these experimental observations, supported by molecular simulations of a minimalist model. We speculate that surfactant proteins may play a significant role in regulating the structure and function of biomolecular condensates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446223" rel="alternate" title="Amphiphilic proteins coassemble into multiphasic condensates and act as biomolecular surfactants (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445502</id><title>Estimating the Dynamic Range of Quantitative Single-Molecule Localization Microscopy (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.451749+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel F. Nino</name></author><author><name>Joshua N. Milstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, there have been significant advances in quantifying molecule copy number and protein stoichiometry with single-molecule localization microscopy (SMLM). However, as the density of fluorophores per diffraction-limited spot increases, distinguishing between detection events from different fluorophores becomes progressively more difficult, affecting the accuracy of such measurements. Although essential to the design of quantitative experiments, the dynamic range of SMLM counting techniques has not yet been studied in detail. Here we provide a working definition of the dynamic range for quantitative SMLM in terms of the relative number of missed localizations or blinks, and explore the photophysical and experimental parameters that affect it. We begin with a simple two-state model of blinking fluorophores, then extend the model to incorporate photobleaching and temporal binning by the detection camera. From these models, we first show that our estimates of the dynamic range agree with realistic simulations of the photoswitching. We find that the dynamic range scales inversely with the duty cycle when counting both blinks and localizations. Finally, we validate our theoretical approach on dSTORM datasets of photo-switching Alexa647 dyes. Our results should help guide researchers in designing and implementing SMLM-based molecular counting experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445502" rel="alternate" title="Estimating the Dynamic Range of Quantitative Single-Molecule Localization Microscopy (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445403</id><title>Insights into substrate recognition and specificity for IgG by Endoglycosidase S2 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.451933+00:00</updated><author><name>Asaminew H. Aytenfisu</name></author><author><name>Daniel Deredge</name></author><author><name>Erik H. Klontz</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Du</name></author><author><name>Eric J. Sundberg</name></author><author><name>Alexander D. MacKerell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies bind foreign antigens with high affinity and specificity leading to their neutralization and/or clearance by the immune system. The conserved N-glycan on IgG has significant impact on antibody effector function, with the endoglycosidases of &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus pyogen&lt;/italic&gt;es deglycosylating the IgG to evade the immune system, a process catalyzed by the endoglycosidase EndoS2. Studies have shown that two of the four domains of EndoS2, the carbohydrate binding module (CBM) and the glycoside hydrolase (GH) domain site are critical for catalytic activity. To yield structural insights into contributions of the CBM and the GH domains, as well as the overall flexibility of EndoS2, to the proteins’ catalytic activity, models of EndoS2-Fc complexes were generated through enhanced-sampling molecular-dynamics (MD) simulation and site-identification by ligand competitive saturation (SILCS) docking followed by reconstruction and long-time MD simulations. Modeling results predict that EndoS2 initially interacts with the IgG through its CBM followed by interactions with the GH yielding catalytically competent states. These may involve the CBM and GH of EndoS2 simultaneously interacting with either the same Fc CH2/CH3 domain or individually with the two Fc CH2/CH3 domains, with EndoS2 predicted to assume closed conformations in the former case and open conformations in the latter. Apo EndoS2 is predicted to sample both the open and closed states, suggesting that either complex can directly form following initial IgG-EndoS2 encounter. Interactions of the CBM and GH domains with the IgG are predicted to occur through both its glycan and protein regions. Simulations also predict that the Fc glycan can directly transfer from the CBM to the GH, facilitating formation of catalytically competent complexes. The predicted models are compared and consistent with Hydrogen/Deuterium Exchange data. In addition, the complex models are consistent with the high specificity of EndoS2 for the glycans on IgG supporting the validity of the predicted models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Streptococcus pyogen&lt;/italic&gt;es uses the endoglycosidases S and S2 to cleave the glycans on the Fc portion of IgG antibodies, leading to a decreased cytotoxicity of the antibodies, thereby evading the host immune response. To identify potential structures of the complex of EndoS2 with IgG that could lead to the catalytic hydrolysis of the IgG glycan, molecular modeling and molecular dynamics simulations were applied. The resulting structural models predict that EndoS2 initially interacts through its carbohydrate binding module (CBM) with the IgG with subsequent interactions with the catalytic glycoside hydrolase (GH) domain yielding stable complexes. In the modeled complexes the CBM and the GH interact either simultaneously with the same Fc CH2/CH3 domain or with the two individual Fc CH2/CH3 domains separately to yield potentially catalytically competent species. In addition, apo EndoS2 is shown to assume both open and closed conformations allowing it to directly form either type of complex from which deglycosylation of either mono- or diglycosylated IgG species may occur.
&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="445403v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445403" rel="alternate" title="Insights into substrate recognition and specificity for IgG by Endoglycosidase S2 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>