<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv biophysics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.958860+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biophysics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449614</id><title>Quantitative Mining of Compositional Heterogeneity in Cryo-EM Datasets of Ribosome Assembly Intermediates (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.959149+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica N. Rabuck-Gibbons</name></author><author><name>Dmitry Lyumkis</name></author><author><name>James R. Williamson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macromolecular complexes are dynamic entities whose function is often intertwined with their many structural configurations. Single particle cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) offers a unique opportunity to characterize macromolecular structural heterogeneity by virtue of its ability to place distinct populations into different groups through computational classification. However, current workflows are limited, and there is a dearth of tools for surveying the heterogeneity landscape, quantitatively analyzing heterogeneous particle populations after classification, deciding how many unique classes are represented by the data, and accurately cross-comparing reconstructions. Here, we develop a workflow that contains discovery and analysis modules to quantitatively mine cryo-EM data for a set of structures with maximal diversity. This workflow was applied to a dataset of &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; 50S ribosome assembly intermediates, which is characterized by significant structural heterogeneity. We identified new branch points in the assembly process and characterized the interactions of an assembly factor with immature intermediates. While the tools described here were developed for ribosome assembly, they should be broadly applicable to the analysis of other heterogeneous cryo-EM datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449614" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative Mining of Compositional Heterogeneity in Cryo-EM Datasets of Ribosome Assembly Intermediates (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.20.449177</id><title>A Machine Learning-Enabled Pipeline for Large-Scale Virtual Drug Screening (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.959414+00:00</updated><author><name>Aayush Gupta</name></author><author><name>Huan-Xiang Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virtual screening is receiving renewed attention in drug discovery, but progress is hampered by challenges on two fronts: handling the ever increasing sizes of libraries of drug-like compounds, and separating true positives from false positives. Here we developed a machine learning-enabled pipeline for large-scale virtual screening that promises breakthroughs on both fronts. By clustering compounds according to molecular properties and limited docking against a drug target, the full library was trimmed by 10-fold; the remaining compounds were then screened individually by docking; and finally a dense neural network was trained to classify the hits into true and false positives. As illustration, we screened for inhibitors against RPN11, the deubiquitinase subunit of the proteasome and a drug target for breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;TOC Graphic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="449177v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.20.449177" rel="alternate" title="A Machine Learning-Enabled Pipeline for Large-Scale Virtual Drug Screening (9 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>