<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv biophysics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.612436+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biophysics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444182</id><title>Conformational buffering underlies functional selection in intrinsically disordered protein regions (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.613995+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicolas S Gonzalez-Foutel</name></author><author><name>Wade M Borcherds</name></author><author><name>Juliana Glavina</name></author><author><name>Susana Barrera-Vilarmau</name></author><author><name>Amin Sagar</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Estana</name></author><author><name>Amelie Barozet</name></author><author><name>Gregorio Fernandez-Ballester</name></author><author><name>Clara Blanes-Mira</name></author><author><name>Ignacio Enrique Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Gonzalo de Prat Gay</name></author><author><name>Juan Cortes</name></author><author><name>Pau Bernado</name></author><author><name>Rohit V Pappu</name></author><author><name>Alex S Holehouse</name></author><author><name>Gary W Daughdrill</name></author><author><name>Lucia Beatriz Chemes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many disordered proteins conserve essential functions in the face of extensive sequence variation. This makes it challenging to identify the forces responsible for functional selection. Viruses are robust model systems to investigate functional selection and they take advantage of protein disorder to acquire novel traits. Here, we combine structural and computational biophysics with evolutionary analysis to determine the molecular basis for functional selection in the intrinsically disordered adenovirus early gene 1A (E1A) protein. E1A competes with host factors to bind the retinoblastoma (Rb) protein, triggering early S-phase entry and disrupting normal cellular proliferation. We show that the ability to outcompete host factors depends on the picomolar binding affinity of E1A for Rb, which is driven by two binding motifs tethered by a hypervariable disordered linker. Binding affinity is determined by the spatial dimensions of the linker, which constrain the relative position of the two binding motifs. Despite substantial sequence variation across evolution, the linker dimensions are finely optimized through compensatory changes in amino acid sequence and sequence length, leading to conserved linker dimensions and maximal affinity. We refer to the mechanism that conserves spatial dimensions despite large-scale variations in sequence as conformational buffering. Conformational buffering explains how variable disordered proteins encode functions and could be a general mechanism for functional selection within disordered protein regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.444182" rel="alternate" title="Conformational buffering underlies functional selection in intrinsically disordered protein regions (52 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443786</id><title>Probing DNA - transcription factor interactions using single-molecule fluorescence detection in nanofluidic devices (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.614918+00:00</updated><author><name>Mattia Fontana</name></author><author><name>Šarūnė Ivanovaitė</name></author><author><name>Simon Lindhoud</name></author><author><name>Willy van den Berg</name></author><author><name>Dolf Weijers</name></author><author><name>Johannes Hohlbein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-molecule fluorescence detection offers powerful ways to study biomolecules and their complex interactions. Here, we combine nanofluidic devices and camera-based, single-molecule Förster resonance energy transfer (smFRET) detection to study the interactions between plant transcription factors of the auxin response family (ARF) and DNA oligonucleotides that contain target DNA response elements. In particular, we show that the binding of the unlabelled ARF DNA binding domain (ARF-DBD) to donor and acceptor labelled DNA oligonucleotides can be detected by changes in the FRET efficiency and changes in the diffusion coefficient of the DNA. In addition, our data on fluorescently labelled ARF-DBDs suggest that, at nanomolar concentrations, ARF-DBDs are exclusively present as monomers. In general, the fluidic framework of freely diffusing molecules minimizes potential surface-induced artifacts, enables high-throughput measurements and proved to be instrumental in shedding more light on the interactions between ARF-DBDs monomers and between ARF-DBDs and their DNA response element.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443786" rel="alternate" title="Probing DNA - transcription factor interactions using single-molecule fluorescence detection in nanofluidic devices (20 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444064</id><title>Markov state models from hierarchical density-based assignment (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.615130+00:00</updated><author><name>Ion Mitxelena</name></author><author><name>Xabier López</name></author><author><name>David de Sancho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Markov state models (MSMs) have become one of the preferred methods for the analysis and interpretation of molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of conformational transitions in biopolymers. While there is great variation in terms of implementation, a well-defined workflow involving multiple steps is often adopted. Typically, molecular coordinates are first subjected to dimensionality reduction and then clustered into small “microstates”, which are subsequently lumped into “macrostates” using the information from the slowest eigenmodes. However, the microstate dynamics is often non-Markovian and long lag times are required to converge the MSM. Here we propose a variation on this typical workflow, taking advantage of hierarchical density-based clustering. When applied to simulation data, this type of clustering separates high population regions of conformational space from others that are rarely visited. In this way, density-based clustering naturally implements assignment of the data based on transitions between metastable states. As a result, the state definition becomes more consistent with the assumption of Markovianity and the timescales of the slow dynamics of the system are recovered more effectively. We present results of this simplified workflow for a model potential and MD simulations of the alanine dipeptide and the FiP35 WW domain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444064" rel="alternate" title="Markov state models from hierarchical density-based assignment (17 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443683</id><title>Nuclear lamin isoforms differentially contribute to LINC complex-dependent nucleocytoskeletal coupling and whole cell mechanics (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.615282+00:00</updated><author><name>Amir Vahabikashi</name></author><author><name>Suganya Sivagurunathan</name></author><author><name>Fiona Ann Sadsad Nicdao</name></author><author><name>Yu Long Han</name></author><author><name>Chan Young Park</name></author><author><name>Joseph R. Tran</name></author><author><name>Gregg G. Gundersen</name></author><author><name>Karen Reddy</name></author><author><name>GW Gant Luxton</name></author><author><name>Ming Guo</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Fredberg</name></author><author><name>Yixian Zheng</name></author><author><name>Stephen A. Adam</name></author><author><name>Robert D. Goldman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of a cell to regulate its mechanical properties is central to its function. Emerging evidence suggests that interactions between the cell nucleus and cytoskeleton influence cell mechanics through poorly understood mechanisms. Here we show that A- and B-type nuclear lamin isoforms distinctively modulate both nuclear and cellular volume and selectively stabilize the linker of nucleoskeleton and cytoskeleton (LINC) complexes that couple the nucleus to cytoskeletal actin and vimentin. We reveal, further, that loss of each of the four-known lamin isoforms in the mouse embryonic fibroblasts differentially affects cortical and cytoplasmic stiffness as well as cellular contractility, and then propose a LINC complex mediated model that explains these impaired mechanical phenotypes. Finally, we demonstrate that loss of each lamin isoform softens the nucleus in a manner that correlates with loss of heterochromatin. Together, these findings uncover distinctive roles for each lamin isoform in maintaining cellular and nuclear mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443683" rel="alternate" title="Nuclear lamin isoforms differentially contribute to LINC complex-dependent nucleocytoskeletal coupling and whole cell mechanics (13 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443509</id><title>Spontaneous formation of prebiotic compartment colonies on Hadean Earth and pre-Noachian Mars (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.615491+00:00</updated><author><name>Elif S. Köksal</name></author><author><name>Inga Põldsalu</name></author><author><name>Henrik Friis</name></author><author><name>Stephen Mojzsis</name></author><author><name>Martin Bizzarro</name></author><author><name>Irep Gözen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The primitive cells that emerged at the origin of life are commonly viewed as spherical biosurfactant shells, freely suspended in aqueous media&lt;sup&gt;1–3&lt;/sup&gt;. This model explains initial, but not subsequent events in the development process towards structured protocells. Taking into consideration the involvement of naturally occurring surfaces, which were abundant on the early Earth&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;, we report feasible and productive pathways for the development of primitive cells. Surfaces intrinsically possess energy, easily utilized by the interfacing amphiphiles, such as lipids, to attain self-organization and spontaneous transformations&lt;sup&gt;5–7&lt;/sup&gt;. We show that the physical interaction of phospholipid pools with 20 Hadean Earth analogue materials as well as a Martian meteorite composed of fused regolith representing the ancient crust of Mars, consistently lead to the shape transformation and autonomous formation of surfactant compartment assemblies. Dense, colony-like protocell populations grow from these lipid deposits, predominantly at the grain boundaries or cleavages of the investigated natural surfaces, and remain there for several days. The model protocells in our study are able to autonomously develop, transform and pseudo-divide, and encapsulate RNA as well as DNA. We also demonstrate that they can accommodate non-enzymatic, DNA strand displacement reactions. Our findings suggest a feasible route towards the transformation from nonliving to living entities, and provide fresh support for the ‘Lipid World’ hypothesis&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443509" rel="alternate" title="Spontaneous formation of prebiotic compartment colonies on Hadean Earth and pre-Noachian Mars (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444109</id><title>Microinductor-Fused Atomic Force Microscopy Cantilevers for Dynamic Imaging and Multimodal Manipulation (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.615652+00:00</updated><author><name>Charilaos Mousoulis</name></author><author><name>Xin Xu</name></author><author><name>Robert L. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Garrett Chado</name></author><author><name>Joseph Wahlquist</name></author><author><name>Mark P. Stoykovich</name></author><author><name>Virginia L. Ferguson</name></author><author><name>Babak Ziaie</name></author><author><name>Corey P. Neu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in atomic force microscopy (AFM) imaging and force spectroscopy have demonstrated improvements in rapid acquisition of quantitative data for applications in materials science, surface characterization, and biology. However, conventional AFM technology is limited in detection sensitivity and the ability to excite at off-resonance frequencies restricting broad utility of the technology. Here we demonstrate new AFM cantilevers fabricated with a planar microcoil at the tip region, which can be used to generate or sense highly-localized magnetic fields. Torsion/bending actuation of the cantilevers is accomplished with simple experimental configurations, enabling quantitative and simultaneous mapping of both stiffness and friction at the sample surface with more than one order of magnitude improvement in compositional contrast. Our method is compatible with commercial AFM systems, allowing us to clearly resolve small stiffness and friction variations in copolymer and biological samples that were difficult to detect by conventional AFM methods. In combination with fluorescence microscopy, we also generated localized fields to selectively stimulate and monitor structural changes in viable cells with nm-scale detail. Hybrid AFM cantilevers may be useful to characterize a broad range of complex material surfaces, in addition to combined physical and chemical analyses of single cells and biological microenvironments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.13.444109" rel="alternate" title="Microinductor-Fused Atomic Force Microscopy Cantilevers for Dynamic Imaging and Multimodal Manipulation (10 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443618</id><title>Molecular basis and functional consequences of the interaction between the Base Excision Repair DNA glycosylase NEIL1 and RPA (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.615827+00:00</updated><author><name>Rémy A. Le Meur</name></author><author><name>Turner J. Pecen</name></author><author><name>Kateryna V. Le Meur</name></author><author><name>Zachary D. Nagel</name></author><author><name>Walter J. Chazin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;NEIL1 is a DNA glycosylase that recognizes and initiates base excision repair of oxidized bases. The ubiquitous ssDNA binding scaffolding protein replication protein A (RPA) modulates NEIL1 activity in a manner that depends on DNA structure. Interaction between NEIL1 and RPA has been reported, but the molecular basis of this interaction has yet to be investigated. Using a combination of NMR spectroscopy and isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC), we show that NEIL1 interacts with RPA through two contact points. An interaction with the RPA32C protein recruitment domain was mapped to a motif in the common interaction domain (CID) of NEIL1 and a dissociation constant (Kd) of 200 nM was measured. A substantially weaker secondary interaction with the tandem RPA70AB ssDNA binding domains was also mapped to the CID. Together these two contact points reveal NEIL1 has a high overall affinity (Kd ∼ 20 nM) for RPA. A homology model of the complex of RPA32C with the NEIL1 RPA binding motif in the CID was generated and used to design a set of mutations in NEIL1 to disrupt the interaction, which was confirmed by ITC. The mutant NEIL1 remains catalytically active against ionizing radiation-induced DNA lesions in duplex DNA &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Testing the functional effect of disrupting the NEIL1-RPA interaction &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; using a Fluorescence Multiplex-Host Cell Reactivation (FM-HCR) reporter assay revealed that RPA interaction is not required for NEIL1 activity against oxidative damage in duplex DNA, and furthermore revealed an unexpected role for NEIL1 in nucleotide excision repair. These findings are discussed in the context of the role of NEIL1 in replication-associated repair.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443618" rel="alternate" title="Molecular basis and functional consequences of the interaction between the Base Excision Repair DNA glycosylase NEIL1 and RPA (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443644</id><title>PIP2-dependent coupling of voltage sensor and pore domains in Kv7.2 (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.615980+00:00</updated><author><name>Shashank Pant</name></author><author><name>Jiaren Zhang</name></author><author><name>Eung Chang Kim</name></author><author><name>Kin Lam</name></author><author><name>Hee Jung Chung</name></author><author><name>Emad Tajkhorshid</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate (PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) is a signaling lipid which regulates voltage-gated K&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;7/&lt;italic&gt;KCNQ&lt;/italic&gt; potassium channels. Altered PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; sensitivity of neuronal K&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;7.2 channel is involved in &lt;italic&gt;KCNQ2&lt;/italic&gt; epileptic encephalopathy. However, the molecular action of PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; on K&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;7.2 gating remains largely elusive. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulations and electrophysiology to characterize PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; binding sites in a human K&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;7.2 channel. In the closed state, PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; localizes to the periphery of the voltage-sensing domain (VSD). In the open state, PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; binds to 4 distinct interfaces formed by the cytoplasmic ends of the VSD, the gate, intracellular helices A and B and their linkers. PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; binding induces bilayer-interacting conformation of helices A and B and the correlated motion of the VSD and the pore domain, whereas charge-neutralizing mutations block this coupling and reduce PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; sensitivity of K&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;7.2 channels by disrupting PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; binding. These findings reveal the allosteric role of PIP&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in K&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;7.2 channel activation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443644" rel="alternate" title="PIP2-dependent coupling of voltage sensor and pore domains in Kv7.2 (8 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.443726</id><title>Calcium signaling in the photodamaged skin (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.616139+00:00</updated><author><name>Viola Donati</name></author><author><name>Chiara Peres</name></author><author><name>Chiara Nardin</name></author><author><name>Ferdinando Scavizzi</name></author><author><name>Marcello Raspa</name></author><author><name>Catalin Dacian Ciubotaru</name></author><author><name>Mario Bortolozzi</name></author><author><name>Fabio Mammano</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND: The mammalian skin, the body's largest single organ, is a highly organized tissue that forms an essential barrier against dehydration, pathogens, light and mechanical injury. Damage triggers perturbations of the cytosolic free Ca2+ concentration ([Ca2+]c) that spread from cell to cell (known as intercellular Ca2+ waves) in different epithelia, including epidermis. Ca2+ waves are considered a fundamental mechanism for coordinating multicellular responses, however the mechanisms underlying their propagation in the damaged epidermis are incompletely understood. AIM OF THE PROJECT: To dissect the molecular components contributing to Ca2+ wave propagation in murine model of epidermal photodamage. METHODS: To trigger Ca2+ waves, we used intense and focused pulsed laser radiation and targeted a single keratinocyte of the epidermal basal layer in the earlobe skin of live anesthetized mice. To track photodamage-evoked Ca2+ waves, we performed intravital multiphoton microscopy in transgenic mice with ubiquitous expression of the sensitive and selective Ca2+ biosensor GCaMP6s. To dissect the molecular components contributing to Ca2+ wave propagation, we performed in vivo pharmacological interference experiments by intradermal microinjection of different drugs. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS: The major effects of drugs that interfere with degradation of extracellular ATP or P2 purinoceptors suggest that Ca2+ waves in the photodamaged epidermis are primarily due to release of ATP from the target cell, whose plasma membrane integrity was compromised by laser irradiation. The limited effect of the Connexin 43 (Cx43) selective inhibitor TAT-Gap19 suggests ATP-dependent ATP release though connexin hemichannels (HCs) plays a minor role, affecting Ca2+ wave propagation only at larger distances, where the concentration of ATP released from the photodamaged cell was reduced by the combined effect of passive diffusion and hydrolysis due to the action of ectonucleotidases. The ineffectiveness of probenecid suggests pannexin channels have no role. As GCaMP6s signals in bystander keratinocytes were augmented by exposure to the Ca2+ chelator EGTA in the extracellular medium, the corresponding transient increments of the [Ca2+]c should be ascribed primarily to Ca2+ release from the ER, downstream of ATP binding to P2Y purinoceptors, with Ca2+ entry through plasma membrane channels playing a comparatively negligible role. The effect of thapsigargin (a well-known inhibitor of SERCA pumps) and carbenoxolone (a recently recognized inhibitor of Ca2+ release through IP3 receptors) support this conclusion. CONCLUSIONS: The one presented here is an experimental model for accidental skin injury that may also shed light on the widespread medical practice of laser skin resurfacing, used to treat a range of pathologies from photodamage and acne scars to hidradenitis suppurativa and posttraumatic scarring from basal cell carcinoma excision. The results of our experiments support the notion that Ca2+ waves reflect chiefly the sequential activation of bystander keratinocytes by the ATP released through the compromised plasma membrane of the cell hit by laser radiation. We attributed the observed increments of the [Ca2+]c chiefly to signal transduction through purinergic P2Y receptors. Several studies have highlighted fundamental roles of P2Y receptors during inflammatory and infectious diseases, and the initial phase of wound healing involves acute inflammation. In addition, hyaluronan is a major component of the extracellular matrix and its synthesis is rapidly upregulated after tissue wounding via P2Y receptor activation. It is tempting to speculate that response coordination after injury in the epidermis occurs via propagation of the ATP-dependent intercellular Ca2+ waves described in this work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.443726" rel="alternate" title="Calcium signaling in the photodamaged skin (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443823</id><title>Neural cell injury pathology due to high-rate mechanical loading (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.616308+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan B. Estrada</name></author><author><name>Harry C. Cramer</name></author><author><name>Mark T. Scimone</name></author><author><name>Selda Buyukozturk</name></author><author><name>Christian Franck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Successful detection and prevention of brain injuries relies on the quantitative identification of cellular injury thresholds associated with the underlying pathology. Here, by combining a recently developed inertial microcavitation rheology technique with a 3D &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; neural tissue model, we quantify and resolve the structural pathology and critical injury strain thresholds of neural cells occurring at high loading rates such as encountered in blast exposures or cavitation-based medical procedures. We find that neuronal dendritic spines characterized by MAP2 displayed the lowest physical failure strain at 7.3%, whereas microtubules and filamentous actin were able to tolerate appreciably higher strains (14%) prior to injury. Interestingly, while these critical injury thresholds were similar to previous literature values reported for moderate and lower strain rates (&amp;lt; 100 1/s), the pathology of primary injury reported here was distinctly different by being purely physical in nature as compared to biochemical activation during apoptosis or necrosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443823" rel="alternate" title="Neural cell injury pathology due to high-rate mechanical loading (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.440221</id><title>Biofilm self-patterning: mechanical force landscaping drives a collective reorientation cascade (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.616461+00:00</updated><author><name>Japinder Nijjer</name></author><author><name>Changhao Li</name></author><author><name>Qiuting Zhang</name></author><author><name>Haoran Lu</name></author><author><name>Sulin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jing Yan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During development, cells often self-organize into distinctive patterns with long-range orientational order. However, the mechanism by which long-range order emerges through complex interactions, particularly in the prokaryotic domain, remains elusive. Here we report, in growing &lt;italic&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/italic&gt; biofilms, a reorientation cascade consisting of cell verticalization in the core and radial alignment in the rim, generating a pattern reminiscent of a blooming aster. Single-cell imaging combined with agent-based simulations reveal that cell verticalization and radial alignment are spatiotemporally coupled, each generating the driving force for the other, to cause a dynamic cascade of differential orientational ordering. Such self-patterning is absent in nonadherent mutants but can be restored through opto-manipulation of growth. A two-phase active nematic model is developed to elucidate the mechanism underlying biofilm self-patterning, which offers insights into the control of organization in complex bacterial communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bacterial biofilms robustly pattern themselves through orientation-dependent, growth induced flows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.440221" rel="alternate" title="Biofilm self-patterning: mechanical force landscaping drives a collective reorientation cascade (5 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>