<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv biophysics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.707848+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biophysics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446472</id><title>Direct Energy Transfer from Allophycocyanin-Free Rod-Type CpcL-Phycobilisome to Photosystem I (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.708180+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomoyasu Noji</name></author><author><name>Mai Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Takehisa Dewa</name></author><author><name>Shigeru Itoh</name></author><author><name>Masahiko Ikeuchib</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phycobilisomes (PBSs) are photosynthetic antenna megacomplexes comprised of pigment-binding proteins (cores and rods) joined with linker proteins. A rod-type PBS that does not have a core is connected to photosystem I (PSI) by a pigment-free CpcL linker protein, which induces a red-shift of the absorption band of phycocyanobilin (PCB) in the rod (red-PCB). Herein, the isolated supercomplex of the rod-type PBS and the PSI tetramer from &lt;italic&gt;Anabaena&lt;/italic&gt; sp. PCC 7120 were probed by picosecond laser spectroscopy at 77 K and by decay-associated spectral analysis to show that red-PCB mediates the fast (time constant = 90 ps) and efficient (efficiency = 95%) transfer of excitation energy from PCB in rod to chlorophyll &lt;italic&gt;a&lt;/italic&gt; (Chl &lt;italic&gt;a&lt;/italic&gt;) in PSI. According to the Förster energy transfer mechanism, this high efficiency corresponds to a 4-nm distance between red-PCB and Chl &lt;italic&gt;a&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting that β-84 PCB in rod acts as red-PCB.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;TOC GRAPHIC&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="446472v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446472" rel="alternate" title="Direct Energy Transfer from Allophycocyanin-Free Rod-Type CpcL-Phycobilisome to Photosystem I (11 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446396</id><title>Structural and biochemical analysis of ATPase activity and EsxAB substrate binding of M. tuberculosis EccCb1 enzyme (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.708612+00:00</updated><author><name>Arkita Bandyopadyay</name></author><author><name>Ajay K. Saxena</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The EccC enzyme of &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; ESX-1 system is a promising target for antivirulence drug development. The EccC enzyme comprises two polypeptides (i) EccCa1, a membrane bound enzyme having two ATPase domains D2 &amp;amp; D3 (ii) cytosolic EccCb, which contains two ATPase domains. In current study, we have analyzed the low-resolution structure of EccCb1, performed ATPase activity and EsxAB substrate binding analysis. The EccCb1 enzyme eluted as oligomer from size exclusion column and small angle X-ray scattering analysis revealed the double hexameric structure in solution. The EccCb1 enzyme showed catalytic efficiency (&lt;italic&gt;k&lt;sub&gt;cat&lt;/sub&gt;/K&lt;sub&gt;M&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;)∼ 0.020±0.005 μM&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, however ∼ 3.7 fold lower than its D2 and ∼1.7 fold lower than D3 domains respectively. The D2 and D3 domains exhibited the ATPase activity and mutation of residues involved in ATP+Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; binding have yielded 56-94% reduction in catalytic efficiency for both D2 and D3 domains. The EccCb1 binds the EsxAB substrate with &lt;italic&gt;K&lt;sub&gt;D&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; ∼ 11.4±3.4 nM via specific groove located at C-terminal region of D3 domain. ATP binding to EccCb1 enhanced the EsxAB substrate binding by ∼ 3 fold, indicating ATPase energy involvement in EsxAB substrate translocation. We modeled the dodecameric EccCb1+EsxAB+ ATP+Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; complex, which showed the binding pockets involved in ATP+Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and EsxAB substrate binding. The enzyme dynamics involved in ATP+Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and EsxAB substrate recognition were identified and showed the enhanced stability of EccCb1 enzyme as a result of ligand binding. Overall, our structural and biochemical analysis showed the low-resolution structure and mechanism involved in ATPase activity and EsxAB substrate binding and dynamics involved in EsxAB substrate and ATP+Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; recognition. Overall, our structural and biochemical data on EccCb1 will contribute significantly in development of antivirulence inhibitors, which will prevent virulence factor secretion by &lt;italic&gt;M. tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; ESX-1 system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446396" rel="alternate" title="Structural and biochemical analysis of ATPase activity and EsxAB substrate binding of M. tuberculosis EccCb1 enzyme (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>