<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv biophysics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.783074+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biophysics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450193</id><title>Making high-dimensional molecular distribution functions tractable through Belief Propagation on Factor Graphs (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.783832+00:00</updated><author><name>Zachary Smith</name></author><author><name>Pratyush Tiwary</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations provide a wealth of high-dimensional data at all-atom and femtosecond resolution but deciphering mechanistic information from this data is an ongoing challenge in physical chemistry and biophysics. Theoretically speaking, joint probabilities of the equilibrium distribution contain all thermodynamic information, but they prove increasingly difficult to compute and interpret as the dimensionality increases. Here, inspired by tools in probabilistic graphical modeling, we develop a factor graph trained through belief propagation that helps factorize the joint probability into an approximate tractable form that can be easily visualized and used. We validate the study through the analysis of the conformational dynamics of two small peptides with 5 and 9 residues. Our validations include testing the conditional dependency predictions through an intervention scheme inspired by Judea Pearl. Secondly we directly use the belief propagation based approximate probability distribution as a high-dimensional static bias for enhanced sampling, where we achieve spontaneous back-and-forth motion between metastable states that is up to 350 times faster than unbiased MD. We believe this work opens up useful ways to thinking about and dealing with high-dimensional molecular simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450193" rel="alternate" title="Making high-dimensional molecular distribution functions tractable through Belief Propagation on Factor Graphs (12 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450034</id><title>MCX Cloud – a modern, scalable, high-performance and in-browser Monte Carlo simulation platform with cloud computing (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.784086+00:00</updated><author><name>Qianqian Fang</name></author><author><name>Shijie Yan</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the ample progress made towards faster and more accurate Monte Carlo (MC) simulation tools over the past decade, the limited usability and accessibility of these advanced modeling tools remain key barriers towards widespread use among the broad user community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;An open-source, high-performance, web-based MC simulator that builds upon modern cloud computing architectures is highly desirable to deliver state-of-the-art MC simulations and hardware acceleration to general users without the need for special hardware installation and optimization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Approach&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have developed a configuration-free, in-browser 3-D MC simulation platform – MCX Cloud – built upon an array of robust and modern technologies, including a Docker Swarm-based cloud-computing backend and a web-based graphical user interface (GUI) that supports in-browser 3-D visualization, asynchronous data communication, and automatic data validation via JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) schemas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The front-end of the MCX Cloud platform offers an intuitive simulation design, fast 3-D data rendering, and convenient simulation sharing. The Docker Swarm container orchestration backend is highly scalable and can support high-demand GPU MC simulations using Monte Carlo eXtreme (MCX) over a dynamically expandable virtual cluster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MCX Cloud makes fast, scalable, and feature-rich MC simulations readily available to all biophotonics researchers without overhead. It is fully open-source and can be freely accessed at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mcx.space/cloud"&gt;http://mcx.space/cloud&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450034" rel="alternate" title="MCX Cloud – a modern, scalable, high-performance and in-browser Monte Carlo simulation platform with cloud computing (6 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>