<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv biophysics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.619169+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/biophysics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.06.446989</id><title>Structural insights into the modes of relaxin-binding and tethered-agonist activation of RXFP1 and RXFP2 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.619454+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashish Sethi</name></author><author><name>Shoni Bruell</name></author><author><name>Tim Ryan</name></author><author><name>Fei Yan</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Tanipour</name></author><author><name>Yee-Foong Mok</name></author><author><name>Chris Draper-Joyce</name></author><author><name>Yogesh Khandokar</name></author><author><name>Riley D. Metcalfe</name></author><author><name>Michael D. W. Griffin</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Scott</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Akhter Hossain</name></author><author><name>Emma J. Petrie</name></author><author><name>Ross A. D. Bathgate</name></author><author><name>Paul R. Gooley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our poor understanding of the mechanism by which the peptide-hormone H2 relaxin activates its G protein coupled receptor, RXFP1 and the related receptor RXFP2, has hindered progress in its therapeutic development. Both receptors possess large ectodomains, which bind H2 relaxin, and contain an N-terminal LDLa module that is essential for receptor signalling and postulated to be a tethered agonist. Here, we show that a conserved motif (GDxxGWxxxF), C-terminal to the LDLa, is critical for receptor activity. Importantly, this motif adopts different structures in RXFP1 and RXFP2, suggesting distinct activation mechanisms. For RXFP1, the motif is flexible, weakly associates with the LDLa, and requires H2 relaxin binding to stabilize an active conformation. Conversely, the GDxxGWxxxF motif in RXFP2 is more closely associated with the LDLa, forming an essential binding interface for H2 relaxin. These differences in the activation mechanism will aid drug development targeting these receptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.06.446989" rel="alternate" title="Structural insights into the modes of relaxin-binding and tethered-agonist activation of RXFP1 and RXFP2 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Biophysics"/><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>