<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv molecular-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.728807+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450627</id><title>A Genetic Screen for Suppressors of Cryptic 5’ Splicing in C. elegans Reveals Roles for KIN17 and PRCC in Maintaining Both 5’ and 3’ Splice Site Identity (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.729874+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessie M.N.G. Lopez</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Osterhoudt</name></author><author><name>Catiana Holland Cartwright</name></author><author><name>Sol Katzman</name></author><author><name>Alan M. Zahler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pre-mRNA splicing is an essential step of eukaryotic gene expression carried out by a series of dynamic macromolecular protein/RNA complexes, known collectively and individually as the spliceosome. This series of spliceosomal complexes define, assemble on, and catalyze the removal of introns. Molecular model snapshots of intermediates in the process have been created from cryo-EM data, however, many aspects of the dynamic changes that occur in the spliceosome are not fully understood. &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; follow the GU-AG rule of splicing, with almost all introns beginning with 5’ GU and ending with 3’ AG. These splice sites are identified early in the splicing cycle, but as the cycle progresses and “custody” of the pre-mRNA splice sites is passed from factor to factor as the catalytic site is built, the mechanism by which splice site identity is maintained or re-established through these dynamic changes is unclear. We performed a genetic screen in &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; for factors that are capable of changing 5’ splice site choice. We report that KIN17 and PRCC are involved in splice site choice, the first functional splicing role proposed for either of these proteins. Previously identified suppressors of cryptic 5’ splicing promote distal cryptic GU splice sites, however, mutations in KIN17 and PRCC instead promote usage of an unusual proximal 5’ splice site which defines an intron beginning with UU, separated by 1nt from a GU donor. We performed high-throughput mRNA sequencing analysis and found that mutations in PRCC but not KIN17 changed 5’ splice sites genome-wide, promoting usage of nearby non-consensus sites. We further found that mutations in KIN17 and PRCC changed dozens of 3’ splice sites, promoting non-consensus sites upstream of canonical splice sites. Our work has uncovered both fine and coarse mechanisms by which the spliceosome maintains splice site identity during the complex assembly process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pre-mRNA splicing is an essential step of gene regulation, carried out by an unusual molecular machine, the spliceosome. Unlike other molecular machines, such as ribosomes, that simply assemble and catalyze chemical reactions, “the spliceosome” is a highly-dynamic cycle, carried out by 5 specialized small nuclear RNAs and over 100 proteins, which sequentially join, rearrange, and withdraw from the splicing assembly during each splicing cycle. These assemblies initially choose “splice sites” where the pre-mRNA will be cut, and then undergo multiple rearrangements to finally form the active site which catalyzes the splicing reactions which remove an intron from a pre-mRNA. We are currently in the midst of a “resolution revolution”, with ever-clearer cryo-EM snapshots of stalled complexes allowing researchers to visualize moments in time in the splicing cycle. These models are illuminating, but do not always elucidate mechanistic functioning, therefore our lab takes a complementary approach, using the power of genetics in a multicellular animal to gain functional insights into the spliceosome. Using a &lt;italic&gt;C .elegans&lt;/italic&gt; genetic screen, we have found novel functional splicing roles for two proteins, KIN17 and PRCC. Our results suggest that the spliceosome does not just rely on its initial identification of the splice site, but in a later step, re-identifies where to cut. We liken this two-stage identification to using a microscope by first using the coarse focus to find the area of interest, and then using the fine focus to adjust as needed. This work moves us closer to full mechanistic understanding of how the spliceosome chooses where to cut a pre-mRNA message.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450627" rel="alternate" title="A Genetic Screen for Suppressors of Cryptic 5’ Splicing in C. elegans Reveals Roles for KIN17 and PRCC in Maintaining Both 5’ and 3’ Splice Site Identity (14 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450569</id><title>Oxidative phosphorylation is required for powering motility and development of the sleeping sickness parasite Trypanosoma brucei within the tsetse fly vector (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.752101+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline E. Dewar</name></author><author><name>Aitor Casas-Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Constentin Dieme</name></author><author><name>Aline Crouzols</name></author><author><name>Lee R. Haines</name></author><author><name>Álvaro Acosta-Serrano</name></author><author><name>Brice Rotureau</name></author><author><name>Achim Schnaufer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The single-celled parasite &lt;italic&gt;Trypanosoma brucei&lt;/italic&gt; causes sleeping sickness in humans and nagana in livestock and is transmitted by hematophagous tsetse flies. Lifecycle progression from mammalian bloodstream form to tsetse midgut form and, subsequently, infective salivary gland form depends on complex developmental steps and migration within different fly tissues. As the parasite colonises the glucose-poor insect midgut, its ATP production is thought to depend on activation of mitochondrial amino acid catabolism via oxidative phosphorylation. This process involves respiratory chain complexes and the F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;F&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt;-ATP synthase, and it requires protein subunits of these complexes that are encoded in the parasite’s mitochondrial DNA (kinetoplast or kDNA). Here we show that a progressive loss of kDNA-encoded functions correlates with an increasingly impaired ability of &lt;italic&gt;T. brucei&lt;/italic&gt; to initiate and complete its development in the tsetse. First, parasites with a mutated F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;F&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt;-ATP synthase with a reduced capacity for oxidative phosphorylation can initiate differentiation from bloodstream to insect form, but they are unable to proliferate &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Unexpectedly, these cells can still colonise the tsetse midgut. However, these parasites exhibit a motility defect and are severely impaired in colonising or migrating to subsequent tsetse tissues. Second, parasites with a fully disrupted F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;F&lt;sub&gt;O&lt;/sub&gt;-ATP synthase complex that is completely unable to produce ATP by oxidative phosphorylation can still differentiate to the first insect stage &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; but die within a few days and cannot establish a midgut infection &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Third, mutant parasites lacking kDNA entirely can initiate differentiation but die within 24 h. Together, these three scenarios show that efficient ATP production via oxidative phosphorylation is not essential for initial colonisation of the tsetse vector, but it is required to power trypanosome migration within the fly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450569" rel="alternate" title="Oxidative phosphorylation is required for powering motility and development of the sleeping sickness parasite Trypanosoma brucei within the tsetse fly vector (11 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>