<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv molecular-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.414673+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445366</id><title>Cryo-ET reveals two major tubulin-based cytoskeleton structures in Toxoplasma gondii (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.415146+00:00</updated><author><name>Stella Y. Sun</name></author><author><name>Li-av Segev-Zarko</name></author><author><name>Muyuan Chen</name></author><author><name>Grigore D. Pintilie</name></author><author><name>Michael F. Schmid</name></author><author><name>Steven J. Ludtke</name></author><author><name>John C. Boothroyd</name></author><author><name>Wah Chiu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the obligate intracellular parasite, &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/italic&gt;, the subpellicular microtubules (SPMTs) help maintain shape, while the apical conoid (also tubulin-based) is implicated in invasion. Here, we use cryo-electron tomography to determine the molecular structures of the SPMTs and the conoid-fibrils (CFs) in vitrified and detergent-lysed parasites. Subvolume densities from detergent-extracted parasites yielded averaged density maps at subnanometer resolutions, and these were related back to their architecture &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;. An intraluminal spiral (IS) lines the interior of the 13-protofilament SPMTs, revealing a preferred orientation of these microtubules relative to the parasite’s long axis. Each CF is composed of 9 tubulin protofilaments, that produce a comma-shaped cross-section, plus additional associated components. Conoid protrusion, a crucial step in invasion, is associated with an altered pitch of each CF. The use of basic building blocks of protofilaments and different accessory proteins in one organism, illustrates the versatility of these critical structures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445366" rel="alternate" title="Cryo-ET reveals two major tubulin-based cytoskeleton structures in Toxoplasma gondii (17 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446202</id><title>Development and applications of sialoglycan-recognizing probes (SGRPs) with defined specificities: exploring the dynamic mammalian sialoglycome (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.415749+00:00</updated><author><name>Saurabh Srivastava</name></author><author><name>Andrea Verhagen</name></author><author><name>Aniruddha Sasmal</name></author><author><name>Brian R Wasik</name></author><author><name>Sandra Diaz</name></author><author><name>Hai Yu</name></author><author><name>Barbara A Bensing</name></author><author><name>Naazneen Khan</name></author><author><name>Zahra Khedri</name></author><author><name>Patrick Secrest</name></author><author><name>Paul Sullam</name></author><author><name>Nissi Varki</name></author><author><name>Xi Chen</name></author><author><name>Colin R Parrish</name></author><author><name>Ajit Varki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glycans that are abundantly displayed on vertebrate cell surface and secreted molecules are often capped with terminal sialic acids (Sias). These diverse 9-carbon-backbone monosaccharides are involved in numerous intrinsic biological processes. They also interact with commensals and pathogens, while undergoing dynamic changes in time and space, often influenced by environmental conditions. However, most of this sialoglycan complexity and variation remains poorly characterized by conventional techniques, which often tend to destroy or overlook crucial aspects of Sia diversity and/or fail to elucidate native structures in biological systems i.e., in the intact sialome. To date, in situ detection and analysis of sialoglycans has largely relied on the use of plant lectins, sialidases or antibodies, whose preferences (with certain exceptions) are limited and/or uncertain. We took advantage of naturally-evolved microbial molecules (bacterial adhesins, toxin subunits and viral hemagglutinin-esterases) that recognize sialoglycans with defined specificity to delineate 9 classes of Sialoglycan Recognizing Probes (SGRPs: SGRP1SGRP9) that can be used to explore mammalian sialome changes in a simple and systematic manner, using techniques common in most laboratories. SGRP candidates with specificity defined by sialoglycan microarray studies were engineered as tagged probes, each with a corresponding non-binding mutant probe as a simple and reliable negative control. The optimized panel of SGRPs can be used in methods commonly available in most bioscience labs, such as ELISA, Western Blot, flow cytometry and histochemistry. To demonstrate the utility of this approach, we provide examples of sialoglycome differences in tissues from C57BL/6 wild type mice and human-like Cmah-/- mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446202" rel="alternate" title="Development and applications of sialoglycan-recognizing probes (SGRPs) with defined specificities: exploring the dynamic mammalian sialoglycome (13 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>