<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv molecular-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.690530+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446434</id><title>Time-resolved cryo-EM visualizes ribosomal translocation with EF-G and GTP (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.691117+00:00</updated><author><name>Christine E. Carbone</name></author><author><name>Anna B. Loveland</name></author><author><name>Howard Gamper</name></author><author><name>Ya-Ming Hou</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Demo</name></author><author><name>Andrei A. Korostelev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During translation, a conserved GTPase elongation factor—EF-G in bacteria or eEF2 in eukaryotes—translocates tRNA and mRNA through the ribosome. EF-G has been proposed to act as a flexible motor that propels tRNA and mRNA movement, as a rigid pawl that biases unidirectional translocation resulting from ribosome rearrangements, or by various combinations of motor- and pawl-like mechanisms. Using time-resolved cryo-EM, we visualized GTP-catalyzed translocation without inhibitors, capturing elusive structures of ribosome•EF-G intermediates at near-atomic resolution. Prior to translocation, EF-G binds near peptidyl-tRNA, while the rotated 30S subunit stabilizes the EF-G GTPase center. Reverse 30S rotation releases Pi and translocates peptidyl-tRNA and EF-G by ∼20 Å. An additional 4-Å translocation initiates EF-G dissociation from a transient ribosome state with highly swiveled 30S head. The structures visualize how nearly rigid EF-G rectifies inherent and spontaneous ribosomal dynamics into tRNA-mRNA translocation, whereas GTP hydrolysis and Pi release drive EF-G dissociation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446434" rel="alternate" title="Time-resolved cryo-EM visualizes ribosomal translocation with EF-G and GTP (36 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446417</id><title>Systematic identification of a CDYL1-dependent decrease in lysine crotonylation at DNA double-strand break sites functionally uncouples transcriptional silencing and repair (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.692041+00:00</updated><author><name>Enas R. Abu-Zhayia</name></author><author><name>Feras E. Machour</name></author><author><name>Laila A. Bishara</name></author><author><name>Bella M. Ben-Oz</name></author><author><name>Nabieh Ayoub</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previously, we showed that CDYL1 is recruited to DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) to promote homology-directed repair (HDR) and foster transcriptional silencing. Yet, how CDYL1 elicits DSB-induced silencing is not fully understood. Here, we systematically identify a CDYL1-dependent local decrease in the transcriptionally active marks lysine crotonylation (PanKcr) and crotonylated histone residue H3K9cr at &lt;italic&gt;Asi&lt;/italic&gt;SI-induced DSBs, which correlates with transcriptional silencing. Mechanistically, we reveal that CDYL1 crotonyl-CoA hydratase activity counteracts PanKcr and H3K9cr at &lt;italic&gt;Asi&lt;/italic&gt;SI sites, which triggers the eviction of the transcriptional elongation factor ENL and foster transcriptional silencing. Furthermore, genetic inhibition of CDYL1 hydratase activity blocks the reduction in H3K9cr and alleviates DSB-induced silencing, while HDR efficiency unexpectedly remains intact. Therefore, our results functionally uncouple the repair and silencing activity of CDYL1 at DSBs. In a broader context, we address a long-standing question concerning the functional relationship between HDR and DSB-induced transcriptional silencing, suggesting that they may occur independently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systematic identification of a local decrease in lysine crotonylation PanKcr and H3K9cr at &lt;italic&gt;Asi&lt;/italic&gt;SI-induced DSBs that correlates with transcriptional silencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;CDYL1 crotonyl-CoA hydratase activity downregulates Kcr at DSBs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kcr reduction at DSBs promotes ENL eviction and fosters transcriptional silencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;CDYL1 roles in DSB-induced transcriptional silencing and HDR are functionally uncoupled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446417" rel="alternate" title="Systematic identification of a CDYL1-dependent decrease in lysine crotonylation at DNA double-strand break sites functionally uncouples transcriptional silencing and repair (12 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446896</id><title>RNA inhibits dMi-2/CHD4 chromatin binding and nucleosome remodelling (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.692436+00:00</updated><author><name>Ikram Ullah</name></author><author><name>Clemens Thoelken</name></author><author><name>Yichen Zhong</name></author><author><name>Mara John</name></author><author><name>Oliver Rossbach</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Lenz</name></author><author><name>Markus Großringer</name></author><author><name>Andrea Nist</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Stiewe</name></author><author><name>Roland Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Olalla Vazquez</name></author><author><name>Ho-Ryung Chung</name></author><author><name>Joel P Mackay</name></author><author><name>Alexander Brehm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ATP-dependent nucleosome remodeller Mi-2/CHD4 broadly modulates epigenetic landscapes to repress transcription and to maintain genome integrity. Here we use individual nucleotide resolution crosslinking and immunoprecipitation (iCLIP) to show that &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; Mi-2 associates with thousands of mRNA molecules &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Biochemical data reveal that recombinant dMi-2 preferentially binds to G-rich RNA molecules using two intrinsically disordered regions of previously undefined function. Pharmacological inhibition of transcription and RNase digestion approaches establish that RNA inhibits the association of dMi-2 with chromatin. We also show that RNA inhibits dMi-2-mediated nucleosome mobilization by competing with the nucleosome substrate. Importantly, this activity is shared by CHD4, the human homolog of dMi-2, strongly suggesting that RNA-mediated regulation of remodeller activity is an evolutionary conserved mechanism. Our data support a model in which RNA serves to protect actively transcribed regions of the genome from dMi-2/CHD4- mediated establishment of repressive chromatin structures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446896" rel="alternate" title="RNA inhibits dMi-2/CHD4 chromatin binding and nucleosome remodelling (10 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>