<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv molecular-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.819496+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448903</id><title>Structural basis for the context-specific action of classic peptidyl transferase inhibitors (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.820033+00:00</updated><author><name>Egor A. Syroegin</name></author><author><name>Laurin Flemmich</name></author><author><name>Dorota Klepacki</name></author><author><name>Nora Vazquez-Laslop</name></author><author><name>Ronald Micura</name></author><author><name>Yury S. Polikanov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ribosome-targeting antibiotics serve both as powerful antimicrobials and as tools for studying the ribosome. The ribosomal catalytic site, the peptidyl transferase center (PTC), is targeted by a large number of various drugs. The classical and best-studied PTC-acting antibiotic chloramphenicol, as well as the newest clinically significant linezolid, were considered indiscriminate inhibitors of every round of peptide bond formation, presumably inhibiting protein synthesis by stalling ribosomes at every codon of every gene being translated. However, it was recently discovered that chloramphenicol or linezolid, and many other PTC-targeting drugs, preferentially arrest translation when the ribosome needs to polymerize particular amino acid sequences. The molecular mechanisms and structural bases that underlie this phenomenon of context-specific action of even the most basic ribosomal antibiotics, such as chloramphenicol, are unknown. Here we present high-resolution structures of ribosomal complexes, with or without chloramphenicol, carrying specific nascent peptides that support or negate the drug action. Our data suggest that specific amino acids in the nascent chains directly modulate the antibiotic affinity to the ribosome by either establishing specific interactions with the drug molecule or obstructing its placement in the binding site. The model that emerged from our studies rationalizes the critical importance of the penultimate residue of a growing peptide for the ability of the drug to stall translation and provides the first atomic-level understanding of context specificity of antibiotics that inhibit protein synthesis by acting upon the PTC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448903" rel="alternate" title="Structural basis for the context-specific action of classic peptidyl transferase inhibitors (11 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>