<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv molecular-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.751706+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/molecular-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451483</id><title>Dynamics in Fip1 regulate eukaryotic mRNA 3'-end processing (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.752374+00:00</updated><author><name>Ananthanarayanan Kumar</name></author><author><name>Conny W.H. Yu</name></author><author><name>Juan B. Rodríguez-Molina</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Han Li</name></author><author><name>Stefan MV Freund</name></author><author><name>Lori A Passmore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cleavage and polyadenylation factor (CPF/CPSF) is a multiprotein complex essential for mRNA 3’-end processing in eukaryotes. It contains an endonuclease that cleaves pre-mRNAs, and a polymerase that adds a poly(A) tail onto the cleaved 3’-end. Several CPF subunits, including Fip1, contain intrinsically-disordered regions (IDRs). IDRs within multiprotein complexes can be flexible, or can become ordered upon interaction with binding partners. Here, we show that yeast Fip1 anchors the poly(A) polymerase Pap1 onto CPF via an interaction with zinc finger 4 of another CPF subunit, Yth1. We also reconstitute a fully recombinant 850-kDa CPF. By incorporating selectively-labelled Fip1 into recombinant CPF, we could study the dynamics of this single protein within the megadalton complex using nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy (NMR). This reveals that a Fip1 IDR that connects the Yth1- and Pap1-binding sites remains highly dynamic within CPF. Together, our data suggest that Fip1 dynamics mediate conformational transitions within the 3’-end processing machinery to coordinate cleavage and polyadenylation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451483" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics in Fip1 regulate eukaryotic mRNA 3'-end processing (24 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451174</id><title>Antisense-mediated repression of SAGA-dependent genes involves the HIR histone chaperone (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.752759+00:00</updated><author><name>Julien Soudet</name></author><author><name>Nissrine Beyrouthy</name></author><author><name>Anna Marta Pastucha</name></author><author><name>Andrea Maffioletti</name></author><author><name>Zahra Bakir</name></author><author><name>Françoise Stutz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Eukaryotic genomes are pervasively transcribed by RNA polymerase II (RNAPII), and transcription of long non-coding RNAs often overlaps with coding gene promoters. This might lead to coding gene repression in a process named Transcription Interference (TI). In &lt;italic&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/italic&gt;), TI is mainly driven by antisense non-coding transcription and occurs through re-shaping of promoter Nucleosome-Depleted Regions (NDRs). In this study, we developed a genetic screen to identify new players involved in Antisense-Mediated Transcription Interference (AMTI). Among the candidates, we found the HIR histone chaperone complex known to be involved in &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; histone deposition. Using genome-wide approaches, we reveal that HIR-dependent histone deposition represses the promoters of SAGA-dependent genes &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; antisense non-coding transcription. However, while antisense transcription is enriched at promoters of SAGA-dependent genes, this feature is not sufficient to define the mode of gene regulation. We further show that the balance between HIR-dependent nucleosome incorporation and transcription factor binding at promoters directs transcription into a SAGA- or TFIID-dependent regulation. This study sheds light on a new connection between antisense non-coding transcription and the nature of coding transcription initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451174" rel="alternate" title="Antisense-mediated repression of SAGA-dependent genes involves the HIR histone chaperone (7 tweets)"/><category term="Molecular Biology"/><published>2021-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>