<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.259253+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.468420</id><title>Plasticity of extrachromosomal and intrachromosomal BRAF amplifications in mediating targeted therapy dosage challenges (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.259580+00:00</updated><author><name>Kai Song</name></author><author><name>Jenna K. Minami</name></author><author><name>William P. Crosson</name></author><author><name>Jesus Salazar</name></author><author><name>Eli Pazol</name></author><author><name>Niroshi T. Senaratne</name></author><author><name>Nagesh Rao</name></author><author><name>Kim Paraiso</name></author><author><name>Thomas G. Graeber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer cells display two modes of focal amplifications (FAs), extrachromosomal DNA/double-minutes (ecDNA/DMs) and intrachromosomal homogenously staining regions (HSRs). Understanding the plasticity of these two modes is critical for preventing targeted therapy resistance. We developed a combined BRAF plus MEK inhibitor resistance melanoma model that bears high BRAF amplifications through both DM and HSR modes, and investigated FA dynamics in the context of drug resistance plasticity. Cells harboring FAs displayed mode switching between DMs and HSRs, from both de novo genetic changes and selection of preexisting subpopulations. We found that copy number plasticity is not exclusive to DMs. Single cell-derived clones with HSRs also exhibit BRAF copy number and corresponding HSR length plasticity that allows them to respond to dose reduction and recover from drug addiction. Upon kinase inhibitor escalation, we observed reproducible selection for cells with BRAF kinase domain duplications residing on DMs. In sum, the plasticity of FAs allows cancer cells to respond to drug dose changes through a myriad of mechanisms. These mechanisms include increases or decreases in DMs, shortening of HSRs, acquisition of secondary resistance mechanisms, and expression of alternative slicing oncogene variants. These results highlight the challenges in targeting the cellular vulnerabilities tied to focal amplifications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding the dynamics of oncogene amplifications is critical for appreciating tumorigenesis and preventing anticancer drug resistance. We found melanoma cells harboring BRAF amplifications in either DM or HSR formats to have high plasticity under different kinase inhibitor dosage challenges with evidence supporting de novo alterations, clonal selection, and coupling to additional resistance mechanisms. In in the absence of DMs, HSRs can offer comparable levels of plasticity as DMs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.468420" rel="alternate" title="Plasticity of extrachromosomal and intrachromosomal BRAF amplifications in mediating targeted therapy dosage challenges (54 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469456</id><title>NetrinG1+ cancer-associated fibroblasts generate unique extracellular vesicles that support the survival of pancreatic cancer cells under nutritional stress (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.259787+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristopher S. Raghavan</name></author><author><name>Ralph Francescone</name></author><author><name>Janusz Franco-Barraza</name></author><author><name>Jaye C. Gardiner</name></author><author><name>Débora Barbosa Vendramini-Costa</name></author><author><name>Tiffany Luong</name></author><author><name>Narges Pourmandi</name></author><author><name>Anthony Andren</name></author><author><name>Alison Kurimchak</name></author><author><name>Charline Ogier</name></author><author><name>James S. Duncan</name></author><author><name>Costas A. Lyssiotis</name></author><author><name>Lucia R. Languino</name></author><author><name>Edna Cukierman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is projected that, in 5 years, pancreatic cancer will become the second deadliest cancer in the United States. A unique aspect of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) is its stroma; rich in cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAFs) and a dense CAF-generated extracellular matrix (ECM). This fibrous stroma, known as desmoplasia, causes the collapse of local blood vessels rendering a nutrient-deprived milieu. Hence, PDAC cells are nurtured by local CAF-secreted products, which include, among others, CAF-generated small extracellular vesicles (sEVs). It is well-accepted that upon culturing functionally tumor-promoting CAFs under pathophysiological-relevant conditions (e.g., within self-produced ECM), these cells express NetrinG1 (NetG1) and sustain endosomal pools rich in active α5β1-integrin; traits indicative of poor patient survival. We herein report that NetG1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CAFs generate sEVs that rescue PDAC cells from nutrient-deprived induced apoptosis. Two unique sEVs, NetG1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and α5β1-integrin&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;, were uncovered. The former constitutes cargo of CAF-generated exomeres, and the latter is detected in classic exosomes. Proteomic and metabolomic analyses showed that the sEV-dependent PDAC survival is, at least in part, dictated by the cargo packaged within sEVs in a NetG1-dependent manner. Indeed, despite producing a similar number of vesicles, selected key proteins and metabolites (e.g., glutamine) were incorporated within the unique sEVs. Finally, we found that NetG1 and α5β1-integrin were detected in sEVs collected from plasma of PDAC patients, while their concomitant levels were significantly lower in plasma of sex/age-matched healthy donors. The discovery of these tumor-supporting CAF sEVs opens a new investigative avenue in tumor-stroma interactions and stroma staging detection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469456" rel="alternate" title="NetrinG1+ cancer-associated fibroblasts generate unique extracellular vesicles that support the survival of pancreatic cancer cells under nutritional stress (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469535</id><title>EZH2 inhibition in glioblastoma stem cells increases the expression of neuronal genes and the neuronal developmental regulators ZIC2, ZNF423 and MAFB (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.260143+00:00</updated><author><name>Bnar Abdul Kader</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Distefano</name></author><author><name>Katherine L. West</name></author><author><name>Adam G. West</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) is an aggressive brain cancer with a very poor prognosis. It has been shown that GBM stem cells within a GBM tumour have increased resistance to standard therapies, so new approaches are needed to increase the range of treatment options available. Here we use two GBM stem cell lines, representing the classical/pro-neural and mesenchymal GBM subtypes, to investigate the effects of three different EZH2 inhibitors on GBM stem cell survival and gene expression: EPZ6438, GSK343 and UNC1999. EZH2 is the catalytic component of the PRC2 chromatin repressor complex, which represses transcription through methylation of histone H3 at lysine 27. Both cell lines showed significantly reduced colony formation after 48-hour exposure to the inhibitors, indicating they were sensitive to all three EZH2 inhibitors. RNA-seq analysis revealed that all three EZH2 inhibitors led to increased expression of genes related to neurogenesis and/or neuronal structure in both GBM stem cell lines. Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP-Seq) was used to identify potential direct targets of the histone methylation activity of EZH2 that might be driving the increase in neuronal gene expression. Three genes were identified as candidate regulatory targets common to both cell lines: MAFB, ZIC2 and ZNF423. These transcription factors all have known roles in regulating neurogenesis, brain development and/or neuronal function. Through analysis of three different EZH2 inhibitors and two GBM stem cell lines, this study demonstrates a common underlying mechanism for how inhibition of EZH2 activity reduces GBM stem cell proliferation and survival.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469535" rel="alternate" title="EZH2 inhibition in glioblastoma stem cells increases the expression of neuronal genes and the neuronal developmental regulators ZIC2, ZNF423 and MAFB (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470089</id><title>Homologous recombination repair creates mutations in the non-coding genome that alter Topoisomerase-1 cleavage sites &amp; orchestrates irinotecan resistance (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.260280+00:00</updated><author><name>Santosh Kumar</name></author><author><name>Valid Gahramanov</name></author><author><name>Julia Yaglom</name></author><author><name>Shivani Patel</name></author><author><name>Lukasz Kaczmarczyk</name></author><author><name>Ivan Alexandrov</name></author><author><name>Gabi Gerlitz</name></author><author><name>Mali Salmon-Divon</name></author><author><name>Michael Y. Sherman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The selection of drug-resistant mammalian cell mutants requires multiple drug exposures. When cloned genetically identical cells are exposed to the drug, resistance is unlikely to result from the selection of pre-existent mutations. Therefore, adaptation must involve the generation of drug-resistant mutations de-novo. Understanding how adaptive mutations are generated and protect cells is important for our knowledge of cancer biology and evolution. Here, we studied the adaptation of cancer cells to topoisomerase (Top1) inhibitor irinotecan, which triggers DNA breaks, resulting in cytotoxicity. The resistance mechanism was based on the gradual accumulation of hundreds of thousands of recurrent mutations in non-coding DNA at sequence-specific Top1 cleavage sites. Repair of DSBs at these sites following initial irinotecan exposures created mutant sequences that were resistant to further Top1 cleavage. Therefore, by creating DNA breaks Top1 increases the rate of highly protective mutations specifically at such spots, thus explaining a puzzling need of dose escalation in resistance development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470089" rel="alternate" title="Homologous recombination repair creates mutations in the non-coding genome that alter Topoisomerase-1 cleavage sites &amp; orchestrates irinotecan resistance (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469962</id><title>Deciphering heterogeneity of circulating epithelial cells in breast cancer patients (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.260436+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxim E. Menyailo</name></author><author><name>Viktoria R. Zainullina</name></author><author><name>Liubov A. Tashireva</name></author><author><name>Sofia Yu. Zolotareva</name></author><author><name>Tatiana S. Gerashchenko</name></author><author><name>Vladimir V. Alifanov</name></author><author><name>Olga E. Savelieva</name></author><author><name>Evgeniya S. Grigoryeva</name></author><author><name>Nataliya A. Tarabanovskaya</name></author><author><name>Nataliya O. Popova</name></author><author><name>Anna A. Khozyainova</name></author><author><name>Evgeny L. Choinzonov</name></author><author><name>Nadezhda V. Cherdyntseva</name></author><author><name>Vladimir M. Perelmuter</name></author><author><name>Evgeny V. Denisov</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Circulating tumor cells (CTCs) and tumor hybrid cells, being the leading players in metastasis, have prognostic relevance and are potential antimetastatic targets. CTCs are identified as epithelial-positive and CD45 (leukocyte)-negative cells, whereas tumor hybrid cells usually have epithelial and leukocyte components. However, epithelial and hybrid cells are also observed in healthy subjects that complicate the detection of CTCs and tumor hybrid cells in cancer patients. This study evaluated the diversity of CD45-negative and CD45-positive circulating epithelial cells (CECs) in breast cancer patients (n=20) using single-cell RNA sequencing. We also tried to detect CTCs and tumor hybrid cells among CD45&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; CECs and CD45&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CECs by analyzing DNA ploidy since aneuploidy is a hallmark of cancer cells. Aneuploid cells were predominantly detected in CD45&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; CECs, whereas CD45&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CECs were mainly diploid. Most transcriptional cancer features, including many cancer-associated signaling pathways, were specific to aneuploid cells of one CD45&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; CEC cluster. These cells were also enriched by platelet genes and signaling pathways that may indicate their increased potential to adhere with thrombocytes. In CD45&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CECs, only one cluster had many aneuploid cells that were surprisingly negative for transcriptional cancer features. Thus, CD45&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; and CD45&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CECs are highly heterogeneous in breast cancer patients and consist of transcriptionally-distinct cell populations with varying degrees of DNA ploidy where aneuploid cells are likely CTCs and tumor hybrid cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469962" rel="alternate" title="Deciphering heterogeneity of circulating epithelial cells in breast cancer patients (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469674</id><title>Interplay of adherens junctions and matrix proteolysis determines the invasive pattern and growth of squamous cell carcinoma (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.260625+00:00</updated><author><name>Takuya Kato</name></author><author><name>Robert P. Jenkins</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Derzsi</name></author><author><name>Melda Tozluoglu</name></author><author><name>Antonio Rullan</name></author><author><name>Steven Hooper</name></author><author><name>Raphael A. G. Chaleil</name></author><author><name>Xiao Fu</name></author><author><name>Holly Joyce</name></author><author><name>Selvam Thavaraj</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Bates</name></author><author><name>Erik Sahai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancers, such as squamous cell carcinoma, frequently invade as multicellular units. However, these invading units can be organized in a variety of ways, ranging from thin discontinuous strands to thick ‘pushing’ collectives. Here we employ an integrated experimental and computational approach to identify the factors that determine the mode of collective cancer cell invasion. We find that matrix proteolysis is linked to the formation of wide strands, but has little effect on the maximum extent of invasion. Cell-cell junctions also favour wide strands, but our analysis also reveals a requirement for cell-cell junctions for efficient invasion in response to uniform directional cues. Unexpectedly, the ability to generate wide invasive strands is coupled to the ability to grow effectively when surrounded by ECM in 3D assays. Combinatorial perturbation of both matrix proteolysis and cell-cell adhesion demonstrates that the most aggressive cancer behaviour, both in terms of invasion and growth, is achieved at high levels of cell-cell adhesion and high levels of proteolysis. Contrary to expectation, cells with canonical mesenchymal traits – no cell-cell junctions and high proteolysis – exhibit reduced growth and lymph node metastasis. Thus, we conclude that the ability of squamous cell carcinoma cells to invade effectively is also linked to their ability to generate space for proliferation in confined contexts. These data provide an explanation for the apparent advantage of retaining cell-cell junctions in SCC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469674" rel="alternate" title="Interplay of adherens junctions and matrix proteolysis determines the invasive pattern and growth of squamous cell carcinoma (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470260</id><title>Oncogenic RAS commandeers amino acid sensing machinery to aberrantly activate mTORC1 in multiple myeloma (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.260794+00:00</updated><author><name>Yandan Yang</name></author><author><name>Thomas Oellerich</name></author><author><name>Ping Chen</name></author><author><name>Arnold Bolomsky</name></author><author><name>Michele Ceribelli</name></author><author><name>Bjorn Haupl</name></author><author><name>George W. Wright</name></author><author><name>James D. Phelan</name></author><author><name>Da Wei Huang</name></author><author><name>James W. Lord</name></author><author><name>Callie K. Van Winkle</name></author><author><name>Xin Yu</name></author><author><name>Jan Wisnieski</name></author><author><name>James Q. Wang</name></author><author><name>Frances A. Tosto</name></author><author><name>Erin Beck</name></author><author><name>Kelli Wilson</name></author><author><name>Crystal McKnight</name></author><author><name>Jameson Travers</name></author><author><name>Carleen Klumpp-Thomas</name></author><author><name>Grace A. Smith</name></author><author><name>Stefania Pittaluga</name></author><author><name>Irina Maric</name></author><author><name>Dickran Kazandjian</name></author><author><name>Craig J. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Ryan M. Young</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oncogenic mutations within the RAS pathway are common in multiple myeloma (MM), an incurable malignancy of plasma cells.  However, the mechanisms of pathogenic RAS signaling in this disease remain enigmatic and difficult to inhibit therapeutically.  We employed an unbiased proteogenomic approach to dissect RAS signaling in MM by combining genome-wide CRISPR-Cas9 screening with quantitative mass spectrometry focused on RAS biology.  We discovered that mutant isoforms of RAS organized a signaling complex with the amino acid transporter, SLC3A2, and MTOR on endolysosomes, which directly activated mTORC1 by co-opting amino acid sensing pathways.  MM tumors with high expression of mTORC1-dependent genes were more aggressive and enriched in RAS mutations, and we detected interactions between RAS and MTOR in MM patient tumors harboring mutant RAS isoforms.  Inhibition of RAS-dependent mTORC1 activity synergized with MEK and ERK inhibitors to quench pathogenic RAS signaling in MM cells.  This study redefines the RAS pathway in MM and provides a mechanistic and rational basis to target this novel mode of RAS signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470260" rel="alternate" title="Oncogenic RAS commandeers amino acid sensing machinery to aberrantly activate mTORC1 in multiple myeloma (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.468946</id><title>FLI1 and FRA1 transcription factors drive the transcriptional regulatory networks characterizing muscle invasive bladder cancer (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.261043+00:00</updated><author><name>Perihan Yagmur Guneri-Sozeri</name></author><author><name>Gulden Ozden Yilmaz</name></author><author><name>Asli Kisim</name></author><author><name>Aleyna Eray</name></author><author><name>Hamdiye Uzuner</name></author><author><name>Gökhan Karakülah</name></author><author><name>Devrim Pesen Okvur</name></author><author><name>Serif Senturk</name></author><author><name>Serap Erkek-Ozhan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bladder cancer is mostly present in the form of urothelium carcinoma, causing over 150.000 deaths each year. Its histopathological classification as muscle invasive (MIBC) and non-muscle invasive (NMIBC) is the most prominent aspect, affecting the prognosis and progression of this disease. In this study, we defined the active regulatory landscape of MIBC and NMIBC cell lines using H3K27ac-seq and used an integrative data approach to combine our findings with existing data. Our analysis revealed FRA1 and FLI1 as the two critical transcription factors differentially regulating MIBC regulatory landscape. Importantly, we show that FRA1 and FLI1 regulate the genes involved in epithelial cell migration and cell junction organization. Knock-down of FRA1 and FLI1 in MIBC revealed the downregulation of several EMT-related genes such as &lt;italic&gt;MAP4K4&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;FLOT1&lt;/italic&gt;. Further, ChIP-SICAP performed for FRA1 and FLI1 enabled us to infer chromatin binding partners of these two transcription factors and link this information with their target genes, providing a comprehensive regulatory circuit for the genes implicated in invasive ability of the bladder cancer cells. Finally, for the first time we show that knock-down of FRA1 and FRA1-FLI1 double knock-down results in significant reduction of invasion capacity of MIBC cells towards muscle microenvironment using IC-CHIP assays. Our results collectively highlight the role of these two transcription factors in invasive characteristics of bladder cancer in selection and design of targeted options for treatment of MIBC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.468946" rel="alternate" title="FLI1 and FRA1 transcription factors drive the transcriptional regulatory networks characterizing muscle invasive bladder cancer (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469612</id><title>Copy number alterations and epithelial-mesenchymal transition genes in diffuse and intestinal gastric cancers in Mexican patients (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.261198+00:00</updated><author><name>Violeta Larios-Serrato</name></author><author><name>José-Darío Martínez-Ezquerro</name></author><author><name>Hilda-Alicia Valdez-Salazar</name></author><author><name>Javier Torres</name></author><author><name>Margarita Camorlinga-Ponce</name></author><author><name>Patricia Piña-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Martha-Eugenia Ruiz-Tachiquín</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gastric cancer (GC) is a malignancy with the highest mortality among diseases of the digestive system worldwide. The study of GC-alterations is crucial to understand tumor biology, to establish important aspects of cancer prognosis and treatment response. Here, we purified DNA and performed whole-genome analysis with high-density arrays in samples from Mexican patients diagnosed with GC: diffuse (DGC) or intestinal (IGC), or non-atrophic gastritis (NAG) samples that served as controls. We identified shared and unique copy number alterations (CNA) between these altered tissues involving key genes and signaling pathways associated with cancer, allowing their molecular distinction and identification of the most relevant molecular functions impacted. When focused on epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) genes, our bioinformatic analysis revealed that the altered network associated with chromosomal alterations included 11 genes shared between DGC, IGC, and NAG, as well as 19 DGC- and 7 IGC-exclusive genes, whose main molecular functions included adhesion, angiogenesis, migration, metastasis, morphogenesis, proliferation, and survival. This study presents the first whole-genome high-density array study in GC from Mexican patients and reveals shared and exclusive CNA-genes in DGC and IGC. In addition, we provide a bioinformatically predicted network focused on CNA-altered genes involved in the EMT, associated with the hallmarks of cancer, as well as precancerous alterations that could lead to gastric cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Implications&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Molecular signatures of diffuse and intestinal GC, predicted bioinformatically, involve common and distinct CNA-EMT genes related to the hallmarks of cancer that are potential candidates for screening GC biomarkers, including early stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469612" rel="alternate" title="Copy number alterations and epithelial-mesenchymal transition genes in diffuse and intestinal gastric cancers in Mexican patients (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469785</id><title>Ribonucleotide Reductase Regulatory Subunit M2 as a Driver of Glioblastoma TMZ-Resistance through Modulation of dNTP Production (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.261340+00:00</updated><author><name>Ella N Perrault</name></author><author><name>Jack M Shireman</name></author><author><name>Eunus S Ali</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Preddy</name></author><author><name>Peiyu Lin</name></author><author><name>Cheol Park</name></author><author><name>Luke Tomes</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Zolp</name></author><author><name>Shreya Budhiraja</name></author><author><name>Shivani Baisiwala</name></author><author><name>C. David James</name></author><author><name>Issam Ben-Sahra</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Pott</name></author><author><name>Anindita Basu</name></author><author><name>Atique U Ahmed</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma (GBM) remains one of the most resistant and fatal forms of cancer. Previous studies have examined primary and recurrent GBM tumors, but it is difficult to study tumor evolution during therapy where resistance develops. To investigate this, we performed an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; single-cell RNA sequencing screen in a patient-derived xenograft (PDX) model. Primary GBM was modeled by mice treated with DMSO control, recurrent GBM was modeled by mice treated with temozolomide (TMZ), and during therapy GBM was modeled by mice euthanized after two of five TMZ treatments. Our analysis revealed the cellular population present during therapy to be distinct from primary and recurrent GBM. We found the Ribonucleotide Reductase gene family to exhibit a unique signature in our data due to an observed subunit switch to favor RRM2 during therapy. GBM cells were shown to rely on RRM2 during therapy causing RRM2-knockdown (KD) cells to be TMZ-sensitive. Using targeted metabolomics, we found RRM2-KDs to produce less dGTP and dCTP than control cells in response to TMZ (&lt;italic&gt;p&amp;lt;0.0001&lt;/italic&gt;). Supplementing RRM2-KDs with deoxycytidine and deoxyguanosine rescued TMZ-sensitivity, suggesting an RRM2-driven mechanism of chemoresistance, established by regulating the production of these nucleotides. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, tumor-bearing mice treated with the RRM2-inhibitor, Triapine, in combination with TMZ, survived longer than mice treated with TMZ alone (&lt;italic&gt;p&amp;lt;0.01&lt;/italic&gt;), indicating promising clinical opportunities in targeting RRM2. Our data present a novel understanding of RRM2 activity, and its alteration during therapeutic stress as response to TMZ-induced DNA damage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469785" rel="alternate" title="Ribonucleotide Reductase Regulatory Subunit M2 as a Driver of Glioblastoma TMZ-Resistance through Modulation of dNTP Production (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>