<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.205940+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.464824</id><title>Transcriptional variability accelerates pre-leukemia by cell diversification and perturbation of protein synthesis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.206614+00:00</updated><author><name>Shikha Gupta</name></author><author><name>Oliver M. Dovey</name></author><author><name>Ana Filipa Domingues</name></author><author><name>Oliwia W. Cyran</name></author><author><name>Caitlin M. Cash</name></author><author><name>George Giotopoulos</name></author><author><name>Justyna Rak</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Cooper</name></author><author><name>Malgorzata Gozdecka</name></author><author><name>Ryan J. Asby</name></author><author><name>Noor Al-Jabery</name></author><author><name>Victor Hernandez-Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Sudhakaran Prabakaran</name></author><author><name>Brian J. Huntly</name></author><author><name>George S. Vassiliou</name></author><author><name>Cristina Pina</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Transcriptional variability facilitates stochastic cell diversification and can in turn underpin adaptation to stress or injury. We hypothesize that it may analogously facilitate progression of pre-malignancy to cancer. To investigate this, we initiated pre-leukemia in mouse cells with enhanced transcriptional variability due to conditional disruption of the histone lysine acetyltransferase gene &lt;italic&gt;Kat2a&lt;/italic&gt;. By combining single-cell RNA-sequencing of pre-leukemia with functional analysis of transformation, we show that &lt;italic&gt;Kat2a&lt;/italic&gt; loss results in global variegation of cell identity and accumulation of pre-leukemic cells. Leukemia progression is subsequently facilitated by destabilization of ribosome biogenesis and protein synthesis, which confer a transient transformation advantage. The contribution of transcriptional variability to early cancer evolution reflects a generic role in promoting cell fate transitions, which, in the case of well-adapted malignancies, contrastingly differentiates and depletes cancer stem cells. In other words, transcriptional variability confers forward momentum to cell fate systems, with differential multi-stage impact throughout cancer evolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss of Kat2a enhances transcriptional variability of ribosome biosynthetic programs and transiently accelerates pre-leukemia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.464824" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional variability accelerates pre-leukemia by cell diversification and perturbation of protein synthesis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>