<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.396377+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473565</id><title>Recurrence of cancer cell states across diverse tumors and their interactions with the microenvironment (130 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.397077+00:00</updated><author><name>Dalia Barkley</name></author><author><name>Reuben Moncada</name></author><author><name>Maayan Pour</name></author><author><name>Deborah A. Liberman</name></author><author><name>Ian Dryg</name></author><author><name>Gregor Werba</name></author><author><name>Wei Wang</name></author><author><name>Maayan Baron</name></author><author><name>Anjali Rao</name></author><author><name>Bo Xia</name></author><author><name>Gustavo S. França</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Weil</name></author><author><name>Deborah F. Delair</name></author><author><name>Cristina Hajdu</name></author><author><name>Amanda W. Lund</name></author><author><name>Iman Osman</name></author><author><name>Itai Yanai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While genetic tumor heterogeneity has long been recognized, recent work has revealed significant variation among cancer cells at the epigenetic and transcriptional levels. Profiling tumors at the single-cell level in individual cancer types has shown that transcriptional heterogeneity is organized into cancer cell states, implying that diverse cell states may represent stable and functional units with complementary roles in tumor maintenance and progression. However, it remains unclear to what extent these states span tumor types, constituting general features of cancer. Furthermore, the role of cancer cell states in tumor progression and their specific interactions with cells of the tumor microenvironment remain to be elucidated. Here, we perform a pan-cancer single-cell RNA-Seq analysis across 15 cancer types and identify a catalog of 16 gene modules whose expression defines recurrent cancer cell states, including ‘stress’, ‘interferon response’, ‘epithelial-mesenchymal transition’, ‘metal response’, ‘basal’ and ‘ciliated’. Using mouse models, we find that induction of the interferon response module varies by tumor location and is diminished upon elimination of lymphocytes. Moreover, spatial transcriptomic analysis further links the interferon response in cancer cells to T cells and macrophages in the tumor microenvironment. Our work provides a framework for studying how cancer cell states interact with the tumor microenvironment to form organized systems capable of immune evasion, drug resistance, and metastasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473565" rel="alternate" title="Recurrence of cancer cell states across diverse tumors and their interactions with the microenvironment (130 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473393</id><title>Electrical activity between skin cells regulates melanoma initiation (100 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.397757+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohita Tagore</name></author><author><name>Emiliano Hergenreder</name></author><author><name>Shruthy Suresh</name></author><author><name>Maayan Baron</name></author><author><name>Sarah C. Perlee</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Melendez</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Hollmann</name></author><author><name>Trey Ideker</name></author><author><name>Lorenz Studer</name></author><author><name>Richard M. White</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oncogenes can only initiate tumors in certain cellular contexts, which is referred to as oncogenic competence. In melanoma, whether cells in the microenvironment can endow such competence remains unclear. Using a combination of zebrafish transgenesis coupled with human tissues, we demonstrate that GABAergic signaling between keratinocytes and melanocytes promotes melanoma initiation by BRAF&lt;sup&gt;V600E&lt;/sup&gt;. GABA is synthesized in melanoma cells, which then acts on GABA-A receptors on keratinocytes. Electron microscopy demonstrates synapse-like structures between keratinocytes and melanoma cells, and multi-electrode array analysis shows that GABA acts to inhibit electrical activity in melanoma/keratinocyte co-cultures. Genetic and pharmacologic perturbation of GABA synthesis abrogates melanoma initiation in vivo. These data suggest that electrical activity across the skin microenvironment determines the ability of oncogenes to initiate melanoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473393" rel="alternate" title="Electrical activity between skin cells regulates melanoma initiation (100 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473423</id><title>Endothelial Rbpj is essential for the education of tumour-associated macrophages (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.398471+00:00</updated><author><name>Ronja Mülfarth</name></author><author><name>Elisenda Alsina-Sanchis</name></author><author><name>Iris Moll</name></author><author><name>Sarah Böhn</name></author><author><name>Lena Wiedmann</name></author><author><name>Lorea Jordana</name></author><author><name>Tara Ziegelbauer</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline Taylor</name></author><author><name>Francesca De Angelis Rigotti</name></author><author><name>Adrian Stögbauer</name></author><author><name>Benedetto Daniele Giaimo</name></author><author><name>Adelheid Cerwenka</name></author><author><name>Tilman Borggrefe</name></author><author><name>Andreas Fischer</name></author><author><name>Juan Rodriguez-Vita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epithelial ovarian cancer (EOC) is one of the most lethal gynaecological cancers worldwide. EOC cells educate tumour-associated macrophages (TAMs) through CD44-mediated cholesterol depletion to generate an immunosuppressive tumour microenvironment (TME). In addition, tumour cells frequently activate Notch1 receptors on endothelial cells (ECs) to facilitate metastasis. However, little is known whether the endothelium would also influence the education of recruited monocytes. Here, we report that canonical Notch signalling through RBPJ in ECs is an important player in the education of TAMs and EOC progression. Deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Rbpj&lt;/italic&gt; in the endothelium of adult mice reduced infiltration of monocyte-derived macrophages into the TME of EOC and prevented the acquisition of a typical TAM gene signature. This was associated with stronger cytotoxic activity of T cells and decreased tumour burden. Mechanistically, we identified CXCL2 as a novel Notch/RBPJ target gene. This angiocrine factor regulates the expression of CD44 on monocytes and subsequent cholesterol depletion of TAMs. Bioinformatic analysis of ovarian cancer patient data showed that increased CXCL2 expression is accompanied by higher expression of CD44 and TAM education. As such, EOC cells employ the tumour endothelium to secrete CXCL2 in order to facilitate an immunosuppressive microenvironment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473423" rel="alternate" title="Endothelial Rbpj is essential for the education of tumour-associated macrophages (28 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473663</id><title>SerpinB3 drives cancer stem cell survival in glioblastoma (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.399384+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam Lauko</name></author><author><name>Josephine Volovetz</name></author><author><name>Soumya M. Turaga</name></author><author><name>Defne Bayik</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Silver</name></author><author><name>Kelly Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Erin E. Mulkearns-Hubert</name></author><author><name>Dionysios C. Watson</name></author><author><name>Kiran Desai</name></author><author><name>Manav Midha</name></author><author><name>Jing Hao</name></author><author><name>Kathleen McCortney</name></author><author><name>Alicia Steffens</name></author><author><name>Ulhas Naik</name></author><author><name>Manmeet S. Ahluwalia</name></author><author><name>Shideng Bao</name></author><author><name>Craig Horbinski</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Yu</name></author><author><name>Justin D. Lathia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite therapeutic interventions for glioblastoma (GBM), cancer stem cells (CSCs) drive recurrence. The precise mechanisms underlying CSC therapeutic resistance, namely inhibition of cell death, are unclear. We built on previous observations that the high cell surface expression of junctional adhesion molecule-A drives CSC maintenance and identified downstream signaling networks, including the cysteine protease inhibitor SerpinB3. Using genetic depletion approaches, we found that SerpinB3 is necessary for CSC maintenance, survival, and tumor growth, as well as CSC pathway activation. The knockdown of SerpinB3 also increased apoptosis and susceptibility to radiation therapy. Mechanistically, SerpinB3 was essential to buffer cathepsin L-mediated cell death, which was enhanced with radiation. Finally, we found that SerpinB3 knockdown dramatically increased the efficacy of radiation in pre-clinical models. Taken together, our findings identify a novel GBM CSC-specific survival mechanism involving a previously uninvestigated cysteine protease inhibitor, SerpinB3, and provide a potential target to improve the efficacy of standard-of-care GBM therapies against therapeutically resistant CSCs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lauko et al. demonstrate a functional role for SerpinB3, which is elevated in glioblastoma cancer stem cells and protects against lysosomal-mediated cell death. SerpinB3 can be targeted to increase the efficacy of radiation in glioblastoma pre-clinical models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473663" rel="alternate" title="SerpinB3 drives cancer stem cell survival in glioblastoma (17 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267985</id><title>Validation of Genomic and Transcriptomic Models of Homologous Recombination Deficiency in a Real-World Pan-Cancer Cohort (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.400489+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Leibowitz</name></author><author><name>Bonnie V Dougherty</name></author><author><name>Joshua SK Bell</name></author><author><name>Joshuah Kapilivsky</name></author><author><name>Jackson Michuda</name></author><author><name>Andrew Sedgwick</name></author><author><name>Wesley Munson</name></author><author><name>Tushar Chandra</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R Dry</name></author><author><name>Nike Beaubier</name></author><author><name>Catherine Igartua</name></author><author><name>Timothy Taxter</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the introduction of DNA-damaging therapies into standard of care cancer treatment, there is a growing need for predictive diagnostics assessing homologous recombination deficiency (HRD) status across tumor types. Following the strong clinical evidence for the utility of DNA-sequencing-based HRD testing in ovarian cancer, and growing evidence in breast cancer, we present analytical validation of the Tempus|HRD-DNA test. We further developed, validated, and explored the Tempus|HRD-RNA model, which uses gene expression data from 16,470 RNA-seq samples to predict HRD status from formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor samples across numerous cancer types.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genomic and transcriptomic profiling was performed using next-generation sequencing from Tempus|xT, Tempus|xO, Tempus|xE, Tempus|RS, and Tempus|RS.v2 assays on 48,843 samples. Samples were labeled based on their &lt;italic&gt;BRCA1, BRCA2&lt;/italic&gt; and selected Homologous Recombination Repair (HRR) pathway gene (&lt;italic&gt;CDK12, PALB2, RAD51B, RAD51C, RAD51D&lt;/italic&gt;) mutational status to train and validate HRD-DNA, a genome-wide loss-of-heterozygosity biomarker, and HRD-RNA, a logistic regression model trained on gene expression, using several performance metrics and statistical tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a sample of 2,058 breast and 1,216 ovarian tumors, BRCA status was predicted by HRD-DNA with F1-scores of 0.98 and 0.96, respectively. Across an independent set of 1,363 samples across solid tumor types, the HRD-RNA model was predictive of BRCA status in prostate, pancreatic, and non-small cell lung cancer, with F1-scores of 0.88, 0.69, and 0.62, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We predict HRD-positive patients across many cancer types and believe both HRD models may generalize to other mechanisms of HRD outside of BRCA loss. HRD-RNA complements DNA-based HRD detection methods, especially for indications with low prevalence of BRCA alterations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.21267985" rel="alternate" title="Validation of Genomic and Transcriptomic Models of Homologous Recombination Deficiency in a Real-World Pan-Cancer Cohort (15 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473923</id><title>De novo serine biosynthesis from glucose predicts sex-specific response to antifolates in non-small cell lung cancer cell lines (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.401103+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasmin Sponagel</name></author><author><name>Siddhartha Devarakonda</name></author><author><name>Joshua B Rubin</name></author><author><name>Jingqin Luo</name></author><author><name>Joseph Edward Ippolito</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer-related death. Intriguingly, males with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), the most common type of lung cancer, have a higher mortality rate than females. Here, we investigated the role of serine metabolism as a predictive marker for sensitivity to the antifolate pemetrexed in male and female NSCLC cell lines. Using [13C6] glucose tracing in NSCLC cell lines, we found that male cells generated significantly more serine from glucose than female cells. Higher serine biosynthesis was further correlated with increased sensitivity to pemetrexed in male cells only. Concordant sex differences in metabolic gene expression were evident in NSCLC and pan-cancer transcriptome datasets, suggesting a potential mechanism with wide-reaching applicability. These data were further validated by integrating antifolate drug cytotoxicity and metabolic pathway transcriptome data from pan-cancer cell lines. Together, these findings highlight the importance of considering sex differences in cancer metabolism to improve treatment for all patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473923" rel="alternate" title="De novo serine biosynthesis from glucose predicts sex-specific response to antifolates in non-small cell lung cancer cell lines (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.472552</id><title>Antibodies to ILT3 abrogate myeloid immunosuppression and enable tumor killing (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.401822+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip E. Brandish</name></author><author><name>Anthony Palmieri</name></author><author><name>Gulesi Ayanoglu</name></author><author><name>Jeanne Baker</name></author><author><name>Raphael Bueno</name></author><author><name>Alan Byford</name></author><author><name>Michael Caniga</name></author><author><name>Craig Chappell</name></author><author><name>Holly Cherwinski</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Cua</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyan Du</name></author><author><name>Laurence Fayadat-Dilman</name></author><author><name>Brian E. Hall</name></author><author><name>Hassan Issafras</name></author><author><name>Barbara Joyce-Shaikh</name></author><author><name>Veronica Juan</name></author><author><name>Rachel D. Levy</name></author><author><name>Andrey Loboda</name></author><author><name>Jared Lunceford</name></author><author><name>Carl Mieczkowski</name></author><author><name>Michael Meehl</name></author><author><name>Yujie Qu</name></author><author><name>Michael Rosenzweig</name></author><author><name>Latika Singh</name></author><author><name>Peter Stivers</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Tramontozzi</name></author><author><name>Kimberly Vermilya</name></author><author><name>Karin Vroom</name></author><author><name>Douglas C. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Chungsheng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jie Zhang-Hoover</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tumor myeloid suppressor cells impede response to T cell checkpoint immunotherapy. Immunoglobulin-like transcript 3 (ILT3, gene name, &lt;italic&gt;LILRB4&lt;/italic&gt;) expressed on dendritic cells (DCs) promotes antigen-specific tolerance. Circulating monocytic MDSCs that express ILT3 have been linked to clinical outcomes and a soluble form of ILT3 is elevated in certain cancers. We find that &lt;italic&gt;LILRB4&lt;/italic&gt; expression is correlated with Gene Expression Profile of T-cell inflamed tumor microenvironment shown to be significantly associated with response to the anti-PD1 antibody pembrolizumab across several tumor types. A potent and selective anti-ILT3 mAb effectively antagonized IL-10 polarization of DCs and enabled T cell priming. In an MLR assay anti-ILT3 combined with pembrolizumab afforded greater CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell activation compared to either agent alone. Anti-ILT3 antibodies impaired the acquisition of a suppressive phenotype of monocytes co-cultured with SK-MEL-5 cancer cells, accompanied by a reduction in surface detection of peptidase inhibitor 16, a &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt; interaction candidate for ILT3. Growth of myeloid cell-abundant SK-MEL-5 tumors was abrogated by ILT3 blockade and remodeling of the immune tumor microenvironment was evident by CyTOF. These data support the testing of anti-ILT3 antibodies for the treatment of a wide range of solid tumors replete with myeloid cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.472552" rel="alternate" title="Antibodies to ILT3 abrogate myeloid immunosuppression and enable tumor killing (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472715</id><title>Urine and Fecal Microbiota in a Canine Model of Bladder Cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.402803+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Mrofchak</name></author><author><name>Christopher Madden</name></author><author><name>Morgan V. Evans</name></author><author><name>William C. Kisseberth</name></author><author><name>Deepika Dhawan</name></author><author><name>Deborah W. Knapp</name></author><author><name>Vanessa L. Hale</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Urothelial carcinoma (UC) is the tenth most diagnosed cancer in humans worldwide. Dogs are a robust model for invasive UC as tumor development and progression is similar in humans and dogs. Recent studies on urine microbiota in humans revealed alterations in microbial diversity and composition in individuals with UC; however, the potential role of microbiota in UC has yet to be elucidated. Dogs could be valuable models for this research, but microbial alterations in dogs with UC have not been evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The objective of this this pilot study was to compare the urine and fecal microbiota of dogs with UC (n = 7) and age-, sex-, and breed-matched healthy controls (n = 7).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNA was extracted from mid-stream free-catch urine and fecal samples using Qiagen Bacteremia and PowerFecal kits, respectively. 16S rRNA gene sequencing was performed followed by sequence processing and analyses (QIIME 2 and R).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Canine urine and fecal samples were dominated by taxa similar to those found in humans. Significantly decreased microbial diversity (Kruskal-Wallis: Shannon, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.048) and altered bacterial composition were observed in the urine but not feces of dogs with UC (PERMANOVA: Unweighted UniFrac, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.011). The relative abundances of &lt;italic&gt;Fusobacterium&lt;/italic&gt; was also increased, although not significantly, in the urine and feces of dogs with UC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study characterizes urine and fecal microbiota in dogs with UC, and it provides a foundation for future work exploring host-microbe dynamics in UC carcinogenesis, prognosis, and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472715" rel="alternate" title="Urine and Fecal Microbiota in a Canine Model of Bladder Cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>