<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.072682+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.461531</id><title>Sex Differences in Brain Tumor Glutamine Metabolism Reveal Sex-Specific Vulnerabilities to Treatment (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.073645+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasmin Sponagel</name></author><author><name>Jill K. Jones</name></author><author><name>Cheryl Frankfater</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Olivia Tung</name></author><author><name>Kevin Cho</name></author><author><name>Kelsey L. Tinkum</name></author><author><name>Hannah Gass</name></author><author><name>Elena Nunez</name></author><author><name>Douglas R. Spitz</name></author><author><name>Prakash Chinnaiyan</name></author><author><name>Jacob Schaefer</name></author><author><name>Gary J. Patti</name></author><author><name>Maya S. Graham</name></author><author><name>Audrey Mauguen</name></author><author><name>Milan Grkovski</name></author><author><name>Mark P. Dunphy</name></author><author><name>Simone Krebs</name></author><author><name>Jingqin Luo</name></author><author><name>Joshua B. Rubin</name></author><author><name>Joseph E. Ippolito</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex differences in normal metabolism are well described, but whether they persist in cancerous tissue is unknown. We assessed metabolite abundance in glioblastoma surgical specimens and found that male glioblastomas are enriched for amino acids, including glutamine. Using PET imaging, we found that gliomas in male patients exhibit significantly higher glutamine uptake. These sex differences were well-modeled in murine transformed astrocytes, in which male cells imported and metabolized more glutamine and were more sensitive to glutaminase 1 (GLS1) inhibition. The sensitivity to GLS1 inhibition in males was driven by their dependence on glutamine-derived glutamate for α-ketoglutarate synthesis and TCA cycle replenishment. Females were resistant to GLS1 inhibition through greater pyruvate carboxylase-mediated TCA cycle replenishment. Thus, clinically important sex differences exist in targetable elements of metabolism. Recognition of sex-biased metabolism is an opportunity to improve treatments for all patients through further laboratory and clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.461531" rel="alternate" title="Sex Differences in Brain Tumor Glutamine Metabolism Reveal Sex-Specific Vulnerabilities to Treatment (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462786</id><title>Chi3l1 is a modulator of glioma stem cell states and a therapeutic vulnerability for glioblastoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.074191+00:00</updated><author><name>Charlotte Guetta-Terrier</name></author><author><name>David Karambizi</name></author><author><name>Bedia Akosman</name></author><author><name>Jia-Shu Chen</name></author><author><name>Suchitra Kamle</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Fajardo</name></author><author><name>Andras Fiser</name></author><author><name>Ritambhara Singh</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Toms</name></author><author><name>Chun Geun Lee</name></author><author><name>Jack A. Elias</name></author><author><name>Nikos Tapinos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chi3l1 (Chitinase 3-like 1) is a secreted protein highly expressed in glioblastoma. Here, we show that exposure of glioma stem cells (GSCs) to Chi3l1 reduces the CD133&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/SOX2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells and increases the CD44&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/Chi3l1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells. Chi3l1 binds to CD44 and induces phosphorylation and nuclear translocation of beta-catenin, Akt and STAT3. Single cell RNA-seq and RNA velocity following incubation of GSCs with Chi3l1 show significant changes in GSC state dynamics driving GSCs towards a mesenchymal expression profile and reducing transition probabilities towards terminal cellular states. ATAC-seq reveals that Chi3l1 increases accessibility of promoters containing MAZ transcription factor footprint. Inhibition of MAZ directly regulates genes with highest expression in cellular clusters exhibiting significant cell state transitions. Finally, targeting Chi3l1 in vivo with a blocking antibody, resets the transcriptomic profile of glioblastoma and inhibits tumor growth. Our work implicates Chi3l1 as modulator of GSC cellular states and demonstrates pre-clinical efficacy of anti-Chi3l1 antibody treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462786" rel="alternate" title="Chi3l1 is a modulator of glioma stem cell states and a therapeutic vulnerability for glioblastoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462236</id><title>Tracking chromatin state changes using μMap photo-proximity labeling (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.074594+00:00</updated><author><name>Ciaran P. Seath</name></author><author><name>Antony J. Burton</name></author><author><name>David W. C. MacMillan</name></author><author><name>Tom W. Muir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interactions between biomolecules, particularly proteins, underlie all cellular processes, and ultimately control cell fate. Perturbation of native interactions through mutation, changes in expression levels, or external stimuli leads to altered cellular physiology and can result in either disease or therapeutic effects.&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; Mapping these interactions and determining how they respond to stimulus is the genesis of many drug development efforts, leading to new therapeutic targets and improvements in human health.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; However, in the complex environment of the nucleus it is challenging to determine protein-protein interactions due to low abundance, transient or multi-valent binding, and a lack of technologies that are able to interrogate these interactions without disrupting the protein binding surface under study.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; Chromatin remodelers, modifying enzymes, interactors, and transcription factors can all be redirected by subtle changes to the microenvironment, causing global changes in protein expression levels and subsequent physiology. Here, we describe the Chroma-&lt;italic&gt;μ&lt;/italic&gt;Map method for the traceless incorporation of Ir-photosensitizers into the nuclear microenvironment using engineered split inteins. These Ir-catalysts can activate diazirine warheads to form reactive carbenes within a ~10 nm radius, cross-linking with proteins within the immediate microenvironment for analysis via quantitative chemoproteomics.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; We demonstrate this concept on nine different nuclear proteins with varied function and in each case, elucidating their microenvironments. Additionally, we show that this short-range proximity labeling method can reveal the critical changes in interactomes in the presence of cancer-associated mutations, as well as treatment with small-molecule inhibitors. Chroma-&lt;italic&gt;μ&lt;/italic&gt;Map improves our fundamental understanding of nuclear protein-protein interactions, as well as the effects that small molecule therapeutics have on the local chromatin environment, and in doing so is expected to have a significant impact on the field of epigenetic drug discovery in both academia and industry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462236" rel="alternate" title="Tracking chromatin state changes using μMap photo-proximity labeling (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>