<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.877312+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455048</id><title>The longitudinal dynamics and natural history of clonal haematopoiesis (98 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.877648+00:00</updated><author><name>Margarete A. Fabre</name></author><author><name>José Guilherme de Almeida</name></author><author><name>Edoardo Fiorillo</name></author><author><name>Emily Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Aristi Damaskou</name></author><author><name>Justyna Rak</name></author><author><name>Valeria Orrù</name></author><author><name>Michele Marongiu</name></author><author><name>MS Vijayabaskar</name></author><author><name>Joanna Baxter</name></author><author><name>Claire Hardy</name></author><author><name>Federico Abascal</name></author><author><name>Michael Spencer Chapman</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Williams</name></author><author><name>Jyoti Nangalia</name></author><author><name>Iñigo Martincorena</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Eoin F. McKinney</name></author><author><name>Francesco Cucca</name></author><author><name>Moritz Gerstung</name></author><author><name>George S. Vassiliou.</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human cells acquire somatic mutations throughout life, some of which can drive clonal expansion. Such expansions are frequent in the haematopoietic system of healthy individuals and have been termed clonal haematopoiesis (CH). While CH predisposes to myeloid neoplasia and other diseases, we have limited understanding of how and when CH develops, what factors govern its behaviour, how it interacts with ageing and how these variables relate to malignant progression. Here, we track 697 CH clones from 385 individuals aged 55 or older over a median of 13 years. We find that 92.4% of clones expanded at a stable exponential rate over the study period, with different mutations driving substantially different growth rates, ranging from 5% (&lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;TP53&lt;/italic&gt;) to over 50%/yr (&lt;italic&gt;SRSF2-&lt;/italic&gt;P95H). Growth rates of clones with the same mutation differed by approximately +/−5%/yr, proportionately impacting “slow” drivers more substantially. By combining our time-series data with phylogenetic analysis of 1,731 whole genome-sequenced haematopoietic colonies from 7 older individuals, we reveal distinct patterns of lifelong clonal behaviour. &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt;-mutant clones preferentially expanded early in life and displayed slower growth in old age, in the context of an increasingly competitive oligoclonal landscape. By contrast, splicing gene mutations only drove expansion later in life, while growth of &lt;italic&gt;TET2&lt;/italic&gt;-mutant clones showed minimal age-dependency. Finally, we show that mutations driving faster clonal growth carry a higher risk of malignant progression. Our findings characterise the lifelong natural history of CH and give fundamental insights into the interactions between somatic mutation, ageing and clonal selection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455048" rel="alternate" title="The longitudinal dynamics and natural history of clonal haematopoiesis (98 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456199</id><title>Light-controlled elimination of PD-L1+ cells (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.877941+00:00</updated><author><name>Judith Jing Wen Wong</name></author><author><name>Paal K. Selbo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The programmed death ligand-1 (PD-L1), also known as CD274 or B7-H1, is mainly expressed on cancer cells and/or immunosuppressive cells in the tumor microenvironment (TME) and plays an essential role in tumor progression and immune escape. Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) of the PD-1/PD-L1 axis have shown impressive clinical success, however, the majority of the patients do not respond to immune checkpoint therapy (ICT). Thus, to overcome ICT resistance there is a high need for potent and novel strategies that simultaneously target both tumor cells and immunosuppressive cells in the TME. In this study, we show that the intracellular light-controlled drug delivery method photochemical internalization (PCI) induce specific and strongly enhanced cytotoxic effects of the PD-L1-targeting immunotoxin, anti-PD-L1-saporin (Anti-PDL1-SAP), in the PD-L1+ triple-negative breast cancer MDA-MB-231 cell line, while no enhanced efficacy was obtained in the PD-L1 negative control cell line MDA-MB-453. Using fluorescence microscopy, we reveal that the anti-PD-L1 antibody binds to PD-L1 on the surface of the MDA-MD-231 cells and overnight accumulates in late endosomes and lysosomes where it co-localizes with the PCI photosensitizer fimaporfin (TPCS2a). Moreover, light-controlled endosomal/lysosomal escape of the anti-PD-L1 antibody and fimaporfin into the cytosol was obtained. We also confirm that the breast MDA-MB-468 and the prostate PC-3 and DU-145 cancer cell lines have subpopulations with PD-L1 expression. In addition, we show that interferon-gamma strongly induce PD-L1 expression in the per se PD-L1 negative CT26.WT cells and enhance the PD-L1 expression in MC-38 cells, of which both are murine colon cancer cell lines. In conclusion, our work provides an in vitro proof-of-concept of PCI-enhanced targeting and eradication of PD-L1 positive immunosuppressive cells. This light-controlled combinatorial strategy has a potential to advance cancer immunotherapy and should be explored in preclinical studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456199" rel="alternate" title="Light-controlled elimination of PD-L1+ cells (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455638</id><title>Construction of competing endogenous RNA interaction networks as prognostic markers in metastatic melanoma (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.878090+00:00</updated><author><name>Zan He</name></author><author><name>Zijuan Xin</name></author><author><name>Yongfei Peng</name></author><author><name>Hua Zhao</name></author><author><name>Xiangdong Fang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malignant melanoma (MM) is a highly aggressive, metastatic cancer originating from melanocytes. These tumors have an extremely poor prognosis. MM accounts for 4% of skin cancers with an 80% mortality rate. The median survival of patients with metastatic melanoma is approximately six months, with a five-year survival rate of less than 10%. In recent years, the incidence of melanoma has gradually increased and has become one of the deadliest cancers. Competitive endogenous RNA (ceRNA) models the mechanism by which long chain non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) play a regulatory role in the disease. LncRNAs can act as a sponge, competitively attracting small RNAs (micoRNAs; miRNAs) and interfering with miRNA function. This can affect the expression of target gene messenger RNAs (mRNAs), ultimately promoting tumorigenesis and tumor progression. Bioinformatics analysis may identify potentially prognostic and therapeutically-relevant differentially expressed genes in MM, as well as lncRNAs, miRNAs and mRNAs that are interconnected through the ceRNA network. This may provide further insight into gene regulation and the prognosis of metastatic melanoma. Weighted co-expression networks were used to identify lncRNA and mRNA modules associated with the metastatic phenotype, as well as the co-expression genes contained in the modules. We used 17 lncRNAs, six miRNAs, and 11 mRNAs to construct a ceRNA interaction network with a regulatory role in patients with metastatic melanoma. The prognostic risk model was used as a sorter to classify the survival prognosis of melanoma patients. Four groups of ceRNA interaction triplets were obtained, and miR-3662 may be used in the treatment of metastatic melanoma patients. Experiments confirmed the regulating relationship and phenotype of this assumption. This study provides new targets to regulate the metastatic process, predict metastatic potential and determine that miR-3662 may be used in the treatment of melanoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455638" rel="alternate" title="Construction of competing endogenous RNA interaction networks as prognostic markers in metastatic melanoma (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456166</id><title>Autoimmune Alleles at the Major Histocompatibility Locus Modify Melanoma Susceptibility (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.878248+00:00</updated><author><name>James Talwar</name></author><author><name>David Laub</name></author><author><name>Meghana Pagadala</name></author><author><name>Andrea Castro</name></author><author><name>McKenna Lewis</name></author><author><name>Georg E. Luebeck</name></author><author><name>Gerald P. Morris</name></author><author><name>Rany M. Salem</name></author><author><name>Wesley K. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Kit Curtius</name></author><author><name>Maurizio Zanetti</name></author><author><name>Hannah Carter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autoimmunity and cancer represent two different aspects of immune dysfunction. Autoimmunity is characterized by breakdowns in immune self-tolerance, while impaired immune surveillance can allow for tumorigenesis. The class I major histocompatibility complex (MHC-I), which displays derivatives of the cellular peptidome for immune surveillance by CD8+ T cells, serves as a common genetic link between these conditions. As melanoma-specific CD8+ T-cells have been shown to target melanocyte-specific peptide antigens more often than melanoma-specific antigens, we investigated whether vitiligo and psoriasis predisposing MHC-I alleles conferred a melanoma protective effect. In individuals with cutaneous melanoma from both The Cancer Genome Atlas (N = 451) and an independent validation cohort (N = 586), MHC-I autoimmune allele carriers are significantly associated with a later age of melanoma diagnosis. MHC-I autoimmune allele contributions to melanoma risk are not captured by current polygenic risk scores (PRS) and incorporation of autoimmune MHC allele presence can improve relative risk stratification. Mechanisms of autoimmune protection were neither associated with improved melanoma-driver mutation association nor improved gene-level conserved antigen presentation relative to common alleles (population frequency &amp;gt; 1%). However, autoimmune alleles showed a marked affinity relative to common alleles for particular windows of melanocyte conserved antigens suggesting a potential relationship between antigen processing, binding, and cell-surface presentation. Overall, this study presents evidence that MHC-I autoimmune risk alleles modulate melanoma risk currently unaccounted for by current PRS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456166" rel="alternate" title="Autoimmune Alleles at the Major Histocompatibility Locus Modify Melanoma Susceptibility (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455931</id><title>DNAJB1-PRKACA in HEK293T cells induces LINC00473 overexpression that depends on PKA signaling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.878482+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephanie S. Kim</name></author><author><name>Ina Kycia</name></author><author><name>Michael Karski</name></author><author><name>Rosanna K. Ma</name></author><author><name>Evan A. Bordt</name></author><author><name>Julian Kwan</name></author><author><name>Anju Karki</name></author><author><name>Elle Winter</name></author><author><name>Ranan G. Aktas</name></author><author><name>Yuxuan Wu</name></author><author><name>Andrew Emili</name></author><author><name>Daniel E. Bauer</name></author><author><name>Praveen Sethupathy</name></author><author><name>Khashayar Vakili</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fibrolamellar carcinoma (FLC) is a primary liver cancer that most commonly arises in adolescents and young adults in a background of normal liver tissue and has an poor prognosis due to lack of effective chemotherapeutic agents. The &lt;italic&gt;DNAJB1-PRKACA&lt;/italic&gt; gene fusion (DP) has been reported in the majority of FLC tumors, however its oncogenic mechanisms remain unclear. Given the paucity of cellular models, in particular FLC tumor cell lines, we hypothesized that engineering the DP fusion gene in HEK293T cells would provide insight into the cellular effects of the fusion gene. We used CRISPR/Cas9 to engineer HEK293T clones expressing DP fusion gene (HEK-DP) and performed transcriptomic, proteomic, and mitochondrial studies to characterize this cellular model. Proteomic analysis of DP interacting partners identified mitochondrial proteins as well as proteins in other subcellular compartments. HEK-DP cells demonstrated significantly elevated mitochondrial fission, which suggests a role for DP in altering mitochondrial dynamics. Transcriptomic analysis of HEK-DP cells revealed a significant increase in &lt;italic&gt;LINC00473&lt;/italic&gt; expression, similar to what has been observed in primary FLC samples. &lt;italic&gt;LINC00473&lt;/italic&gt; overexpression was reversible with siRNA targeting of &lt;italic&gt;PRKACA&lt;/italic&gt; as well as pharmacologic targeting of PKA and Hsp40 in HEK-DP cells. Therefore, our model suggests that &lt;italic&gt;LINC00473&lt;/italic&gt; is a candidate marker for DP activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455931" rel="alternate" title="DNAJB1-PRKACA in HEK293T cells induces LINC00473 overexpression that depends on PKA signaling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455957</id><title>NSUN6, an RNA methyltransferase of 5-mC controls glioblastoma response to Temozolomide (TMZ) via NELFB and RPS6KB2 interaction (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.878851+00:00</updated><author><name>Chidiebere U Awah</name></author><author><name>Jan Winter</name></author><author><name>Claudiane M Mazdoom</name></author><author><name>Olorunseun O. Ogunwobi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nop2/Sun RNA methyltransferase (NSUN6) is an RNA 5 - methyl cytosine (5mC) transferase with little information known of its function in cancer and response to cancer therapy. Here, we show that NSUN6 methylates both large and small RNA in glioblastoma and controls glioblastoma response to temozolomide with or without influence of the MGMT promoter status, with high NSUN6 expression conferring survival benefit to glioblastoma patients and in other cancers. Mechanistically, our results show that NSUN6 controls response to TMZ therapy via 5mC mediated regulation of NELFB and RPS6BK2. Taken together, we present evidence that show that NSUN6 mediated 5mC deposition regulates transcriptional pause (by accumulation of NELFB and the general transcription factor complexes (POLR2A, TBP, TFIIA, TFIIE) on the preinitiation complex at TATA binding site to control translation machinery in glioblastoma response to alkylating agents. Our findings open a new frontier into controlling of transcriptional regulation by RNA methyltransferase and 5mC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455957" rel="alternate" title="NSUN6, an RNA methyltransferase of 5-mC controls glioblastoma response to Temozolomide (TMZ) via NELFB and RPS6KB2 interaction (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456108</id><title>Identification and validation of E3 ubiquitin ligase XIAP as a novel substrate of deubiquitinase USP7 (HAUSP) - Implication towards oncogenesis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.879027+00:00</updated><author><name>Gouranga Saha</name></author><author><name>Sibani Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Partha S Mohanta</name></author><author><name>Krishna Kumar</name></author><author><name>Saikat Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Mrinal K Ghosh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The induction of apoptosis upon USP7 (HAUSP) inhibition is established in cancers that contain a wild-type p53 (p53&lt;sup&gt;Wt&lt;/sup&gt;) through the ‘USP7-Mdm2-p53’ axis, but no clear explanation has yet been reported for the same to occur in cancers containing mutant 53 (p53&lt;sup&gt;Mut&lt;/sup&gt;) or even p53 null (p53&lt;sup&gt;Null&lt;/sup&gt;) systems. Instead of this ‘USP7-Mdm2-p53’ axis USP7 also works through an alternative new pathway identified in this study. Here in this study, we observed that the magnitude of apoptosis induction in response to USP7 inhibition was remarkably similar between cancer cells showing p53&lt;sup&gt;Null&lt;/sup&gt; or p53&lt;sup&gt;Mut&lt;/sup&gt; and those with p53&lt;sup&gt;Wt&lt;/sup&gt;. Through a proteomics-based approach, we were able to identify XIAP as a novel interacting partner for USP7. XIAP is a potent and well-characterized member of the inhibitor of apoptosis proteins (IAPs), which function through caspase inhibition. We successfully identified USP7 as a positive regulator of XIAP at post-translational but not at its transcriptional level. Using molecular modelling coupled with domain deletion studies, we show that the first three Ubl domains in association with the catalytic domain of USP7 interact with the BIR2 and the linker region between BIR2 and BIR3 domains of XIAP. Modulation of expression and catalytic activity of USP7 in multiple type of cancer cell lines showed that USP7 stabilizes XIAP through its deubiquitinase activity. We have also observed that USP7 sensitizes cells against chemotherapeutic drugs through stabilization of XIAP. Thus, USP7 promotes tumorigenesis in multiple cancers, &lt;italic&gt;via&lt;/italic&gt; stabilization of XIAP that results in apoptosis inhibition in caspase dependent pathway. Moreover, we observed that combinatorial inhibition of USP7 and XIAP can induce cellular apoptosis in a higher magnitude than their individual inhibition. Additionally, our results indicates that nanoformulated P5091 and P22077 showed higher potency for killing C6 cells in comparison to normal drugs. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on identification and validation of XIAP, a crucial E3 ubiquitin ligase, as a novel substrate of the deubiquitinase USP7 and they together involve in empowerment of the tumorigenic potential of cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456108" rel="alternate" title="Identification and validation of E3 ubiquitin ligase XIAP as a novel substrate of deubiquitinase USP7 (HAUSP) - Implication towards oncogenesis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456223</id><title>Ras/MAPK signalling intensity defines subclonal fitness in a mouse model of primary and metastatic hepatocellular carcinoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.879195+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Lozano</name></author><author><name>Francois-Regis Souche</name></author><author><name>Christel Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Serena Vegna</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Desandre</name></author><author><name>Anais Riviere</name></author><author><name>Valerie Dardalhon</name></author><author><name>Amal Zine El Aabidine</name></author><author><name>Philippe Fort</name></author><author><name>Leila Akkari</name></author><author><name>Urszula Hibner</name></author><author><name>Damien Gregoire</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantitative differences in signal transduction are to date an understudied feature of tumour heterogeneity. The MAPK Erk pathway, which is activated in a large proportion of human tumours, is a prototypic example of distinct cell fates being driven by signal intensity. We have used primary hepatocyte precursors transformed with different dosages of an oncogenic form of Ras to model subclonal variations in MAPK signalling. Orthotopic allografts of Ras-transformed cells in immunocompromised mice gave rise to fast-growing aggressive tumours, both at the primary location and in the peritoneal cavity. Fluorescent labelling of cells expressing different oncogene levels, and consequently varying levels of MAPK Erk activation, highlighted the selection processes operating at the two sites of tumour growth. Indeed, significantly higher Ras expression was observed in primary as compared to metastatic tumours, despite the evolutionary trade-off of increased apoptotic death in the liver that correlated with high Ras dosage. Analysis of the immune tumoral microenvironment at the two locations suggests that fast metastatic growth in the immunocompromised setting is abrogated in immunocompetent animals due to efficient antigen presentation by peritoneal dendritic cells. Furthermore, our data indicate that, in contrast to the metastatic outgrowth,  strong MAPK signalling is required in the primary liver tumours to resist elimination by NK cells. Overall, this study describes a quantitative aspect of tumour heterogeneity and highlights potential vulnerability of a subtype of hepatocellular carcinoma as a function of MAPK Erk signalling intensity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456223" rel="alternate" title="Ras/MAPK signalling intensity defines subclonal fitness in a mouse model of primary and metastatic hepatocellular carcinoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>