<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.415897+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466159</id><title>Clonal hematopoiesis detection in cancer patients using cell free DNA sequencing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.416684+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Fairchild</name></author><author><name>Jeanne Whalen</name></author><author><name>Katie D'Aco</name></author><author><name>Jincheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Carroll B Gustafson</name></author><author><name>Nadia Solovieff</name></author><author><name>Fei Su</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Leary</name></author><author><name>Catarina D Campbell</name></author><author><name>Oscar Alejandro Balbin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the context of cancer, clonal hematopoiesis of indeterminate potential (CHIP) is associated with the development of therapy-related myeloid neoplasms and shorter overall survival. Cell-free DNA (cfDNA) sequencing is becoming widely adopted for genomic screening of cancer patients but has not been used extensively to determine CHIP status due to a requirement for matched blood and tumor sequencing. Here we present an accurate machine learning approach to determine clonal hematopoiesis (CH) status from cfDNA sequencing alone and apply our model to 4,096 oncology clinical cfDNA samples. Using this method, we determine that 26% of patients in this cohort have evidence of CH and CH is most common in lung cancer patients. Matched RNAseq data shows signals of increased inflammation, especially neutrophil activation, within the tumor microenvironment of CH-positive patients. Additionally, CH patients showed evidence of neutrophil activation systemically, pointing to a potential mechanism of action for the worse outcomes associated with CH status. Neutrophil activation may be one of many mechanisms however, as estrogen positive breast cancer patients harboring TET2 frameshift mutations had worse outcomes but similar neutrophil levels to CH-negative patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466159" rel="alternate" title="Clonal hematopoiesis detection in cancer patients using cell free DNA sequencing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466226</id><title>Inhibition of Metastatic Uveal Melanoma Cell Proliferation by the Histone Deacetylase 6 Inhibitor, Ricolinostat, is Linked to Altered Microphthalmia-associated Transcription Factor and Phospho-ERK Expression (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.417680+00:00</updated><author><name>Husvinee Sundaramurthi</name></author><author><name>Sandra Garcia-Mulero</name></author><author><name>Kayleigh Slater</name></author><author><name>Simone Marcone</name></author><author><name>Josep M. Piulats</name></author><author><name>R.William Watson</name></author><author><name>Desmond Tobin</name></author><author><name>Lasse Jensen</name></author><author><name>Breandan N. Kennedy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metastatic uveal melanoma (MUM) is characterized by poor patient survival. Unfortunately, current treatment options demonstrate limited benefits. In this study, we evaluate the efficacy of ACY-1215, a histone deacetylase 6 inhibitor (HDAC6i), to attenuate MUM cell growth in vitro and in vivo, and elucidate the underlying molecular mechanisms. Treatment of OMM2.5 MUM cells with ACY-1215 resulted in a significant (p = 0.0001), dose-dependent reduction in cell survival and proliferation in vitro, and in vivo regression of primary OMM2.5 xenografts in zebrafish larvae. Furthermore, flow cytometry analysis revealed that ACY-1215 significantly arrested the OMM2.5 cell cycle in S phase (p = 0.0006) following 24 hours of treatment and significant apoptosis was triggered in a time- and dose-dependent manner (p = &amp;lt;0.0001). Additionally, ACY-1215 treatment resulted in a significant reduction in OMM2.5 p-ERK expression levels. Through proteome-profiling, attenuation of the microphthalmia-associated transcription factor (MITF) signaling pathway was linked to the observed anti-cancer effects of ACY-1215. In agreement, pharmacological inhibition of MITF signaling with ML329, significantly reduced OMM2.5 cell survival and viability in vitro (p = 0.0001) and in vivo (p = 0.0006). Our findings provide evidence that ACY-1215 and ML329 are efficacious against growth and survival of MUM cells and are potential therapeutic options for MUM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466226" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of Metastatic Uveal Melanoma Cell Proliferation by the Histone Deacetylase 6 Inhibitor, Ricolinostat, is Linked to Altered Microphthalmia-associated Transcription Factor and Phospho-ERK Expression (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>