<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.758581+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.459529</id><title>Germline Missense Variants in CDC20 Result in Aberrant Mitotic Progression and Familial Cancer (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.759151+00:00</updated><author><name>Owen J. Chen</name></author><author><name>Ester Castellsagué</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Moustafa-Kamal</name></author><author><name>Javad Nadaf</name></author><author><name>Barbara Rivera</name></author><author><name>Somayyeh Fahiminiya</name></author><author><name>Yilin Wang</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Gamache</name></author><author><name>Caterina Pacifico</name></author><author><name>Lai Jiang</name></author><author><name>Jian Carrot-Zhang</name></author><author><name>Leora Witkowski</name></author><author><name>Albert M. Berghuis</name></author><author><name>Stefan Schoenberger</name></author><author><name>Dominik Schneider</name></author><author><name>Susanne Bens</name></author><author><name>Reiner Siebert</name></author><author><name>Colin J. R. Stewart</name></author><author><name>Ziguo Zhang</name></author><author><name>William C. Chao</name></author><author><name>Celia M.T. Greenwood</name></author><author><name>David Barford</name></author><author><name>Marc Tischkowitz</name></author><author><name>Jacek Majewski</name></author><author><name>William D. Foulkes</name></author><author><name>Jose G. Teodoro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CDC20 is a co-activator of the anaphase promoting complex/cyclosome (APC/C) and is essential for mitotic progression. APC/C&lt;sup&gt;CDC20&lt;/sup&gt; is inhibited by the spindle assembly checkpoint (SAC), which prevents premature separation of sister chromatids and aneuploidy in daughter cells. Although overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;CDC20&lt;/italic&gt; is common in many cancers, oncogenic mutations have never been identified in humans. Using whole exome sequencing, we identified heterozygous missense &lt;italic&gt;CDC20&lt;/italic&gt; variants (L151R and N331K) that segregate with cancer in two families. Characterization of these mutants showed they retain APC/C activation activity but show reduced binding to BUBR1, a component of the SAC. Expression of L151R and N331K promoted mitotic slippage in HeLa cells and primary skin fibroblasts derived from carriers. CRISPR/Cas9 was used to generate mice carrying N331K. Homozygous mice carrying N331K were non-viable, however, heterozygotes displayed accelerated oncogenicity in Myc-driven cancers. These findings highlight an unappreciated role for &lt;italic&gt;CDC20&lt;/italic&gt; variants as tumor promoting genes in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.459529" rel="alternate" title="Germline Missense Variants in CDC20 Result in Aberrant Mitotic Progression and Familial Cancer (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460311</id><title>Elevated phosphorylation of EGFR in NSCLC due to mutations in PTPRH (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.759616+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew R. Swiatnicki</name></author><author><name>Jonathan P. Rennhack</name></author><author><name>Daniel P. Hollern</name></author><author><name>Ashlee V. Perry</name></author><author><name>Rachel Kubiak</name></author><author><name>Sarai M. Riveria Riveria</name></author><author><name>Sandra O’Reilly</name></author><author><name>Eran R. Andrechek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The role of EGFR in lung cancer is well described with numerous activating mutations that result in phosphorylation and tyrosine kinase inhibitors that target EGFR. While the role of the EGFR kinase in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is appreciated, control of EGFR signaling pathways through dephosphorylation by phosphatases is not as clear. In recent work we identified mutations in Protein Tyrosine Phosphatase Receptor Type H (&lt;italic&gt;Ptprh&lt;/italic&gt;, also known as SAP-1) as being associated with elevated phosphorylation of EGFR in a mouse model of breast cancer. We have examined a series of tumors from this mouse model, revealing conserved V483M &lt;italic&gt;Ptprh&lt;/italic&gt; mutations within the FVB background, but a series of varied mutations in other backgrounds. Despite the varied &lt;italic&gt;Ptprh&lt;/italic&gt; mutations in other background strains, matched primary and metastatic tumors largely shared mutational profiles. Profiling the downstream events of &lt;italic&gt;Ptprh&lt;/italic&gt; mutant tumors revealed AKT activation, suggesting a key target of PTPRH was EGFR tyrosine 1197. Given the role of EGFR in lung cancer, we explored TCGA data which revealed that a subset of &lt;italic&gt;PTPRH&lt;/italic&gt; mutant tumors shared gene expression profiles with &lt;italic&gt;EGFR&lt;/italic&gt; mutant tumors, but that &lt;italic&gt;EGFR&lt;/italic&gt; mutations and &lt;italic&gt;PTPRH&lt;/italic&gt; mutations were mutually exclusive. Generation of a PTPRH knockout NSCLC cell line resulted in Y1197 phosphorylation of EGFR, and a rescue with expression of wild type PTPRH returned EGFR phosphorylation to parental line values while a rescue with a D986A catalytically dead mutant PTPRH did not, demonstrating that PTPRH targets EGFR. As expected with active EGFR, the knockout of PTPRH was associated with increased growth rate. Moreover, a dose response curve illustrated that two human NSCLC lines that had naturally occurring &lt;italic&gt;PTPRH&lt;/italic&gt; mutations responded to EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibition. Injection of one of the NSCLC human lines into mice resulted in tumors, and Osimertinib treatment resulted in a reduction of tumor volume relative to vehicle controls. Consistent with prior literature from breast cancer, &lt;italic&gt;PTPRH&lt;/italic&gt; mutation resulted in nuclear pEGFR as seen in immunohistochemistry, suggesting that there may also be a role for EGFR as a transcriptional co-factor. Other roles for PTPRH were explored through a receptor tyrosine kinase array, noting elevated phosphorylation of FGFR1. Knockout of PTPRH in NSCLC cell lines resulted in elevated phosphorylated FGFR1 relative to controls, indicating that PTPRH has a number of targets that may be aberrantly activated in NSCLC with mutations in PTPRH. Together these data suggest that mutations in PTPRH in NSCLC may result in clinically actionable alterations using existing therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460311" rel="alternate" title="Elevated phosphorylation of EGFR in NSCLC due to mutations in PTPRH (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>