<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.123926+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461908</id><title>Disentangling heterogeneity of Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma through deep integrative omics analyses (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.124470+00:00</updated><author><name>Lise Mangiante</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Alcala</name></author><author><name>Alex Di Genova</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Sexton-Oates</name></author><author><name>Abel Gonzalez-Perez</name></author><author><name>Azhar Khandekar</name></author><author><name>Erik N. Bergstrom</name></author><author><name>Jaehee Kim</name></author><author><name>Colin Giacobi</name></author><author><name>Nolwenn Le Stang</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Boyault</name></author><author><name>Cyrille Cuenin</name></author><author><name>Severine Tabone-Eglinger</name></author><author><name>Francesca Damiola</name></author><author><name>Catherine Voegele</name></author><author><name>Maude Ardin</name></author><author><name>Marie-Cecile Michallet</name></author><author><name>Lorraine Soudade</name></author><author><name>Tiffany M. Delhomme</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Poret</name></author><author><name>Marie Brevet</name></author><author><name>Marie-Christine Copin</name></author><author><name>Sophie Giusiano-Courcambeck</name></author><author><name>Diane Damotte</name></author><author><name>Cecile Girard</name></author><author><name>Veronique Hofman</name></author><author><name>Paul Hofman</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Mouroux</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Lacomme</name></author><author><name>Julien Mazieres</name></author><author><name>Vincent Thomas de Montpreville</name></author><author><name>Corinne Perrin</name></author><author><name>Gaetane Planchard</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Rouquette</name></author><author><name>Christine Sagan</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Scherpereel</name></author><author><name>Francoise Thivolet</name></author><author><name>Jean-Michel Vignaud</name></author><author><name>Didier Jean</name></author><author><name>Anabelle Gilg Soit Ilg</name></author><author><name>Robert Olaso</name></author><author><name>Vincent Meyer</name></author><author><name>Anne Boland</name></author><author><name>Jean-Francois Deleuze</name></author><author><name>Janine Altmuller</name></author><author><name>Peter Nuernberg</name></author><author><name>Sylvie Lantuejoul</name></author><author><name>Akram Ghantous</name></author><author><name>Charles Maussion</name></author><author><name>Pierre Courtiol</name></author><author><name>Hector Hernandez-Vargas</name></author><author><name>Christophe Caux</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Girard</name></author><author><name>Nuria Lopez-Bigas</name></author><author><name>Ludmil B. Alexandrov</name></author><author><name>Françoise Galateau Salle</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Foll</name></author><author><name>Lynnette Fernandez-Cuesta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma (MPM) is an aggressive cancer with rising incidence and challenging clinical management. Using the largest series of whole-genome sequencing data integrated with transcriptomic and epigenomic data using multi-omic factor analysis, we demonstrate that MPM heterogeneity arises from four sources of variation: tumor cell morphology, ploidy, adaptive immune response, and CpG island methylator phenotype. Previous genomic studies focused on describing only the tumor cell morphology factor, although we robustly find the three other sources in all publicly available cohorts. We prove how these sources of variation explain the biological functions performed by the cancer cells, and how genomic events shape MPM molecular profiles. We show how these new sources of variation help understand the heterogeneity of the clinical behavior of MPM and drug responses measured in cell lines. These findings unearth the interplay between MPM functional biology and its genomic history, and ultimately, inform classification, prognostication and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461908v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461908" rel="alternate" title="Disentangling heterogeneity of Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma through deep integrative omics analyses (17 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.459429</id><title>Chromosomal instability mediates immune exclusion and response to cytotoxic chemotherapy in colorectal liver metastases (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.125119+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos A Martinez</name></author><author><name>Liam F Spurr</name></author><author><name>Soumya C Iyer</name></author><author><name>Sian A Pugh</name></author><author><name>John A Bridgewater</name></author><author><name>John N Primrose</name></author><author><name>Enric Domingo</name></author><author><name>Timothy S Maughan</name></author><author><name>Michael I D’Angelica</name></author><author><name>Mark Talamonti</name></author><author><name>Mitchell C Posner</name></author><author><name>Philip P Connell</name></author><author><name>Ralph R Weichselbaum</name></author><author><name>Sean P Pitroda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The genomic drivers of immune exclusion in colorectal cancer liver metastases (CRCLM) remain poorly understood. Chromosomal instability (CIN), resulting in aneuploidy and genomic rearrangements, is the central pathway of mismatch repair-proficient colorectal cancer pathogenesis; however, it is unknown whether CIN impacts the outcomes of patients with limited spread of CRCLM treated with curative intent cytotoxic chemotherapy and surgery. Herein, we examined the relationship between CIN and the molecular subtypes of CRCLM, immune signaling, treatment sensitivity, and patient outcomes in three independent CRCLM patient cohorts. We established that a previously developed 70-gene CIN signature (CIN70) is a reliable measure of CIN, encompassing features of both aneuploidy and cellular proliferation. We demonstrated that tumors with the canonical subtype of CRCLM exhibit elevated levels of CIN and aneuploidy. Genomically unstable tumors were associated with an immune-depleted tumor microenvironment, and patients with genomically unstable tumors were at increased risk for disease progression in adverse metastatic sites, resulting in poor progression-free and overall survival. However, high-CIN tumors were particularly susceptible to DNA-damaging chemotherapies, including topoisomerase inhibitors, as well as radiation therapy. Treatment with genotoxic agents depleted CIN-rich cell populations, which resulted in a concomitant increase in intratumoral CD8+ T-cells in patients with primary rectal, breast, and bladder cancer. Taken together, we propose a mechanistic explanation for why cytotoxic chemotherapy can augment anti-tumor immunity and improve outcomes in patients with genomically unstable cancers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.459429" rel="alternate" title="Chromosomal instability mediates immune exclusion and response to cytotoxic chemotherapy in colorectal liver metastases (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461526</id><title>Targeting of MCL-1 in breast cancer associated fibroblasts reverses their myofibroblastic phenotype and pro-invasive properties (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.125541+00:00</updated><author><name>TL Bonneaud</name></author><author><name>L Nocquet</name></author><author><name>A Basseville</name></author><author><name>H Weber</name></author><author><name>M Campone</name></author><author><name>PP Juin</name></author><author><name>F Souazé</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer associated fibroblasts (CAF) are a major cellular component of epithelial tumors. In breast cancers in particular these stromal cells have numerous tumorigenic effects in part due to their acquisition of a myofibroblastic phenotype. Breast CAFs (bCAFS) typically express MCL-1. We show here that targeting this regulator of mitochondrial integrity using a specific BH-3 mimetic promotes fragmentation of these organelles without inducing cell death. MCL-1 antagonism in primary bCAFs directly derived from human samples mitigates myofibroblastic features and decreases expression of genes involved in actomyosin organization and contractility, associated with a cytoplasmic retention of the transcriptional regulator, Yes&lt;italic&gt;-&lt;/italic&gt;Associated Protein &lt;italic&gt;(&lt;/italic&gt;YAP). Such treatment decreases bCAFs ability to promote cancer cells invasion in 3D co-culture assays. These effects are counteracted by an inhibitor of the mitochondrial fission protein DRP-1, which interacts with MCL-1 upon BH3 mimetic treatment. Our findings underscore the usefulness of targeting MCL-1 in breast cancer ecosystems, not only to favor death of cancer cells but also to counteract the tumorigenic activation of fibroblasts with which they co-evolve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors declare no conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461526" rel="alternate" title="Targeting of MCL-1 in breast cancer associated fibroblasts reverses their myofibroblastic phenotype and pro-invasive properties (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461735</id><title>Single-cell RNA Sequencing Reveals Immunosuppressive Myeloid Cell Diversity and Restricted Cytotoxic Effector Cell Trafficking and Activation During Malignant Progression in Glioma (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.125853+00:00</updated><author><name>Sakthi Rajendran</name></author><author><name>Clayton Peterson</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Canella</name></author><author><name>Yang Hu</name></author><author><name>Amy Gross</name></author><author><name>Maren Cam</name></author><author><name>Akdes Serin-Harmanci</name></author><author><name>Rosario Distefano</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Nigita</name></author><author><name>Wesley Wang</name></author><author><name>Katherine E. Miller</name></author><author><name>Olivier Elemento</name></author><author><name>Ryan Roberts</name></author><author><name>Eric C. Holland</name></author><author><name>Ganesh Rao</name></author><author><name>Elaine R. Mardis</name></author><author><name>Prajwal Rajappa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Low grade gliomas &lt;bold&gt;(LGG)&lt;/bold&gt; account for about two-thirds of all glioma diagnoses in adolescents and young adults (AYA) and malignant progression of these patients leads to dismal outcomes. Recent studies have shown the importance of the dynamic tumor microenvironment in high-grade gliomas &lt;bold&gt;(HGG&lt;/bold&gt;), yet its role is still poorly understood in low-grade glioma malignant progression. Here, we investigated the heterogeneity of the immune microenvironment using a platelet-derived growth factor (&lt;bold&gt;PDGF&lt;/bold&gt;)-driven &lt;bold&gt;RCAS&lt;/bold&gt; (replication-competent ASLV long terminal repeat with a splice acceptor) glioma model that recapitulates the malignant progression of low to high-grade glioma in humans and also provides a model system to characterize immune cell trafficking and evolution. To illuminate changes in the immune cell landscape during tumor progression, we performed single-cell RNA sequencing on immune cells isolated from animals bearing no tumor &lt;bold&gt;(NT)&lt;/bold&gt;, LGG and HGG, with a particular focus on the myeloid cell compartment, which is known to mediate glioma immunosuppression. LGGs demonstrated significantly increased infiltrating T cells, CD4 T cells, CD8 T cells, B cells, and natural killer cells in the tumor microenvironment, whereas HGGs significantly abrogated this infiltration. Our study identified two distinct macrophage clusters in the tumor microenvironment; one cluster appeared to be bone marrow-derived while another was defined by overexpression of Trem2, a marker of tumor associated macrophages. Our data demonstrates that these two distinct macrophage clusters show an immune-activated phenotype (&lt;italic&gt;Stat1, Tnf, Cxcl9 and Cxcl10&lt;/italic&gt;) in LGG which evolves to an immunosuppressive state (&lt;italic&gt;Lgals3, Apoc1 and Id2&lt;/italic&gt;) in HGG that restricts T cell recruitment and activation. We identified CD74 and macrophage migration inhibition factor (&lt;bold&gt;MIF&lt;/bold&gt;) as potential targets for these distinct macrophage populations. Interestingly, these results were mirrored by our analysis of the TCGA dataset, which demonstrated a statistically significant association between CD74 overexpression and decreased overall survival in AYA patients with grade II gliomas. Targeting immunosuppressive myeloid cells and intra-tumoral macrophages within this therapeutic window may ameliorate mechanisms associated with immunosuppression before and during malignant progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461735" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell RNA Sequencing Reveals Immunosuppressive Myeloid Cell Diversity and Restricted Cytotoxic Effector Cell Trafficking and Activation During Malignant Progression in Glioma (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462210</id><title>Comprehensive analysis of mutational signatures in pediatric cancers (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.126159+00:00</updated><author><name>Venu Thatikonda</name></author><author><name>S. M. Ashiqul Islam</name></author><author><name>Barbara C. Jones</name></author><author><name>Susanne N. Gröbner</name></author><author><name>Gregor Warsow</name></author><author><name>Barbara Hutter</name></author><author><name>Daniel Huebschmann</name></author><author><name>Stefan Fröhling</name></author><author><name>Mirjam Blattner-Johnson</name></author><author><name>David T.W. Jones</name></author><author><name>Ludmil B. Alexandrov</name></author><author><name>Stefan M. Pfister</name></author><author><name>Natalie Jäger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Analysis of mutational signatures can reveal the underlying molecular mechanisms of the processes that have imprinted the somatic mutations found in a cancer genome. Here, we present a pan-cancer mutational signatures analysis of single base substitutions (SBS) and small insertion and deletions (ID) in pediatric cancers encompassing 537 whole genome sequenced tumors from 20 molecularly defined cancer subtypes. We identified only a small number of mutational signatures active in pediatric cancers when compared to the previously analyzed adult cancers. Further, we report a significant difference in the proportion of pediatric tumors which show homologous recombination repair defect signature SBS3 compared to prior analyses. Correlating genomic alterations with signature activities, we identified an association of &lt;italic&gt;TP53&lt;/italic&gt; mutation status with substitution signatures SBS2, SBS8, SBS13 and indel signatures ID2 and ID9, as well as chromothripsis associated with SBS8, SBS40 and ID9. This analysis provides a systematic overview of COSMIC v.3 SBS and ID mutational signatures active across pediatric cancers, which is highly relevant for understanding tumor biology as well as enabling future research in defining biomarkers of treatment response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462210" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive analysis of mutational signatures in pediatric cancers (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461461</id><title>Modelling 3D tumour microenvironment in vivo: a tool to predict cancer fate (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.126436+00:00</updated><author><name>J. Marines</name></author><author><name>F. Lorenzini</name></author><author><name>K. Kissa</name></author><author><name>L. Fontenille</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recently, many studies demonstrated the fundamental role of tumour microenvironment (TME) in cancer progression. Here, we describe a state-of-the-art method to visualize in 3D the behaviour of tumours in zebrafish embryos. We highlight two major actors of TME, macrophages and vessels. This valuable tool is transposable to Patients Derived Xenograft imaging in order to predict the fate of malignant tumours according to the dynamics of their TME.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461461" rel="alternate" title="Modelling 3D tumour microenvironment in vivo: a tool to predict cancer fate (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.461531</id><title>Sex Differences in Brain Tumor Glutamine Metabolism Reveal Sex-Specific Vulnerabilities to Treatment (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.126599+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasmin Sponagel</name></author><author><name>Jill K. Jones</name></author><author><name>Cheryl Frankfater</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Olivia Tung</name></author><author><name>Kevin Cho</name></author><author><name>Kelsey L. Tinkum</name></author><author><name>Hannah Gass</name></author><author><name>Elena Nunez</name></author><author><name>Douglas R. Spitz</name></author><author><name>Prakash Chinnaiyan</name></author><author><name>Jacob Schaefer</name></author><author><name>Gary J. Patti</name></author><author><name>Maya S. Graham</name></author><author><name>Audrey Mauguen</name></author><author><name>Milan Grkovski</name></author><author><name>Mark P. Dunphy</name></author><author><name>Simone Krebs</name></author><author><name>Jingqin Luo</name></author><author><name>Joshua B. Rubin</name></author><author><name>Joseph E. Ippolito</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex differences in normal metabolism are well described, but whether they persist in cancerous tissue is unknown. We assessed metabolite abundance in glioblastoma surgical specimens and found that male glioblastomas are enriched for amino acids, including glutamine. Using PET imaging, we found that gliomas in male patients exhibit significantly higher glutamine uptake. These sex differences were well-modeled in murine transformed astrocytes, in which male cells imported and metabolized more glutamine and were more sensitive to glutaminase 1 (GLS1) inhibition. The sensitivity to GLS1 inhibition in males was driven by their dependence on glutamine-derived glutamate for α-ketoglutarate synthesis and TCA cycle replenishment. Females were resistant to GLS1 inhibition through greater pyruvate carboxylase-mediated TCA cycle replenishment. Thus, clinically important sex differences exist in targetable elements of metabolism. Recognition of sex-biased metabolism is an opportunity to improve treatments for all patients through further laboratory and clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.461531" rel="alternate" title="Sex Differences in Brain Tumor Glutamine Metabolism Reveal Sex-Specific Vulnerabilities to Treatment (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462236</id><title>Tracking chromatin state changes using μMap photo-proximity labeling (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.126867+00:00</updated><author><name>Ciaran P. Seath</name></author><author><name>Antony J. Burton</name></author><author><name>David W. C. MacMillan</name></author><author><name>Tom W. Muir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interactions between biomolecules, particularly proteins, underlie all cellular processes, and ultimately control cell fate. Perturbation of native interactions through mutation, changes in expression levels, or external stimuli leads to altered cellular physiology and can result in either disease or therapeutic effects.&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; Mapping these interactions and determining how they respond to stimulus is the genesis of many drug development efforts, leading to new therapeutic targets and improvements in human health.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; However, in the complex environment of the nucleus it is challenging to determine protein-protein interactions due to low abundance, transient or multi-valent binding, and a lack of technologies that are able to interrogate these interactions without disrupting the protein binding surface under study.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; Chromatin remodelers, modifying enzymes, interactors, and transcription factors can all be redirected by subtle changes to the microenvironment, causing global changes in protein expression levels and subsequent physiology. Here, we describe the Chroma-&lt;italic&gt;μ&lt;/italic&gt;Map method for the traceless incorporation of Ir-photosensitizers into the nuclear microenvironment using engineered split inteins. These Ir-catalysts can activate diazirine warheads to form reactive carbenes within a ~10 nm radius, cross-linking with proteins within the immediate microenvironment for analysis via quantitative chemoproteomics.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; We demonstrate this concept on nine different nuclear proteins with varied function and in each case, elucidating their microenvironments. Additionally, we show that this short-range proximity labeling method can reveal the critical changes in interactomes in the presence of cancer-associated mutations, as well as treatment with small-molecule inhibitors. Chroma-&lt;italic&gt;μ&lt;/italic&gt;Map improves our fundamental understanding of nuclear protein-protein interactions, as well as the effects that small molecule therapeutics have on the local chromatin environment, and in doing so is expected to have a significant impact on the field of epigenetic drug discovery in both academia and industry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462236" rel="alternate" title="Tracking chromatin state changes using μMap photo-proximity labeling (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461627</id><title>Inhibition of pyrimidine biosynthesis targets protein translation in AML (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.127041+00:00</updated><author><name>Joan So</name></author><author><name>Alexander C. Lewis</name></author><author><name>Lorey K. Smith</name></author><author><name>Kym Stanley</name></author><author><name>Lizzy Pijpers</name></author><author><name>Pilar Dominguez</name></author><author><name>Simon J. Hogg</name></author><author><name>Stephin J. Vervoort</name></author><author><name>Ricky W. Johnstone</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle McDonald</name></author><author><name>Danielle B. Ulanet</name></author><author><name>Josh Murtie</name></author><author><name>Emily Gruber</name></author><author><name>Lev M. Kats</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mitochondrial enzyme dihydroorotate dehydrogenase (DHODH) catalyzes one of the rate-limiting steps in &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; pyrimidine biosynthesis, a pathway that provides essential metabolic precursors for nucleic acids, glycoproteins and phospholipids. DHODH inhibitors (DHODHi) are clinically used for autoimmune diseases and are emerging as a novel class of anti-cancer agents, especially in acute myeloid leukemia (AML) where pyrimidine starvation was recently shown to reverse the characteristic differentiation block in AML cells. Herein we show that DHODH blockade rapidly shuts down protein translation in leukemic stem cells (LSCs) by down-regulation of the multi-functional transcription factor YY1, has potent activity against AML &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and is well tolerated with minimal impact on normal blood development. Moreover, we find that ablation of CDK5, a gene that is recurrently deleted in AML and related disorders, increases the sensitivity of AML cells to DHODHi. Our studies provide important molecular insights and identify a potential biomarker for an emerging strategy to target AML.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461627" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of pyrimidine biosynthesis targets protein translation in AML (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461149</id><title>Overcoming microenvironment-mediated chemoprotection through stromal galectin-3 inhibition in acute lymphoblastic leukemia (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.127260+00:00</updated><author><name>Somayeh S. Tarighat</name></author><author><name>Fei Fei</name></author><author><name>Eun Ji Joo</name></author><author><name>Hisham Abdel-Azim</name></author><author><name>Lu Yang</name></author><author><name>Huimin Geng</name></author><author><name>Khuchtumur Bum-Erdene</name></author><author><name>I. Darren Grice</name></author><author><name>Mark von Itzstein</name></author><author><name>Helen Blanchard</name></author><author><name>Nora Heisterkamp</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Environmentally-mediated drug resistance in B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia (BCP-ALL) significantly contributes to relapse. Stromal cells in the bone marrow environment protect leukemia cells by secretion of chemokines as cues for BCP-ALL migration towards, and adhesion to, stroma. Stromal cells and BCP-ALL cells communicate through stromal galectin-3. Here, we investigated the significance of stromal galectin-3 to BCP-ALL cells. We used CRISPR/Cas9 genome editing to ablate galectin-3 in stromal cells and found that galectin-3 is dispensable for steady-state BCP-ALL proliferation and viability. However, efficient leukemia migration and adhesion to stromal cells are significantly dependent on stromal galectin-3. Importantly, loss of stromal galectin-3 production sensitized BCP-ALL cells to conventional chemotherapy. We therefore tested novel carbohydrate-based small molecule compounds (Cpd14 and Cpd17) with high specificity for galectin-3. Consistent with results obtained using galectin-3-knockout stromal cells, treatment of stromal-BCP-ALL co-cultures inhibited BCP-ALL migration and adhesion. Moreover, these compounds induced anti-leukemic responses in BCP-ALL cells including a dose-dependent reduction of viability and proliferation, induction of apoptosis and, importantly, inhibition of drug resistance. Collectively, these findings indicate galectin-3 regulates BCP-ALL cell responses to chemotherapy through the interactions between leukemia cells and the stroma, and show that a combination of galectin-3 inhibition with conventional drugs can sensitize the leukemia cells to chemotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461149" rel="alternate" title="Overcoming microenvironment-mediated chemoprotection through stromal galectin-3 inhibition in acute lymphoblastic leukemia (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263942</id><title>Predicting Progression Free Survival after Systemic Therapy in Advanced Head and Neck Cancer: Bayesian regression and Model development (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.127496+00:00</updated><author><name>Paul R Barber</name></author><author><name>Fabian Flores-Borja</name></author><author><name>Giovanna Alfano</name></author><author><name>Kenrick Ng</name></author><author><name>Gregory Weitsman</name></author><author><name>Luigi Dolcetti</name></author><author><name>Rami Mustapha</name></author><author><name>Felix Wong</name></author><author><name>Jose M Vicencio</name></author><author><name>Myria Galazi</name></author><author><name>James W Opzoomer</name></author><author><name>James N Arnold</name></author><author><name>Shahram Kordasti</name></author><author><name>Jana Doyle</name></author><author><name>Jon Greenberg</name></author><author><name>Magnus T Dillon</name></author><author><name>Kevin J Harrington</name></author><author><name>Martin D Forster</name></author><author><name>Anthony C C Coolen</name></author><author><name>Tony Ng</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Cancer (HNSCC) is associated with a poor prognosis, and biomarkers that predict response to treatment are highly desirable. The primary aim was to predict Progression Free Survival (PFS) with a multivariate risk prediction model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blood samples from 56 HNSCC patients were prospectively obtained within a Phase 2 clinical trial (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT02633800"&gt;NCT02633800&lt;/ext-link&gt;), before and after the first treatment cycle of platinum-based chemotherapy, to identify biological covariates predictive of outcome. A total of 42 baseline covariates were derived pre-treatment, which were combined with 29 covariates after one cycle of treatment. These covariates were ranked and selected by Bayesian multivariate regression to form risk scores to predict PFS, producing “baseline” and “combined” risk prediction models respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The baseline model comprised of CD33+CD14+ monocytes, Double Negative B cells and age, in a weighted risk signature which predicted PFS with a concordance index (C-index) of 0.661. The combined model composed of baseline CD33+CD14+ monocytes, baseline Tregs, after-treatment changes in CD8 effector memory T cells, CD8 Central memory T cells and CD3 T Cells, along with the hypopharyngeal primary tumor subsite. This weighted risk signature exhibited an improved C-index of 0.757. There was concordance between levels of CD33+CD14+ myeloid cells in tumor tissue, as demonstrated by imaging mass cytometry, and peripheral blood in the same patients. This monocyte subpopulation also had univariate predictive value (log-rank p value = 0.03) but the C-index was inferior to the combined signature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This immune-based combined multimodality signature, obtained through longitudinal peripheral blood monitoring, presents a novel means of predicting response early on during the treatment course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Funding&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daiichi Sankyo Inc, Cancer Research UK, EU IMI2 IMMUCAN, UK Medical Research Council, European Research Council (335326), National Institute for Health Research and The Institute of Cancer Research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.21263942" rel="alternate" title="Predicting Progression Free Survival after Systemic Therapy in Advanced Head and Neck Cancer: Bayesian regression and Model development (5 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461612</id><title>SMC1A facilitates gastric cancer cells proliferation, migration and invasion via promoting SNAI2 activated EMT (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.127749+00:00</updated><author><name>Yaling Liu</name></author><author><name>Xianrui Fang</name></author><author><name>Qianqian Wang</name></author><author><name>Da Xiao</name></author><author><name>Zhenyu Peng</name></author><author><name>Ting Zhou</name></author><author><name>Feng Ren</name></author><author><name>Jingyu Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;structural maintenance of chromosomes protein 1A (SMC1A) is a crucial subunit of the cohesion protein complex and plays a vital role in cell cycle regulation, genomic stability maintenance, chromosome dynamics. Recent studies demonstrated that SMC1A participate in tumorigenesis. This reseach aims to explore the role and the underlying mechanisms of SMC1A in gastric cancer (GC).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RT-qPCR and western blot were used to examine the expression levels of SMC1A in GC tissues and cell lines. The role of SMC1A on GC cell proliferation, migration, invasion and epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)were analyzed. Furthermore,the mechanism of SMC1A action was investigated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SMC1A was highly expressed in GC tissues and cell lines. The high expression of SMC1A indicated the poor overall survival of GC patients from Kaplan-Meier Plotter. Enhancing the expression of SMC1A in AGS remarkably promoted cell proliferation, migration and invasion. While knockdown of SMC1A in HCG27 inhibited cell proliferation, migration and invasion of HGC27 cells. Moreover, it’s observed that SMC1A promoted EMT and malignant cell behaviors via regulating SNAI2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;our study revealed SMC1A facilitates gastric cancer cell proliferation, migration and invasion via promoting SNAI2 activated EMT, which indicated SMC1A may be a potential target for gastric cancer therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461612" rel="alternate" title="SMC1A facilitates gastric cancer cells proliferation, migration and invasion via promoting SNAI2 activated EMT (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461496</id><title>DHODH is an independent prognostic marker and potent therapeutic target in neuroblastoma (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.127949+00:00</updated><author><name>Thale Kristin Olsen</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Dyberg</name></author><author><name>Bethel Embaie</name></author><author><name>Adele Alchahin</name></author><author><name>Jelena Milosevic</name></author><author><name>Jörg Otte</name></author><author><name>Conny Tümmler</name></author><author><name>Ida Hed Myrberg</name></author><author><name>Ellen M. Westerhout</name></author><author><name>Jan Koster</name></author><author><name>Rogier Versteeg</name></author><author><name>Per Kogner</name></author><author><name>John Inge Johnsen</name></author><author><name>David B. Sykes</name></author><author><name>Ninib Baryawno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite intensive therapy, children with high-risk neuroblastoma are at risk of treatment failure. We applied a pan-cancer, multi-omic system approach to evaluate metabolic vulnerabilities in human neuroblastoma. By combining metabolomics, CRISPR screen and gene expression data from more than 700 solid tumor cell lines, we identified &lt;italic&gt;DHODH&lt;/italic&gt;, a critical enzyme in pyrimidine synthesis, as a potential novel treatment target in neuroblastoma. Of note, DHODH inhibition is currently under clinical investigation in patients with hematologic malignancies. In neuroblastoma, &lt;italic&gt;DHODH&lt;/italic&gt; expression was identified as an independent risk factor for aggressive disease, and high &lt;italic&gt;DHODH&lt;/italic&gt; levels correlated to worse overall and event-free survival. A subset of high-risk neuroblastoma tumors with the highest &lt;italic&gt;DHODH&lt;/italic&gt; expression was associated with a dismal prognosis, with a 5-year survival of less than 10%. In neuroblastoma cell lines, &lt;italic&gt;DHODH&lt;/italic&gt; gene dependency was found to correlate with &lt;italic&gt;MYCN&lt;/italic&gt; dependency, rendering these cell lines highly sensitive to DHODH inhibition &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. In xenograft and transgenic neuroblastoma mouse models, tumor growth was dramatically reduced, and survival extended following treatment with the DHODH inhibitor brequinar. A combination of brequinar and temozolomide cured the majority of transgenic TH-MYCN neuroblastoma mice, indicating a highly active clinical combination therapy with curative potential. Overall, DHODH inhibition combined with temozolomde has clear therapeutic potential in neuroblastoma and we propose this combination as a candidate for clinical testing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461496" rel="alternate" title="DHODH is an independent prognostic marker and potent therapeutic target in neuroblastoma (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461749</id><title>Cancer missense mutations in the BRC repeats of BRCA2 protein disrupt RAD51 binding and activity leading to chemotherapeutic sensitivity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.128274+00:00</updated><author><name>Judit Jimenez-Sainz</name></author><author><name>Joshua Mathew</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Garbarino</name></author><author><name>Joseph P. Eder</name></author><author><name>Ryan B. Jensen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;BRCA2 is a tumor suppressor gene that maintains genome stability by mediating the high fidelity repair of DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) through homology-directed repair (HDR). Pathogenic mutations in BRCA2 predispose to breast, ovarian, pancreatic, prostate, and other cancers. Mutations in BRCA2 leading to severe protein truncation predict pathogenicity, however, missense mutations with unknown functional consequences, designated Variants of Uncertain Significance (VUS), comprise 60% of BRCA2 sequence changes deposited in clinical databases. Classifying BRCA2 VUS correctly is critical for relaying clinically actionable information to patients concerning future cancer risk or current treatment options. In this study, we identified and biochemically characterized three BRCA2 VUS located in BRC repeats to determine the impact on canonical HDR functions. Two of the germline variants, S1221P and T1980I, map to conserved residues in BRC2 and BRC7, disrupt RAD51 binding, and are diminished in their ability to stabilize RAD51-ssDNA complexes. We provide supporting cellular evidence that S1221P and T1980I are significantly compromised in their response to chemotherapeutics and ionizing radiation. The third variant, T1346I, lies within the spacer region between BRC2 and BRC3 but remains fully functional. We conclude that T1346I has a neutral impact on BRCA2 function, while S1221P and T1980I are hypomorphic alleles that disrupt the ability of BRCA2 to fully engage and stabilize RAD51 nucleoprotein filaments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions/Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BRCA2 missense variants, S1221P in BRC2 and T1980I in BRC7, are hypomorphic alleles which exhibit multiple defects in response to chemotherapeutics, DNA damage, and cellular stress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biochemical defects in S1221P and T1980I include disruption of RAD51 binding and failure to stimulate RAD51-ssDNA complex formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;-&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identification of a tumor derived somatic BRCA2 missense mutation in the spacer region between BRC2 and BRC3, T1346I, is a benign variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Potential Limitations&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that BRCA2 plays several roles in cellular function, it is possible that the VUS studied disrupt BRCA2 function in ways not measured by the assays described here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, further experimentation is necessary to validate the observed functionality of the variants studied and discern partial loss of function variants from fully neutral or pathogenic ones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overexpression of the &lt;italic&gt;BRCA2&lt;/italic&gt; cDNA may underestimate the functional effect of some variants. However, it is feasible that cDNA-based overexpression of these variants can partially rescue HR and other BRCA2 functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Caution is warranted when interpreting results from an assay focusing on a single specific biochemical activity to predict pathogenicity of BRCA2. This is extremely challenging for proteins with multiple biochemical and biological functions such as BRCA2. Up to date a small number of pathogenic or non-pathogenic variants have been evaluated and based on. Therefore, &lt;bold&gt;discriminating a true intermediate function variant from a neutral or fully pathogenic variant&lt;/bold&gt; remains difficult and integration of multiple functional assays may be necessary as the presented in this study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461749v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461749" rel="alternate" title="Cancer missense mutations in the BRC repeats of BRCA2 protein disrupt RAD51 binding and activity leading to chemotherapeutic sensitivity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461727</id><title>Insight into mammary gland development and tumor prevention in a newly developed metastatic mouse model of breast cancer (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.128443+00:00</updated><author><name>Briana To</name></author><author><name>Carson Broeker</name></author><author><name>Jing-Ru Jhan</name></author><author><name>Rachel Rempel</name></author><author><name>Jonathan P. Rennhack</name></author><author><name>Daniel Hollern</name></author><author><name>Lauren Jackson</name></author><author><name>David Judah</name></author><author><name>Matt Swiatnicki</name></author><author><name>Evan Bylett</name></author><author><name>Rachel Kubiak</name></author><author><name>Jordan Honeysett</name></author><author><name>Shams Reaz</name></author><author><name>Joseph Nevins</name></author><author><name>Eran Andrechek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of breast cancer has been observed due to altered regulation of mammary gland developmental processes. Thus, a better understand of the normal mammary gland development can reveal possible mechanism in how normal cells are re-programmed to become malignant cells. E2F1-4 are part of the E2F transcription factor family with varied roles in mammary development. However, little is known about the role of E2F5 in mammary gland development. A combination of scRNAseq and predictive signature tools demonstrate the presence of E2F5 in the mammary gland and showed altered activity during the various phases of mammary gland development and function. Testing the hypothesis that E2F5 regulates mammary function, we generated a mammary-specific E2F5 knockout mouse model, resulting in modest mammary gland development changes. However, after a prolonged latency the E2F5 conditional knockout mice developed highly metastatic mammary tumors with metastases in both the lung and liver. Transplantation of the tumors revealed metastases to lymph nodes that was enriched through serial transplantation. Through whole genome sequencing and RNAseq analysis we identified, and then confirmed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, that Cyclin D1 was dysregulated in E2F5 conditional knockout mammary glands and tumors. Based on these findings, we propose that loss of E2F5 leads altered regulation of Cyclin D1, which facilitates the development of mammary tumors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461727" rel="alternate" title="Insight into mammary gland development and tumor prevention in a newly developed metastatic mouse model of breast cancer (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461866</id><title>Spatiotemporal co-dependency between macrophages and exhausted CD8+ T cells in cancer (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.129106+00:00</updated><author><name>Kelly Kersten</name></author><author><name>Kenneth H. Hu</name></author><author><name>Alexis J. Combes</name></author><author><name>Bushra Samad</name></author><author><name>Tory Harwin</name></author><author><name>Arja Ray</name></author><author><name>Arjun Arkal Rao</name></author><author><name>En Cai</name></author><author><name>Kyle Marchuk</name></author><author><name>Jordan Artichoker</name></author><author><name>Tristan Courau</name></author><author><name>Quanming Shi</name></author><author><name>Julia Belk</name></author><author><name>Ansuman T. Satpathy</name></author><author><name>Matthew F. Krummel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T cell exhaustion is a major impediment to anti-tumor immunity. However, it remains elusive how other immune cells in the tumor microenvironment (TME) contribute to this dysfunctional state. Here we show that the biology of tumor-associated macrophages (TAM) and exhausted T cells (T&lt;sub&gt;ex&lt;/sub&gt;) in the TME is extensively linked. We demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; depletion of TAM reduces exhaustion programs in tumor-infiltrating CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells and reinvigorates their effector potential. Reciprocally, transcriptional and epigenetic profiling reveals that T&lt;sub&gt;ex&lt;/sub&gt; express factors that actively recruit monocytes to the TME and shape their differentiation. Using lattice light sheet microscopy, we show that TAM and CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells engage in unique long-lasting antigen-specific synaptic interactions that fail to activate T cells, but prime them for exhaustion, which is then accelerated in hypoxic conditions. Spatially resolved sequencing supports a spatiotemporal self-enforcing positive feedback circuit that is aligned to protect rather than destroy a tumor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461866v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461866" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal co-dependency between macrophages and exhausted CD8+ T cells in cancer (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461934</id><title>HSD11β1 promotes EMT-mediated breast cancer metastasis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.129422+00:00</updated><author><name>Joji Nakayama</name></author><author><name>Takamasa Ishikawa</name></author><author><name>Tatsunori Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Sanae Yamanaka</name></author><author><name>Noriko Gotoh</name></author><author><name>Chisako Yamauchi</name></author><author><name>Tatsuya Ohnishi</name></author><author><name>Tomoyoshi Soga</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Fujii</name></author><author><name>Hideki Makinoshima</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abnormal biosyntheses of steroid hormones and dysregulation of steroid hormone receptors contribute to breast cancer metastasis but the mechanisms of that are poorly understand. Here we report a stress hormone producing enzyme, Hydroxysteroid (11-Beta) Dehydrogenase 1 (HSD11β1) promotes breast cancer metastasis. HSD11β1 was ectopically expressed in seventy-one percent of triple-negative breast tumors and correlated with shorter overall survival. HSD11β1 significantly promoted breast cancer metastasis through induction of epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT); conversely, pharmacologic and genetic inhibition of HSD11β1 suppressed metastatic progression of breast cancer cells. Moreover, 11-hydroxyprogesterone (11-OHP) whom HSD11β1 produced in breast cancer cells, conferred metastatic properties on non-metastatic breast cancer cells through induction of EMT. We identified Peroxisome Proliferator-activated Receptor Alpha (PPAR-α) as essential for both HSD11β1 and 11OHP-driven EMT. Knockdown of PPAR-α induced MET on HSD11β1-expressing breast cancer cells. Taken together, HSD11β1 promotes breast cancer metastasis and would be a novel target for suppressing breast cancer metastasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461934" rel="alternate" title="HSD11β1 promotes EMT-mediated breast cancer metastasis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461957</id><title>Modeling tissue-specific breakpoint proximity of structural variations from 2,382 whole-genomes to identify cancer drivers (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.129630+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Martinez-Fundichely</name></author><author><name>Austin Dixon</name></author><author><name>Ekta Khurana</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural variations (SVs) in cancer cells often impact large genomic regions with functional consequences. However, little is known about the genomic features related to the breakpoint distribution of SVs in different cancers, a prerequisite to distinguish loci under positive selection from those with neutral evolution. We developed a method that uses a generalized additive model to investigate the breakpoint proximity curves from 2,382 whole-genomes of 32 cancer types. We find that a multivariate model, which includes linear and nonlinear partial contributions of various tissue-specific features and their interaction terms, can explain up to 57% of the observed deviance of breakpoint proximity. In particular, three-dimensional genomic features such as topologically associating domains (TADs), TAD-boundaries and their interaction with other features show significant contributions. The model is validated by identification of known cancer genes and revealed putative drivers in novel cancers that have previous evidence of therapeutic relevance in other cancers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461957" rel="alternate" title="Modeling tissue-specific breakpoint proximity of structural variations from 2,382 whole-genomes to identify cancer drivers (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462102</id><title>Tumor-Cell Invasion Initiates at Invasion Hotspots, an Epithelial Tissue-Intrinsic Microenvironment (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.129865+00:00</updated><author><name>Rei Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Takishima</name></author><author><name>Sheng Deng</name></author><author><name>Yasuyuki Fujita</name></author><author><name>Yoichiro Tamori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malignant cancers emerge in epithelial tissues through a progressive process in which a single transformed mutant cell becomes tumorigenic and invasive. Although numerous genes involved in the malignant transformation of cancer cells have been described, how tumor cells launch an invasion into the basal side of epithelial tissues remains elusive. Here, using a &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; wing imaginal disc epithelia, we show that genetically mosaic clones of cells mutant for a neoplastic-tumor-suppressor gene (&lt;italic&gt;nTSG&lt;/italic&gt;) in combination with the oncogenic Ras (&lt;italic&gt;Ras&lt;sup&gt;V12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;) expression initiate invasion into the basal side of the epithelial layer at specific spots in the epithelial tissue. In this “invasion hotspot”, the oncogenic double-mutant cells activate c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) signaling, which causes basal extrusion of the double-mutant cells and destruction of basement membrane through upregulation of a matrix metalloprotease, MMP1. Conversely, in other regions of the epithelial tissue, the double-mutant cells do not strongly activate JNK, deviate from the apical side of the epithelial layer, and show benign tumor growth in the lumen. These data indicate that the onset of tumor-cell invasion is highly dependent on the tissue-intrinsic local microenvironment. Given the conservation of genetic signaling pathways involved in this process, initiation of tumor-cell invasion from invasion hotspots in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; wing imaginal epithelia could help us to understand the developmental mechanisms of invasive cancers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462102" rel="alternate" title="Tumor-Cell Invasion Initiates at Invasion Hotspots, an Epithelial Tissue-Intrinsic Microenvironment (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462067</id><title>Nanopore sequencing methods detect cell-free DNA associated with minimal residual disease and central nervous system infiltration in pediatric Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.130048+00:00</updated><author><name>Shilpa Sampathi</name></author><author><name>Yelena Chernyavskaya</name></author><author><name>Meghan G. Haney</name></author><author><name>L. Henry Moore</name></author><author><name>Isabel A. Snyder</name></author><author><name>Anna H. Cox</name></author><author><name>Tamara J. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Brittany L. Fuller</name></author><author><name>Tom C. Badgett</name></author><author><name>Jessica S. Blackburn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) patients that have minimal residual disease (MRD) after therapy or infiltration of ALL into the central nervous system (CNS) are considered high risk. These patients are often given intensified and/or additional rounds of chemotherapy in the hopes of eliminating their disease. Current methods to diagnose MRD and CNS infiltration rely on detecting ALL cells in patient samples using pathology, flow cytometry, or isolation of ALL genomic DNA for next-generation sequencing. However, blasts may be present in the patient but not detectable in a bone marrow biopsy or cerebrospinal (CSF) fluid sample, leading to incorrect or delayed patient diagnosis. We have developed a nanopore sequencing assay to detect B-ALL-associated cell-free DNA in patient blood and CSF samples. Quantitation of B-cell specific VDJ recombination events in cell-free DNA samples defined B-ALL clonal heterogeneity. Monitoring cfDNA in blood and CSF samples allowed us to track the response of individual B-ALL clones throughout each patient’s course of treatment. Detection of cell-free DNA predicted the clinical diagnosis of MRD and CNS disease. We also identified patients diagnosed as CNS negative who had low levels of cell-free DNA in their CSF sample. These data suggest that cell-free DNA assays may be useful in detecting the presence of ALL in the patient even when blasts are not in the biofluid sample. In total, nanopore analysis of cell-free DNA is a simple, rapid, and inexpensive assay that can serve as a useful complement to traditional clinical diagnostic approaches in the treatment of ALL.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462067" rel="alternate" title="Nanopore sequencing methods detect cell-free DNA associated with minimal residual disease and central nervous system infiltration in pediatric Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462786</id><title>Chi3l1 is a modulator of glioma stem cell states and a therapeutic vulnerability for glioblastoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.130254+00:00</updated><author><name>Charlotte Guetta-Terrier</name></author><author><name>David Karambizi</name></author><author><name>Bedia Akosman</name></author><author><name>Jia-Shu Chen</name></author><author><name>Suchitra Kamle</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Fajardo</name></author><author><name>Andras Fiser</name></author><author><name>Ritambhara Singh</name></author><author><name>Steven A. Toms</name></author><author><name>Chun Geun Lee</name></author><author><name>Jack A. Elias</name></author><author><name>Nikos Tapinos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chi3l1 (Chitinase 3-like 1) is a secreted protein highly expressed in glioblastoma. Here, we show that exposure of glioma stem cells (GSCs) to Chi3l1 reduces the CD133&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/SOX2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells and increases the CD44&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/Chi3l1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells. Chi3l1 binds to CD44 and induces phosphorylation and nuclear translocation of beta-catenin, Akt and STAT3. Single cell RNA-seq and RNA velocity following incubation of GSCs with Chi3l1 show significant changes in GSC state dynamics driving GSCs towards a mesenchymal expression profile and reducing transition probabilities towards terminal cellular states. ATAC-seq reveals that Chi3l1 increases accessibility of promoters containing MAZ transcription factor footprint. Inhibition of MAZ directly regulates genes with highest expression in cellular clusters exhibiting significant cell state transitions. Finally, targeting Chi3l1 in vivo with a blocking antibody, resets the transcriptomic profile of glioblastoma and inhibits tumor growth. Our work implicates Chi3l1 as modulator of GSC cellular states and demonstrates pre-clinical efficacy of anti-Chi3l1 antibody treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462786" rel="alternate" title="Chi3l1 is a modulator of glioma stem cell states and a therapeutic vulnerability for glioblastoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461902</id><title>Lomitapide, a cholesterol-lowering drug, is an anticancer agent that induces autophagic cell death via inhibiting mTOR (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.130543+00:00</updated><author><name>Boah Lee</name></author><author><name>Seung Ju Park</name></author><author><name>Seulgi Lee</name></author><author><name>Jinwook Lee</name></author><author><name>Eunbeol Lee</name></author><author><name>Eun-Seon Yoo</name></author><author><name>Won-Suk Chung</name></author><author><name>Jong-Woo Sohn</name></author><author><name>Byung-Chul Oh</name></author><author><name>Seyun Kim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autophagy is a biological process that maintains cellular homeostasis and regulates the internal cellular environment. Hyperactivating autophagy to trigger cell death has been a suggested therapeutic strategy for cancer treatment. Mechanistic target of rapamycin (mTOR) is a crucial protein kinase that regulates autophagy; therefore, using a structure-based virtual screen analysis, we identified lomitapide, a cholesterol-lowering drug, as a potential mTOR complex 1 (mTORC1) inhibitor. Our results showed that lomitapide directly inhibits mTORC1 &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and induces autophagy-dependent cancer cell death by decreasing mTOR signaling, thereby inhibiting the downstream events associated with increased LC3 conversion in various cancer cells (e.g., HCT116 colorectal cancer cells) and tumor xenografts. Lomitapide also significantly suppresses the growth and viability along with elevated autophagy in patient-derived colorectal cancer organoids. Furthermore, a combination of lomitapide and immune checkpoint blocking antibodies synergistically inhibits tumor growth in murine MC-38 or B16-F10 pre-clinical syngeneic tumor models. These results elucidates the direct, tumor-relevant immune-potentiating benefits of mTORC1 inhibition by lomitapide, which complement the current immune checkpoint blockade. This study highlights the potential repurposing of lomitapide as a new therapeutic option for cancer treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461902" rel="alternate" title="Lomitapide, a cholesterol-lowering drug, is an anticancer agent that induces autophagic cell death via inhibiting mTOR (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>