<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.141072+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.458711</id><title>Targeting metabolic adaptations in the breast cancer–liver metastatic niche using dietary approaches to improve endocrine therapy efficacy (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.141510+00:00</updated><author><name>Qianying Zuo</name></author><author><name>Ayca Nazli Mogol</name></author><author><name>Yu-Jeh Liu</name></author><author><name>Ashlie Santaliz Casiano</name></author><author><name>Christine Chien</name></author><author><name>Jenny Drnevich</name></author><author><name>Ozan Berk Imir</name></author><author><name>Eylem Kulkoyluoglu-Cotul</name></author><author><name>Nicole Hwajin Park</name></author><author><name>David J Shapiro</name></author><author><name>Ben Ho Park</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Ziegler</name></author><author><name>Benita S. Katzenellenbogen</name></author><author><name>Evelyn Aranda</name></author><author><name>John D. O’Neill</name></author><author><name>Akshara Singareeka Raghavendra</name></author><author><name>Debu Tripathy</name></author><author><name>Zeynep Madak Erdogan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estrogen receptor-positive (ER&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;) metastatic tumors contribute to nearly 70% of breast cancer-related deaths. Most patients with ER&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; metastatic breast cancer (MBC) undergo treatment with the estrogen receptor agonist fulvestrant (Fulv) as standard of care. Yet, among such patients, metastasis in liver is associated with reduced overall survival compared to other metastasis sites. The factors underlying the reduced responsiveness of liver metastases to ER agonists remain unknown, impeding the development of more effective treatment approaches to improve outcomes for patients with ER&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; liver metastases. We therefore evaluated site-specific changes in MBC cells and determined the mechanisms through which the liver metastatic niche specifically influences ER&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; tumor metabolism and drug resistance. We characterized ER activity of MBC cells both in vitro, using a novel system of tissue-specific extracellular matrix hydrogels representing the stroma of ER&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; tumor metastatic sites (liver, lung and bone), and in vivo, in liver and lung metastasis mouse models. ER&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; metastatic liver tumors and MBC cells grown in liver hydrogels displayed upregulated expression of glucose metabolism enzymes in response to Fulv. Furthermore, differential ERα activity, but not expression, was detected in liver hydrogels. In vivo, increased glucose metabolism led to increased glycogen deposition in liver metastatic tumors, while a fasting-mimicking diet increased efficacy of Fulv treatment to reduce the metastatic burden. Our findings identify a novel mechanism of endocrine resistance driven by the liver tumor microenvironment. These results may guide the development of dietary strategies to circumvent drug resistance in liver metastasis, with potential applicability in other metastatic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.458711" rel="alternate" title="Targeting metabolic adaptations in the breast cancer–liver metastatic niche using dietary approaches to improve endocrine therapy efficacy (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459864</id><title>Cysteine induces mitochondrial reductive stress in glioblastoma through hydrogen peroxide production (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.141905+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan K. Noch</name></author><author><name>Laura Palma</name></author><author><name>Isaiah Yim</name></author><author><name>Daniel Barnett</name></author><author><name>Alexander Walsh</name></author><author><name>Bhavneet Bhinder</name></author><author><name>Elisa Benedetti</name></author><author><name>Jan Krumsiek</name></author><author><name>Justin Gurvitch</name></author><author><name>Sumaiyah Khwaja</name></author><author><name>Olivier Elemento</name></author><author><name>Lewis Cantley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glucose and amino acid metabolism are critical for glioblastoma (GBM) growth, but little is known about the specific metabolic alterations in GBM that are targetable with FDA-approved compounds. To investigate tumor metabolism signatures unique to GBM, we interrogated The Cancer Genome Atlas for alterations in glucose and amino acid signatures in GBM relative to other human cancers and found that GBM exhibits the highest levels of cysteine and methionine pathway gene expression of 32 human cancers. Treatment of patient-derived GBM cells with the FDA-approved cysteine compound N-acetylcysteine (NAC) reduce GBM cell growth and mitochondrial oxygen consumption, which was worsened by glucose starvation. Mechanistic experiments revealed that cysteine compounds induce rapid mitochondrial hydrogen peroxide production and reductive stress in GBM cells, an effect blocked by oxidized glutathione, thioredoxin, and redox enzyme overexpression. These findings indicate that GBM is uniquely susceptible to NAC-driven reductive stress and could synergize with glucose-lowering treatments for GBM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459864" rel="alternate" title="Cysteine induces mitochondrial reductive stress in glioblastoma through hydrogen peroxide production (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459062</id><title>SETDB1 Fuels the Lung Cancer Phenotype by Modulating Epigenome, 3D Genome Organization and Chromatin Mechanical Properties (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.142287+00:00</updated><author><name>Vlada V. Zakharova</name></author><author><name>Mikhail D. Magnitov</name></author><author><name>Laurence Del-Maestro</name></author><author><name>Sergey V. Ulianov</name></author><author><name>Alexandros Glentis</name></author><author><name>Burhan Ulyanik</name></author><author><name>Alice Williart</name></author><author><name>Anna Karpukhina</name></author><author><name>Oleg Demidov</name></author><author><name>Veronique Joliot</name></author><author><name>Yegor S. Vassetzky</name></author><author><name>René-Marc Mège</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Piel</name></author><author><name>Sergey V. Razin</name></author><author><name>Slimane Ait-Si-Ali</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Imbalance in the finely orchestrated system of chromatin-modifying enzymes is a hallmark of many pathologies such as cancers, since causing the affection of the epigenome and transcriptional reprogramming. Here, we demonstrate that a loss-of-function mutation (LOF) of the major histone lysine methyltransferase SETDB1 possessing oncogenic activity in lung cancer cells leads to broad changes in the overall architecture and mechanical properties of the nucleus through genome-wide redistribution of heterochromatin, which perturbs chromatin spatial compartmentalization. Together with the enforced activation of the epithelial expression program, cytoskeleton remodeling, reduced proliferation rate and restricted cellular migration, this leads to the reversed oncogenic potential of lung adenocarcinoma cells. These results emphasize an essential role of chromatin architecture in the determination of oncogenic programs and illustrate a relationship between gene expression, epigenome, 3D genome and nuclear mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459062" rel="alternate" title="SETDB1 Fuels the Lung Cancer Phenotype by Modulating Epigenome, 3D Genome Organization and Chromatin Mechanical Properties (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459734</id><title>Deep Learning identifies new morphological patterns of Homologous Recombination Deficiency in luminal breast cancers from whole slide images. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.142840+00:00</updated><author><name>Tristan Lazard</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Bataillon</name></author><author><name>Peter Naylor</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Popova</name></author><author><name>Francois-clement Bidard</name></author><author><name>Dominique Stoppa-Lyonnet</name></author><author><name>Marc-Henri Stern</name></author><author><name>Etienne Decenciere</name></author><author><name>Thomas Walter</name></author><author><name>Anne Salomon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Homologous Recombination DNA-repair deficiency (HRD) is a well-recognized marker of platinum-salt and PARP inhibitor chemotherapies in ovarian and breast cancers (BC). Causing high genomic instability, HRD is currently determined by BRCA1/2 sequencing or by genomic signatures, but its morphological manifestation is not well understood. Deep Learning (DL) is a powerful machine learning technique that has been recently shown to be capable of predicting genomic signatures from stained tissue slides. However, DL is known to be sensitive to dataset biases and lacks interpretability. Here, we present and evaluate a strategy to control for biases in retrospective cohorts. We train a deep-learning model to predict the HRD in a controlled cohort with unprecedented accuracy (AUC: 0.86) and we develop a new visualization technique that allows for automatic extraction of new morphological features related to HRD. We analyze in detail the extracted morphological patterns that open new hypotheses on the phenotypic impact of HRD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459734" rel="alternate" title="Deep Learning identifies new morphological patterns of Homologous Recombination Deficiency in luminal breast cancers from whole slide images. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>