<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.777970+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467244</id><title>Mapping single-cell transcriptomes to copy number evolutionary trees (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.778877+00:00</updated><author><name>Pedro F Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Jack Kuipers</name></author><author><name>Niko Beerenwinkel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer arises and evolves by the accumulation of somatic mutations that provide a selective advantage. The interplay of mutations and their functional consequences shape the evolutionary dynamics of tumors and contribute to different clinical outcomes. In the absence of scalable methods to jointly assay genomic and transcriptomic profiles of the same individual cell, the two data modalities are usually measured separately and need to be integrated computationally. Here, we introduce SCATrEx, a statistical model to map single-cell gene expression data onto the evolutionary history of copy number alterations of the tumor. SCATrEx jointly assigns cancer cells assayed with scRNA-seq to copy number profiles arranged in a copy number aberration tree and augments the tree with clone-specific clusters. Our simulations show that SCATrEx improves over both state-of-the-art unsupervised clustering methods and cell-to-clone assignment methods. In an application to real data, we observe that SCATrEx finds inter-clone and intra-clone gene expression heterogeneity not detectable using other integration methods. SCATrEx will allow for a better understanding of tumor evolution by jointly analysing the genomic and transcriptomic changes that drive it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467244" rel="alternate" title="Mapping single-cell transcriptomes to copy number evolutionary trees (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466907</id><title>Single-cell epigenetic analysis reveals principles of chromatin states in H3.3-K27M gliomas (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.780507+00:00</updated><author><name>Nofar Harpaz</name></author><author><name>Tamir Mittelman</name></author><author><name>Olga Beresh</name></author><author><name>Tomer-Meir Salame</name></author><author><name>Noa Furth</name></author><author><name>Guy Ron</name></author><author><name>Efrat Shema</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer cells are highly heterogeneous, both at the transcriptional level and in their epigenetic state. Methods to study epigenetic heterogeneity are limited in their throughput and the information obtained per cell. Here, we adapted Cytometry by Time of Flight (CyTOF) to analyze a wide panel of histone modifications and chromatin regulators in primary tumor-derived lines of Diffused Intrinsic Pontine Glioma (DIPG). DIPG is a lethal pediatric brain cancer, driven by a mutation in histone H3 leading to substitution of lysine 27 with methionine (H3-K27M mutation). We identified two epigenetically distinct subpopulations in DIGP, reflecting inherent heterogeneity in the expression levels of the mutant histone. These two epigenetic subpopulations are robust across tumor lines derived from different patients and show differential proliferation capacity as well as expression of stem-cell and differentiation markers. Moreover, we demonstrate the use of this single-cell high-dimensional data to elucidate potential interactions between histone modifications and epigenetic alterations during the cell-cycle. Our work establishes new concepts for the analysis of epigenetic heterogeneity and cross-talk in cancer that could be applied to diverse biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466907" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell epigenetic analysis reveals principles of chromatin states in H3.3-K27M gliomas (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466939</id><title>DDK inhibition disrupts replication leading to mitotic catastrophe in Ewing sarcoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.796726+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey C Martin</name></author><author><name>Ajay Gupta</name></author><author><name>Tamara J Hagoel</name></author><author><name>Lingqiu Gao</name></author><author><name>Miranda L. Lynch</name></author><author><name>Anna Woloszynska</name></author><author><name>Thomas Melendy</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Kane</name></author><author><name>Joseph Kuechle</name></author><author><name>Joyce Ohm</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ewing sarcoma is the second most common bone malignancy in children and adolescents. Patients with upfront metastatic or recurrent disease have poor outcomes with 5-year survival rates of &amp;lt;30%. CDC7, also known as DDK (DBF4-dependent kinase), is a serine-threonine kinase that, in coordination with its activation subunit ASK (or DBF4), is involved in a diverse array of cellular functions including the regulation of DNA replication initiation and activation of the replication stress response. Due to DDK diverse roles during replication, coupled with an increased level of genomic instability and R-loop-mediated replication stress within Ewing sarcoma cells, we hypothesized that Ewing sarcoma cells would be particularly vulnerable to DDK inhibitors. Here, we show that treatment with two selective DDK inhibitors, TAK-931 and XL413, results in apoptosis and a significant reduction in cell viability in EWS-FLI1-harboring Ewing sarcoma cell lines. We show that low dose DDK inhibition in Ewing sarcoma cells causes an accumulation of cells in late-S phase with a reduced replication capacity. There is also evidence of premature mitotic entry indicating an inability to properly complete DNA replication in a timely manner upon DDK inhibition. Also, there is a significant increase in the formation of micronuclei and other aberrant mitotic structures upon DDK inhibition in Ewing sarcoma cells indicating a failure to properly progress through S-phase followed by improper mitotic entry/progression, resulting in mitotic catastrophe. Interestingly, we observed minimal signs of mitotic accumulation, despite clear evidence of replication and mitotic stress, suggesting a failure to properly enforce the mitotic checkpoint. Together, these results suggest that Ewing sarcoma cells rely on the activity of DDK to maintain cell viability and suggest that DDK inhibition may prove to be a viable therapeutic strategy for patients with Ewing sarcoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466939" rel="alternate" title="DDK inhibition disrupts replication leading to mitotic catastrophe in Ewing sarcoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466444</id><title>Improving mathematical models of cancer by including resistance to therapy: a study in non-small cell lung cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.797991+00:00</updated><author><name>Virginia Ardévol Martinez</name></author><author><name>Narmin Ghaffari Laleh</name></author><author><name>Monica Salvioli</name></author><author><name>Frank Thuijsman</name></author><author><name>Joel S. Brown</name></author><author><name>Rachel Cavill</name></author><author><name>Jakob Nikolas Kather</name></author><author><name>Kateřina Staňková</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, a large dataset of 590 Non-Small Cell Lung Patients treated with either chemotherapy or immunotherapy was used to determine whether a game-theoretic model including both evolution of therapy resistance and cost of resistance provides a better fit than classical mathematical models of population growth (exponential, logistic, classic Bertalanffy, general Bertalanffy, Gompertz, general Gompertz). This is the first time a large clinical patient cohort (as opposed to only in-vitro data) has been used to apply a game-theoretic cancer model. The game-theoretic model provides a better fit to the tumor dynamics of the 590 Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer patients than any of the non-evolutionary population growth models. This is not simply due to having more parameters in the game-theoretic model. The game-theoretic model is able to fit accurately patients whose tumor burden exhibit a U-shaped trajectory over time. We then demonstrate how this game-theoretic model provides predictions of tumor growth based on just a few initial measurements. Assuming that treatment-specific parameters define the treatment impact completely, we then explore alternative treatment protocols and their impact on the tumor growth. As such, the model can be used to suggest patient-specific optimal treatment regimens with the goal of minimizing final tumor burden. Therapeutic protocols based on game-theoretic modeling can predict tumor growth, and improve patient outcome. The model invites evolutionary therapies that anticipate and steer the evolution of therapy resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466444" rel="alternate" title="Improving mathematical models of cancer by including resistance to therapy: a study in non-small cell lung cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265077</id><title>Predicting Melanoma Staging using Targeted RNA Sequencing data using Machine Learning. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.798367+00:00</updated><author><name>Fahad Shabbir Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Furqan Bin Irfan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study is to use machine learning to predict tumor staging and metastasis in melanoma with differentially expressed genes. Machine has been used in different clinical setting to predict different outcomes. However, it has not been used to look at predicting the diagnostic aspect of tumor staging. We used the TCGA RNA-Sequencing data on melanomas to predict tumor staging nodal and/or metastasis using deep neural networks (DNN) and random forest classifier (RF). Results: We were able to predict tumor staging (lower vs higher stage, i.e. Tis / T1 / T2 vs T3 and higher), nodal metastasis and combined nodal or distant metastasis in patients with melanomas with high accuracies. However, we need to further validate these results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.21265077" rel="alternate" title="Predicting Melanoma Staging using Targeted RNA Sequencing data using Machine Learning. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>