<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.996939+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468622</id><title>The evolution of genomic, transcriptomic, and single-cell protein markers of metastatic upper tract urothelial carcinoma (80 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.997351+00:00</updated><author><name>Kentaro Ohara</name></author><author><name>Andrè Figueiredo Rendeiro</name></author><author><name>Bhavneet Bhinder</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Wha Eng</name></author><author><name>Hiranmayi Ravichandran</name></author><author><name>David Pisapia</name></author><author><name>Aram Vosoughi</name></author><author><name>Evan Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Kyrillus Shohdy</name></author><author><name>Jyothi Manohar</name></author><author><name>Shaham Beg</name></author><author><name>David Wilkes</name></author><author><name>Brian Robinson</name></author><author><name>Francesca Khani</name></author><author><name>Rohan Bareja</name></author><author><name>Scott Tagawa</name></author><author><name>Andrea Sboner</name></author><author><name>Olivier Elemento</name></author><author><name>Bishoy Morris Faltas</name></author><author><name>Juan Miguel Mosquera</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The molecular characteristics of metastatic upper tract urothelial carcinoma (UTUC) are unknown. The genomic and transcriptomic differences between primary and metastatic UTUC is not well described either. We combined whole-exome sequencing, RNA-sequencing, and Imaging Mass Cytometry&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; (IMC&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt;) of 44 tumor samples from 28 patients with high-grade primary and metastatic UTUC. IMC enables spatially resolved single-cell analyses to examine the evolution of cancer cell, immune cell, and stromal cell markers using mass cytometry with lanthanide metal-conjugated antibodies. We discovered that actionable genomic alterations are frequently discordant between primary and metastatic UTUC tumors in the same patient. In contrast, molecular subtype membership and immune depletion signature were stable across primary and matched metastatic UTUC. Molecular and immune subtypes were consistent between bulk RNA-sequencing and mass cytometry of protein markers from 340,798 single-cells. Molecular subtyping at the single cell level was highly conserved between primary and metastatic UTUC tumors within the same patient.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468622" rel="alternate" title="The evolution of genomic, transcriptomic, and single-cell protein markers of metastatic upper tract urothelial carcinoma (80 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469182</id><title>TK216 targets microtubules in Ewing sarcoma cells (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.997645+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Manuel Povedano Selfa</name></author><author><name>Vicky Li</name></author><author><name>Katherine E. Lake</name></author><author><name>Xin Bai</name></author><author><name>Rameshu Rallabandi</name></author><author><name>Jiwoong Kim</name></author><author><name>Yang Xie</name></author><author><name>Jef K. De Brabander</name></author><author><name>David G. McFadden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ewing sarcoma (EWS) is a pediatric malignancy driven by the EWSR1-FLI1 fusion protein formed by the chromosomal translocation t(11;22).  The small molecule TK216 was developed as a first-in-class direct EWSR1-FLI1 inhibitor and is in phase II clinical trials in combination with vincristine for EWS patients. However, TK216 exhibits anti-cancer activity against cancer cell lines and xenografts that do not express EWSR1-FLI1, and the mechanism underlying cytotoxicity remains unresolved. We apply a forward genetics screening platform utilizing engineered hypermutation in EWS cell lines and identify recurrent mutations in TUBA1B, encoding α-tubulin, that prove sufficient to drive resistance to TK216.  Using reconstituted microtubule (MT) polymerization in vitro and cell-based chemical probe competition assays, we demonstrate that TK216 acts as an MT destabilizing agent. This work defines the mechanism of cytotoxicity of TK216, explains the synergy observed with vincristine, and calls for a reexamination of ongoing clinical trials with TK216.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469182" rel="alternate" title="TK216 targets microtubules in Ewing sarcoma cells (20 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468656</id><title>A nuclear cAMP microdomain suppresses tumor growth by Hippo pathway inactivation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.997807+00:00</updated><author><name>Marek M. Drozdz</name></author><author><name>Ashley S. Doane</name></author><author><name>Rached Alkallas</name></author><author><name>Garrett Desman</name></author><author><name>Rohan Bareja</name></author><author><name>Michael Reilly</name></author><author><name>Jakyung Bang</name></author><author><name>Maftuna Yusupova</name></author><author><name>Jaewon You</name></author><author><name>Jenny Z. Wang</name></author><author><name>Akansha Verma</name></author><author><name>Kelsey Aguirre</name></author><author><name>Elsbeth Kane</name></author><author><name>Ian R. Watson</name></author><author><name>Olivier Elemento</name></author><author><name>Elena Piskounova</name></author><author><name>Taha Merghoub</name></author><author><name>Jonathan H. Zippin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;cAMP signaling pathways are critical for both oncogenesis and tumor suppression. cAMP signaling is localized to multiple spatially distinct microdomains, but the role of cAMP microdomains in cancer cell biology is poorly understood. We developed a tunable genetic system that allows us to activate cAMP signaling in specific microdomains. We uncovered a previously unappreciated nuclear cAMP microdomain that functionally activates a tumor suppressive pathway in a broad range of cancers by inhibiting YAP, a key effector protein of the Hippo pathway, inside the nucleus. We show that nuclear cAMP induces a LATS-dependent pathway leading to phosphorylation of nuclear YAP solely at serine 397, export of YAP from the nucleus, without YAP protein degradation. Thus, nuclear cAMP inhibition of nuclear YAP is distinct from other known mechanisms of Hippo regulation. Pharmacologic targeting of specific cAMP microdomains remains an untapped therapeutic approach for cancer, and since Hippo pathway deregulation can lead to oncogenesis and chemotherapeutic resistance, drugs directed at the nuclear cAMP microdomain may provide new avenues for the treatment of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468656" rel="alternate" title="A nuclear cAMP microdomain suppresses tumor growth by Hippo pathway inactivation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469115</id><title>Characterization of plasma circulating small extracellular vesicles in patients with metastatic solid tumors and newly diagnosed brain metastasis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.998015+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Carretero-González</name></author><author><name>Sara Sánchez-Redondo</name></author><author><name>Luis Manso Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Eva Ciruelos Gil</name></author><author><name>Daniel Castellano</name></author><author><name>Marta Hergueta-Redondo</name></author><author><name>Guillermo de Velasco</name></author><author><name>Héctor Peinado</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nearly 40% of the advanced cancer patients will present brain metastases during the course of their disease, with a 2-year life expectancy of less than 10%. Immune system impairment, including the modulation of both STAT3 and PD-L1, is one of the hallmarks of brain metastases. Liquid biopsy could offer several advantages in brain metastases management, such as the possibility of non-invasive dynamic monitoring. Extracellular vesicles (EVs) have been recently proposed as novel biomarkers especially useful in liquid biopsy due to their secretion in biofluids and their role in cell communication during tumor progression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main aim of this work was to characterize the size and protein cargo of plasma circulating EVs in patients with solid tumors and their correlation with newly diagnosed brain metastases, in addition to their association with other relevant clinical variables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed circulating EVs in the plasma of 123 patients: 42 patients with brain metastases, 50 without brain metastases and 31 healthy controls. Patients with newly diagnosed brain metastases had a lower number of circulating EVs in the plasma and a higher protein concentration in small EVs (sEVs) compared to patients without brain metastases and healthy controls. Interestingly, melanoma patients with brain metastases presented decreased STAT3 activation and increased PD-L1 levels in circulating sEVs compared to patients without central nervous system metastases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decreased STAT3 activation and increased PD-L1 in plasma circulating sEVs identify melanoma patients with brain metastasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of translational relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brain metastases are critical for outcomes and quality of life in almost 50% of oncological patients, generally associated with a poor short-term prognosis. Early or preventive diagnosis of this complication represents an unmet need. There is a necessity of discovering new biomarkers that could aid to predict disease outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we analyzed plasma circulating extracellular vesicles (EVs) from a cohort of 92 patients with different solid tumors (lung, breast, kidney cancer and melanoma) and found that newly diagnosed patients with brain metastases presented lower number of circulating particles and a higher protein concentration in small extracellular vesicles (sEVs) compared to patients without brain metastases and healthy controls. Out of all groups analyzed, melanoma patients with brain metastases presented decreased STAT3 activation and increased PD-L1 levels in circulating sEVs compared to patients without central nervous system metastases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data presented in this work suggest that circulating sEVs may represent the immunosuppressive status of newly diagnosed brain metastases characterized by the reduced phospho-STAT3 (pSTAT3) and increased PD-L1, although the origin of these molecules found in circulating sEVs remains to be uncovered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469115" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of plasma circulating small extracellular vesicles in patients with metastatic solid tumors and newly diagnosed brain metastasis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.21266196</id><title>Development of an accessible gene expression bioinformatics pipeline to study driver mutations of colorectal cancer (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.998212+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa van den Driest</name></author><author><name>Caroline H Johnson</name></author><author><name>Nicholas JW Rattray</name></author><author><name>Zahra Rattray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Colorectal cancer (CRC) is a global cause of cancer-related mortality driven by genetic and environmental factors which influence therapeutic outcomes. The emergence of next-generation sequencing technologies enables the rapid and extensive collection and curation of genetic data for each cancer type into clinical gene expression biobanks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study we used a combination of bioinformatics tools to investigate the expression patterns and prognostic significance of two genes, adenomatous polyposis coli (&lt;italic&gt;APC&lt;/italic&gt;) and B-Raf proto-oncogene (&lt;italic&gt;BRAF&lt;/italic&gt;), that are commonly dysregulated in colon cancer. Subsequently, we investigated the pathways and biomolecular effectors implicated in &lt;italic&gt;APC&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;BRAF&lt;/italic&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results show mutation types, frequency, anatomical location and differential expression patterns for &lt;italic&gt;APC&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;BRAF&lt;/italic&gt; between colorectal tumour and matched healthy tissue. The prognostic values of &lt;italic&gt;APC&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;BRAF&lt;/italic&gt; was investigated as a function of expression level in CRC and other cancer types.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the era of precision medicine and with significant advancements in biobanking and data curation, there is significant scope to use existing clinical datasets for evaluating the role of mutational drivers in carcinogenesis. This offers the potential for studying combinations of less well-known genes and the discovery of novel biomarkers or studying the association between various effector proteins and pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.21266196" rel="alternate" title="Development of an accessible gene expression bioinformatics pipeline to study driver mutations of colorectal cancer (8 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468684</id><title>Engraftment of allotransplantated tumour cells in adult rag2 mutant Xenopus tropicalis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.998468+00:00</updated><author><name>Dieter Tulkens</name></author><author><name>Dionysia Dimitrakopoulou</name></author><author><name>Tom Van Nieuwenhuysen</name></author><author><name>Marthe Boelens</name></author><author><name>Suzan Demuynck</name></author><author><name>Wendy Toussaint</name></author><author><name>David Creytens</name></author><author><name>Pieter Van Vlierberghe</name></author><author><name>Kris Vleminckx</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modelling human genetic diseases and cancer in lab animals has been greatly aided by the emergence of genetic engineering tools such as TALENs and CRISPR/Cas9. We have previously demonstrated the ease with which genetically engineered &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus&lt;/italic&gt; models (GEXM) can be generated. This included the induction of autochthonous tumour formation by injection of early embryos with Cas9 recombinant protein loaded with sgRNAs targeting multiple tumour suppressor genes. What has been lacking so far is the possibility to propagate the induced cancers via transplantation. In this paper we describe the generation of a &lt;italic&gt;rag2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;-/-&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; knock-out line in &lt;italic&gt;Xenopus tropicalis&lt;/italic&gt; that is deficient in functional T- and B-cells. This line was validated by means of an allografting experiment with a primary &lt;italic&gt;tp53&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;-/-&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; donor tumour. In addition, we optimized available protocols for sub-lethal gamma irradiation of &lt;italic&gt;X. tropicalis&lt;/italic&gt; froglets. Irradiated animals also allowed stable, albeit transient, engraftment of transplanted &lt;italic&gt;tp53&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;-/-&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; tumour cells. The novel &lt;italic&gt;X. tropicalis rag2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;-/-&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; line and the irradiated wild type froglets will further expand the experimental toolbox in this diploid amphibian, and help to establish it as a versatile and relevant model for exploring human cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468684" rel="alternate" title="Engraftment of allotransplantated tumour cells in adult rag2 mutant Xenopus tropicalis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468905</id><title>Gene expression based inference of drug resistance in cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:39.998860+00:00</updated><author><name>Smriti Chawla</name></author><author><name>Anja Rockstroh</name></author><author><name>Melanie Lehman</name></author><author><name>Ellca Rather</name></author><author><name>Atishay Jain</name></author><author><name>Anuneet Anand</name></author><author><name>Apoorva Gupta</name></author><author><name>Namrata Bhattacharya</name></author><author><name>Sarita Poonia</name></author><author><name>Priyadarshini Rai</name></author><author><name>Nirjhar Das</name></author><author><name>Angshul Majumdar</name></author><author><name>Jayadeva Jayadeva</name></author><author><name>Gaurav Ahuja</name></author><author><name>Brett G Hollier</name></author><author><name>Colleen C Nelson</name></author><author><name>Debarka Sengupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inter and intra-tumoral heterogeneity are major stumbling blocks in the treatment of cancer and are responsible for imparting differential drug responses in cancer patients. Recently, the availability of large-scale drug screening datasets has provided an opportunity for predicting appropriate patient-tailored therapies by employing machine learning approaches. In this study, we report a predictive modeling approach to infer treatment response in cancers using gene expression data. In particular, we demonstrate the benefits of considering integrated chemogenomics approach, utilizing the molecular drug descriptors and pathway activity information as opposed to gene expression levels. We performed extensive validation of our approach on tissue-derived single-cell and bulk expression data. Further, we constructed several prostate cancer cell lines and xenografts, exposed to differential treatment conditions to assess the predictability of the outcomes. Our approach was further assessed on pan-cancer RNA-sequencing data from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) archives, as well as an independent clinical trial study describing the treatment journey of three melanoma patients. To summarise, we benchmarked the proposed approach on cancer RNA-seq data, obtained from cell lines, xenografts, as well as humans. We concluded that pathway-activity patterns in cancer cells are reasonably indicative of drug resistance, and therefore can be leveraged in personalized treatment recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468905" rel="alternate" title="Gene expression based inference of drug resistance in cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>