<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.231540+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472574</id><title>Combined SHP2 and ERK inhibition for the treatment of KRAS-driven Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.232051+00:00</updated><author><name>Katrin J. Ciecielski</name></author><author><name>Antonio Mulero-Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Berninger</name></author><author><name>Laura Ruiz Cañas</name></author><author><name>Astrid Bosma</name></author><author><name>Kıvanç Görgülü</name></author><author><name>Nan Wu</name></author><author><name>Kalliope N. Diakopoulos</name></author><author><name>Ezgi Kaya-Aksoy</name></author><author><name>Dietrich A. Ruess</name></author><author><name>Derya Kabacaoğlu</name></author><author><name>Fränze Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Larissa Heinemann</name></author><author><name>Yuhui Fan</name></author><author><name>Bram Thijssen</name></author><author><name>Marieke van de Ven</name></author><author><name>Natalie Proost</name></author><author><name>Susanne Kossatz</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang A. Weber</name></author><author><name>Bruno Sainz</name></author><author><name>Rene Bernards</name></author><author><name>Hana Algül</name></author><author><name>Marina Lesina</name></author><author><name>Sara Mainardi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutant KRAS is present in over 90% of pancreatic as well as 30-40% of lung and colorectal cancers and is one of the most common oncogenic drivers. Despite decades of research and the recent emergence of isoform-specific KRAS&lt;sup&gt;G12C&lt;/sup&gt;-inhibitors, most mutant KRAS isoforms, including the ones frequently associated with pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC), cannot be targeted directly. Moreover, targeting single RAS downstream effectors induces adaptive mechanisms leading to tumor recurrence or resistance. We report here on the combined inhibition of SHP2, a non-receptor tyrosine phosphatase upstream of KRAS, and ERK, a serine/threonine kinase and a key molecule downstream of KRAS in PDAC. This combination shows synergistic anticancer activity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, superior disruption of the MAPK pathway, and significantly increased apoptosis induction compared to single-agent treatments. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, we demonstrate good tolerability and efficacy of the combination. Concurrent inhibition of SHP2 and ERK induces significant tumor regression in multiple PDAC mouse models. Finally, we show evidence that &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;F-FDG PET scans can be used to detect and predict early drug responses in animal models. Based on these compelling results, we will investigate this drug combination in a clinical trial (SHERPA, &lt;bold&gt;SH&lt;/bold&gt;P2 and &lt;bold&gt;ER&lt;/bold&gt;K inhibition in &lt;bold&gt;pa&lt;/bold&gt;ncreatic cancer, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="clintrialgov" xlink:href="NCT04916236"&gt;NCT04916236&lt;/ext-link&gt;), enrolling patients with &lt;italic&gt;KRAS&lt;/italic&gt;-mutant PDAC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472574" rel="alternate" title="Combined SHP2 and ERK inhibition for the treatment of KRAS-driven Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma (26 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472370</id><title>A convergent malignant phenotype in B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia involving the splicing factor SRRM1 (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.232464+00:00</updated><author><name>Adria Closa</name></author><author><name>Marina Reixachs-Solé</name></author><author><name>Antonio C. Fuentes-Fayos</name></author><author><name>Katharina E. Hayer</name></author><author><name>Juan Luis Melero</name></author><author><name>Fabienne R. S. Adriaanse</name></author><author><name>Romy S. Bos</name></author><author><name>Manuel Torres-Diz</name></author><author><name>Stephen Hunger</name></author><author><name>Kathryn G. Roberts</name></author><author><name>Charles Mullighan</name></author><author><name>Ronald W. Stam</name></author><author><name>Andrei Thomas-Tikhonenko</name></author><author><name>Justo P. Castaño</name></author><author><name>Raúl M. Luque</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Eyras</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A significant proportion of B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) patients remains with a dismal prognosis due to yet undetermined mechanisms. We performed a comprehensive multicohort analysis of gene fusions, gene expression, and RNA splicing alterations to uncover molecular signatures potentially linked to the observed poor outcome. We identified 84 fusions with significant allele frequency across patients. We identified an expression signature that predicts high risk independently of the gene fusion background. This signature includes the upregulation of the splicing factor &lt;italic&gt;SRRM1&lt;/italic&gt;, which potentially impacts splicing events associated with poor outcomes through protein-protein interactions with other splicing factors. Experiments in B-ALL cell lines provided further evidence for the role of SRRM1 on cell survival, proliferation, and invasion. Our findings reveal a convergent mechanism of aberrant RNA processing that sustains a malignant phenotype independently of gene fusions and could complement current clinical strategies in B-ALL.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472370" rel="alternate" title="A convergent malignant phenotype in B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia involving the splicing factor SRRM1 (17 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472756</id><title>Short senolytic or senostatic interventions rescue progression of radiation-induced frailty and premature ageing in mice (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.232712+00:00</updated><author><name>Edward Fielder</name></author><author><name>Tengfei Wan</name></author><author><name>Ghazaleh Alimohammadiha</name></author><author><name>Abbas Ishaq</name></author><author><name>Evon Low</name></author><author><name>Melanie B Weigand</name></author><author><name>George Kelly</name></author><author><name>Craig Parker</name></author><author><name>Brigid Griffin</name></author><author><name>Diana Jurk</name></author><author><name>Viktor Korolchuk</name></author><author><name>Thomas von Zglinicki</name></author><author><name>Satomi Miwa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer survivors suffer from progressive frailty, multimorbidity and premature morbidity. We hypothesize that therapy-induced senescence and senescence progression via bystander effects is a significant cause of this premature ageing phenotype. Accordingly, the study addresses the question whether a short anti-senescence intervention is able to block progression of radiation-induced frailty and disability in a pre-clinical setting. Male mice were sub-lethally irradiated at 5 months of age and treated (or not) with either a senolytic drug (Navitoclax or dasatinib + quercetin) for 10 days or with the senostatic metformin for 10 weeks. Follow up was for one year. Treatments commencing within a month after irradiation effectively reduced frailty progression (p&amp;lt;0.05) and improved muscle (p&amp;lt;0.01) and liver (p&amp;lt;0.05) function as well as short-term memory (p&amp;lt;0.05) until advanced age with no need for repeated interventions. Senolytic interventions that started late, after radiation-induced premature frailty was manifest, still had beneficial effects on frailty (p&amp;lt;0.05) and short-term memory (p&amp;lt;0.05). Metformin was similarly effective as senolytics. At therapeutically achievable concentrations metformin acted as a senostatic neither via inhibition of mitochondrial complex I, nor via improvement of mitophagy or mitochondrial function, but by reducing non-mitochondrial ROS production via NOX4 inhibition in senescent cells. Our study suggests that the progression of adverse long-term health and quality-of-life effects of radiation exposure, as experienced by cancer survivors, might be rescued by short-term adjuvant antisenescence interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472756" rel="alternate" title="Short senolytic or senostatic interventions rescue progression of radiation-induced frailty and premature ageing in mice (16 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472809</id><title>A Precision Medicine Approach to Metabolic Therapy for Breast Cancer in Mice (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.232960+00:00</updated><author><name>Ngozi D Akingbesote</name></author><author><name>Aaron Norman</name></author><author><name>Wanling Zhu</name></author><author><name>Alexandra A Halberstam</name></author><author><name>Xinyi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Julia R Foldi</name></author><author><name>Maryam B Lustberg</name></author><author><name>Rachel J. Perry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Increasing evidence highlights the possibility for approaches targeting metabolism as potential adjuvants to cancer therapy. Sodium-glucose transport protein 2 (SGLT2) inhibitors are the newest class of antihyperglycemic therapies and have recently been highlighted as a novel therapeutic approach to breast cancer. To our knowledge, however, SGLT2 inhibitors have not been applied in the neoadjuvant setting as a precision medicine approach to combining metabolic therapy with standard of care therapy for this devastating disease. In this study, we combine the SGLT2 inhibitor dapagliflozin with paclitaxel chemotherapy in both lean and obese mice. We show that dapagliflozin enhances the efficacy of paclitaxel, reducing tumor glucose uptake and prolonging survival in an insulin-dependent manner in some but not all breast tumors. Our data find a genetic signature for breast tumors most likely to respond to dapagliflozin in combination with paclitaxel. Tumors driven by mutations upstream of canonical insulin signaling pathways are likely to respond to such treatment, whereas tumors driven by mutations downstream of canonical insulin signaling are not. These data demonstrate that dapagliflozin enhances the response to chemotherapy in mice with breast cancer and suggest that breast cancer patients with driver mutations upstream of canonical insulin signaling may be most likely to benefit from this neoadjuvant approach. A clinical trial is currently in preparation, with an application recently submitted for Yale Human Investigations Committee approval, to test this hypothesis in breast cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472809" rel="alternate" title="A Precision Medicine Approach to Metabolic Therapy for Breast Cancer in Mice (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472780</id><title>A simple and direct method to define clonal selection in somatic mosaicism (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.233267+00:00</updated><author><name>Verena Körber</name></author><author><name>Naser Ansari-Pour</name></author><author><name>Niels Asger Jakobsen</name></author><author><name>Rachel Moore</name></author><author><name>Nina Claudino</name></author><author><name>Marlen Metzner</name></author><author><name>Batchimeg Usukhbayar</name></author><author><name>Mirian Angulo Salazar</name></author><author><name>Simon Newman</name></author><author><name>Benjamin JL Kendrick</name></author><author><name>Adrian H Taylor</name></author><author><name>Rasheed Afinowi-Luitz</name></author><author><name>Roger Gundle</name></author><author><name>Bridget Watkins</name></author><author><name>Kim Wheway</name></author><author><name>Debra Beazley</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Carr</name></author><author><name>Paresh Vyas</name></author><author><name>Thomas Höfer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dividing somatic stem cells acquire DNA changes marking different clones. With time, clones can become large, either stochastically through neutral drift, or increased fitness and consequent selection. We present a simple, direct, and general approach that distinguishes between these two processes in normal somatic tissue in individuals. The method relies on single time point whole genome sequencing to study somatic mosaicism as tissues age. Using this method, we show that in human clonal hemopoiesis (CH), clones with CH driver mutations, that comprise a median of 24% of hematopoiesis originate decades before they are detected. They expand, through selection by a median of 26% per year. Overall, there is a 3-fold increased rate of stem cell division and an 8.6-fold increase in active long-term stem cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present an approach to distinguish genetic drift from selection, as subclones arise in somatic tissues, in individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472780" rel="alternate" title="A simple and direct method to define clonal selection in somatic mosaicism (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>