<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.436117+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471791</id><title>CXCL8/CXCR2 signaling mediates bone marrow fibrosis and represents a therapeutic target in myelofibrosis (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.436467+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Dunbar</name></author><author><name>Dongjoo Kim</name></author><author><name>Min Lu</name></author><author><name>Mirko Farina</name></author><author><name>Julie L. Yang</name></author><author><name>Young Park</name></author><author><name>Francesca Gobbo</name></author><author><name>Paola Verachi</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Martelli</name></author><author><name>Abdul Karzai</name></author><author><name>Wenbin Xiao</name></author><author><name>Lijuan Xia</name></author><author><name>Nada Elmansy</name></author><author><name>Maria Kleppe</name></author><author><name>Zhuo Chen</name></author><author><name>Yang Xiao</name></author><author><name>Erin McGovern</name></author><author><name>Jenna Snyder</name></author><author><name>Aishwarya Krishnan</name></author><author><name>Corinne Hill</name></author><author><name>Keith Cordner</name></author><author><name>Anouar Zouak</name></author><author><name>Mohamed Salama</name></author><author><name>Jayden Yohai</name></author><author><name>Eric Tucker</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Chen</name></author><author><name>Jing Zhou</name></author><author><name>Tim McConnell</name></author><author><name>Richard Koche</name></author><author><name>Raajit Rampal</name></author><author><name>Anna Rita Migliaccio</name></author><author><name>Rong Fan</name></author><author><name>Ross Levine</name></author><author><name>Ronald Hoffman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pro-inflammatory signaling is a hallmark feature of human cancer, including in myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPNs), most notably myelofibrosis (MF). Dysregulated inflammatory signaling contributes to fibrotic progression in MF; however, the individual cytokine mediators elicited by malignant MPN cells to promote collagen-producing fibrosis and disease evolution remain yet to be fully elucidated. Previously we identified a critical role for combined constitutive JAK/STAT and aberrant NF-kB pro-inflammatory signaling in myelofibrosis development. Using single-cell transcriptional and cytokine-secretion studies of primary MF patient cells and two separate murine models of myelofibrosis, we extend this previous work and delineate the role of CXCL8/CXCR2 signaling in MF pathogenesis and bone marrow fibrosis progression. MF patient hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells are enriched in a CXCL8/CXCR2 gene signature and display dose- dependent proliferation and fitness in response to exogenous CXCL8 ligand in vitro. Genetic deletion of Cxcr2 in the hMPLW515L adoptive transfer model abrogates fibrosis and extends overall survival, and pharmacologic inhibition of the CXCR1/2 pathway improves hematologic parameters, attenuates bone marrow fibrosis, and synergizes with JAK inhibitor therapy. Our mechanistic insights provide a rationale for therapeutic targeting of the CXCL8/CXCR2 pathway in MF patients at risk for continued fibrotic progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471791" rel="alternate" title="CXCL8/CXCR2 signaling mediates bone marrow fibrosis and represents a therapeutic target in myelofibrosis (20 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471610</id><title>Chemical, molecular, and single cell analysis reveal chondroitin sulfate proteoglycan aberrancy in fibrolamellar carcinoma (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.436836+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam B. Francisco</name></author><author><name>Jine Li</name></author><author><name>Alaa R. Farghli</name></author><author><name>Matt Kanke</name></author><author><name>Bo Shui</name></author><author><name>Paul D. Soloway</name></author><author><name>Zhangjie Wang</name></author><author><name>Lola M. Reid</name></author><author><name>Jian Liu</name></author><author><name>Praveen Sethupathy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fibrolamellar carcinoma (FLC) is an aggressive liver cancer with no effective therapeutic options. The extracellular environment of FLC tumors is poorly characterized and may contribute to cancer growth and/or metastasis. To bridge this knowledge gap, we assessed pathways relevant to proteoglycans, a major component of the extracellular matrix. We first analyzed gene expression data from FLC and non-malignant liver tissue to identify changes in glycosaminoglycan (GAG) biosynthesis pathways. We then implemented a novel LC-MS/MS based method to quantify the abundance of different types of GAGs in patient tumors, followed by measurement of the levels of different GAG-associated proteins. Finally, we performed the first single-cell assay for transposon-accessible chromatin-sequencing on FLC tumors, to identify which cell types are linked to the most dominant GAG-associated protein in FLC. Our results reveal a pathologic aberrancy in chondroitin (but not heparan) sulfate proteoglycans in FLC and highlight a potential role for activated stellate cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471610" rel="alternate" title="Chemical, molecular, and single cell analysis reveal chondroitin sulfate proteoglycan aberrancy in fibrolamellar carcinoma (14 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471619</id><title>MacroH2A impedes metastatic growth by enforcing a discrete dormancy program in disseminated cancer cells (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.437046+00:00</updated><author><name>Dan Sun</name></author><author><name>Dan Filipescu</name></author><author><name>Dan Hasson</name></author><author><name>Deepak K. Singh</name></author><author><name>Saul Carcamo</name></author><author><name>Bassem Khalil</name></author><author><name>Brett A. Miles</name></author><author><name>William Westra</name></author><author><name>Karl Christoph Sproll</name></author><author><name>Emily Bernstein</name></author><author><name>Julio A. Aguirre-Ghiso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MacroH2A variants have been associated with tumor suppression through inhibition of proliferation and metastasis, as well as their role in cellular senescence. However, their role in regulating the dormant state of disseminated cancer cells (DCCs) remains unclear. Here we reveal that solitary dormant DCCs display increased levels of macroH2A variants in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma PDX models and patient samples compared to proliferating primary or metastatic lesions. We further demonstrate that microenvironmental and stress adaptive signals such as TGFβ2 and p38α/β, which induce DCC dormancy, upregulate macroH2A expression. Functionally, we find that overexpression of macroH2A variants is sufficient to induce tumor cells into dormancy and notably, inducible expression of the macroH2A2 variant suppresses the growth of DCCs into overt metastasis. However, this dormant state does not require well-characterized dormancy factors such as DEC2 and NR2F1, suggesting alternate pathways. Our transcriptomic analyses reveal that macroH2A2 overexpression inhibits E2F, RAS and MYC signaling programs, while upregulating inflammatory cytokines commonly secreted by senescent cells. Taken together, our results demonstrate that macroH2A2 enforces a stable dormant phenotype in DCCs by activating a select subset of dormancy and senescence genes that limit metastasis initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471619" rel="alternate" title="MacroH2A impedes metastatic growth by enforcing a discrete dormancy program in disseminated cancer cells (13 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471470</id><title>Processing body dynamics drive non-genetic MEK inhibitors tolerance by fine-tuning KRAS and NRAS translation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.437347+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivia Vidal-Cruchez</name></author><author><name>Victoria J Nicolini</name></author><author><name>Tifenn Rete</name></author><author><name>Roger Rezzonico</name></author><author><name>Caroline Lacoux</name></author><author><name>Julien Fassy</name></author><author><name>Karine Jacquet</name></author><author><name>Marie-Angela Domdom</name></author><author><name>Chloé Ventujol</name></author><author><name>Thierry Juhel</name></author><author><name>Barnabé Roméo</name></author><author><name>Jérémie Roux</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Hubstenberger</name></author><author><name>Bernard Mari</name></author><author><name>Baharia Mograbi</name></author><author><name>Paul Hofman</name></author><author><name>Patrick Brest</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overactivation of the Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway is a critical driver of many human cancers. However, therapies that target this pathway have only been effective in a few cancers, as cancers inevitably end up developing resistance. Puzzling observations have suggested that MAPK targeting in tumor fails because of an early compensatory RAS overexpression, but through unexplained mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lung, breast, and melanoma cancer cells were incubated with MEK inhibitors (MEKi). Kinetics of expression of KRAS, NRAS mRNA and proteins and processing bodies (PBs) proteins were followed overtime by immunoblot and confocal studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we identified a novel mechanism of drug tolerance for MEKi involving PBs essential proteins like DDX6 or LSM14A. MEKi promoted the translation of KRAS and NRAS oncogenes, which in turn triggered BRAF phosphorylation. This overexpression, which occurred in the absence of neo-transcription, depended on PBs dissolution as a source of RAS mRNA reservoir. In addition, in response to MEKi removal, we showed that the process was dynamic since the PBs quickly reformed, reducing MAPK signaling. These results underline a dynamic spatiotemporal negative feedback loop of MAPK signaling via RAS mRNA sequestration. Furthermore, in long-tolerant cells, we observed a LSM14A loss of expression that promoted a low PBs number phenotype together with strong KRAS and NRAS induction capacities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Altogether we describe here a new intricate mechanism involving PB, DDX6 and LSM14A in the translation regulation of essential cellular pathways that pave the way for future therapies altering PBs dissolution to improve cancer targeted-drug therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471470" rel="alternate" title="Processing body dynamics drive non-genetic MEK inhibitors tolerance by fine-tuning KRAS and NRAS translation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471299</id><title>Tissue remodeling and cell signaling underpin changes in tumor microenvironment heterogeneity in glioma oncogenesis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.437576+00:00</updated><author><name>Marija Dinevska</name></author><author><name>Samuel S. Widodo</name></author><author><name>Liam Furst</name></author><author><name>Lucero Cuzcano</name></author><author><name>Yitong Fang</name></author><author><name>Stefano Mangiola</name></author><author><name>Paul J. Neeson</name></author><author><name>Phillip K. Darcy</name></author><author><name>Robert G. Ramsay</name></author><author><name>Fabienne MacKay</name></author><author><name>Stanley S. Stylli</name></author><author><name>Theo Mantamadiotis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain tumor cells thrive by adapting to the signals in their microenvironment. Understanding how the tumor microenvironment evolves during disease progression is crucial to deciphering the mechanisms underlying the functional behavior of cancer cells. To adapt, cancer cells activate signaling and transcriptional programs and migrate to establish micro-niches, in response to signals from neighboring cells and non-cellular stromal factors. Using multiple tissue analysis approaches to identify and measure immune cell infiltration and extracellular matrix deposition in brain tumors, we show that low-grade glioma is largely devoid of infiltrating immune cells and extracellular matrix proteins, while high-grade glioma exhibits abundant immune cell infiltration and activation, as well as extensive collagen deposition. Spatial analysis shows that most T-cells are sequestered in perivascular nests, but macrophages penetrate deep into tumor cell rich regions. High-grade gliomas exhibit heterogeneous PI3K and MAPK signaling, which correlates with distinct pathological hallmarks, including tumor angiogenesis, tumor cell density and extracellular matrix deposition. Our results also provide compelling evidence that tissue remodeling is an important element in glioma progression, and that targeting the extracellular matrix will be critical to improving GBM therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471299" rel="alternate" title="Tissue remodeling and cell signaling underpin changes in tumor microenvironment heterogeneity in glioma oncogenesis (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.21266935</id><title>Treatment of Recurrent Glioblastoma by Chronic Convection-Enhanced Delivery of Topotecan (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.437865+00:00</updated><author><name>Eleonora F. Spinazzi</name></author><author><name>Michael G. Argenziano</name></author><author><name>Pavan S. Upadhyayula</name></author><author><name>Matei A. Banu</name></author><author><name>Justin A. Neira</name></author><author><name>Dominique M.O. Higgins</name></author><author><name>Peter B. Wu</name></author><author><name>Brianna Pereira</name></author><author><name>Aayushi Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Nelson Humala</name></author><author><name>Osama Al-Dalahmah</name></author><author><name>Wenting Zhao</name></author><author><name>Akshay V. Save</name></author><author><name>Deborah M. Boyett</name></author><author><name>Tamara Marie</name></author><author><name>Julia L Furnari</name></author><author><name>Tejaswi D. Sudhakar</name></author><author><name>Sylwia A. Stopka</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Regan</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Catania</name></author><author><name>Laura Good</name></author><author><name>Meenu Behl</name></author><author><name>Sachin Jambawalikar</name></author><author><name>Akiva Mintz</name></author><author><name>Angela Lignelli</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Y.R. Agar</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Sims</name></author><author><name>Mary Welch</name></author><author><name>Andrew Lassman</name></author><author><name>Fabio Iwamoto</name></author><author><name>Randy S. D’Amico</name></author><author><name>Jack Grinband</name></author><author><name>Peter Canoll</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey N. Bruce</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma, the most common primary brain malignancy, is invariably fatal. Systemic chemotherapy is ineffective mostly because of drug delivery limitations. To overcome this, we devised an internalized pump-catheter system for direct chronic convection-enhanced delivery (CED) into peritumoral brain tissue. Topotecan (TPT) by chronic CED in 5 patients with refractory glioblastoma selectively eliminated tumor cells without toxicity to normal brain. Large, stable drug distribution volumes were non-invasively monitored with MRI of co-infused gadolinium. Analysis of multiple radiographically localized biopsies taken before and after treatment showed a decreased proliferative tumor signature resulting in a shift to a slow-cycling mesenchymal/astrocytic-like population. Tumor microenvironment analysis showed an inflammatory response and preservation of neurons. This novel drug delivery strategy and innovative clinical trial paradigm overcomes current limitations in delivery and treatment response assessment as shown here for glioblastoma and is potentially applicable for other anti-glioma agents as well as other CNS diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.21266935" rel="alternate" title="Treatment of Recurrent Glioblastoma by Chronic Convection-Enhanced Delivery of Topotecan (9 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471907</id><title>Nuclear NAD+ homeostasis is essential for naive and chemoresistant BRCA1/2-deficient tumor survival (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.438479+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniele Musiani</name></author><author><name>Hatice Yucel</name></author><author><name>Laura Sourd</name></author><author><name>Elisabetta Marangoni</name></author><author><name>Raphael Ceccaldi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Resistance to PARP inhibitors (PARPi) is emerging as the major obstacle to their effectiveness for the treatment of BRCA1/2-mutated, also referred as homologous recombination (HR)-deficient, tumors (HRD). Over the years, mechanistic studies gained insights on effectors acting downstream of PARP1, lagging behind the understanding of earlier events upstream - and thus independent - of PARP1. Here, we investigated the role of nuclear NAD+, an essential cofactor for the activity of key DNA repair proteins, including PARP1 and sirtuins. We show that NMNAT1- the enzyme synthesizing nuclear NAD+ - is synthetically lethal with BRCA1/2 in a PARP1-independent but SIRT6-dependent manner. Consequently, inhibition of NMNAT1/SIRT6 axis not only kills naive but also PARPi-resistant HRD cancer cells. Our results unravel a unique vulnerability of HRD tumors, therapeutically exploitable even upon PARPi resistance development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471907" rel="alternate" title="Nuclear NAD+ homeostasis is essential for naive and chemoresistant BRCA1/2-deficient tumor survival (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471585</id><title>Sensory nerves enhance triple-negative breast cancer migration and metastasis via the axon guidance molecule PlexinB3 (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.438630+00:00</updated><author><name>Thanh T Le</name></author><author><name>Samantha L Payne</name></author><author><name>Maia N Buckwald</name></author><author><name>Lily A Hayes</name></author><author><name>Christopher B Burge</name></author><author><name>Madeleine J Oudin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In breast cancer, nerve presence has been correlated with more invasive disease and worse prognosis, yet the mechanisms by which different types of peripheral nerves drive tumor progression remain poorly understood. In this study, we identified sensory nerves as more abundant in human triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) tumors. Coinjection of sensory neurons isolated from the dorsal root ganglia (DRG) of adult female mice with human TNBC cells in immunocompromised mice increased the number of lung metastases. Direct &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; co-culture of human TNBC cells with the dorsal root ganglia (DRG) of adult female mice revealed that TNBC cells adhere to sensory neuron fibers leading to an increase in migration speed. Species-specific RNA sequencing revealed that co-culture of TNBC cells with sensory nerves upregulates the expression of genes associated with cell migration and adhesion in cancer cells. We demonstrate that the axon guidance molecule Plexin B3 mediates cancer cell adhesion to and migration on sensory nerves. Together, our results identify a novel mechanism by which nerves contribute to breast cancer migration and metastasis by inducing a shift in TNBC cell gene expression and support the rationale for disrupting neuron-cancer cell interactions to target metastasis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presence of nerves in breast tumors has been associated with poor outcome. Understanding the mechanisms by which nerves contribute to tumor progression could help identify novel strategies to target metastatic disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471585" rel="alternate" title="Sensory nerves enhance triple-negative breast cancer migration and metastasis via the axon guidance molecule PlexinB3 (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471608</id><title>Zebrafish xenografts to isolate unique human breast cancer metastatic cell populations (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.438772+00:00</updated><author><name>Jerry Xiao</name></author><author><name>Joseph R. McGill</name></author><author><name>Apsra Nasir</name></author><author><name>Alexander Lekan</name></author><author><name>Bailey Johnson</name></author><author><name>Devan J. Wilkins</name></author><author><name>Gray W. Pearson</name></author><author><name>Kandice Tanner</name></author><author><name>Hani Goodarzi</name></author><author><name>Eric Glasgow</name></author><author><name>Richard Schlegel</name></author><author><name>Seema Agarwal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer metastasis is a critical culprit frequently blamed for treatment failure, drug resistance, poor prognosis, and high mortality rate among all human cancers. Laboratory efforts to isolate metastatic cell populations have typically been confined to mouse models, which are time-consuming and expensive. Here, we present a model system based on xenografting zebrafish embryos to select for cells that are predisposed to progress through the early stages of metastasis. This model requires only 3-5 days to achieve distinct intravasation to the zebrafish circulatory system. The metastatic cells are easily tracked in real-time as they migrate, as well as isolated and propagated &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. Once expanded, molecular characterization of the serially derived invasive cell populations from the tails of the zebrafish accurately predicts genes, signaling pathways, protein-protein interactions, and differential splicing products that are important for an invasive phenotype. This zebrafish model therefore offers a high-throughput and robust method for identifying gene targets critical for cancer metastasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471608" rel="alternate" title="Zebrafish xenografts to isolate unique human breast cancer metastatic cell populations (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471308</id><title>Regulation of protein complex partners as a compensatory mechanism in aneuploid tumors (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.438946+00:00</updated><author><name>Gökçe Senger</name></author><author><name>Stefano Santaguida</name></author><author><name>Martin H. Schaefer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aneuploidy, a state of chromosome imbalance, is a hallmark of human tumors, but its role in cancer still remains to be fully elucidated. To understand the consequences of whole chromosome-level aneuploidies on the proteome, we integrated aneuploidy, transcriptomic and proteomic data from hundreds of TCGA/CPTAC tumor samples. We found a surprisingly large number of expression changes happened on other, non-aneuploid chromosomes. Moreover, we identified an association between those changes and co-complex members of proteins from aneuploid chromosomes. This co-abundance association is tightly regulated for aggregation-prone aneuploid proteins and those involved in a smaller number of complexes. On the other hand, we observe that complexes of the cellular core machinery are under functional selection to maintain their stoichiometric balance in aneuploid tumors. Ultimately, we provide evidence that those compensatory and functional maintenance mechanisms are established through post-transcriptional control and that the degree of success of a tumor to deal with aneuploidy-induced stoichiometric imbalance impacts the activation of cellular protein degradation programs and patient survival.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471308" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of protein complex partners as a compensatory mechanism in aneuploid tumors (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471373</id><title>Cathelicidin-3 associated with serum extracellular vesicles enables early diagnosis of a transmissible cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.439228+00:00</updated><author><name>Camila Espejo</name></author><author><name>Richard Wilson</name></author><author><name>Ruth J. Pye</name></author><author><name>Julian C. Ratcliffe</name></author><author><name>Manuel Ruiz-Aravena</name></author><author><name>Eduard Willms</name></author><author><name>Barrett W. Wolfe</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Hamede</name></author><author><name>Andrew F. Hill</name></author><author><name>Menna E. Jones</name></author><author><name>Gregory M. Woods</name></author><author><name>A. Bruce Lyons</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The identification of practical early diagnosis biomarkers is a cornerstone of improved prevention and treatment of cancers. Such a case is devil facial tumour disease (DFTD), a highly lethal transmissible cancer afflicting virtually an entire species, the Tasmanian devil (&lt;italic&gt;Sarcophilus harrisii&lt;/italic&gt;). Despite a latent period that can exceed one year, to date DFTD diagnosis requires visual identification of tumour lesions. To enable earlier diagnosis, which is essential for the implementation of effective conservation strategies, we analysed the extracellular vesicle (EV) proteome of 87 Tasmanian devil serum samples. The antimicrobial peptide cathelicidin-3 (CATH3) was enriched in serum EVs of both devils with clinical DFTD (87.9% sensitivity and 94.1% specificity) and devils with latent infection (i.e., collected while overtly healthy, but 3-6 months before subsequent DFTD diagnosis; 93.8% sensitivity and 94.1% specificity). As antimicrobial peptides can play a variety of roles in the cancer process, our results suggest that the specific elevation of serum EV-associated CATH3 may be mechanistically involved in DFTD pathogenesis. This EV-based approach to biomarker discovery is directly applicable to improving understanding and diagnosis of a broad range of diseases in other species, and these findings directly enhance the capacity of conservation strategies to ensure the viability of the imperilled Tasmanian devil population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471373" rel="alternate" title="Cathelicidin-3 associated with serum extracellular vesicles enables early diagnosis of a transmissible cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471340</id><title>Characterization of epigenetic alterations in esophageal cancer by whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.440939+00:00</updated><author><name>Feng Pan</name></author><author><name>Shuai-Xia Yu</name></author><author><name>Xuan Wang</name></author><author><name>He-Cheng Huang</name></author><author><name>Zeng-Ying Cai</name></author><author><name>Jia-Min Wang</name></author><author><name>Shu-Yuan Lin</name></author><author><name>Yu-Lin Gao</name></author><author><name>En-Min Li</name></author><author><name>Li-Yan Xu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Esophageal carcinoma is a common and aggressive malignancy, and its patients have dismal clinical outcomes. The epigenetic dysregulation in both major subtypes, esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC) and adenocarcinoma (EAC), awaits further characterization. Here, we perform whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) on a total of 43 esophageal cancer and normal samples, generating one of the largest WGBS datasets in this cancer to date. Focusing on hypomethylated regions in cancer, we show that they are associated with increased chromatin activity and enhancer RNA expression. Using this large collection of WGBS dataset, we reveal and validate novel clusters in both ESCC and EAC. We further identify specific molecular features in each cluster, with potential clinical implications. These data together advance our understanding of the epigenetic alterations in esophageal cancer and provide a rich resource for the research community of this disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471340" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of epigenetic alterations in esophageal cancer by whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471658</id><title>Microneedle-mediated intratumoral delivery of anti-CTLA-4 promotes cDC1-dependent eradication of oral squamous cell carcinoma with limited irAEs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.441923+00:00</updated><author><name>Mara Gilardi</name></author><author><name>Robert Saddawi-Konefka</name></author><author><name>Victoria H. Wu</name></author><author><name>Miguel Angel Lopez-Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Zhiyong Wang</name></author><author><name>Fernando Soto</name></author><author><name>Dana J. Steffen</name></author><author><name>Marco Proietto</name></author><author><name>Zbigniew Mikulski</name></author><author><name>Haruka Miki</name></author><author><name>Andrew Sharabi</name></author><author><name>Daniel Kupor</name></author><author><name>Ricardo Rueda</name></author><author><name>Daniel P. Hollern</name></author><author><name>Joseph Wang</name></author><author><name>J. Silvio Gutkind</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) ranks 6th in cancer incidence worldwide and has a five-year survival rate of only 63%. Immunotherapies – principally immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICI), such as anti-PD-1 and anti-CTLA-4 antibodies that restore endogenous antitumor T-cell immunity – offer the greatest promise for HNSCC treatment. Anti-PD-1 has been recently approved for first line treatment of recurrent and metastatic HNSCC; however less than 20% of patients show clinical benefit and durable responses. In addition, the clinical application of ICI has been limited by immune-related adverse events (irAEs) consequent to compromised peripheral immune tolerance. Although irAEs are often reversible, they can become severe, prompting premature therapy termination or becoming life-threatening. To address the irAEs inherent to systemic ICI therapy, we developed a novel, local delivery strategy based upon an array of soluble microneedles (MN). Using our recently reported syngeneic, tobacco-signature murine HNSCC model, we found that both systemic and local-MN anti-CTLA-4 therapy lead to &amp;gt;90% tumor response, which is dependent on CD8 T cells and conventional dendritic cell type 1 (cDC1). However, local-MN delivery limited the distribution of anti-CTLA-4 antibody from areas distal to draining lymphatic basins. Employing Foxp3-&lt;italic&gt;GFP&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;DTR&lt;/sup&gt; transgenic mice to interrogate irAEs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, we found that local-MN delivery of anti-CTLA-4 protects animals from irAEs observed with systemic therapy. Taken together, our findings support the exploration of MN-intratumoral ICI delivery as a viable strategy for HNSCC treatment with reduced irAEs, and the opportunity to target cDC1s as part of multimodal treatment options to boost ICI therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471658" rel="alternate" title="Microneedle-mediated intratumoral delivery of anti-CTLA-4 promotes cDC1-dependent eradication of oral squamous cell carcinoma with limited irAEs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>