<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.661626+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474388</id><title>Interleukin 4 controls the role of macrophages in pulmonary metastatic tumor cell seeding and growth (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.662382+00:00</updated><author><name>Carolina A Rodriguez-Tirado</name></author><author><name>David Entenberg</name></author><author><name>Jiufeng Li</name></author><author><name>Bin-Zhi Qian</name></author><author><name>John S Condeelis</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey W Pollard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metastasis is the systemic manifestation of cancer and the main cause of death from breast cancer. In mouse models of lung metastases, recruitment of classical monocytes from blood to the lung and their differentiation to metastasis-associated macrophages (MAMs) facilitate cancer cell extravasation, survival, and growth. Ablation of MAMs or their monocytic progenitors inhibits metastasis. We hypothesized that factors controlling macrophage polarization modulate tumor cell extravasation in the lung. We evaluated whether signaling by Th1 or Th2 cytokines in macrophages affected trans-endothelial migration of tumor cells in vitro. Interferon γ and LPS inhibited macrophage-dependent tumor cell extravasation while the Th2 cytokine interleukin-4 (IL4) enhanced this process. We demonstrated that IL4 receptor (IL4rα) null mice develop fewer and smaller lung metastasis. Adoptive transfer of wild type monocytes to IL4rα deficient mice rescued this phenotype. IL4 signaling in macrophages controls the expression of the chemokine receptor CXCR2, necessary for IL4-mediated tumor cell extravasation in vitro. Furthermore, IL4 signaling in macrophages transcriptionally regulates several other genes already causally associated with lung metastasis including CCL2, CSF1, CCR1, HGF and FLT1. The central role for IL4 signaling in MAMs was confirmed by high-resolution intravital imaging of the lung in mice at the time of metastatic seeding, which showed reduced physical interaction between tumor cells and IL4rα-deficient macrophages. This interaction enhances tumor cell survival. These data indicate that IL4 signaling in monocytes and macrophages is key during seeding and growth of breast metastasis in the lung as it regulates pro-tumoral paracrine signaling between cancer cells and macrophages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474388" rel="alternate" title="Interleukin 4 controls the role of macrophages in pulmonary metastatic tumor cell seeding and growth (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474412</id><title>Biomechanical and biochemical assessment of YB-1 expression in melanoma cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.663098+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Magdalena Cykowska</name></author><author><name>Ulf Krister Hofmann</name></author><author><name>Aadhya Tiwari</name></author><author><name>Corinna Kosnopfel</name></author><author><name>Rosa Riester</name></author><author><name>Marina Danalache</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Malignant melanoma is the most lethal form of skin cancer; its incidence has increased over the last five decades. Y-box binding protein 1 (YB-1) plays a prominent role in mediating metastatic behavior by promoting epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT) processes. Migratory melanoma cells exhibit two major phenotypes: elongated mesenchymal or rounded amoeboid. The actomyosin cytoskeleton is key in both phenotypes, but intermediate filaments also undergo a significant rearrangement process, switching from cytokeratin-rich to vimentin and nestin-rich network. In this study, we aimed to investigate to what extent YB-1 impacts the biomechanical (cell stiffness) and biochemical aspects of melanoma cells and their cytoskeleton. To this end, we subjected A375 YB-1 knock-out and parental cells to atomic force microscopy investigations (stiffness determination), immunolabelling, and proteome analysis. We found that YB-1 expressing cells were significantly stiffer compared to the corresponding YB-1 knock-out cell line. Proteomic analysis revealed that expression of YB-1 results in a strong co-expression of nestin, vimentin, fascin-1, and septin-9. In the YB-1 knock-out nestin was completely depleted, but zyxin was strongly upregulated. Collectively, our results showed that YB-1 knock-out acquires some characteristics of mesenchymal phenotype but lacks important markers of malignancy and invasiveness such as nestin or vimentin. We posit that there is an association of YB-1 expression with an amoeboid phenotype, which would explain the increased migratory capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474412" rel="alternate" title="Biomechanical and biochemical assessment of YB-1 expression in melanoma cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>