<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.362492+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476225</id><title>Single-cell multi-omics of human clonal hematopoiesis reveals that DNMT3A R882 mutations perturb early progenitor states through selective hypomethylation (104 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.362635+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna S. Nam</name></author><author><name>Neville Dusaj</name></author><author><name>Franco Izzo</name></author><author><name>Rekha Murali</name></author><author><name>Robert M. Myers</name></author><author><name>Tarek Mouhieddine</name></author><author><name>Jesus Sotelo</name></author><author><name>Salima Benbarche</name></author><author><name>Michael Waarts</name></author><author><name>Federico Gaiti</name></author><author><name>Sabrin Tahri</name></author><author><name>Ross Levine</name></author><author><name>Omar Abdel-Wahab</name></author><author><name>Lucy A. Godley</name></author><author><name>Ronan Chaligne</name></author><author><name>Irene M Ghobrial</name></author><author><name>Dan Landau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Somatic mutations in cancer genes have been ubiquitously detected in clonal expansions across healthy human tissue, including in clonal hematopoiesis. However, mutated and wildtype cells are morphologically and phenotypically similar, limiting the ability to link genotypes with cellular phenotypes. To overcome this limitation, we leveraged multi-modality single-cell sequencing, capturing the mutation with transcriptomes and methylomes in stem and progenitors from individuals with &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt; R882 mutated clonal hematopoiesis. &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt; mutations resulted in myeloid over lymphoid bias, and in expansion of immature myeloid progenitors primed toward megakaryocytic-erythroid fate. We observed dysregulated expression of lineage and leukemia stem cell markers. DNMT3A R882 led to preferential hypomethylation of polycomb repressive complex 2 targets and a specific sequence motif. Notably, the hypomethylation motif is enriched in binding motifs of key hematopoietic transcription factors, serving as a potential mechanistic link between &lt;italic&gt;DNMT3A&lt;/italic&gt; R882 mutations and aberrant transcriptional phenotypes. Thus, single-cell multi-omics pave the road to defining the downstream consequences of mutations that drive human clonal mosaicism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476225" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell multi-omics of human clonal hematopoiesis reveals that DNMT3A R882 mutations perturb early progenitor states through selective hypomethylation (104 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475944</id><title>Epigenetic dysregulation from chromosomal transit in micronuclei (23 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.362784+00:00</updated><author><name>Albert Agustinus</name></author><author><name>Ramya Raviram</name></author><author><name>Bhargavi Dameracharla</name></author><author><name>Jens Luebeck</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Stransky</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Scipioni</name></author><author><name>Robert M. Myers</name></author><author><name>Melody Di Bona</name></author><author><name>Mercedes Duran</name></author><author><name>Britta Weigelt</name></author><author><name>Shira Yomtoubian</name></author><author><name>Eléonore Toufektchan</name></author><author><name>Paul S. Mischel</name></author><author><name>Vivek Mittal</name></author><author><name>Sohrab Shah</name></author><author><name>John Maciejowski</name></author><author><name>Enrico Gratton</name></author><author><name>Peter Ly</name></author><author><name>Mathieu F. Bakhoum</name></author><author><name>Dan Landau</name></author><author><name>Vineet Bafna</name></author><author><name>Simone Sidoli</name></author><author><name>Yael David</name></author><author><name>Samuel F. Bakhoum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosomal instability (CIN) and epigenetic alterations are characteristics of advanced and metastatic cancers [1-4], yet whether they are mechanistically linked is unknown. Here we show that missegregation of mitotic chromosomes, their sequestration in micronuclei [5, 6], and subsequent micronuclear envelope rupture [7] profoundly disrupt normal histone post-translational modifications (PTMs), a phenomenon conserved across humans and mice as well as cancer and non-transformed cells. Some of the changes to histone PTMs occur due to micronuclear envelope rupture whereas others are inherited from mitotic abnormalities prior to micronucleus formation. Using orthogonal techniques, we show that micronuclei exhibit extensive differences in chromatin accessibility with a strong positional bias between promoters and distal or intergenic regions. Finally, we show that inducing CIN engenders widespread epigenetic dysregulation and that chromosomes which transit in micronuclei experience durable abnormalities in their accessibility long after they have been reincorporated into the primary nucleus. Thus, in addition to genomic copy number alterations, CIN can serve as a vehicle for epigenetic reprogramming and heterogeneity in cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475944" rel="alternate" title="Epigenetic dysregulation from chromosomal transit in micronuclei (23 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269035</id><title>Whole genome analysis reveals the genomic complexity in metastatic cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.362929+00:00</updated><author><name>Amarinder S. Thind</name></author><author><name>Bruce Ashford</name></author><author><name>Dario Strbenac</name></author><author><name>Ruta Gupta</name></author><author><name>Jonathan R Clark</name></author><author><name>N. Gopalakrishna Iyer</name></author><author><name>Jenny Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Jenny Lee</name></author><author><name>Simon A Mueller</name></author><author><name>Elahe Minaei</name></author><author><name>Jay Perry</name></author><author><name>Marie Ranson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metastatic cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (cSCC) is associated with a high risk of recurrence and poor prognosis. There is limited published data exploring whole genome sequencing (WGS). The aim of this project was to provide the first comprehensive genomic understanding of the state of metastatic cSCC. In this study, we used WGS on matched tumor and blood DNA to detect somatic genetic alterations from 25 patients with regional metastases of head and neck cSCC. Our computational analyses interrogate clinical impacts of these genetic alterations on metastatic cSCC across the cohort for both the coding and non-coding genome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the non-coding genome, 3’UTR regions of &lt;italic&gt;EVC&lt;/italic&gt; (48%), &lt;italic&gt;PPP1R1A&lt;/italic&gt; (48%) and &lt;italic&gt;LUM&lt;/italic&gt; (16%) were significantly functionally altered (Q-value &amp;lt; 0.05). Further, significant functional alterations are observed in the tumor suppressing lncRNA LINC01003 (68% of specimens, Q-value: 0.0158). In addition, significant recurrent copy number loss in tumor suppressor genes &lt;italic&gt;KANSL1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;PTPRD&lt;/italic&gt; and gain in &lt;italic&gt;CALR, CCND1&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;FGF3&lt;/italic&gt; was observed for coding regions. SNV’s driver analyses predicted &lt;italic&gt;TP53, CDKN2A&lt;/italic&gt;, as potential drivers of the metastasis cSCC (using 3 different tools). Indel signature analysis highlight dominance of ID signature 13 followed by ID8 &amp;amp; ID9. Interestingly, ID 9 has previously been shown to have no association with skin melanoma, unlike ID 13 and 8, suggesting some point of difference between these two skin-based diseases. The overall landscape of variation in metastatic cSCC is dominated by cell cycle and DNA repair disruption.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.22269035" rel="alternate" title="Whole genome analysis reveals the genomic complexity in metastatic cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (10 tweets)"/><category term="Oncology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475595</id><title>mTORC2 Drives ZFX-mediated Ganglioside Biosynthesis to Promote Breast Cancer Progression (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.363023+00:00</updated><author><name>Kajal Rajput</name></author><author><name>Mohd. Nafees Ansari</name></author><author><name>Somesh K. Jha</name></author><author><name>Nihal Medatwal</name></author><author><name>Pankaj Sharma</name></author><author><name>Sudeshna Datta</name></author><author><name>Animesh Kar</name></author><author><name>Trishna Pani</name></author><author><name>Kaushavi Cholke</name></author><author><name>Kajal Rana</name></author><author><name>Ali Khan</name></author><author><name>Geetashree Mukherjee</name></author><author><name>SVS Deo</name></author><author><name>Jyothi S Prabhu</name></author><author><name>Arnab Mukhopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Avinash Bajaj</name></author><author><name>Ujjaini Dasgupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sphingolipid and ganglioside metabolic pathways are crucial components of cell signalling, having established roles in tumor cell proliferation, invasion, and migration. However, regulatory mechanisms controlling sphingolipid and ganglioside synthesis in mammalian cells is less known. Here, we show that RICTOR, the regulatory subunit of mTORC2, regulates the synthesis of sphingolipids and gangliosides in Luminal breast cancer-specific MCF-7 cells through transcriptional and epigenetic mechanisms. RICTOR regulates glucosylceramide levels by modulating the expression of UDP-Glucose Ceramide Glucosyl transferase (UGCG). We identify Zinc Finger protein X-linked (ZFX) as a RICTOR-responsive transcription factor whose recruitment to the &lt;italic&gt;UGCG&lt;/italic&gt; promoter is regulated by DNA methyltransferases and histone demethylase (KDM5A) that are known AKT substrates. We further demonstrate that RICTOR regulates the synthesis of GD3 gangliosides through ZFX and UGCG, and triggers the activation of the EGFR signalling pathway, thereby promoting tumor growth. In line with our findings in cell culture and mice models, we observe an elevated expression of RICTOR, ZFX, and UGCG in Indian Luminal breast cancer patient samples, and in TCGA and METABRIC datasets. Together, we establish a key regulatory circuit, RICTOR-AKT-ZFX-UGCG-Ganglioside-EGFR-AKT, and elucidate its contribution to breast cancer progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475595" rel="alternate" title="mTORC2 Drives ZFX-mediated Ganglioside Biosynthesis to Promote Breast Cancer Progression (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475617</id><title>Pervasive conditional selection of driver mutations and modular epistasis networks in cancer (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.363139+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaime Iranzo</name></author><author><name>George Gruenhagen</name></author><author><name>Jorge Calle-Espinosa</name></author><author><name>Eugene V. Koonin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer driver mutations often display mutual exclusion or co-occurrence, underscoring the key role of epistasis in carcinogenesis. However, estimating the magnitude of epistatic interactions and their quantitative effect on tumor evolution remains a challenge. We developed a method to quantify &lt;italic&gt;COnditional SELection on the Excess of Nonsynonymous Substitutions&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Coselens&lt;/italic&gt;) in cancer genes. &lt;italic&gt;Coselens&lt;/italic&gt; infers the number of drivers per gene in different partitions of a cancer genomics dataset using covariance-based mutation models and determines whether coding mutations in a gene affect selection for drivers in any other gene. Using &lt;italic&gt;Coselens&lt;/italic&gt;, we identified 296 conditionally selected gene pairs across 16 cancer types in the TCGA dataset. Conditional selection accounts for 25-50% of driver substitutions in tumors with &amp;gt;2 drivers. Conditionally co-selected genes form modular networks, whose structures challenge the traditional interpretation of within-pathway mutual exclusivity and across-pathway synergy, suggesting a more complex scenario, where gene-specific across-pathway interactions shape differentiated cancer subtypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475617" rel="alternate" title="Pervasive conditional selection of driver mutations and modular epistasis networks in cancer (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.474416</id><title>Collagen XVIII promotes breast cancer through EGFR/ErbB signaling and its ablation improves the efficacy of ErbB-targeting inhibitors (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.363205+00:00</updated><author><name>Raman Devarajan</name></author><author><name>Hellevi Peltoketo</name></author><author><name>Valerio Izzi</name></author><author><name>Heli Ruotsalainen</name></author><author><name>Saila Kauppila</name></author><author><name>Marja-Riitta Väisänen</name></author><author><name>Gunilla Rask</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Martínez-Nieto</name></author><author><name>Sanna-Maria Karppinen</name></author><author><name>Timo Väisänen</name></author><author><name>Inderjeet Kaur</name></author><author><name>Jussi Koivunen</name></author><author><name>Takako Sasaki</name></author><author><name>Robert Winqvist</name></author><author><name>Fredrik Wärnberg</name></author><author><name>Malin Sund</name></author><author><name>Taina Pihlajaniemi</name></author><author><name>Ritva Heljasvaara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The tumor extracellular matrix (ECM) is a critical regulator of cancer progression and metastasis, significantly affecting the treatment response. Expression of collagen XVIII (ColXVIII), a ubiquitous component of basement membranes, is induced in many solid tumors, but its involvement in tumorigenesis has remained elusive. We show here that ColXVIII is markedly upregulated in human breast cancer (BC) cells and is closely associated with a poor prognosis in high-grade BC, especially in human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-positive and basal/triple-negative cases. We identified a novel mechanism of action for ColXVIII as a modulator of epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR/ErbB) signaling and show that it forms a complex with EGFR, HER2 and α6 integrin to promote cancer cell proliferation in a pathway involving its N-terminal portion and the MAPK/ERK1/2 and PI3K/Akt cascades. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; studies with &lt;italic&gt;Col18a1&lt;/italic&gt; mouse models crossed with the MMTV-PyMT mammary carcinogenesis model showed that the short ColXVIII isoform promotes BC growth and metastasis in a tumor cell-autonomous manner. Moreover, the number of mammary cancer stem cells was significantly reduced in both mouse and human cell models upon ColXVIII inhibition. Finally, ablation of ColXVIII in human BC cells and the MMTV-PyMT model substantially improved the efficacy of certain EGFR/ERbB-targeting therapies, even abolishing resistance to EGFR/ErbB inhibitors in some cell lines. In summary, a new function is revealed for ColXVIII in sustaining the stemness properties of BC cells, and tumor progression and metastasis through EGFR/ErbB signaling, suggesting that targeting ColXVIII in the tumor milieu may have significant therapeutic potential.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Collagen XVIII is upregulated in breast cancer and promotes mammary carcinogenesis through EGFR/ErbB signaling and by sustaining cancer stem cells, so that its targeting improves the efficacy of ErbB-targeted therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.474416" rel="alternate" title="Collagen XVIII promotes breast cancer through EGFR/ErbB signaling and its ablation improves the efficacy of ErbB-targeting inhibitors (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475900</id><title>Reciprocal epigenetic Sox2 regulation by SMAD1-SMAD3 is critical for anoikis resistance and metastasis in cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.363320+00:00</updated><author><name>Zainab Shonibare</name></author><author><name>Mehri Monavarian</name></author><author><name>Kathleen O’ Connell</name></author><author><name>Diego Altomare</name></author><author><name>Abigail Shelton</name></author><author><name>Shubham Mehta</name></author><author><name>Renata Jaskula-Sztul</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Phaeton</name></author><author><name>Mark D. Starr</name></author><author><name>Regina Whitaker</name></author><author><name>Andrew Berchuck</name></author><author><name>Andrew B Nixon</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Arend</name></author><author><name>Nam Y Lee</name></author><author><name>C. Ryan Miller</name></author><author><name>Nadine Hempel</name></author><author><name>Karthikeyan Mythreye</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Growth factors in the tumor environment are key regulators of cell survival and metastasis. Here we reveal, dichotomy between TGF-β superfamily growth factors BMP and TGF-β/activin, and their downstream SMAD effectors. Gene expression profiling uncovered Sox2 as a key signaling node regulated in an opposing manner by anoikis-promoting BMP2, 4 and 9, and anoikis-suppressing TGF-β and activin A. We find that Sox2 repression by BMPs robustly inhibits intraperitoneal tumor burden and increases survival in multiple ovarian cancer models. Repression of Sox2 is driven by SMAD1 dependent histone H3K27me3 recruitment and DNA methylation at &lt;italic&gt;SOX2’s&lt;/italic&gt; promoter. Conversely, TGF-β and activin A promote Sox2 expression, and anoikis resistance by SMAD3 mediated histone H3K4me3 recruitment. We find that balancing Sox2 levels is critical for anoikis, as transcriptomics reveals regulation of key cell death pathways. Moreover, BMP-driven SMAD1 signaling can override TGF-β and activin’s effect on Sox2, which has clinical significance due to the high levels of TGF-β we find in ovarian cancer patients. Together, our findings identify Sox2 as a contextual and contrastingly regulated key node, downstream of TGF-β superfamily members controlling anoikis and metastasis in ovarian cancers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sox2 is a key node for anoikis resistance in cancer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sox2 is differentially regulated by TGF-β/activin and BMPs in broad cancers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;BMP9 is a robust metastasis suppressor by lowering Sox2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sox2 regulation is contextual, epigenetic and at the transcriptional level&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475900" rel="alternate" title="Reciprocal epigenetic Sox2 regulation by SMAD1-SMAD3 is critical for anoikis resistance and metastasis in cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>