<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.832707+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467878</id><title>In vivo label-free observation of tumor-related blood vessels in small animals using a newly designed photoacoustic 3D imaging system (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.834697+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasufumi Asao</name></author><author><name>Kenichi Nagae</name></author><author><name>Koichi Miyasaka</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Sekiguchi</name></author><author><name>Sadakazu Aiso</name></author><author><name>Shigeaki Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Marika Sato</name></author><author><name>Shinae Kizaka-Kondoh</name></author><author><name>Yukari Nakajima</name></author><author><name>Kazuo Kishi</name></author><author><name>Takayuki Yagi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Photoacoustic technology can be used for non-invasive imaging of blood vessels. In this paper, we report on our prototype photoacoustic imaging system with a newly designed ultrasound sensor and its visualization performance of microvascular in animal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We fabricated an experimental system for animals using a high-frequency sensor. The system has two modes: still image mode by wide scanning and moving image mode by small rotation of sensor array. Optical test target, euthanized mice and rats, and live mice were used as objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of optical test target showed that the spatial resolution was about 2 times higher than that of our conventional prototype. The image performance in vivo was evaluated in euthanized healthy mice and rats, allowing visualization of detailed blood vessels in the liver and kidneys. In tumor-bearing mice, different results of vascular induction were shown depending on the type of tumor and the method of transplantation. By utilizing the video imaging function, we were able to observe the movement of blood vessels around the tumor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have demonstrated the feasibility of the system as a less invasive animal experimental device, as it can acquire vascular images in animals in a non-contrast and non-invasive manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467878" rel="alternate" title="In vivo label-free observation of tumor-related blood vessels in small animals using a newly designed photoacoustic 3D imaging system (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467708</id><title>Oncogenic and Tumor Suppressor Functions for Lymphoid Enhancer Factor 1 in a Murine Model of T Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.851911+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiffany Carr</name></author><author><name>Stephanie McGregor</name></author><author><name>Sheila Dias</name></author><author><name>Mihalis Verykokakis</name></author><author><name>Michelle M. LeBeau</name></author><author><name>Hai-Hui Xue</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth T. Bartom</name></author><author><name>Barbara L. Kee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;T lymphocyte acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL) is a heterogeneous disease affecting T cells at multiple stages of their development and is characterized by frequent genomic alterations. The transcription factor LEF1 is inactivated through mutation in a subset of T-ALL cases but elevated LEF1 expression and activating mutations have also been identified in this disease. Here we show, in a murine model of T-ALL, that the developmental timing of &lt;italic&gt;Lef1&lt;/italic&gt; mutation impacts its ability to function as a cooperative tumor suppressor or oncogene. T cell transformation in the presence of LEF1 allows leukemic cells to become addicted to its presence. In contrast, deletion prior to transformation both accelerates leukemogenesis and results in leukemic cells with altered expression of genes controlling receptor signaling pathways. Our data demonstrate that the developmental timing of &lt;italic&gt;Lef1&lt;/italic&gt; mutations impact its apparent oncogenic or tumor suppressive characteristics and demonstrate the utility of mouse models for understanding the cooperation and consequence of mutational order in leukemogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467708" rel="alternate" title="Oncogenic and Tumor Suppressor Functions for Lymphoid Enhancer Factor 1 in a Murine Model of T Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (9 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468531</id><title>Chromosome 1q amplification perturbs a ceRNA network to promote melanoma metastasis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.876300+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaonan Xu</name></author><author><name>Kaizhen Wang</name></author><author><name>Olga Vera</name></author><author><name>Akanksha Verma</name></author><author><name>Olivier Elemento</name></author><author><name>Xiaoqing Yu</name></author><author><name>Florian A Karreth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deregulated gene expression through epigenetic, transcriptional, and copy number alterations is a major driver of melanoma progression and metastasis. In addition to serving as blueprints for translation, some mRNAs post-transcriptionally regulate gene expression by competitively sequestering miRNAs they share with other targets. Here we report that such mRNAs, termed competitive endogenous RNAs (ceRNAs), contribute to melanoma progression and metastasis. ceRNA predictions identified multiple candidate genes on chromosome 1q, which is recurrently amplified in melanoma. Genetic studies reveal that three of these mRNAs, CEP170, NUCKS1, and ZC3H11A, promote melanoma migration, invasion, and metastasis in a protein coding-independent and miRNA binding site-dependent manner. Interestingly, CEP170, NUCKS1, and ZC3H11A cooperate to elicit oncogenic effects by collectively impairing the tumor suppressor activity of 8 miRNAs on several pro-metastatic target genes. Finally, this complex chromosome 1q ceRNA network is evident in other cancer types, suggesting ceRNA network deregulation is a common driver of cancer progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468531" rel="alternate" title="Chromosome 1q amplification perturbs a ceRNA network to promote melanoma metastasis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467929</id><title>Photoimmunotherapy retains its anti-tumor efficacy with increasing stromal content in heterotypic pancreatic cancer spheroids (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.880815+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohammad A. Saad</name></author><author><name>Wonho Zhung</name></author><author><name>Margaret Elizabeth Stanley</name></author><author><name>Sydney Formica</name></author><author><name>Stacey Grimaldo-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Girgis Obaid</name></author><author><name>Tayyaba Hasan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) is an aggressive disease characterized by increased levels of desmoplasia that contributes to reduced drug delivery and poor treatment outcomes. In PDAC, the stromal content can account for up to 90% of the total tumor volume. The complex interplay between stromal components, including pancreatic cancer associated fibroblasts (PCAFs), and PDAC cells in the tumor microenvironment (TME) have a significant impact on prognoses and thus needs to be recapitulated in vitro when evaluating various treatment strategies. This study is a systematic evaluation of photodynamic therapy (PDT) in 3D heterotypic coculture models of PDAC with varying ratios of patient derived PCAFs that simulate heterogenous PDAC tumors with increasing stromal content. The efficacy of antibody-targeted PDT (photoimmunotherapy; PIT) using cetuximab photoimmunoconjugates (PICs) of benzoporphyrin derivative (BPD) is contrasted with that of liposomal BPD (Visudyne®), which is currently in PDT clinical trials for PDAC. We demonstrate that both Visudyne®-PDT and PIT were effective in heterotypic PDAC 3D spheroids with a low stromal content. However, as the stromal content increases above 50% in the 3D spheroids, the efficacy of Visudyne®-PDT is reduced by up to 10-fold, while PIT retains its efficacy. PIT was found to be 10-fold, 19-fold and 14-fold more phototoxic in spheroids with 50%, 75% and 90% PCAFs, respectively, as compared to Visudyne®-PDT. This marked difference in efficacy is attributed to the ability of PICs to penetrate and distribute within spheroids with a higher stromal content, whereas Visudyne® is restricted to the spheroid periphery. This study thus demonstrates how the stromal content in PDAC spheroids directly impacts their responsiveness to PDT and proposes PIT to be a highly suited treatment option for desmoplastic tumors with particularly high degrees of stromal content.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467929" rel="alternate" title="Photoimmunotherapy retains its anti-tumor efficacy with increasing stromal content in heterotypic pancreatic cancer spheroids (6 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.465791</id><title>A connectivity signature for glioblastoma (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.881266+00:00</updated><author><name>Ling Hai</name></author><author><name>Dirk C Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Henriette Mandelbaum</name></author><author><name>Ruifan Xie</name></author><author><name>Jakob Ito</name></author><author><name>Erik Jung</name></author><author><name>Sophie Weil</name></author><author><name>Philipp Sievers</name></author><author><name>Varun Venkataramani</name></author><author><name>Daniel Dominguez Azorin</name></author><author><name>Kati Ernst</name></author><author><name>Denise Reibold</name></author><author><name>Rainer Will</name></author><author><name>Mario L. Suvà</name></author><author><name>Christel Herold-Mende</name></author><author><name>Felix Sahm</name></author><author><name>Frank Winkler</name></author><author><name>Matthias Schlesner</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Wick</name></author><author><name>Tobias Kessler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tumor cell extensions called tumor microtubes (TMs) in glioma resemble neurites during neurodevelopment and connect glioma cells to a network that has considerable relevance for tumor progression and therapy resistance. The determination of interconnectivity in individual tumors has been challenging and the impact of tumor cell connectivity on patient survival remained unresolved so far. Here, a connectivity signature from single-cell RNA-sequenced (scRNA-Seq) xenografted primary glioblastoma (GB) cells was established and clinically validated. Thirty-four of 40 connectivity genes were related to neurogenesis, neural tube development or glioma progression, including the TM-network-relevant &lt;italic&gt;GAP43&lt;/italic&gt; gene. Astrocytic-like and mesenchymal-like GB cells had the highest connectivity signature scores in scRNA-Seq data of patient-derived xenografts and patient samples. In 230 human GBs, high connectivity correlated with the mesenchymal expression subtype, &lt;italic&gt;TP53&lt;/italic&gt; wildtype, and with dismal patient survival. &lt;italic&gt;CHI3L1&lt;/italic&gt; was identified as a robust molecular marker of connectivity. Thus, the connectivity signature allows novel insights into brain tumor biology, provides a proof-of-principle that tumor cell connectivity is relevant for patients’ prognosis, and serves as a robust biomarker that can be used for future clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Integration of GB cells into functional networks drives tumor progression and resistance. Here, we established and validated a novel connectivity gene expression signature of single GB cells and whole tumors that can be easily applied to clinical and preclinical samples. It is shown that connectivity is determining prognosis combining molecular, functional and clinical insights into the disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.465791" rel="alternate" title="A connectivity signature for glioblastoma (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468007</id><title>A platform of patient-derived microtumors identifies treatment response and therapeutic vulnerabilities of ovarian cancer (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.881751+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole Anderle</name></author><author><name>André Koch</name></author><author><name>Berthold Gierke</name></author><author><name>Anna-Lena Keller</name></author><author><name>Annette Staebler</name></author><author><name>Andreas Hartkopf</name></author><author><name>Sara Y. Brucker</name></author><author><name>Michael Pawlak</name></author><author><name>Katja Schenke-Layland</name></author><author><name>Christian Schmees</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ovarian cancer (OvCa) is an insidious disease: due to nonspecific symptoms, these tumors are usually diagnosed at advanced stage with correspondingly devastating consequences for treatment outcome and patient survival. The broad heterogeneity of OvCa manifests itself in the complex composition of the tumor microenvironment. Given the frequent development of therapeutic resistance, there is a strong need for model systems accurately representing OvCa heterogeneity, while enabling parallel drug testing and prediction of appropriate treatment responses in individual patients. Here, we demonstrate the efficient isolation of highly viable OvCa patient-derived microtumors (OvCa PDM). Importantly, our data demonstrate histopathological comparability of OvCa PDM with corresponding patient tumor tissue. Reverse phase protein array (RPPA)-based analyses of &amp;gt;110 total and phospho-proteins enabled the identification of sensitivities to standard, platinum-based as well as experimental, selumetinib-based therapy, and thereby the prediction of treatment-responder. Parallelized drug testing in OvCa PDM allowed functional validation of RPPA data and detection of on- and off-target treatment effects. Strikingly, clinical follow-up of corresponding patients confirmed significantly increased metastasis-free survival of identified carboplatin-responder. Furthermore, flow cytometry-based characterization of autologous TIL populations confirmed the presence of tumor-specific, cytotoxic TILs with stem-like CD39&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;PD1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and terminally differentiated CD39&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;PD1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; phenotypes. Interestingly, our results showed a significant correlation between the presence of CD8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;CD39&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; Tils and lymph node metastasis in the associated patients. Finally, combining OvCa PDM and autologous TILs for efficacy testing of immune checkpoint inhibitors demonstrated the potential for patient-specific enhancement of cytotoxic TIL activity by this therapeutic approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468007" rel="alternate" title="A platform of patient-derived microtumors identifies treatment response and therapeutic vulnerabilities of ovarian cancer (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468146</id><title>The hexokinase ″HKDC1″ interaction with the mitochondria is essential for hepatocellular carcinoma progression (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.882962+00:00</updated><author><name>Md. Wasim Khan</name></author><author><name>Alexander Terry</name></author><author><name>Medha Priyadarshini</name></author><author><name>Grace Guzman</name></author><author><name>Jose Cordoba-Chacon</name></author><author><name>Issam Ben-Sahra</name></author><author><name>Barton Wicksteed</name></author><author><name>Brian T Layden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is a leading cause of death from cancer malignancies. Recently, hexokinase domain containing 1 (HKDC1), was shown to have significant overexpression in HCC compared to healthy tissue. Using in vitro and in vivo tools, we examined the role of HKDC1 in HCC progression. Importantly, HKDC1 ablation stops HCC progression by promoting metabolic reprogramming by shifting glucose flux away from the TCA cycle.  Next, HKDC1 ablation leads to mitochondrial dysfunction resulting in less cellular energy which cannot be compensated by enhanced glucose uptake. And finally, we show that the interaction of HKDC1 with the mitochondria is essential for its role in HCC progression, and without this mitochondrial interaction mitochondrial dysfunction occurs. In sum, HKDC1 is highly expressed in HCC cells compared to normal hepatocytes, therefore targeting HKDC1, specifically its interaction with the mitochondria, reveals a highly selective approach to target cancer cells in HCC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468146" rel="alternate" title="The hexokinase ″HKDC1″ interaction with the mitochondria is essential for hepatocellular carcinoma progression (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468447</id><title>Microfluidic system-based time-course tracking of physical proximity between cells and its effect on gene expression for elucidating live single cancer-immune cell interactions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.884142+00:00</updated><author><name>Bianca C.T Flores</name></author><author><name>Smriti Chawla</name></author><author><name>Ning Ma</name></author><author><name>Chad Sanada</name></author><author><name>Praveen Kumar Kujur</name></author><author><name>Ludimilla T.D Chinen</name></author><author><name>Kyle Hukari</name></author><author><name>Mark Lynch</name></author><author><name>Naveen Ramalingam</name></author><author><name>Debarka Sengupta</name></author><author><name>Stefanie S Jeffrey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell-cell communication and physical interactions play a vital role in cancer initiation, homeostasis, progression, and immune response. Here, we report a system that combines live capture of different cell types, co-incubation, time-lapse imaging, and gene expression profiling of doublets using a microfluidic integrated fluidic circuit (IFC) that enables measurement of physical distances between cells and the associated transcriptional profiles due to cell-cell interactions. The temporal variations in natural killer (NK) - triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) cell distances were tracked and compared with terminally profiled cellular transcriptomes. The results showed the time-bound activities of regulatory modules and alluded to the existence of transcriptional memory. Our experimental and bioinformatic approaches serve as a proof of concept for interrogating live cell interactions at doublet resolution, which can be applied across different cancers and cell types.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468447" rel="alternate" title="Microfluidic system-based time-course tracking of physical proximity between cells and its effect on gene expression for elucidating live single cancer-immune cell interactions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467778</id><title>Prostate tumor-induced stromal reprogramming generates Tenascin C that promotes prostate cancer metastasis through YAP/TAZ inhibition (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.884548+00:00</updated><author><name>Yu-Chen Lee</name></author><author><name>Song-Chang Lin</name></author><author><name>Guoyu Yu</name></author><author><name>Ming Zhu</name></author><author><name>Jian H Song</name></author><author><name>Keith Rivera</name></author><author><name>Darryl Pappin</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Logothetis</name></author><author><name>Theocharis Panaretakis</name></author><author><name>Guocan Wang</name></author><author><name>Li-Yuan Yu-Lee</name></author><author><name>Sue-Hwa Lin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metastatic prostate cancer (PCa) in bone induces bone-forming lesions that enhance PCa progression. How tumor-induced bone formation enhances PCa progression is not known. We have previously shown that PCa-induced bone originates from endothelial cells (EC) that have undergone endothelial-to-osteoblast (EC-to-OSB) transition by tumor-secreted BMP4. Here, we show that EC-to-OSB transition leads to changes in the tumor microenvironment that increases the metastatic potential of PCa cells. We found that conditioned medium (CM) from EC-OSB hybrid cells increases the migration, invasion and survival of PC3-mm2 and C4-2B4 PCa cells. Quantitative mass spectrometry (iTRAQ) identified Tenascin C (TNC) as one of the major proteins secreted from EC-OSB hybrid cells. TNC expression in tumor-induced osteoblasts was confirmed by immunohistochemistry of MDA-PCa118b xenograft and human bone metastasis specimens. Mechanistically, BMP4 increases TNC expression in EC-OSB cells through the Smad1-Notch/Hey1 pathway. How TNC promotes PCa metastasis was next interrogated by in vitro and in vivo studies. In vitro studies showed that a TNC neutralizing antibody inhibits EC-OSB-CM-mediated PCa cell migration and survival. TNC knockdown decreased, while addition of recombinant TNC or TNC overexpression increased migration and anchorage-independent growth of PC3 or C4-2b cells. When injected orthotopically, PC3-mm2-shTNC clones decreased metastasis to bone, while C4-2b-TNC overexpressing cells increased metastasis to lymph nodes. TNC enhances PCa cell migration through α5β1 integrin-mediated YAP/TAZ inhibition. These studies elucidate that tumor-induced stromal reprogramming generates TNC that enhances PCa metastasis and suggest that TNC may be a target for PCa therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467778" rel="alternate" title="Prostate tumor-induced stromal reprogramming generates Tenascin C that promotes prostate cancer metastasis through YAP/TAZ inhibition (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467567</id><title>Vitamin D deficiency increases prostatic megalin expression and globulin-bound testosterone import, increasing prostatic androgens in African American men (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.885177+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Garcia</name></author><author><name>Kirstin D. Krieger</name></author><author><name>Candice Loitz</name></author><author><name>Lillian Perez</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. Richards</name></author><author><name>Yves Helou</name></author><author><name>Steve Kregel</name></author><author><name>Clementina A. Mesaros</name></author><author><name>Peter H. Gann</name></author><author><name>Donald Vander Griend</name></author><author><name>Rick Kittles</name></author><author><name>Gail S. Prins</name></author><author><name>Trevor Penning</name></author><author><name>Larisa Nonn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vitamin D deficiency associates with an increased risk of prostate cancer (PCa) mortality and is hypothesized to contribute to PCa aggressiveness and disparities in African Americans. We reported a relationship between African-ancestry, circulating and intraprostatic vitamin D metabolites and prostatic expression of megalin, an endocytic membrane receptor that internalizes globulin-bound hormones. Here, we show that megalin imports sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG)-bound testosterone, potentially regulating intraprostatic hormone levels. Vitamin D levels regulated megalin expression in cell lines, patient-derived prostate epithelial cells, and prostate tissue explants, and mice with prostatic knockout of &lt;italic&gt;Lrp2&lt;/italic&gt; (megalin) showed reduced prostatic testosterone. Notably, prostatic 5α-dihydrotestosterone levels were higher in African American men and correlated inversely with serum vitamin D status, while megalin protein levels were reduced in PCa tissue. Our findings highlight the negative impact of vitamin D deficiency on PCa and the potential link to PCa disparities observed in African Americans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467567" rel="alternate" title="Vitamin D deficiency increases prostatic megalin expression and globulin-bound testosterone import, increasing prostatic androgens in African American men (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>