<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.012584+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475061</id><title>Neomorphic DNA-binding enables tumor-specific therapeutic gene expression in fusion-addicted childhood sarcoma (42 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.013132+00:00</updated><author><name>Tilman L. B. Hölting</name></author><author><name>Florencia Cidre-Aranaz</name></author><author><name>Dana Matzek</name></author><author><name>Bastian Popper</name></author><author><name>Severin J. Jacobi</name></author><author><name>Jing Li</name></author><author><name>Ignazio Piseddu</name></author><author><name>Bruno L. Cadilha</name></author><author><name>Stephan Ledderose</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Zwilling</name></author><author><name>Shunya Ohmura</name></author><author><name>David Anz</name></author><author><name>Annette Künkele</name></author><author><name>Frederick Klauschen</name></author><author><name>Thomas G. P. Grünewald</name></author><author><name>Maximilian M. L. Knott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chimeric fusion transcription factors are oncogenic hallmarks of several devastating cancer types including pediatric sarcomas, such as Ewing sarcoma (EwS) and alveolar rhabdomyosarcoma (ARMS). Despite their exquisite specificity, these driver oncogenes have been considered largely undruggable due to their lack of enzymatic activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we show in the EwS model that – capitalizing on neomorphic DNA-binding preferences – the addiction to the respective fusion transcription factor EWSR1-FLI1 can be leveraged to express therapeutic genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We genetically engineered a &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; enhancer-based, synthetic and highly potent expression cassette that can elicit EWSR1-FLI1-dependent expression of a therapeutic payload as evidenced by episomal and CRISPR-edited genomic reporter assays. Combining &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; screens and immunohistochemistry, we identified GPR64 as a highly specific cell surface antigen for targeted transduction strategies in EwS. Functional experiments demonstrated that anti-GPR64-pseudotyped lentivirus harboring our expression cassette can specifically transduce EwS cells to promote the expression of viral thymidine kinase sensitizing EwS for treatment to the otherwise relatively non-toxic (Val)ganciclovir and leading to strong anti-tumorigenic, but no adverse effects &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Further, we prove that similar vector designs can be applied in PAX3-FOXO1-driven ARMS, and to express immunomodulatory cytokines, such as IL-15 and XCL1, in tumor types typically considered to be immunologically ‘cold’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Collectively, these results generated in pediatric sarcomas indicate that exploiting, rather than suppressing, the neomorphic functions of chimeric transcription factors may open inroads to innovative and personalized therapies, and that our highly versatile approach may be translatable to other cancers addicted to oncogenic transcription factors with unique DNA-binding properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475061" rel="alternate" title="Neomorphic DNA-binding enables tumor-specific therapeutic gene expression in fusion-addicted childhood sarcoma (42 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474951</id><title>PACpAInt: a deep learning approach to identify molecular subtypes of pancreatic adenocarcinoma on histology slides (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.013524+00:00</updated><author><name>C. Saillard</name></author><author><name>F. Delecourt</name></author><author><name>B. Schmauch</name></author><author><name>O. Moindrot</name></author><author><name>M. Svrcek</name></author><author><name>A. Bardier-Dupas</name></author><author><name>J-F. Emile</name></author><author><name>M. Ayadi</name></author><author><name>V. Rebours</name></author><author><name>L. de Mestier</name></author><author><name>P. Hammel</name></author><author><name>C. Neuzillet</name></author><author><name>J-B. Bachet</name></author><author><name>J. Iovanna</name></author><author><name>N. Dusetti</name></author><author><name>Y. Blum</name></author><author><name>M. Richard</name></author><author><name>Y. Kermezli</name></author><author><name>V. Paradis</name></author><author><name>M. Zaslavskiy</name></author><author><name>P. Courtiol</name></author><author><name>A. Kamoun</name></author><author><name>R. Nicolle</name></author><author><name>J. Cros</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PAC) is a highly heterogeneous and plastic tumor with different transcriptomic molecular subtypes that hold great prognostic and theranostic values. We developed PACpAInt, a multistep approach using deep learning models to determine tumor cell type and their molecular phenotype on routine histological preparation at a resolution enabling to decipher complete intratumor heterogeneity on a massive scale never achieved before. PACpAInt effectively identified molecular subtypes at the slide level in three validation cohorts and had an independent prognostic value. It identified an interslide heterogeneity within a case in 39% of tumors that impacted survival. Diving at the cell level, PACpAInt identified “pure” classical and basal-like main subtypes as well as an intermediary phenotype and hybrid tumors that co-carried both classical and basal-like phenotypes. These novel artificial intelligence-based subtypes, together with the proportion of basal-like cells within a tumor had a strong prognostic impact.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474951" rel="alternate" title="PACpAInt: a deep learning approach to identify molecular subtypes of pancreatic adenocarcinoma on histology slides (15 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474882</id><title>Evaluation of a predictive method for the H&amp;E-based molecular profiling of breast cancer with deep learning (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.013922+00:00</updated><author><name>Salim Arslan</name></author><author><name>Xiusi Li</name></author><author><name>Julian Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Julius Hense</name></author><author><name>Andre Geraldes</name></author><author><name>Cher Bass</name></author><author><name>Keelan Brown</name></author><author><name>Angelica Marcia</name></author><author><name>Tim Dewhirst</name></author><author><name>Pahini Pandya</name></author><author><name>Shikha Singhal</name></author><author><name>Debapriya Mehrotra</name></author><author><name>Pandu Raharja-Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present a public validation of PANProfiler (ER, PR, HER2), an in-vitro medical device (IVD) that predicts the qualitative status of estrogen receptor (ER), progesterone receptor (PR) and human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) by analysing the hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;amp;E)-stained tissue scan. In public validation on 648 (ER), 648 (PR) and 560 (HER2) unseen cases with known biomarker status, the device achieves an accuracy of 87% (ER), 83% (PR) and 87% (HER2). The validation offers early evidence of the ability to predict clinically relevant breast biomarkers from an H&amp;amp;E slide in a relevant clinical setting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474882" rel="alternate" title="Evaluation of a predictive method for the H&amp;E-based molecular profiling of breast cancer with deep learning (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475258</id><title>LIX1 controls digestive mesenchyme-derived cell fate decision by regulating cristae organization in mitochondria (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.014244+00:00</updated><author><name>Amandine Guerin</name></author><author><name>Claire Angebault</name></author><author><name>Sandrina Kinet</name></author><author><name>Chantal Cazevieille</name></author><author><name>Manuel Rojo</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Fauconnier</name></author><author><name>Alain Lacampagne</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Mourier</name></author><author><name>Naomi Taylor</name></author><author><name>Pascal de Santa Barbara</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Faure</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Limb Expression 1 (LIX1) is a master regulator of digestive mesenchymal progenitor and GastroIntestinal Stromal Tumor (GIST) cell proliferation by controlling the expression of the Hippo effectors YAP1/TAZ and KIT. However, the underlying mechanisms of these LIX1- mediated regulations and tumor promotion remain to be elucidated. Here, we report that LIX1 is S-palmitoylated on cysteine 84 and localized in mitochondria. LIX1 knock-down affects the mitochondrial ultrastructure, resulting in decreased respiration and mitochondrial reactive oxygen species production. This is sufficient to downregulate YAP1/TAZ and reprogram KIT- positive GIST cells towards the smooth muscle cell lineage with reduced proliferative and invasive capacities. Mechanistically, LIX1 knock-down impairs the stability of the mitochondrial proteins PHB2 and OPA1 that are found in complexes with mitochondrial- specific phospholipids and are required for cristae organization. Supplementation with unsaturated fatty acids counteracts the effects of LIX1 knock-down on mitochondrial morphology and ultrastructure, restores YAP1/TAZ signaling, and consequently KIT levels. Altogether, our findings demonstrate that LIX1 contributes to GIST aggressive potential by modulating YAP1/TAZ and KIT levels, a process that depends on mitochondrial remodeling. Our work brings new insights into the mechanisms that could be targeted in tumors in which YAP1 and TAZ are implicated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475258" rel="alternate" title="LIX1 controls digestive mesenchyme-derived cell fate decision by regulating cristae organization in mitochondria (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474437</id><title>Serum metabolomic analysis of men on a low-carbohydrate diet for biochemically recurrent prostate cancer reveal the potential role of ketogenesis to slow tumor growth: A secondary analysis of the CAPS2 diet trial (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.014510+00:00</updated><author><name>Jen-Tsan Chi</name></author><author><name>Pao-Hwa Lin</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Tolstikov</name></author><author><name>Lauren Howard</name></author><author><name>Emily Y. Chen</name></author><author><name>Valerie Bussberg</name></author><author><name>Bennett Greenwood</name></author><author><name>Niven R. Narain</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Kiebish</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Freedland</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Systemic treatments for prostate cancer (PC) have significant side effects. Thus, newer alternatives with fewer side effects are urgently needed. Animal and human studies suggest the therapeutic potential of low carbohydrate diet (LCD) for PC. To test this possibility, Carbohydrate and Prostate Study 2 (CAPS2) trial was conducted in PC patients with biochemical recurrence (BCR) after local treatment to determine the effect of a 6-month LCD intervention vs. usual care control on PC growth as measured by PSA doubling time (PSADT). We previously reported the LCD intervention led to significant weight loss, higher HDL, and lower triglycerides and HbA1c with a suggested longer PSADT. However, the metabolic basis of these effects are unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To identify the potential metabolic basis of effects of LCD on PSADT, serum metabolomic analysis was performed using baseline, month 3, and month 6 banked sera to identify the metabolites significantly altered by LCD and that correlated with varying PSADT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;LCD increased the serum levels of ketone bodies, glycine and hydroxyisocaproic acid. Reciprocally, LCD reduced the serum levels of alanine, cytidine, asymmetric dimethylarginine (ADMA) and 2-oxobutanoate. As high ADMA level is shown to inhibit nitric oxide (NO) signaling and contribute to various cardiovascular diseases, the ADMA repression under LCD may contribute to the LCD-associated health benefit. Regression analysis of the PSADT revealed a correlation between longer PSADT with higher level of 2-hydroxybutyric acids, ketone bodies, citrate and malate. Longer PSADT was also associated with LCD reduced nicotinamide, fructose-1, 6-biphosphate (FBP) and 2-oxobutanoate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results suggest a potential association of ketogenesis and TCA metabolites with slower PC growth and conversely glycolysis with faster PC growth. The link of high ketone bodies with longer PSADT supports future studies of ketogenic diets to slow PC growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474437" rel="alternate" title="Serum metabolomic analysis of men on a low-carbohydrate diet for biochemically recurrent prostate cancer reveal the potential role of ketogenesis to slow tumor growth: A secondary analysis of the CAPS2 diet trial (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475158</id><title>Cytocapsular tubes and networks function as physical superdefence freeway systems conducting conventional cancer drug pan-resistant tumor metastasis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.014751+00:00</updated><author><name>Tingfang Yi</name></author><author><name>Gerhard Wagner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer drug pan-resistant tumor metastasis (cdp-rtm) is a major source of cancer lethality. Cytocapsular tubes (CCTs) and their networks are physical membrane-enclosed freeway systems for cancer cell dissemination across tissues and organs in vivo. Whether cytocapsular tube superlarge biomembranes function as superdenfence and conduct cdp-rtm is unknown. It is also unknown whether conventional cancer drug development methods, including cancer cell line derived xenograft (CDX) and patient cancer cell derived xenograft (PDX), generate cytocapsular tubes (CCTs). It is also unclear whether xenografts can be created that contain CCTs for efficient cancer drug development. Here, we investigated CCT functions related to cancer drug resistance, CCTs in CDX and PDX and CCT xenograft (CCTX). Using clinical cancer tissues, we discovered that CCTs potently shielded against multiple chemotherapy treatments with diverse conventional cancer drugs. Next, our quantitative analyses show that CCT biomembrane drug barriers significantly increase cancer drug resistance by 6.6-folds to14-folds. We found that conventional CDX and PDX animal models do not generate CCTs in these xenografts. By mimicking in vivo cancer cell environments for cancer patient cancer cell culturing, we have successfully isolated CH-5high/CH-6high subpopulations of patient breast cancer cells and pancreas cancer cells that are propertied with cytocapsular tube generation capacities and engender large quantities of CCTs in mouse xenografts. Biochemical and immunohistochemistry analyses demonstrated that CCTs in these xenografts are similar to those in clinical cancer tissues. In summary, our research has identified that CCTs and networks function as physical superdefence freeway systems conducting conventional cancer drug pan-resistant tumor metastasis, and developed a CCTX platform for highly efficient cancer drug development, which pave avenues for more efficient development of effective and precise cancer drugs for tumor cure at both personal and broad-spectrum levels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475158" rel="alternate" title="Cytocapsular tubes and networks function as physical superdefence freeway systems conducting conventional cancer drug pan-resistant tumor metastasis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475106</id><title>Integrin signaling is critical for myeloid-mediated support of T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.014918+00:00</updated><author><name>Aram Lyu</name></author><author><name>Seo Hee Nam</name></author><author><name>Ryan S Humphrey</name></author><author><name>Tyler A Durham</name></author><author><name>Zicheng Hu</name></author><author><name>Dhivya Arasappan</name></author><author><name>Terzah M Horton</name></author><author><name>Lauren I. R Ehrlich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We previously found that T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL) requires support from tumor-associated myeloid cells, which activate IGF1R signaling in the leukemic blasts. However, IGF1 is not sufficient to sustain T-ALL survival in vitro, implicating additional myeloid-mediated signals in T-ALL progression. Here, we find that T-ALL cells require close contact with myeloid cells to survive. Transcriptional profiling and in vitro assays demonstrate that integrin-mediated cell adhesion and activation of the downstream FAK/PYK2 kinases are required for myeloid-mediated support of T-ALL cells and promote IGF1R activation. Consistent with these findings, inhibition of integrins or FAK/PYK2 signaling diminishes leukemia burden in multiple organs and confers a survival advantage in a mouse model of T-ALL. Inhibiting integrin mediated cell adhesion or FAK/PYK2 also diminishes survival of primary patient T-ALL cells co-cultured with myeloid cells. Furthermore, elevated integrin pathway gene signatures correlate significantly with myeloid enrichment and an inferior prognosis in pediatric T-ALL patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475106" rel="alternate" title="Integrin signaling is critical for myeloid-mediated support of T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474890</id><title>Single-cell multi-omics analyses reveal EZH2 as a main driver of retinoic acid resistance in PLZF-RARA leukemia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.015315+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Poplineau</name></author><author><name>N. Platet</name></author><author><name>A. Mazuel</name></author><author><name>L. Hérault</name></author><author><name>S. Koide</name></author><author><name>W. Kuribayashi</name></author><author><name>N. Carbuccia</name></author><author><name>L. N’Guyen</name></author><author><name>J. Vernerey</name></author><author><name>M. Oshima</name></author><author><name>D. Birnbaum</name></author><author><name>A. Iwama</name></author><author><name>E. Duprez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer relapse is caused by a subset of malignant cells that are resistant to treatment. To characterize resistant cells and their vulnerabilities, we studied the retinoic acid (RA)-resistant PLZF-RARA acute promyelocytic leukemia (APL) using single-cell multi-omics. We uncovered transcriptional and chromatin heterogeneity in leukemia cells and identified a subset of cells resistant to RA that depend on a fine-tuned transcriptional network targeting the epigenetic regulator Enhancer of Zeste Homolog 2 (EZH2). Epigenomic and functional analyses validated EZH2 selective dependency of PLZF-RARA leukemia and its driver role in RA resistance. Targeting pan-EZH2 activities (canonical/non-canonical) was necessary to eliminate leukemia relapse initiating cells, which underlies a dependency of resistant cells on an EZH2 non-canonical activity and the necessity to degrade EZH2 to overcome resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study provides critical insights into the mechanisms of RA resistance that allow us to eliminate treatment-resistant leukemia cells by targeting EZH2, thus highlighting a potential targeted therapy approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- sc-RNAseq identifies PLZF-RARA leukemia heterogeneity and retinoic acid resistant cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- sc-ATACseq refines leukemic cell identity and resolves retinoic acid resistant networks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- EZH2 is a selective dependency of PLZF-RARA leukemia and drives retinoic acid resistance&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Targeting pan-EZH2 activities (canonical/non-canonical) is necessary to overcome leukemia onset&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474890" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell multi-omics analyses reveal EZH2 as a main driver of retinoic acid resistance in PLZF-RARA leukemia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>