<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.918388+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456823</id><title>Divergent transcriptional and transforming properties of PAX3-FOXO1 and PAX7-FOXO1 paralogs (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.918764+00:00</updated><author><name>Line Manceau</name></author><author><name>Julien Richard Albert</name></author><author><name>Pier-Luigi Lollini</name></author><author><name>Maxim V. C. Greenberg</name></author><author><name>Pascale Gilardi-Hebenstreit</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Ribes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hallmarks of the alveolar subclass of rhabdomyosarcoma are chromosomal translocations that generate chimeric PAX3-FOXO1 or PAX7-FOXO1 transcription factors. Both PAX-FOXO1s result in related cell transformation in animal models, but both mutations are associated with distinct pathological manifestations in patients. To assess the mechanisms underlying these differences, we generated isogenic fibroblast lines expressing either PAX-FOXO1 paralog. Mapping of their genomic recruitment using CUT&amp;amp;Tag revealed that the two chimeric proteins have distinct DNA binding preferences. In addition, PAX7-FOXO1 causes stronger &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; transactivation of its bound regions than PAX3-FOXO1, resulting in greater transcriptomic dynamics involving genes regulating cell shape and cycle. Consistently, PAX3-FOXO1 accentuates fibroblast cellular traits associated with contractility and surface adhesion and limits entry into M phase. In contrast, PAX7-FOXO1 drives cells to adopt an amoeboid shape, reduces entry into S phase, and causes more genomic instabilities. Altogether, our results argue that the diversity of rhabdomyosarcoma manifestation arises, in part, from the divergence between the transcriptional activities of PAX3-FOXO1 and PAX7-FOXO1. Furthermore, the identified pronounced deleterious effects of PAX7-FOXO1 provide an explanation for the low frequency of the translocation generating this factor in patients with rhabdomyosarcoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456823" rel="alternate" title="Divergent transcriptional and transforming properties of PAX3-FOXO1 and PAX7-FOXO1 paralogs (14 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456809</id><title>Optimized detection of somatic allelic imbalances specific for homologous recombination deficiency improves the prediction of clinical outcomes in ovarian cancer (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.918999+00:00</updated><author><name>Fernando Perez-Villatoro</name></author><author><name>Jaana Oikkonen</name></author><author><name>Julia Casado</name></author><author><name>Anastasiya Chernenko</name></author><author><name>Doga C. Gulhan</name></author><author><name>Manuela Tumiati</name></author><author><name>Sakari Hietanen</name></author><author><name>Johanna Hynninen</name></author><author><name>Ulla-Maija Haltia</name></author><author><name>Hannele Laivuori</name></author><author><name>Panagiotis Konstantinopoulos</name></author><author><name>Sampsa Hautaniemi</name></author><author><name>Liisa Kauppi</name></author><author><name>Anniina Färkkilä</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Specific patterns of genomic allelic imbalances (AIs) have been associated with Homologous recombination DNA-repair deficiency (HRD). We performed a systematic pan-cancer characterization of AIs across tumor types, revealing unique patterns in ovarian cancer. Using machine learning on a multi-omics dataset, we generated an optimized algorithm to detect HRD in ovarian cancer (ovaHRDscar). ovaHRDscar improved the prediction of clinical outcomes in three independent validation cohorts (PCAWG, HERCULES, TERVA). Characterization of 98 spatiotemporally distinct tumor samples indicated ovary/adnex as the preferred site to assess HRD. In conclusion, ovaHRDscar improves the detection of HRD in ovarian cancer with the premise to improve patient selection for HR-targeted therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456809" rel="alternate" title="Optimized detection of somatic allelic imbalances specific for homologous recombination deficiency improves the prediction of clinical outcomes in ovarian cancer (4 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>