<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular cancer preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.000700+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463652</id><title>A sense-antisense RNA interaction promotes breast cancer metastasis via regulation of NQO1 expression (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.001289+00:00</updated><author><name>Bruce Culbertson</name></author><author><name>Kristle Garcia</name></author><author><name>Daniel Markett</name></author><author><name>Hosseinali Asgharian</name></author><author><name>Li Chen</name></author><author><name>Lisa Fish</name></author><author><name>Albertas Navickas</name></author><author><name>Johnny Yu</name></author><author><name>Brian Woo</name></author><author><name>Scott Nanda</name></author><author><name>Joshua Rabinowitz</name></author><author><name>Hani Goodarzi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antisense RNAs are ubiquitous in human cells, yet the role that they play in healthy and diseased states remains largely unexplored. Here, we developed a computational framework to catalog and profile antisense RNAs and applied it to poorly and highly metastatic breast cancer cell lines. We identified one antisense RNA that plays a functional role in driving breast cancer progression by upregulating the redox enzyme NQO1, and hence named NQO1-antisense RNA or NQO1-AS. This upregulation occurs via a stabilizing interaction between NQO1-AS and its complementary region in the 3'UTR of NQO1 mRNA. By increasing expression of NQO1 protein, breast cancer cells are able to tolerate higher levels of oxidative stress, enabling them to colonize the lung. During this process the cancer cells become dependent on NQO1 to protect them from ferroptosis. We have shown that this dependence can be exploited therapeutically in xenograft models of metastasis. Together, our findings establish a previously unknown role for NQO1-AS in the progression of breast cancer by serving as a post-transcriptional regulator of RNA processing and decay for its sense mRNA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463652" rel="alternate" title="A sense-antisense RNA interaction promotes breast cancer metastasis via regulation of NQO1 expression (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463728</id><title>Mistic: an open-source multiplexed image t-SNE viewer (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.002080+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandhya Prabhakaran</name></author><author><name>Chandler Gatenbee</name></author><author><name>Mark Robertson-Tessi</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey West</name></author><author><name>Amer A Beg</name></author><author><name>Jhanelle E Gray</name></author><author><name>Scott Antonia</name></author><author><name>Robert A Gatenby</name></author><author><name>Alexander R. A. Anderson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the complex ecology of a tumor tissue and the spatio-temporal relationships between its cellular and microenvironment components is becoming a key component of translational research, especially in immune-oncology. The generation and analysis of multiplexed images from patient samples is of paramount importance to facilitate this understanding. In this work, we present Mistic, an open-source multiplexed image t-SNE viewer that enables the simultaneous viewing of multiple 2D images rendered using multiple layout options to provide an overall visual preview of the entire dataset. In particular, the positions of the images can be taken from t-SNE or UMAP coordinates. This grouped view of all the images further aids an exploratory understanding of the specific expression pattern of a given biomarker or collection of biomarkers across all images, helps to identify images expressing a particular phenotype or to select images for subsequent downstream analysis. Currently there is no freely available tool to generate such image t-SNEs. Mistic   is   open-source   and   can   be   downloaded at: https://github.com/MathOnco/Mistic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463728" rel="alternate" title="Mistic: an open-source multiplexed image t-SNE viewer (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463153</id><title>Biomarker Candidates for Tumors Identified from Deep-Profiled Plasma Stem Predominantly from the Low Abundant Area (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.002892+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco Tognetti</name></author><author><name>Kamil Sklodowski</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Müller</name></author><author><name>Dominique Kamber</name></author><author><name>Jan Muntel</name></author><author><name>Roland Bruderer</name></author><author><name>Lukas Reiter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The plasma proteome has the potential to enable a holistic analysis of the health state of an individual. However, plasma biomarker discovery is difficult due to its high dynamic range and variability. Here, we present a novel automated analytical approach for deep plasma profiling and applied it to a 180-sample cohort of human plasma from lung, breast, colorectal, pancreatic, and prostate cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a controlled quantitative experiment, we demonstrate a 257% increase in protein identification and a 263% increase in significantly differentially abundant proteins over neat plasma.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the cohort, we identified 2,732 proteins. Using machine learning, we discovered biomarker candidates such as STAT3 in colorectal cancer and developed models that classify the disease state. For pancreatic cancer, a separation by stage was achieved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Importantly, biomarker candidates came predominantly from the low abundance region, demonstrating the necessity to deeply profile because they would have been missed by shallow profiling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463153" rel="alternate" title="Biomarker Candidates for Tumors Identified from Deep-Profiled Plasma Stem Predominantly from the Low Abundant Area (3 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>