<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv cancer biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.584078+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443359</id><title>Pioneer transcription factors are associated with the modulation of DNA methylation patterns across cancers (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.584307+00:00</updated><author><name>Roza Berhanu Lemma</name></author><author><name>Thomas Fleischer</name></author><author><name>Emily Martinsen</name></author><author><name>Vessela N. Kristensen</name></author><author><name>Ragnhild Eskeland</name></author><author><name>Odd Stokke Gabrielsen</name></author><author><name>Anthony Mathelier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methylation of cytosines on DNA is a prominent modification associated with gene expression regulation. Aberrant DNA methylation patterns have recurrently been linked to dysregulation of the regulatory program in cancer cells. To shed light on the underlying molecular mechanism driving this process, we hypothesized that aberrant methylation patterns could be controlled by the binding of specific transcription factors (TFs) across cancer types. By combining DNA methylation arrays and gene expression data with TF binding sites (TFBSs), we explored the interplay between TF binding and DNA methylation in 19 cancer cohorts. We performed emQTL (expression-methylation quantitative trait loci) analyses in each cohort and identified 13 TFs whose expression levels are correlated with local DNA methylation patterns around their binding site in at least 2 cancer types. The 13 TFs are mainly associated with local demethylation and are enriched for pioneer function, suggesting a specific role for these TFs in modulating chromatin structure and transcription in cancer patients. Furthermore, we confirmed that &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; methylation is precluded across cancers at CpGs lying in genomic regions enriched for TF-binding signatures associated with SP1, CTCF, NRF1, GABPA, KLF9, and/or YY1. The modulation of DNA methylation associated with TF binding was observed at cis-regulatory regions controlling immune- and cancer-associated pathways, corroborating that the emQTL signals were derived from both cancer and tumour-infiltrating cells. As a case example, we experimentally confirmed that FOXA1 knock-down is associated with higher methylation in regions bound by FOXA1 in breast cancer MCF-7 cells. Finally, we reported physical interactions between FOXA1 with TET1 and TET2 at physiological levels in MCF-7 cells, adding further support for FOXA1 attracting TET1 and TET2 to induce local demethylation in cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443359" rel="alternate" title="Pioneer transcription factors are associated with the modulation of DNA methylation patterns across cancers (35 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443459</id><title>mSWI/SNF interacts with the ribosome and its inhibition/mutations alter translation and sensitize to mTOR/PI3K inhibitors (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.584521+00:00</updated><author><name>Livia Ulicna</name></author><author><name>Samuel C. Kimmey</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Weber</name></author><author><name>Grace M. Allard</name></author><author><name>Sean C. Bedall</name></author><author><name>Gerald R. Crabtree</name></author><author><name>Gregory R. Bean</name></author><author><name>Capucine Van Rechem</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The chromatin remodelers mammalian SWItch/Sucrose Non-Fermentable (mSWI/SNF) subunits are mutated, deleted or amplified in more than 40% of cancers. Understanding their functions in normal cells and the consequences of cancer’s alterations will lead to path toward new targeted therapies. Canonically, mSWI/SNF complexes regulate the structure of chromatin, however they likely have additional functions which could be relevant in carcinogenesis. Here, we highlight the substantial alteration of mSWI/SNF subunits expression in both the nucleus and cytoplasm in breast cancer cases. We demonstrate mSWI/SNF cytoplasmic localization and interaction with the translation initiation machinery. Short-term inhibition and depletion of specific subunits alter protein synthesis, implicating a direct role for these factors in translation. Inhibition and depletion of specific subunits increase sensitivity to mTOR-PI3K inhibitors, suggesting a potential therapeutic opportunity for diseases harboring mutations in these complexes. Indeed, &lt;italic&gt;SMARCA4&lt;/italic&gt; pathogenic mutations decrease protein synthesis. Furthermore, taking advantage of the DepMap studies, we demonstrate cancer cells harboring mutations of specific mSWI/SNF subunits exhibit a genetic dependency on translation factors and are particularly sensitive to translation pathway inhibitors. In conclusion, we report an unexpected cytoplasmic role for mSWI/SNF in protein synthesis, suggesting potential new therapeutic opportunities for patients afflicted by cancers demonstrating alterations in its subunits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study establishes direct functions for mSWI/SNF in protein synthesis. mSWI/SNF inhibition, depletion and cancer mutations alter translation and increase sensitivity to translation pathway inhibitors, illustrating the potential for new therapeutic strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443459" rel="alternate" title="mSWI/SNF interacts with the ribosome and its inhibition/mutations alter translation and sensitize to mTOR/PI3K inhibitors (12 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443157</id><title>O-GlcNAc transferase regulates glioblastoma acetate metabolism via regulation of CDK5-dependent ACSS2 phosphorylation (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.584696+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorela Ciraku</name></author><author><name>Zachary A. Bacigalupa</name></author><author><name>Jing Ju</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Moeller</name></author><author><name>Rusia H. Lee</name></author><author><name>Michael D. Smith</name></author><author><name>Christina M. Ferrer</name></author><author><name>Sophie Trefely</name></author><author><name>Mary T. Doan</name></author><author><name>Wiktoria A. Gocal</name></author><author><name>Luca D’Agostino</name></author><author><name>Wenyin Shi</name></author><author><name>Joshua G. Jackson</name></author><author><name>Christos D. Katsetos</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel W. Snyder</name></author><author><name>Mauricio J. Reginato</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastomas (GBMs) preferentially generate acetyl-CoA from acetate as a fuel source to promote tumor growth. O-GlcNAcylation has been shown to be elevated by increasing O-GlcNAc transferase (OGT) in many cancers and reduced O-GlcNAcylation can block cancer growth. Here, we identify a novel mechanism whereby OGT regulates acetate-dependent acetyl-CoA production by regulating phosphorylation of acetyl-CoA synthetase 2 (ACSS2) by cyclin-dependent kinase 5 (CDK5). OGT is required and sufficient for GBM cell growth and regulates acetate conversion to acetyl-CoA. Elevating O-GlcNAcylation in GBM cells increases phosphorylation of ACSS2 on Ser-267 in a CDK5-dependent manner. Importantly, we show that ACSS2 Ser-267 phosphorylation regulates its stability by reducing polyubiquitination and degradation. ACSS2 Ser-267 is critical for OGT-mediated GBM growth as overexpression of ACSS2 Ser-267 phospho-mimetic rescues growth &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in&lt;/italic&gt; vivo. Importantly, we show that pharmacologically targeting OGT and CDK5 reduces GBM growth &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Thus, the OGT/CDK5/ACSS2 pathway may be a way to target altered metabolic dependencies in brain tumors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443157" rel="alternate" title="O-GlcNAc transferase regulates glioblastoma acetate metabolism via regulation of CDK5-dependent ACSS2 phosphorylation (11 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443334</id><title>Pyruvate kinase M1 suppresses development and progression of prostate adenocarcinoma (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.584977+00:00</updated><author><name>Shawn M. Davidson</name></author><author><name>Julia E. Heyman</name></author><author><name>James P. O’Brien</name></author><author><name>Amy C. Liu</name></author><author><name>Daniel R. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>William J. Israelsen</name></author><author><name>Talya L. Dayton</name></author><author><name>Raghav Sehgal</name></author><author><name>Roderick T. Bronson</name></author><author><name>Elizaveta Freinkman</name></author><author><name>Howard Mak</name></author><author><name>Scott Malstrom</name></author><author><name>Gary Bellinger</name></author><author><name>Arkaitz Carracedo</name></author><author><name>Pier P. Pandolfi</name></author><author><name>Kevin D. Courtney</name></author><author><name>John Frangioni</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Jha</name></author><author><name>Ronald A. DePinho</name></author><author><name>James W. Horner</name></author><author><name>Craig J. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Lewis C. Cantley</name></author><author><name>Massimo Loda</name></author><author><name>Matthew G. Vander Heiden</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most cancers, including prostate cancers, express the M2 splice isoform of pyruvate kinase (&lt;italic&gt;Pkm2&lt;/italic&gt;). This isoform can promote anabolic metabolism to support cell proliferation; however, &lt;italic&gt;Pkm2&lt;/italic&gt; expression is dispensable for many cancers &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Pyruvate kinase M1 (&lt;italic&gt;Pkm1&lt;/italic&gt;) isoform expression is restricted to relatively few tissues and has been reported to promote growth of select tumors, but the role of PKM1 in cancer has been less studied. &lt;italic&gt;Pkm1&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in normal prostate tissue; thus, to test how differential pyruvate kinase isoform expression affects cancer initiation and progression we generated mice harboring a conditional allele of &lt;italic&gt;Pkm1&lt;/italic&gt; and crossed this allele, as well as a &lt;italic&gt;Pkm2&lt;/italic&gt; conditional allele, to a &lt;italic&gt;Pten&lt;/italic&gt; loss-driven prostate cancer model. We found that &lt;italic&gt;Pkm1&lt;/italic&gt; loss leads to Pkm2 expression and accelerates prostate cancer, while deletion of &lt;italic&gt;Pkm2&lt;/italic&gt; leads to increased Pkm1 expression and suppresses cancer. Consistent with these data, a small molecule pyruvate kinase activator that mimics a PKM1-like state suppresses progression of established prostate tumors. PKM2 expression is retained in most human prostate cancers, arguing that pharmacological PKM2 activation may be beneficial for some prostate cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443334" rel="alternate" title="Pyruvate kinase M1 suppresses development and progression of prostate adenocarcinoma (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443282</id><title>Dual G9A and EZH2 inhibition stimulates an anti-tumour immune response in ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.585246+00:00</updated><author><name>Pavlina Spiliopoulou</name></author><author><name>Sarah Spear</name></author><author><name>Hasan Mirza</name></author><author><name>Ian Garner</name></author><author><name>Lynn McGarry</name></author><author><name>Fabio Grundland-Freile</name></author><author><name>Zhao Cheng</name></author><author><name>Darren P. Ennis</name></author><author><name>Sophie McNamara</name></author><author><name>Marina Natoli</name></author><author><name>Susan Mason</name></author><author><name>Karen Blyth</name></author><author><name>Peter D. Adams</name></author><author><name>Patricia Roxburgh</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Fuchter</name></author><author><name>Bob Brown</name></author><author><name>Iain A. McNeish</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (HGSC) prognosis correlates directly with presence of intratumoral lymphocytes. However, cancer immunotherapy has yet to achieve meaningful survival benefit in patients with HGSC. Epigenetic silencing of immunostimulatory genes is implicated in immune evasion in HGSC and re-expression of these genes could promote tumour immune clearance. We discovered that simultaneous inhibition of the histone methyltransferases G9A and EZH2 activates the CXCL10-CXCR3 axis and increases homing of intratumoral effector lymphocytes and natural killer cells whilst suppressing tumour-promoting FoxP3&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; CD4 T cells. The dual G9A/EZH2 inhibitor HKMTI-1-005 induced chromatin changes that resulted in the transcriptional activation of immunostimulatory gene networks, including the re-expression of elements of the ERV-K endogenous retroviral family. Importantly, treatment with HKMTI-1-005 improved the survival of mice bearing &lt;italic&gt;Trp53&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;-/-&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;null ID8 ovarian tumours and resulted in tumour burden reduction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results indicate that inhibiting G9A and EZH2 in ovarian cancer alters the immune microenvironment and reduces tumour growth and therefore positions dual inhibition of G9A/EZH2 as a strategy for clinical development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="443282v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.09.443282" rel="alternate" title="Dual G9A and EZH2 inhibition stimulates an anti-tumour immune response in ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (8 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443250</id><title>Identification of Cancer-Associated Fibroblasts in Glioblastoma and Defining Their Pro-tumoral Effects (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.585467+00:00</updated><author><name>Saket Jain</name></author><author><name>Jonathan W. Rick</name></author><author><name>Rushikesh Joshi</name></author><author><name>Angad Beniwal</name></author><author><name>Jordan Spatz</name></author><author><name>Alexander Chih-Chieh Chang</name></author><author><name>Alan T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Sweta Sudhir</name></author><author><name>Ankush Chandra</name></author><author><name>Alex Haddad</name></author><author><name>Harsh Wadhwa</name></author><author><name>Sumedh S. Shah</name></author><author><name>Serah Choi</name></author><author><name>Josie L. Hayes</name></author><author><name>Lin Wang</name></author><author><name>Garima Yagnik</name></author><author><name>Joseph F. Costello</name></author><author><name>Aaron Diaz</name></author><author><name>Manish K. Aghi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite their identification in some cancers, pro-tumoral cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAFs) were presumed absent in glioblastoma given the lack of brain fibroblasts. Serial trypsinization of primary glioblastoma cultures yielded cells with CAF morphology, CAF transcriptomic profile, and mesenchymal lineage in single-cell RNA-seq. Glioblastoma CAFs were attracted to glioblastoma stem cells (GSCs) and CAFs enriched GSCs. We created a resource of inferred crosstalk by mapping expression of receptors to their cognate ligands, identifying PDGF-β and TGF-β as mediators of GSC effects on CAFs, and osteopontin and hepatocyte growth factor as mediators of CAF-induced GSC enrichment. Glioblastoma CAFs also induced M2 macrophage polarization by producing the EDA fibronectin variant. Glioblastoma CAFs were enriched in the subventricular zone which houses neural stem cells that produce GSCs. Including CAFs in GSC-derived xenografts induced &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; growth. These findings are among the first to identify glioblastoma CAFs and their GSC interactions, making them an intriguing target.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.08.443250" rel="alternate" title="Identification of Cancer-Associated Fibroblasts in Glioblastoma and Defining Their Pro-tumoral Effects (7 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.443092</id><title>The P2RX7B splice variant modulates osteosarcoma cell behaviour and metastatic properties (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-17T12:04:36.585695+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke Tattersall</name></author><author><name>Karan M. Shah</name></author><author><name>Darren L. Lath</name></author><author><name>Archana Singh</name></author><author><name>Jennifer M. Down</name></author><author><name>Elena De Marchi</name></author><author><name>Alex Williamson</name></author><author><name>Francesco Di Virgilio</name></author><author><name>Dominique Heymann</name></author><author><name>Elena Adinolfi</name></author><author><name>William D. Fraser</name></author><author><name>Darrell Green</name></author><author><name>Michelle A. Lawson</name></author><author><name>Alison Gartland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Osteosarcoma (OS) is the most common type of primary bone cancer affecting children and adolescents. OS has a high propensity to spread, meaning the disease is often incurable and fatal. There have been no improvements in survival rates for decades. This highlights an urgent need for development of novel therapeutic strategies. In this study, we have produced &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; data that demonstrates the role of purinergic signalling, specifically, the B isoform of the purinergic receptor P2RX7 (herein termed “ P2RX7B”), in OS progression and metastasis. Our data shows that P2RX7B expression confers a survival advantage in TE85+P2RX7B and MNNG-HOS+ P2RX7B human OS cell lines &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; that is minimised following treatment with A740003, a specific P2RX7 antagonist. P2RX7B expression reduced cell adhesion and P2RX7B activation promoted invasion and migration &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, suggesting a probable metastatic phenotype. Using an &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; OS xenograft model, MNNG-HOS+P2RX7B tumours exhibited ectopic bone formation that was abrogated with A740003 treatment. An increased metastatic phenotype was further demonstrated &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; as expression of P2RX7B in primary tumour cells increased the propensity of the tumour to metastasise to the lungs. RNA-seq identified a novel gene axis, &lt;italic&gt;FN1&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;LOX&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;PDGFB&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;IGFBP3&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;BMP4&lt;/italic&gt;, downregulated in response to A740003 treatment. In conclusion, our data indicates for the first time a role for P2RX7B in OS tumour growth, progression and metastasis. We show that P2RX7B is a potential therapeutic target in human OS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Novelty and Impact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We provide evidence for the pro-tumorigenic role of the B isoform of the P2RX7 purinergic receptor in osteosarcoma (OS). In addition to increasing proliferation, P2RX7B increases the cancerous properties of OS cells, reducing adhesion and increasing migration and invasion. &lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, P2RX7B does not affect primary tumour growth, but does lead to an increased propensity to metastasize. RNA-seq revealed a new axis of oncogenic genes inhibited by the P2RX7 antagonist and this data could potentially lead to new targets for OS treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.07.443092" rel="alternate" title="The P2RX7B splice variant modulates osteosarcoma cell behaviour and metastatic properties (5 tweets)"/><category term="Cancer Biology"/><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>