<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in cancer_biology posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.471758+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/cancer_biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.442252</id><title>Mesenchymal Lineage Heterogeneity Underlies Non-Redundant Functions of Pancreatic Cancer-Associated Fibroblasts (65 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.472166+00:00</updated><author><name>Erin J. Helms</name></author><author><name>Mark W. Berry</name></author><author><name>R. Crystal Chaw</name></author><author><name>Chris C. DuFort</name></author><author><name>Duanchen Sun</name></author><author><name>M. Kathrina Onate</name></author><author><name>Chet Oon</name></author><author><name>Sohinee Bhattacharyya</name></author><author><name>Hannah Sanford-Crane</name></author><author><name>Wesley Horton</name></author><author><name>Jennifer M. Finan</name></author><author><name>Ariana Sattler</name></author><author><name>Rosemary Makar</name></author><author><name>David W. Dawson</name></author><author><name>Zheng Xia</name></author><author><name>Sunil R. Hingorani</name></author><author><name>Mara H. Sherman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer-associated fibroblast (CAF) heterogeneity is increasingly appreciated, but the origins and functions of distinct CAF subtypes remain poorly understood. The abundant and transcriptionally diverse CAF population in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) is thought to arise from a common cell of origin, pancreatic stellate cells (PSCs), with diversification resulting from cytokine and growth factor gradients within the tumor microenvironment. Here we analyzed the differentiation and function of PSCs during tumor progression &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Contrary to expectations, we found that PSCs give rise to a numerically minor subset of PDAC CAFs. Targeted ablation of PSC-derived CAFs within their host tissue revealed non-redundant functions for this defined CAF population in shaping the PDAC microenvironment, including production of specific components of the extracellular matrix. Together, these findings link stromal evolution from distinct cells of origin to transcriptional heterogeneity among PDAC CAFs, and demonstrate unique functions for CAFs of a defined cellular origin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Statement of significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;By tracking and ablating a specific CAF population, we find that a numerically minor CAF subtype from a defined cell of origin plays unique roles in establishing the pancreatic tumor microenvironment. Together with prior studies, this work suggests that mesenchymal lineage heterogeneity as well as signaling gradients diversify PDAC CAFs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>