<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.959249+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467793</id><title>Fast and sensitive GCaMP calcium indicators for imaging neural populations (171 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.959580+00:00</updated><author><name>Yan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Márton Rózsa</name></author><author><name>Yajie Liang</name></author><author><name>Daniel Bushey</name></author><author><name>Ziqiang Wei</name></author><author><name>Jihong Zheng</name></author><author><name>Daniel Reep</name></author><author><name>Gerard Joey Broussard</name></author><author><name>Arthur Tsang</name></author><author><name>Getahun Tsegaye</name></author><author><name>Sujatha Narayan</name></author><author><name>Christopher J. Obara</name></author><author><name>Jing-Xuan Lim</name></author><author><name>Ronak Patel</name></author><author><name>Rongwei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Misha B. Ahrens</name></author><author><name>Glenn C. Turner</name></author><author><name>Samuel S.-H. Wang</name></author><author><name>Wyatt L. Korff</name></author><author><name>Eric R. Schreiter</name></author><author><name>Karel Svoboda</name></author><author><name>Jeremy P. Hasseman</name></author><author><name>Ilya Kolb</name></author><author><name>Loren L. Looger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Calcium imaging with protein-based indicators is widely used to follow neural activity in intact nervous systems. The popular GCaMP indicators are based on the calcium-binding protein calmodulin and the RS20 peptide. These sensors report neural activity at timescales much slower than electrical signaling, limited by their biophysical properties and trade-offs between sensitivity and speed. We used large-scale screening and structure-guided mutagenesis to develop and optimize several fast and sensitive GCaMP-type indicators. The resulting ‘jGCaMP8’ sensors, based on calmodulin and a fragment of endothelial nitric oxide synthase, have ultra-fast kinetics (rise times, 2 ms) and still feature the highest sensitivity for neural activity reported for any protein-based sensor. jGCaMP8 sensors will allow tracking of larger populations of neurons on timescales relevant to neural computation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467793" rel="alternate" title="Fast and sensitive GCaMP calcium indicators for imaging neural populations (171 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467923</id><title>Age-Dependent Formation of TMEM106B Amyloid Filaments in Human Brain (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.959871+00:00</updated><author><name>Manuel Schweighauser</name></author><author><name>Diana Arseni</name></author><author><name>Melissa Huang</name></author><author><name>Sofia Lövestam</name></author><author><name>Yang Shi</name></author><author><name>Yang Yang</name></author><author><name>Wenjuan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Abhay Kotecha</name></author><author><name>Holly J. Garringer</name></author><author><name>Ruben Vidal</name></author><author><name>Grace I. Hallinan</name></author><author><name>Kathy L. Newell</name></author><author><name>Airi Tarutani</name></author><author><name>Shigeo Murayama</name></author><author><name>Masayuki Miyazaki</name></author><author><name>Yuko Saito</name></author><author><name>Mari Yoshida</name></author><author><name>Kazuko Hasegawa</name></author><author><name>Tammaryn Lashley</name></author><author><name>Tamas Revesz</name></author><author><name>Gabor G. Kovacs</name></author><author><name>John van Swieten</name></author><author><name>Masaki Takao</name></author><author><name>Masato Hasegawa</name></author><author><name>Bernardino Ghetti</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Falcon</name></author><author><name>Alexey G. Murzin</name></author><author><name>Michel Goedert</name></author><author><name>Sjors H.W. Scheres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many age-dependent neurodegenerative diseases, like Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s, are characterised by abundant inclusions of amyloid filaments. Filamentous inclusions of the proteins tau, amyloid-β (Aβ), α-synuclein and TDP-43 are the most common. Here, we used electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM) structure determination to show that residues 120-254 of the lysosomal type II transmembrane protein 106B (TMEM106B) also form amyloid filaments in the human brain. We solved cryo-EM structures of TMEM106B filaments from the brains of 22 individuals with neurodegenerative conditions, including sporadic and inherited tauopathies, Aβ-amyloidoses, synucleinopathies and TDP-43opathies, as well as from the brains of two neurologically normal individuals. We observed three different TMEM106B folds, with no clear relationship between folds and diseases. The presence of TMEM106B filaments correlated with that of a 29 kDa sarkosyl-insoluble fragment of the protein on Western blots. The presence of TMEM106B filaments in the brains of older, but not younger, neurologically normal individuals indicates that they form in an age-dependent manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467923" rel="alternate" title="Age-Dependent Formation of TMEM106B Amyloid Filaments in Human Brain (43 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467566</id><title>Beyond Fixation: detailed characterization of neural selectivity in free-viewing primates (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.960142+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob L. Yates</name></author><author><name>Shanna H. Coop</name></author><author><name>Gabriel H. Sarch</name></author><author><name>Ruei-Jr Wu</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Butts</name></author><author><name>Michele Rucci</name></author><author><name>Jude F. Mitchell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virtually all vision studies use a fixation point to stabilize gaze, rendering stimuli on video screens fixed to retinal coordinates. This approach requires trained subjects, is limited by the accuracy of fixational eye movements, and ignores the role of eye movements in shaping visual input. To overcome these limitations, we developed a suite of hardware and software tools to study vision during natural behavior in untrained subjects. We show this approach recovers receptive fields and tuning properties of visual neurons from multiple cortical areas of marmoset monkeys. Combined with high-precision eye-tracking, it achieves sufficient resolution to recover the receptive fields of foveal V1 neurons. These findings demonstrate the power of free viewing to characterize neural response while simultaneously studying the dynamics of natural behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce a free-viewing paradigm for studying neural mechanisms of visual processing during active vision&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Receptive fields (RFs) and neural selectivity in primary visual cortex (V1) and area MT can be extracted during free-viewing in minimally-trained subjects&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Novel high-resolution eye tracking in this context supports detailed measurements of receptive fields in foveal V1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467566" rel="alternate" title="Beyond Fixation: detailed characterization of neural selectivity in free-viewing primates (31 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468408</id><title>Maternal diet disrupts the placenta-brain axis in a sex-specific manner (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.960478+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexis M Ceasrine</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A Devlin</name></author><author><name>Jessica L Bolton</name></author><author><name>Young Chan Jo</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Huynh</name></author><author><name>Bailey Patrick</name></author><author><name>Kamryn Washington</name></author><author><name>Faith Joo</name></author><author><name>A. Brayan Campos-Salazar</name></author><author><name>Elana R. Lockshin</name></author><author><name>Susan K Murphy</name></author><author><name>Leigh Ann Simmons</name></author><author><name>Staci D Bilbo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High maternal weight is associated with a number of detrimental outcomes in offspring, including increased susceptibility to neurological disorders such as anxiety, depression, and communicative disorders (e.g. autism spectrum disorders). Despite widespread acknowledgement of sex-biases in the prevalence, incidence, and age of onset of these disorders, few studies have investigated potential sex-biased mechanisms underlying disorder susceptibility. Here, we use a mouse model to demonstrate how maternal high-fat diet causes perinatal inflammation that influences sex-specific behavioral outcomes in offspring. In male high-fat diet offspring, increased macrophage toll like receptor 4 signaling results in excess phagocytosis of serotonin neurons in the developing dorsal raphe nucleus, decreasing serotonin bioavailability in the fetal and adult brain. Bulk sequencing from a large cohort of matched first trimester human fetal brain, placenta, and maternal decidua samples reveals sex-specific transcriptome-wide changes in placenta and brain tissue. Further, we find that fetal brain serotonin is significantly negatively correlated with maternal triglyceride accumulation (a proxy for dietary fat content) in male pregnancies only. These findings uncover a fundamental mechanism through which maternal diet may increase offspring susceptibility for neuropsychiatric disorder development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468408" rel="alternate" title="Maternal diet disrupts the placenta-brain axis in a sex-specific manner (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.467812</id><title>'Constituent length' effects in fMRI do not provide evidence for abstract syntactic processing (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.960666+00:00</updated><author><name>Cory Shain</name></author><author><name>Hope Kean</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Lipkin</name></author><author><name>Josef Affourtit</name></author><author><name>Matthew Siegelman</name></author><author><name>Francis Mollica</name></author><author><name>Evelina Fedorenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How are syntactically and semantically connected word sequences, or constituents, represented in the human language system? An influential fMRI study, Pallier et al. (2011, PNAS), manipulated the length of constituents in sequences of words or pseudowords. They reported that some language regions (in the anterior temporal cortex and near the temporo-parietal junction) were sensitive to constituent length only for sequences of real words but not pseudowords. In contrast, language regions in the inferior frontal and posterior temporal cortex showed the same pattern of increased response to longer constituents - and similar overall response magnitudes - for word and pseudoword sequences. Based on these results, Pallier et al. argued that the latter regions represent abstract sentence structure. Here we identify methodological and theoretical concerns with the Pallier et al. study and conduct a replication across two fMRI experiments. Our results do not support Pallier et al.'s critical claim of distinct neural specialization for abstract syntactic representations. Instead, we find that all language regions show a similar profile of sensitivity to both constituent length and lexicality (stronger responses to real-word than pseudoword stimuli). In addition, we argue that the constituent length effect in these experiments i) is not readily grounded in established theories of sentence processing, and ii) may not actually derive from syntactic structure building, but may instead reflect the temporal receptive window of the human language system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.467812" rel="alternate" title="'Constituent length' effects in fMRI do not provide evidence for abstract syntactic processing (28 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468033</id><title>Functional but not obligatory link between microsaccades and neural modulation by covert spatial attention (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.960811+00:00</updated><author><name>Baiwei Liu</name></author><author><name>Anna C. Nobre</name></author><author><name>Freek van Ede</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Covert spatial attention is associated with spatially specific modulation of neural activity as well as with directional biases in fixational eye-movements known as microsaccades. Recently, this link has been suggested to be obligatory, such that modulation of neural activity by covert spatial attention occurs &lt;italic&gt;only&lt;/italic&gt; when paired with microsaccades toward the attended location. Here we revisited this link between microsaccades and neural modulation by covert spatial attention in humans. We investigated spatial modulation of 8-12 Hz EEG alpha activity and microsaccades in a context with no incentive for overt gaze behaviour: when attention is directed internally within the spatial layout of visual working memory. In line with a common attentional origin, we show that spatial modulations of alpha activity and microsaccades co-vary: alpha lateralisation is stronger in trials with microsaccades toward compared to away from the memorised location of the to-be-attended item and occurs earlier in trials with earlier microsaccades toward this item. Critically, however, trials without attention-driven microsaccades nevertheless showed clear spatial modulation of alpha activity – comparable to the neural modulation observed in trials with attention-driven microsaccades. Thus, directional biases in microsaccades are correlated with neural signatures of covert spatial attention, but they are not a prerequisite for neural modulation by covert spatial attention to be manifest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468033" rel="alternate" title="Functional but not obligatory link between microsaccades and neural modulation by covert spatial attention (27 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467979</id><title>Contribution of linear and nonlinear mechanisms to predictive motion estimation (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.960929+00:00</updated><author><name>Belle Liu</name></author><author><name>Arthur Hong</name></author><author><name>Fred Rieke</name></author><author><name>Michael B. Manookin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Successful behavior relies on the ability to use information obtained from past experience to predict what is likely to occur in the future. A salient example of predictive encoding comes from the vertebrate retina, where neural circuits encode information that can be used to estimate the trajectory of a moving object. Predictive computations should be a general property of sensory systems, but the features needed to identify these computations across neural systems are not well understood. Here, we identify several properties of predictive computations in the primate retina that likely generalize across sensory systems. These features include calculating the derivative of incoming signals, sparse signal integration, and delayed response suppression. These findings provide a deeper understanding of how the brain carries out predictive computations and identify features that can be used to recognize these computations throughout the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467979" rel="alternate" title="Contribution of linear and nonlinear mechanisms to predictive motion estimation (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467756</id><title>Inversely proportional myelin growth due to altered Pmp22 gene dosage identifies PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling as a novel therapeutic target in HNPP (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.961051+00:00</updated><author><name>Doris Krauter</name></author><author><name>David Ewers</name></author><author><name>Timon J Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Stefan Volkmann</name></author><author><name>Theresa Kungl</name></author><author><name>Robert Fledrich</name></author><author><name>Sandra Goebbels</name></author><author><name>Klaus-Armin Nave</name></author><author><name>Michael W Sereda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Duplication of the gene encoding the myelin protein PMP22 causes the hereditary neuropathy Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease 1A (CMT1A), characterized by hypomyelination of medium to large caliber peripheral axons. Conversely, haplo-insufficiency of &lt;italic&gt;PMP22&lt;/italic&gt; leads to focal myelin overgrowth in hereditary neuropathy with liability to pressure palsies (HNPP). However, the molecular mechanisms of myelin growth regulation by PMP22 remain obscure. Here, we found that the major inhibitor of the myelin growth signaling pathway PI3K/Akt/mTOR, phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN) is increased in abundance in CMT1A and decreased in HNPP rodent models. Indeed, treatment of DRG co-cultures from HNPP mice with PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathway inhibitors reduced focal hypermyelination and, importantly, treatment of HNPP mice with the mTOR inhibitor Rapamycin improved motor behavior, increased compound muscle amplitudes (CMAP) and reduced tomacula formation in the peripheral nerve. In &lt;italic&gt;Pmp22&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;tg&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; CMT1A mice, we uncovered that the differentiation defect of Schwann cells is independent from PI3K/Akt/mTOR activity, rendering the pathway insufficient as a therapy target on its own. Thus, while CMT1A pathogenesis is governed by dys-differentiation uncoupled from PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling, targeting the pathway provides novel proof-of-principle for a therapeutic approach to HNPP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467756" rel="alternate" title="Inversely proportional myelin growth due to altered Pmp22 gene dosage identifies PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling as a novel therapeutic target in HNPP (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468058</id><title>An essential role for a discrete parasubthalamic nucleus subpopulation in appetite suppression (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.961200+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica H. Kim</name></author><author><name>Grace H. Kromm</name></author><author><name>Olivia K. Barnhill</name></author><author><name>Kenneth Han</name></author><author><name>Lauren B. Heuer</name></author><author><name>Sierra Loomis</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Newman</name></author><author><name>Jacob Sperber</name></author><author><name>Theresa B. Legan</name></author><author><name>Faris F. Gulamali</name></author><author><name>Katharine E. Jensen</name></author><author><name>Samuel C. Funderburk</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Krashes</name></author><author><name>Matthew E. Carter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Food intake behavior is regulated by a network of appetite-inducing and appetite-suppressing neuronal populations throughout the brain. The parasubthalamic nucleus (PSTN), a relatively unexplored population of neurons in the posterior hypothalamus, has been hypothesized to regulate appetite due to its connectivity with other anorexigenic neuronal populations and because these neurons express Fos, a marker of neuronal activation, following a meal. However, the individual cell types that make up the PSTN are not well characterized, nor are their functional roles in food intake behavior. Here we identify and distinguish between two discrete PSTN subpopulations, those that express tachykinin-1 (PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt; neurons) and those that express corticotropin-releasing hormone (PSTN&lt;sup&gt;CRH&lt;/sup&gt; neurons), and use a panel of genetically encoded tools in mice to show that PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt; neurons play an essential role in appetite suppression. Both subpopulations increase activity following a meal and in response to administration of the anorexigenic hormones amylin, cholecystokinin (CCK), and peptide YY (PYY). Interestingly, chemogenetic inhibition of PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt;, but not PSTN&lt;sup&gt;CRH&lt;/sup&gt; neurons, reduces the appetite-suppressing effects of these hormones. Consistently, optogenetic and chemogenetic stimulation of PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt; neurons, but not PSTN&lt;sup&gt;CRH&lt;/sup&gt; neurons, is sufficient to reduce food intake in hungry mice. PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt; and PSTN&lt;sup&gt;CRH&lt;/sup&gt; neurons project to distinct downstream brain regions, and stimulation of PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt; projections to individual anorexigenic populations reduces food consumption. Taken together, these results reveal the functional properties and projection patterns of distinct PSTN cell types and demonstrate an essential, anorexigenic role for PSTN&lt;sup&gt;Tac1&lt;/sup&gt; neurons in the hormonal and central regulation of appetite.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468058" rel="alternate" title="An essential role for a discrete parasubthalamic nucleus subpopulation in appetite suppression (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468144</id><title>Learning enhances behaviorally relevant representations in apical dendrites (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.961376+00:00</updated><author><name>Sam E. Benezra</name></author><author><name>Kripa B. Patel</name></author><author><name>Citlali Pérez Campos</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M.C. Hillman</name></author><author><name>Randy M. Bruno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Learning alters cortical representations and improves perception. Apical tuft dendrites in Layer 1, which are unique in their connectivity and biophysical properties, may be a key site of learning-induced plasticity. We used both two-photon and SCAPE microscopy to longitudinally track tuft-wide calcium spikes in apical dendrites of Layer 5 pyramidal neurons as mice learned a tactile behavior. Mice were trained to discriminate two orthogonal directions of whisker stimulation. Reinforcement learning, but not repeated stimulus exposure, enhanced tuft selectivity for both directions equally, even though only one was associated with reward. Selective tufts emerged from initially unresponsive or low-selectivity populations. Animal movement and choice did not account for changes in stimulus selectivity. Enhanced selectivity persisted even after rewards were removed and animals ceased performing the task. We conclude that learning produces long-lasting realignment of apical dendrite tuft responses to behaviorally relevant dimensions of a task.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468144" rel="alternate" title="Learning enhances behaviorally relevant representations in apical dendrites (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467564</id><title>Brain Networks Detectable by fMRI during On-Line Self Report of Hallucinations in Schizophrenia (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.961503+00:00</updated><author><name>Karanvir Gill</name></author><author><name>Chantal Percival</name></author><author><name>Meighen Roes</name></author><author><name>Leo Arreaza</name></author><author><name>Abhijit Chinchani</name></author><author><name>Nicole Sanford</name></author><author><name>Walter Sena</name></author><author><name>Homa Mohammadsadeghi</name></author><author><name>Mahesh Menon</name></author><author><name>Matthew Hughes</name></author><author><name>Sean Carruthers</name></author><author><name>Philip Sumner</name></author><author><name>Will Woods</name></author><author><name>Renaud Jardri</name></author><author><name>Iris E. Sommer</name></author><author><name>Susan L. Rossell</name></author><author><name>Todd S. Woodward</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An analysis of an internationally shared functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) data involving healthy participants and schizophrenia patients extracted brain networks involved in listening to radio speech and capture hallucination experiences. A multidimensional analysis technique demonstrated that for radio-speech sound files, a brain network matching known auditory perception networks emerged, and importantly, displayed speech-duration-dependent hemodynamic responses (HDRs), confirming fMRI detection of these speech events. In the hallucination-capture data, although a sensorimotor (response) network emerged, it did not show hallucination-duration-dependent HDRs. We conclude that although fMRI retrieved the brain network involved in generating the motor responses indicating the start and end of an experienced hallucination, the hallucination event itself was not detected. Previous reports on brain networks detected by fMRI during hallucination capture is reviewed in this context.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.06.467564" rel="alternate" title="Brain Networks Detectable by fMRI during On-Line Self Report of Hallucinations in Schizophrenia (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468356</id><title>Fluorescent and bioluminescent calcium indicators with tuneable colors and affinities (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.961695+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole Mertes</name></author><author><name>Marvin Busch</name></author><author><name>Magnus-Carsten Huppertz</name></author><author><name>Christina Nicole Hacker</name></author><author><name>Clara-Marie Guerth</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Kuehn</name></author><author><name>Julien Hiblot</name></author><author><name>Birgit Koch</name></author><author><name>Kai Johnsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We introduce a family of bright, rhodamine-based calcium indicators with tuneable affinities and colors. The indicators can be specifically localized to different cellular compartments and are compatible with both fluorescence and bioluminescence readouts through conjugation to HaloTag fusion proteins. Importantly, their increase in fluorescence upon localization enables no-wash live-cell imaging, which greatly facilitates their use in biological assays. Applications as fluorescent indicators in rat hippocampal neurons include the detection of single action potentials and of calcium fluxes in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). Applications as bioluminescent indicators include the recording of the pharmacological modulation of nuclear calcium in high-throughput-compatible assays. The versatility and remarkable ease of use of these indicators make them powerful tools for bioimaging and bioassays.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468356" rel="alternate" title="Fluorescent and bioluminescent calcium indicators with tuneable colors and affinities (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468379</id><title>Age-linked suppression of lipoxin A4 mediates cognitive deficits in mice and humans (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.961843+00:00</updated><author><name>Fabrício A. Pamplona</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Vitória</name></author><author><name>Felipe C. Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Carolina A. Moraes</name></author><author><name>Pitia F. Ledur</name></author><author><name>Karina Karmirian</name></author><author><name>Isis M. Ornelas</name></author><author><name>Luciana M. Leo</name></author><author><name>Bruna Paulsen</name></author><author><name>Felipe K. Sudo</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Coutinho</name></author><author><name>Claudia Drummond</name></author><author><name>Naima Assunção</name></author><author><name>Bart Vanderborght</name></author><author><name>Claudio Canetti</name></author><author><name>Hugo C. Castro-Faria-Neto</name></author><author><name>Paulo Mattos</name></author><author><name>Sergio T. Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Stevens K. Rehen</name></author><author><name>Fernando A. Bozza</name></author><author><name>Mychael V. Lourenco</name></author><author><name>Fernanda Tovar-Moll</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Age increases the risk for cognitive impairment and is the single major risk factor for Alzheimer's disease (AD), the most prevalent form of dementia in the elderly. The pathophysiological processes triggered by aging that render the brain vulnerable to dementia involve, at least in part, changes in inflammatory mediators. Here we show that lipoxin A4 (LXA4), a lipid mediator of inflammation resolution known to stimulate endocannabinoid signaling in the brain, is reduced in the aging central nervous system. We demonstrate that genetic suppression of 5-lipoxygenase (5-LOX), the enzyme mediating LXA4 synthesis, promotes learning impairment in mice. Conversely, administration of exogenous LXA4 attenuated cytokine production and memory loss induced by inflammation in mice. We further show that cerebrospinal fluid LXA4 is reduced in patients with dementia and positively associates with memory performance, brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), and AD-linked amyloid-β. Our findings suggest that reduced LXA4 levels may lead to vulnerability to age-related cognitive disorders and that promoting LXA4 signaling may comprise an effective strategy to prevent early cognitive decline in AD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468379" rel="alternate" title="Age-linked suppression of lipoxin A4 mediates cognitive deficits in mice and humans (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468353</id><title>Reliable population utility signal from diverse economic value coding in orbitofrontal neurons (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.962365+00:00</updated><author><name>Simone Ferrari-Toniolo</name></author><author><name>Wolfram Schultz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Economic value encapsulates the subjective combination of reward magnitude and probability. We investigated the mechanism for subjective value computation in single neurons using an economic axiomatic approach. We found that single neurons in the macaque orbitofrontal cortex, known to be sensitive to reward magnitude and probability, encode the economic value functions (utility and probability weighting) in a heterogeneous manner, such that the activity of individual neurons did not match the animal's choices. However, the utility and probability weighting code from a population of these varied neurons reliably matched the animals' choices and risk attitudes. Thus, the neuronal population code for economic value amounted to a distributional representation of the formal economic functions. With a diverse single-unit economic value code converging into a reliable population-level utility code, this scheme suggests a brain mechanism for the flexible accommodation of multiple choice patterns and risk attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468353" rel="alternate" title="Reliable population utility signal from diverse economic value coding in orbitofrontal neurons (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468101</id><title>Biophysical and Architectural Mechanisms of Subthalamic Theta under Response Conflict (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.962504+00:00</updated><author><name>Prannath Moolchand</name></author><author><name>Stephanie R. Jones</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Frank</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cortico-basal ganglia circuit is needed to suppress prepotent actions and to facilitate controlled behavior. Under conditions of response conflict, the frontal cortex and subthalamic nucleus [STN] exhibit increased spiking and theta band power, which are linked to adaptive regulation of behavioral output. The electrophysiological mechanisms underlying these neural signatures of impulse control remain poorly understood. To address this lacuna, we constructed a novel large-scale, biophysically principled model of the subthalamopallidal [STN-Globus Pallidus externus (GPe)] network, and examined the mechanisms that modulate theta power and spiking in response to cortical input. Simulations confirmed that theta power does not emerge from intrinsic network dynamics but is robustly elicited in response to cortical input as burst events representing action selection dynamics. Rhythmic burst events of multiple cortical populations, representing a state of conflict where cortical motor plans vacillate in the theta range, led to prolonged STN theta and increased spiking, consistent with empirical literature. Notably, theta band signaling required NMDA, but not AMPA, currents, which were in turn related to a triphasic STN response characterized by spiking, silence and bursting periods. Finally, theta band resonance was also strongly modulated by architectural connectivity, with maximal theta arising when multiple cortical populations project to individual STN “conflict detector” units, due to an NMDA-dependent supralinear response. Our results provide insights into the biophysical principles and architectural constraints that give rise to STN dynamics during response conflict, and how their disruption can lead to impulsivity and compulsivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468101" rel="alternate" title="Biophysical and Architectural Mechanisms of Subthalamic Theta under Response Conflict (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468098</id><title>IFN-γ stimulated murine and human neurons mount anti-parasitic defenses against the intracellular parasite Toxoplasma gondii (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.962666+00:00</updated><author><name>Sambamurthy Chandrasekaran</name></author><author><name>Joshua A. Kochanowsky</name></author><author><name>Emily F. Merritt</name></author><author><name>Anita A. Koshy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dogma holds that &lt;italic&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/italic&gt; persists in neurons because neurons cannot clear intracellular parasites, even with IFN-γ stimulation. As several recent studies questioned this idea, we used primary murine neuronal cultures from wild-type and transgenic mice in combination with IFN-γ stimulation and parental and transgenic parasites to reassess IFN-γ dependent neuronal clearance of intracellular parasites. We found that neurons respond to IFN-γ and that a subset of neurons clear intracellular parasites via immunity regulated GTPases. Whole neuron reconstructions from mice infected with parasites that trigger neuron GFP expression only after full invasion revealed that ∼40% of these &lt;italic&gt;T. gondii&lt;/italic&gt;-invaded neurons no longer harbor parasites. Finally, IFN-γ stimulated human stem cell derived neurons showed a ∼ 50% decrease in parasite infection rate when compared to unstimulated cultures. This work highlights the capability of human and murine neurons to mount cytokine-dependent anti-&lt;italic&gt;T. gondii&lt;/italic&gt; defense mechanisms &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468098" rel="alternate" title="IFN-γ stimulated murine and human neurons mount anti-parasitic defenses against the intracellular parasite Toxoplasma gondii (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468053</id><title>An Infant Sleep Electroencephalographic Marker of Thalamocortical Connectivity Predicts Behavioral Outcome in Late Infancy (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.962923+00:00</updated><author><name>Valeria Jaramillo</name></author><author><name>Sarah F. Schoch</name></author><author><name>Andjela Markovic</name></author><author><name>Malcolm Kohler</name></author><author><name>Reto Huber</name></author><author><name>Caroline Lustenberger</name></author><author><name>Salome Kurth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Infancy represents a critical period during which thalamocortical brain connections develop and mature. Deviations in the maturation of thalamocortical connectivity are linked to neurodevelopmental disorders. There is a lack of early biomarkers to detect and localize neuromaturational deviations, which can be overcome with mapping through high-density electroencephalography (hdEEG) assessed in sleep. Specifically, slow waves and spindles in non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep are generated by the thalamocortical system, and their characteristics, slow wave slope and spindle density, are closely related to neuroplasticity and learning. Recent studies further suggest that information processing during sleep underlying sleep-dependent learning is promoted by the temporal coupling of slow waves and spindles, yet slow wave-spindle coupling remains unexplored in infancy. Thus, we evaluated three potential biomarkers: 1) slow wave slope, 2) spindle density, and 3) the temporal coupling of slow waves with spindles. We use hdEEG to first examine the occurrence and spatial distribution of these three EEG features in healthy infants and second to evaluate a predictive relationship with later behavioral outcomes. We report four key findings: First, infants’ EEG features appear locally: slow wave slope is maximal in occipital and frontal areas, whereas spindle density is most pronounced frontocentrally. Second, slow waves and spindles are temporally coupled in infancy, with maximal coupling strength in the occipital areas of the brain. Third, slow wave slope, spindle density, and slow wave-spindle coupling are not associated with concurrent behavioral status (6 months). Fourth, spindle density in central and frontocentral regions at age 6 months predicts later behavioral outcomes at 12 and 24 months. Neither slow wave slope nor slow wave-spindle coupling predict behavioral development. Our results propose spindle density as an early EEG biomarker for identifying thalamocortical maturation, which can potentially be used for early diagnosis of neurodevelopmental disorders in infants. These findings are complemented by our companion paper that demonstrates the linkage of spindle density to infant nighttime movement, framing the possible role of spindles in sensorimotor microcircuitry development. Together, our studies suggest that early sleep habits, thalamocortical maturation, and behavioral outcome are closely interwoven. A crucial next step will be to evaluate whether early therapeutic interventions may be effective to reverse deviations in identified individuals at risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow waves and spindles occur in a temporally coupled manner in infancy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow wave slope, spindle density, and slow wave-spindle coupling are not related to concurrent behavioral development&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spindle density at 6 months predicts behavioral status at 12 and 24 months&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow wave slope and slow wave-spindle coupling are not predictive of behavioral development&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468053" rel="alternate" title="An Infant Sleep Electroencephalographic Marker of Thalamocortical Connectivity Predicts Behavioral Outcome in Late Infancy (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468398</id><title>ORYX-MRSI: A Fully-Automated Open-Source Software for Three-Dimensional Proton Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopic Imaging Data Analysis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.963177+00:00</updated><author><name>Sevim Cengiz</name></author><author><name>Muhammed Yildirim</name></author><author><name>Abdullah Bas</name></author><author><name>Esin Ozturk-Isik</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proton magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging (1H-MRSI) provides noninvasive evaluation of brain metabolism. However, there are some limitations of 1H-MRSI preventing its wider use in the clinics, including the spectral quality issues, partial volume effect and chemical shift artifact. Additionally, it is necessary to create metabolite maps for analyzing spectral data along with other MRI modalities. In this study, a MATLAB-based open-source data analysis software for 3D 1H-MRSI, called Oryx-MRSI, which includes modules for visualization of raw 1H-MRSI data and LCModel outputs, chemical shift correction, tissue fraction calculation, metabolite map production, and registration onto standard MNI152 brain atlas while providing automatic spectral quality control, is presented. Oryx-MRSI implements region of interest analysis at brain parcellations defined on MNI152 brain atlas. All generated metabolite maps are stored in NIfTI format. Oryx-MRSI is publicly available at https://github.com/sevimcengiz/Oryx-MRSI along with six example datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468398" rel="alternate" title="ORYX-MRSI: A Fully-Automated Open-Source Software for Three-Dimensional Proton Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopic Imaging Data Analysis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467941</id><title>Heterogeneous CaMKII-dependent synaptic compensations in CA1 pyramidal neurons from acute slices with dissected CA3 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.963398+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Vergara</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Pino</name></author><author><name>Jorge Vera</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Sanhueza</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prolonged changes in neural activity trigger homeostatic synaptic plasticity (HSP) allowing neuronal networks to operate in functional ranges. Cell-wide or input-specific adaptations can be induced by pharmacological or genetic manipulations of activity, and by sensory deprivation. Reactive functional changes caused by deafferentation may partially share mechanisms with HSP. Acute hippocampal slices constitute a suitable model to investigate relatively rapid (hours) pathway-specific modifications occurring after denervation and explore the underlying mechanisms. As Schaffer collaterals constitute a major glutamatergic input to CA1 pyramidal neurons, we conducted whole-cell recordings of miniature excitatory postsynaptic currents (mEPSCs) to evaluate changes over 12 hours after slice preparation and CA3 dissection. We observed an increment in mEPSCs amplitude and a decrease in decay time, suggesting synaptic AMPA receptor upregulation and subunit content modifications. Sorting mEPSC by rise time, a correlate of synapse location along dendrites, revealed amplitude raises at two separate domains. A specific frequency increase was observed in the same domains and was accompanied by a global, unspecific raise. Amplitude and frequency increments were lower at sites initially more active, consistent with local compensatory processes. Transient preincubation with a specific Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;/calmodulin-dependent kinase II (CaMKII) inhibitor either blocked or occluded amplitude and frequency upregulation in different synapse populations. Results are consistent with the concurrent development of different known CaMKII-dependent HSP processes. Our observations support that deafferentation causes rapid and diverse compensations resembling classical slow forms of adaptation to inactivity. These results may contribute to understand fast-developing homeostatic or pathological events after brain injury.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467941" rel="alternate" title="Heterogeneous CaMKII-dependent synaptic compensations in CA1 pyramidal neurons from acute slices with dissected CA3 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468414</id><title>The dorsal visual pathway represents object-centered spatial relations for object recognition (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.963528+00:00</updated><author><name>Vladislav Ayzenberg</name></author><author><name>Marlene Behrmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although there is mounting evidence that input from the dorsal visual pathway is crucial for object processes in the ventral pathway, the specific functional contributions of dorsal cortex to these processes remains poorly understood. Here, we hypothesized that dorsal cortex computes the spatial relations among an object's parts — a processes crucial for forming global shape percepts — and transmits this information to the ventral pathway to support object categorization. Using multiple functional localizers, we discovered regions in the intraparietal sulcus (IPS) that were selectively involved in computing object-centered part relations. These regions exhibited task-dependent functional connectivity with ventral cortex, and were distinct from other dorsal regions, such as those representing allocentric relations, 3D shape, and tools. In a subsequent experiment, we found that the multivariate response of posterior IPS, defined on the basis of part-relations, could be used to decode object category at levels comparable to ventral object regions. Moreover, mediation and multivariate connectivity analyses further suggested that IPS may account for representations of part relations in the ventral pathway. Together, our results highlight specific contributions of the dorsal visual pathway to object recognition. We suggest that dorsal cortex is a crucial source of input to the ventral pathway and may support the ability to categorize objects on the basis of global shape.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468414" rel="alternate" title="The dorsal visual pathway represents object-centered spatial relations for object recognition (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467738</id><title>Paradoxical excitation of lateral habenula neurons by propofol involves enhanced presynaptic release of glutamate (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.963644+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan David Shepard</name></author><author><name>Kunwei Wu</name></author><author><name>Wei Lu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep is a fundamental physiological process conserved across most species. As such, deficits in sleep can result in a myriad of psychological and physical health issues. However, the mechanisms underlying the induction of sleep are relatively unknown. Interestingly, general anesthetics cause unconsciousness by positively modulating GABA-A receptors (GABA&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;Rs). Based on this observation, it is hypothesized that GABA&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;Rs play a critical role in modulating circuits involved in sleep to promote unconsciousness. Recently, the lateral habenula (LHb) has been demonstrated to play a role in sleep physiology and sedation. Specifically, propofol has been shown to excite LHb neurons to promote sedation. However, the mechanism by which this occurs is unknown. Here, we utilize whole-cell voltage and current clamp recordings from LHb neurons obtained from 8-10 week old male mice to determine the physiological mechanisms for this phenomenon. We show that bath application of 1.5μM propofol is sufficient to increase LHb neuronal excitability involving synaptic transmission, but not through modulation of intrinsic properties. Additionally, although there is increased LHb neuronal excitability, GABA&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;Rs localized postsynaptically on LHb neurons are still responsive to propofol, as indicated by an increase in the decay time. Lastly, we find that propofol increases the synaptic drive onto LHb neurons involving enhanced presynaptic release of both glutamate and GABA. However, the greatest contributor to the potentiated synaptic drive is the increased release of glutamate which shifts the balance of synaptic transmission towards greater excitation. Taken together, this study is the first to identify the physiological basis for why LHb neurons are excited by propofol, rather than inhibited, and as a result promote sedation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467738" rel="alternate" title="Paradoxical excitation of lateral habenula neurons by propofol involves enhanced presynaptic release of glutamate (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468076</id><title>Similarities Between Somatosensory Cortical Responses Induced via Natural Touch and Microstimulation in the Ventral Posterior Lateral Thalamus in Macaques (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.963761+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thachil Francis</name></author><author><name>Anna Rozenboym</name></author><author><name>Lee von Kraus</name></author><author><name>Shaohua Xu</name></author><author><name>Pratik Chhatbar</name></author><author><name>Mulugeta Semework</name></author><author><name>Emerson Hawley</name></author><author><name>John Chapin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lost sensations, such as touch, could be restored by microstimulation (MiSt) along the sensory neural substrate. Such neuroprosthetic sensory information can be used as feedback from an invasive brain-machine interface (BMI) to control a robotic arm/hand, such that tactile and proprioceptive feedback from the sensorized robotic arm/hand is directly given to the BMI user. Microstimulation in the human somatosensory thalamus (Vc) has been shown to produce somatosensory perceptions. However, until recently, systematic methods for using thalamic stimulation to evoke naturalistic touch perceptions were lacking. We have recently presented rigorous methods for determining a mapping between ventral posterior lateral thalamus (VPL) MiSt, and neural responses in the somatosensory cortex (S1), in a rodent model (Choi et al., 2016; Choi and Francis, 2018). Our technique minimizes the difference between S1 neural responses induced by natural sensory stimuli and those generated via VPL MiSt. Our goal is to develop systems that know what MiSt will produce a given neural response and possibly a more natural “sensation.” To date, our optimization has been conducted in the rodent model and simulations. Here we present data from simple non-optimized thalamic MiSt during peri-operative experiments, where we MiSt in the VPL of macaques with a somatosensory system more like humans. We implanted arrays of microelectrodes across the hand area of the macaque S1 cortex as well as in the VPL thalamus. Multi and single-unit recordings were used to compare cortical responses to natural touch and thalamic MiSt in the anesthetized state. Post stimulus time histograms were highly correlated between the VPL MiSt and natural touch modalities, adding support to the use of VPL MiSt towards producing a somatosensory neuroprosthesis in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468076" rel="alternate" title="Similarities Between Somatosensory Cortical Responses Induced via Natural Touch and Microstimulation in the Ventral Posterior Lateral Thalamus in Macaques (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468062</id><title>Sequence learning attenuates cortical responses in both frontal and perceptual cortices in early infancy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.963906+00:00</updated><author><name>Sagi Jaffe-Dax</name></author><author><name>Anna Herbolzheimer</name></author><author><name>Vikranth Rao Bejjanki</name></author><author><name>Lauren L. Emberson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prior work has found that the frontal lobe is involved in higher-order sequential and statistical learning in young infants. Separate lines of work have found evidence of modulation of posterior sensory cortices during and after learning tasks. How do these processes relate? Here, we build evidence the infant frontal lobe was modulated during sequential learning and ask whether posterior perceptual cortices show corresponding modulation. First, replicating and extending past work, we found evidence of frontal lobe involvement in this task. Second, consistent with our hypotheses, we found that there is a corresponding attenuation of neural responses in the posterior perceptual cortices (temporal and occipital) to predictable compared to unpredictable audiovisual sequences. This study provides convergent evidence that the frontal lobe is crucial for higher-level learning in young infants but that it likely works as part of a large, distributed network of regions to modulate infant neural responses during learning. Overall, this work challenges the view that the infant brain is not dynamic and disconnected, lacking in long-range neural connections. Instead, this paper reveals patterns of a highly dynamic and interconnected infant brain that change rapidly as a result of new, learnable experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468062" rel="alternate" title="Sequence learning attenuates cortical responses in both frontal and perceptual cortices in early infancy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467589</id><title>Interneuron Control of C. elegans Developmental Decision-making (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964026+00:00</updated><author><name>Cynthia M. Chai</name></author><author><name>Mahdi Torkashvand</name></author><author><name>Maedeh Seyedolmohadesin</name></author><author><name>Heenam Park</name></author><author><name>Vivek Venkatachalam</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Sternberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals integrate external stimuli to shape their physiological responses throughout development. In adverse environments, &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; larvae can enter a stress-resistant diapause state with arrested metabolism and reproductive physiology. Amphid sensory neurons feed into both rapid chemotactic and short-term foraging mode decisions, mediated by amphid and premotor interneurons, as well as the long-term diapause decision. We identify amphid interneurons that integrate pheromone cues and propagate this information via a neuropeptidergic pathways to influence larval developmental fate, bypassing the pre-motor system. AIA interneuron-derived FLP-2 neuropeptide signaling promotes reproductive growth and AIA activity is suppressed by pheromone. FLP-2 acts antagonistically to the insulin-like INS-1. FLP-2’s growth promoting effects are inhibited by upstream metabotropic glutamatergic signaling and mediated by the broadly-expressed neuropeptide receptor NPR-30. Conversely, the AIB interneurons and their neuropeptide receptor NPR-9/GALR2 promote diapause entry. These neuropeptidergic outputs allow reuse of parts of a sensory system for a decision with a distinct timescale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.07.467589" rel="alternate" title="Interneuron Control of C. elegans Developmental Decision-making (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468479</id><title>Semaphorin signaling restricts neuronal regeneration in C. elegans (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964155+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Belen Harreguy</name></author><author><name>Esha Shah</name></author><author><name>Zainab Tanvir</name></author><author><name>Blandine Simprevil</name></author><author><name>Tracy S. Tran</name></author><author><name>Gal Haspel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extracellular signaling proteins serve as neuronal growth cone guidance molecules during development and are well positioned to be involved in neuronal regeneration and recovery from injury. Semaphorins and their receptors, the plexins, are a family of conserved proteins involved in development that, in the nervous system, are axonal guidance cues mediating axon pathfinding and synapse formation. The Caenorhabditis elegans genome encodes for three semaphorins and two plexin receptors: the transmembrane semaphorins, SMP-1 and SMP-2, signal through their receptor, PLX-1, while the secreted semaphorin, MAB-20, signals through PLX-2. Here, we determined the neuronal morphology and locomotion behavior of knockout animals missing each of the semaphorins and plexins; we described the expression pattern of all plexins in the nervous system of C. elegans; and we evaluated their effect on the regeneration of motoneuron neurites and the recovery of locomotion behavior following precise laser microsurgery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468479" rel="alternate" title="Semaphorin signaling restricts neuronal regeneration in C. elegans (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467533</id><title>The learning curve of murine subretinal injection among clinically trained ophthalmic surgeons (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964289+00:00</updated><author><name>Peirong Huang</name></author><author><name>Siddharth Narendran</name></author><author><name>Felipe Pereira</name></author><author><name>Shinichi Fukuda</name></author><author><name>Yosuke Nagasaka</name></author><author><name>Ivana Apicella</name></author><author><name>Praveen Yerramothu</name></author><author><name>Kenneth M. Marion</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyu Cai</name></author><author><name>Srinivas R. Sadda</name></author><author><name>Bradley D. Gelfand</name></author><author><name>Jayakrishna Ambati</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;P&lt;sc&gt;urpose&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subretinal injection (SRI) in mice is widely used in retinal research, yet the learning curve (LC) of this surgically challenging technique is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;M&lt;sc&gt;ethods&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the LC for SRI in a murine model, we analyzed training data from 3 clinically trained ophthalmic surgeons from 2018 to 2020. Successful SRI was defined as either the absence of retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) degeneration after phosphate buffer saline injection and the presence of RPE degeneration after &lt;italic&gt;Alu&lt;/italic&gt; RNA injection. Multivariable survival-time regression models were used to evaluate the association between surgeon experience and success rate, with adjustment for injection agents, and to calculate an approximate case number to achieve a 95% success rate. A Cumulative Sum (CUSUM) analysis was performed and plotted individually to monitor each surgeon’s simultaneous performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;R&lt;sc&gt;esults&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite prior microsurgery experience, the combined average success rate of the first 50 cases in mice was only 27%. The predicted SRI success rate did not reach a plateau above 95% until approximately 364 prior cases. Using the 364-training case as a “cutoff” point, the predicted probability of success before and after the 364&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; case was 65.38% and 99.32%, respectively (&lt;italic&gt;P&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; 0.0001). CUSUM analysis showed an initial upward slope and then remained within the decision intervals with an acceptable success rate set at 95% in the late stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;C&lt;sc&gt;onclusions&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study demonstrates the complexity and substantial LC for successful SRI in mice with high confidence. A systematic training system could improve the reliability and reproducibility of SRI-related experiments and improve the interpretation of experimental results using this technique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Translational Relevance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our prediction model and monitor system allow objective quantification of technical proficiency in the field of subretinal drug delivery and gene therapy for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467533" rel="alternate" title="The learning curve of murine subretinal injection among clinically trained ophthalmic surgeons (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468067</id><title>Realistic alpha oscillations and transient responses in a cortical microcircuit model (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964516+00:00</updated><author><name>Andres A. Kiani</name></author><author><name>Theoden I. Netoff</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey M. Ghose</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural-mass modeling of neural population data (EEG, ECoG, or LFPs) has shown promise both in elucidating the neural processes underlying cortical rhythms and changes in brain state, as well as offering a framework for testing the interplay between these rhythms and information processing. Models of cortical alpha rhythms (8 - 12 Hz) and their impact in visual sensory processing have been at the forefront of this effort, with the Jansen-Rit being one of the more popular models in this domain. The Jansen-Rit model, however, fails in reproducing key physiological observations including the level of inputs that cortical neurons receive and their responses to visual transients. To address these issues we generated a neural mass model that complies better with synaptic mediated dynamics, intrinsic alpha behavior, and produces realistic responses. The model is robust to many changes in parameter values but critically depends on the ratio of excitation to inhibition, producing response transients whose features are dependent on this ratio and alpha phase and power. The model is sufficiently flexible so as to be able to easily replicate the range of low frequency oscillations observed in different studies. Consistent with experimental observations, we find phase-dependent response dynamics to both visual and electrical stimulation using this model. The model suggests that stimulation facilitates alpha at particular phases and suppresses it in others due to a phase dependent lag in inhibitory responses. Hence, the model generates insight into the physiological parameters responsible for intrinsic oscillations and testable hypotheses regarding the interactions between visual and electrical stimulation on those oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While there is increasing evidence of the fundamental role brain states play in shaping information processing in the cerebral cortex, a mechanistic understanding of how those brain states are manifested and alter the signals underlying sensory processing and decision making has proved challenging. To address this issue we have modeled a well established signature of inattention in visual cortex: synchronized low frequency (8 - 12 Hz) oscillations. To allow for inferences regarding the local generation of these rhythms within a cortical microcircuit we used a neural mass model approach that incorporates physiologically realistic interactions between 3 populations of neurons. Our model is able to explain a variety of experimental observations that previous neural mass models have not, including spontaneous rhythms in the absence of input, the faithful transmission of strong input transients, a range of oscillation frequencies, and phase dependent visual responses. The model is robust to a range of parameters, but critically depends on the balance between local excitation and inhibition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468067" rel="alternate" title="Realistic alpha oscillations and transient responses in a cortical microcircuit model (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468351</id><title>Learning induces coordinated neuronal plasticity of metabolic demands and functional brain networks (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964634+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Klug</name></author><author><name>Godber M Godbersen</name></author><author><name>Lucas Rischka</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Wadsak</name></author><author><name>Verena Pichler</name></author><author><name>Manfred Kloebl</name></author><author><name>Marcus Hacker</name></author><author><name>Rupert Lanzenberger</name></author><author><name>Andreas Hahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The neurobiological basis of learning is reflected in adaptations of brain structure, network organization and energy metabolism. However, it is still unknown how different neuroplastic mechanisms act together and if cognitive advancements relate to general or task-specific changes. To address these questions, we tested how hierarchical network interactions contribute to improvements in the performance of a visuo-spatial processing task by employing simultaneous PET/MR neuroimaging before and after a 4-week learning period. We combined functional PET with metabolic connectivity mapping (MCM) to infer directional interactions across brain regions and subsequently performed simulations to disentangle the role of functional network dynamics and glucose metabolism. As a result, learning altered the top-down regulation of the salience network onto the occipital cortex, with increases in MCM at resting-state and decreases during task execution. Accordingly, a higher divergence between resting-state and task-specific effects was associated with better cognitive performance, indicating that these adaptations are complementary and both required for successful skill learning. Simulations further showed that changes at resting-state were dependent on glucose metabolism, whereas those during task performance were driven by functional connectivity between salience and visual networks. Referring to previous work, we suggest that learning establishes a metabolically expensive skill engram at rest, whose retrieval serves for efficient task execution by minimizing prediction errors between neuronal representations of brain regions on different hierarchical levels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468351" rel="alternate" title="Learning induces coordinated neuronal plasticity of metabolic demands and functional brain networks (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.466928</id><title>Depth-targeted intracortical microstroke by two-photon photothrombosis in rodent brain (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964783+00:00</updated><author><name>Masahiro Fukuda</name></author><author><name>Takayoshi Matsumura</name></author><author><name>Toshio Suda</name></author><author><name>Hajime Hirase</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Photothrombosis is a widely used model of ischemic stroke in rodent experiments. In the photothromboris model, the photosensitizer Rose Bengal is systemically introduced to the blood stream and activated by green light to induce aggregation of platelets that eventually cause vessel occlusion. Since the activation of Rose Bengal is a one-photon phenomenon and the molecules in the illuminated area (light path) are subject to excitation, targeting of thrombosis is unspecific especially in the depth dimension. We have developed a photothrombosis protocol that can target a single vessel in the cortical parenchyma by two-photon excitation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aim&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We aim to induce a thrombotic stroke in the cortical parenchyma by two-photon activation of Rose Bengal so that we confine photothrombosis within a vessel of a target depth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Approach&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;FITC-dextran is injected into the blood stream to visualize the cerebral blood flow in anesthetized adult mice with a cranial window. After a target vessel is chosen by two-photon imaging (950 nm), Rose Bengal is injected into the blood stream. The scanning wavelength is changed to 720 nm and photothrombosis was induced by scanning the target vessel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two-photon depth-targeted single vessel photothrombosis was achieved with a success rate of 84.9±1.7% within 80 s. Attempts without Rose Bengal (i.e., only with FITC) did not result in photothrombosis at the excitation wavelength of 720 nm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We described a protocol that achieves depth-targeted single vessel photothrombosis by two-photon excitation. Simultaneous imaging of blood flow in the targeted vessel using FITC dextran enabled the confirmation of vessel occlusion and prevention of excess irradiation that possibly induces unintended photodamage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.466928" rel="alternate" title="Depth-targeted intracortical microstroke by two-photon photothrombosis in rodent brain (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468469</id><title>Functional ultrasound imaging of recent and remote memory recall in the associative fear neural network in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.964902+00:00</updated><author><name>Gillian Grohs-Metz</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Smausz</name></author><author><name>John Gigg</name></author><author><name>Tobias Boeckers</name></author><author><name>Bastian Hengerer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Emotional learning and memory are affected in numerous psychiatric disorders. At a systems level, however, the underlying neural circuitry is not well defined. Rodent fear conditioning (FC) provides a translational model to study the networks underlying associative memory retrieval. In the current study, functional connectivity among regions related to the cue associative fear network were investigated using functional ultrasound (fUS), a novel imaging technique with great potential for detecting regional neural activity through cerebral blood flow. Behavioral fear expression and fUS imaging were performed one and thirty-one days after FC to assess recent and remote memory recall. Cue-evoked increases in functional connectivity were detected throughout the amygdala, with the lateral (LA) and central (CeA) amygdalar nuclei emerging as major hubs of connectivity, though CeA connectivity was reduced during remote recall. The hippocampus and sensory cortical regions displayed heightened connectivity with the LA during remote recall, whereas interconnectivity between the primary auditory cortex and temporal association areas was reduced. Subregions of the prefrontal cortex exhibited variable connectivity changes, where prelimbic connectivity with the amygdala was refined while specific connections between the infralimbic cortex and amygdalar subregions emerged during remote memory retrieval. Moreover, freezing behavior positively correlated with functional connectivity between hubs of the associative fear network, suggesting that emotional response intensity reflected the strength of the cue-evoked functional network. Overall, our data provide evidence of the functionality of fUS imaging to investigate the neural dynamics of memory encoding and retrieval, applicable in the development of innovative treatments for affective disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468469" rel="alternate" title="Functional ultrasound imaging of recent and remote memory recall in the associative fear neural network in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467818</id><title>Executive control by fronto-parietal activity explains counterintuitive decision behavior in complex value-based decision-making (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.965026+00:00</updated><author><name>Teppei Matsui</name></author><author><name>Yoshiki Hattori</name></author><author><name>Kaho Tsumura</name></author><author><name>Ryuta Aoki</name></author><author><name>Masaki Takeda</name></author><author><name>Kiyoshi Nakahara</name></author><author><name>Koji Jimura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In real life, humans make decisions by taking into account multiple independent factors, such as delay and probability. Cognitive psychology suggests that cognitive control mechanisms play a key role when facing such complex task conditions. However, in value-based decision-making, it still remains unclear to what extent cognitive control mechanisms become essential when the task condition is complex. In this study, we investigated decision-making behaviors and underlying neural mechanisms using a multifactor gambling task where participants simultaneously considered probability and delay. Decision-making behavior in the multifactor task was modulated by both probability and delay. The behavioral effect of probability was stronger than delay, consistent with previous studies. Furthermore, in a subset of conditions that recruited fronto-parietal activations, reaction times were paradoxically elongated despite lower probabilistic uncertainty. Notably, such a reaction time elongation did not occur in control tasks involving single factors. Meta-analysis of brain activations suggested an association between the paradoxical increase of reaction time and strategy switching. Together, these results suggest a novel aspect of complex value-based decision-makings that is strongly influenced by fronto-parietal cognitive control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;•&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;A value-based decision task with concurrent delay and probabilistic uncertainty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;•&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stronger behavioral effect of probability than delay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;•&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paradoxically long reaction time despite low probabilistic uncertainty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;•&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;The task activated fronto-parietal cognitive control network&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;•&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reaction time elongation coincided with activation similar to strategy switching&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467818" rel="alternate" title="Executive control by fronto-parietal activity explains counterintuitive decision behavior in complex value-based decision-making (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>