<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.539382+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454200</id><title>Gene regulatory networks controlling temporal patterning, neurogenesis, and cell fate specification in the mammalian retina (75 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.539661+00:00</updated><author><name>Pin Lyu</name></author><author><name>Thanh Hoang</name></author><author><name>Clayton P. Santiago</name></author><author><name>Eric D. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Andrew E. Timms</name></author><author><name>Haley Appel</name></author><author><name>Megan Gimmen</name></author><author><name>Nguyet Le</name></author><author><name>Lizhi Jiang</name></author><author><name>Dong Won Kim</name></author><author><name>Siqi Chen</name></author><author><name>David Espinoza</name></author><author><name>Ariel E. Telger</name></author><author><name>Kurt Weir</name></author><author><name>Brian S. Clark</name></author><author><name>Timothy J. Cherry</name></author><author><name>Jiang Qian</name></author><author><name>Seth Blackshaw</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene regulatory networks (GRNs), consisting of transcription factors and their target cis- regulatory sequences, control neurogenesis and cell fate specification in the developing central nervous system, but their organization is poorly characterized. In this study, we performed integrated single-cell RNA- and scATAC-seq analysis in both mouse and human retina to profile dynamic changes in gene expression, chromatin accessibility and transcription factor footprinting during retinal neurogenesis. We identified multiple interconnected, evolutionarily-conserved GRNs consisting of cell type-specific transcription factors that both activate expression of genes within their own network and often inhibit expression of genes in other networks. These GRNs control state transitions within primary retinal progenitors that underlie temporal patterning, regulate the transition from primary to neurogenic progenitors, and drive specification of each major retinal cell type. We confirmed the prediction of this analysis that the NFI transcription factors &lt;italic&gt;Nfia&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Nfib&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;Nfix&lt;/italic&gt; selectively activate expression of genes that promote late-stage temporal identity in primary retinal progenitors. We also used GRNs to identify additional transcription factors that promote (&lt;italic&gt;Insm1/2&lt;/italic&gt;) and inhibit (&lt;italic&gt;Tbx3&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;Tcf7l1&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;2&lt;/italic&gt;) rod photoreceptor specification in postnatal retina. This study provides an inventory of cis- and trans-acting factors that control retinal development, identifies transcription factors that control the temporal identity of retinal progenitors and cell fate specification, and will potentially guide cell-based therapies aimed at replacing retinal neurons lost due to disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454200" rel="alternate" title="Gene regulatory networks controlling temporal patterning, neurogenesis, and cell fate specification in the mammalian retina (75 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.454992</id><title>Modulating D1 rather than D2 receptor-expressing spiny-projection neurons corresponds to optimal antipsychotic effect (49 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.540057+00:00</updated><author><name>Seongsik Yun</name></author><author><name>Ben Yang</name></author><author><name>Madison M. Martin</name></author><author><name>Nai-Hsing Yeh</name></author><author><name>Anis Contractor</name></author><author><name>Jones G. Parker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Overactive dopamine transmission in psychosis is predicted to unbalance striatal output via D1- and D2-dopamine receptor-expressing spiny-projection neurons (SPNs). Antipsychotic drugs are thought to re-balance this output by blocking D2-receptor signaling. Here we imaged D1- and D2-SPN Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; dynamics in mice to determine the neural signatures of antipsychotic effect. Initially we compared effective (clozapine and haloperidol) antipsychotics to a candidate drug that failed in clinical trials (MP-10). Clozapine and haloperidol normalized hyperdopaminergic D1-SPN dynamics, while MP-10 only normalized D2-SPN activity. Clozapine, haloperidol or chemogenetic manipulations of D1-SPNs also normalized sensorimotor gating. Given the surprising correlation between clinical efficacy and D1-SPN modulation, we evaluated compounds that selectively target D1-SPNs. D1R partial agonism, antagonism, or positive M4 cholinergic receptor modulation all normalized the levels of D1-SPN activity, locomotion, and sensorimotor gating. Our results suggest that D1-SPN activity is a more relevant therapeutic target than D2-SPN activity for the development of effective antipsychotics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.454992" rel="alternate" title="Modulating D1 rather than D2 receptor-expressing spiny-projection neurons corresponds to optimal antipsychotic effect (49 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.07.455365</id><title>Spatiotemporal dynamics of human microglia are linked with brain developmental processes across the lifespan (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.540599+00:00</updated><author><name>David A. Menassa</name></author><author><name>Tim A. O. Muntslag</name></author><author><name>Maria Martin-Estebane</name></author><author><name>Liam Barry-Carroll</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Chapman</name></author><author><name>Istvan Adorjan</name></author><author><name>Teadora Tyler</name></author><author><name>Bethany Turnbull</name></author><author><name>Matthew J.J. Rose-Zerilli</name></author><author><name>James A.R. Nicoll</name></author><author><name>Zeljka Krsnik</name></author><author><name>Ivica Kostovic</name></author><author><name>Diego Gomez-Nicola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia, the brain's resident macrophages, shape neural development and wiring, and are key neuroimmune hubs in the pathological signature of neurodevelopmental disorders. In the human brain, microglial development has not been carefully examined yet, and most of our knowledge derives from rodents. We established an unprecedented collection of 97 post-mortem tissues enabling quantitative, sex-matched, detailed analysis of microglia across the human lifespan. We identify the dynamics of these cells in the human telencephalon, describing novel waves in microglial density across gestation and infancy, controlled by a balance of proliferation and apoptosis, which track key neurodevelopmental milestones. These profound changes in microglia are also observed in bulk RNAseq and single-cell RNAseq datasets. This study provides unparalleled insight and detail into the spatiotemporal dynamics of microglia across the human lifespan. Our findings serve as a solid foundation for elucidating how microglia contribute to shaping neurodevelopment in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.07.455365" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal dynamics of human microglia are linked with brain developmental processes across the lifespan (18 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455132</id><title>Harmonisation of multi-site MRS data with ComBat (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.541120+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiffany K. Bell</name></author><author><name>Kate J. Godfrey</name></author><author><name>Ashley L. Ware</name></author><author><name>Keith Owen Yeates</name></author><author><name>Ashley D. Harris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) is a non-invasive neuroimaging technique used to measure brain chemistry &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and has been used to study the healthy brain as well as neuropathology in numerous neurological disorders. The number of multi-site studies using MRS are increasing; however, non-biological variability introduced during data collection across multiple sites, such as differences in scanner vendors and site-specific acquisition implementations for MRS, can obscure detection of biological effects of interest. ComBat is a data harmonisation technique that can remove non-biological sources of variance in multisite studies. It has been validated for use with structural and functional MRI metrics but not for MRS metabolites. This study investigated the validity of using ComBat to harmonize MRS metabolites for vendor and site differences. Analyses were performed using data acquired across 20 sites and included edited MRS for GABA+ (N=218) and macromolecule-suppressed GABA data (N=209), as well as standard PRESS data to quantify NAA, creatine, choline, and glutamate (N=195). ComBat harmonisation successfully mitigated vendor and site differences for all metabolites of interest. Moreover, significant associations were detected between sex and choline levels and between age and glutamate and GABA+ levels that were not detectable prior to harmonisation, confirming the importance of removing site and vendor effects in multi-site data. In conclusion, ComBat harmonisation can be successfully applied to MRS data in multi-site MRS studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-site MRS data contains sources of non-biological variance that can mask biological effects of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;ComBat data harmonisation successfully removes variance contributed by scanner and site differences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Removal of this variance revealed biological effects that were previously not detected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;ComBat harmonisation can be successfully applied to MRS data in multi-site MRS studies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455132" rel="alternate" title="Harmonisation of multi-site MRS data with ComBat (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454575</id><title>Environmental enrichment mitigates the long-lasting sequelae of perinatal fentanyl exposure (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.541617+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason Bondoc Alipio</name></author><author><name>Lace Marie Riggs</name></author><author><name>Madeline Plank</name></author><author><name>Asaf Keller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The opioid epidemic is a rapidly evolving societal issue that stems from the abuse of prescription and illicit opioids, including increasing use of synthetic opioids like fentanyl. Fentanyl use among women has increased substantially in the last decade, leading to a 40-fold increase in the number of perinatally-exposed infants. This exposure can result in neuropsychiatric abnormalities that persist into adolescence and, in some cases, adulthood. We previously developed a preclinical model to establish the consequences of perinatal fentanyl exposure and identified a pattern of synaptic pathophysiology that involves lasting impairments in primary somatosensory (S1) circuit function and behavior. Here, we ask if these long-lasting effects can be restored by a non-invasive intervention. We demonstrate that developmental exposure to environmental enrichment ameliorates many of fentanyl’s deleterious behavioral effects, including hyperactivity, enhanced sensitivity to anxiogenic environments, and sensory maladaptation. As an extension of our past work, we found that perinatal fentanyl alters the frequency of miniature excitatory postsynaptic currents and impairs long-term potentiation in S1 layer 2/3 neurons. These deficits in synaptic function were restored by environmental enrichment. Environmental enrichment also affected neurons in control mice, reducing long-term potentiation and depression, and increasing frequency of miniature excitatory postsynaptic currents. These results demonstrate that the lasting somatosensory-related effects of fentanyl can be ameliorated with a non-invasive intervention introduced during early development. These findings can inform ongoing efforts to develop actionable steps toward mitigating the consequences of opioid abuse among pregnant women.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children and adolescents exposed to opioids during perinatal development have a higher risk of developing neuropsychiatric disorders. Here, we employ a preclinical model of perinatal fentanyl exposure that recapitulates these long-term impairments and show, for the first time, that environmental enrichment can reverse deficits in somatosensory circuit function and behavior when introduced early in postnatal development. These findings have the potential to directly inform and guide ongoing efforts to mitigate the consequences of perinatal opioid exposure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.454575" rel="alternate" title="Environmental enrichment mitigates the long-lasting sequelae of perinatal fentanyl exposure (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>