<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.289072+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469762</id><title>In vitro and in vivo CRISPR-Cas9 screens reveal drivers of aging in neural stem cells of the brain (146 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.289419+00:00</updated><author><name>Tyson J. Ruetz</name></author><author><name>Chloe M. Kashiwagi</name></author><author><name>Bhek Morton</name></author><author><name>Robin W. Yeo</name></author><author><name>Dena S. Leeman</name></author><author><name>David W. Morgens</name></author><author><name>C. Kimberly Tsui</name></author><author><name>Amy Li</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Bassik</name></author><author><name>Anne Brunet</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging impairs the ability of neural stem cells to transition from quiescence to activation (proliferation) in the adult mammalian brain. Neural stem cell (NSC) functional decline results in decreased production of new neurons and defective regeneration upon injury during aging&lt;sup&gt;1–9&lt;/sup&gt;, and this is exacerbated in Alzheimer’s disease&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;. Many genes are upregulated with age in NSCs&lt;sup&gt;3, 11–13&lt;/sup&gt;, and the knockout of some of these boosts old NSC activation and rejuvenates aspects of old brain function&lt;sup&gt;14–18&lt;/sup&gt;. But systematic functional testing of genes in old NSCs – and more generally in old cells – has not been done. This has been a major limiting factor in identifying the most promising rejuvenation interventions. Here we develop &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; high-throughput CRISPR-Cas9 screening platforms to systematically uncover gene knockouts that boost NSC activation in old mice. Our genome-wide screening pipeline in primary cultures of young and old NSCs identifies over 300 gene knockouts that specifically restore old NSC activation. Interestingly, the top gene knockouts are involved in glucose import, cilium organization and ribonucleoprotein structures. To determine which gene knockouts have a rejuvenating effect for the aging brain, we establish a scalable CRISPR-Cas9 screening platform &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in old mice. Of the 50 gene knockouts we tested &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, 23 boost old NSC activation and production of new neurons in old brains. Notably, the knockout of &lt;italic&gt;Slc2a4&lt;/italic&gt;, which encodes for the GLUT4 glucose transporter, is a top rejuvenating intervention for old NSCs. GLUT4 protein expression increases in the stem cell niche during aging, and we show that old NSCs indeed uptake ∼2-fold more glucose than their young counterparts. Transient glucose starvation increases the ability of old NSCs to activate, which is not further improved by knockout of &lt;italic&gt;Slc2a4/&lt;/italic&gt;GLUT4. Together, these results indicate that a shift in glucose uptake contributes to the decline in NSC activation with age, but that it can be reversed by genetic or external interventions. Importantly, our work provides scalable platforms to systematically identify genetic interventions that boost old NSC function, including &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; in old brains, with important implications for regenerative and cognitive decline during aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469762" rel="alternate" title="In vitro and in vivo CRISPR-Cas9 screens reveal drivers of aging in neural stem cells of the brain (146 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469533</id><title>The Unique Cytoarchitecture and Wiring of the Human Default Mode Network (143 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.289632+00:00</updated><author><name>Casey Paquola</name></author><author><name>Margaret Garber</name></author><author><name>Stefan Frässle</name></author><author><name>Jessica Royer</name></author><author><name>Shahin Tavakol</name></author><author><name>Raul Rodriguez-Cruces</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Jeffries</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Smallwood</name></author><author><name>Boris Bernhardt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is challenging to specify the role of the default mode network (DMN) in human behaviour. Contemporary theories, based on functional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), suggest that the DMN is insulated from the external world, which allows it to support perceptually-decoupled states and to integrate external and internal information in the construction of abstract meanings. To date, the neuronal architecture of the DMN has received relatively little attention. Understanding the cytoarchitectural composition and connectional layout of the DMN will provide novel insights into its role in brain function. We mapped cytoarchitectural variation within the DMN using a cortical type atlas and a histological model of the entire human brain. Next, we used MRI acquired in healthy young adults to explicate structural wiring and effective connectivity. We discovered profound diversity of DMN cytoarchitecture. Connectivity is organised along the most dominant cytoarchitectural axis. One side of the axis is the prominent receiver, whereas the other side remains more insulated, especially from sensory areas. The structural heterogeneity of the DMN engenders a network-level balance in communication with external and internal sources, which is distinctive, relative to other functional communities. The neuronal architecture of the DMN suggests it is a protuberance from the core cortical processing hierarchy and holds a unique role in information integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469533" rel="alternate" title="The Unique Cytoarchitecture and Wiring of the Human Default Mode Network (143 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469481</id><title>All-optical electrophysiology with improved genetically encoded voltage indicators reveals interneuron network dynamics in vivo (107 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.289843+00:00</updated><author><name>He Tian</name></author><author><name>Hunter C. Davis</name></author><author><name>J. David Wong-Campos</name></author><author><name>Linlin Z. Fan</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Gmeiner</name></author><author><name>Shahinoor Begum</name></author><author><name>Christopher A. Werley</name></author><author><name>Gabriel B. Borja</name></author><author><name>Hansini Upadhyay</name></author><author><name>Himali Shah</name></author><author><name>Jane Jacques</name></author><author><name>Pojeong Park</name></author><author><name>Yitong Qi</name></author><author><name>Vicente Parot</name></author><author><name>Karl Deisseroth</name></author><author><name>Adam E. Cohen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All-optical electrophysiology can be a powerful tool for studying neural dynamics &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, as it offers the ability to image and perturb membrane voltage in multiple cells simultaneously. The “Optopatch” constructs combine a red-shifted archaerhodopsin (Arch)-derived genetically encoded voltage indicator (GEVI) with a blue-shifted channelrhodopsin actuator (ChR). We used a video-based pooled screen to evolve Arch-derived GEVIs with improved signal-to-noise ratio (QuasAr6a) and kinetics (QuasAr6b). By combining optogenetic stimulation of individual cells with high-precision voltage imaging in neighboring cells, we mapped inhibitory and gap junction-mediated connections, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Optogenetic activation of a single NDNF-expressing neuron in visual cortex Layer 1 significantly suppressed the spike rate in some neighboring NDNF interneurons. Hippocampal PV cells showed near-synchronous spikes across multiple cells at a frequency significantly above what one would expect from independent spiking, suggesting that collective inhibitory spikes may play an important signaling role &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. By stimulating individual cells and recording from neighbors, we quantified gap junction coupling strengths. Together, these results demonstrate powerful new tools for all-optical microcircuit dissection in live mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469481" rel="alternate" title="All-optical electrophysiology with improved genetically encoded voltage indicators reveals interneuron network dynamics in vivo (107 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469394</id><title>Miniscope-LFOV: A large field of view, single cell resolution, miniature microscope for wired and wire-free imaging of neural dynamics in freely behaving animals (84 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290043+00:00</updated><author><name>Changliang Guo</name></author><author><name>Garrett J. Blair</name></author><author><name>Megha Sehgal</name></author><author><name>Federico N. Sangiuliano Jimka</name></author><author><name>Arash Bellafard</name></author><author><name>Alcino J. Silva</name></author><author><name>Peyman Golshani</name></author><author><name>Michele A. Basso</name></author><author><name>H. Tad Blair</name></author><author><name>Daniel Aharoni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present a large field of view (FOV) open-source miniature microscope (MiniLFOV) designed to extend the capabilities of the UCLA Miniscope platform to large-scale, single cell resolution neural imaging in freely behaving large rodents and head-fixed mice. This system is capable of multiple imaging configurations, including deep brain imaging using implanted optical probes and cortical imaging through cranial windows. The MiniLFOV interfaces with existing open-source UCLA Miniscope DAQ hardware and software, can achieve single cell resolution imaging across a 3.6 × 2.7 mm field of view at 23 frames per second, has an electrically adjustable working distance of up to 3.5 mm±150 µm using an onboard electrowetting lens, incorporates an absolute head-orientation sensor, and weighs under 14 grams. The MiniLFOV provides a 30-fold larger FOV and yields 20-fold better sensitivity than Miniscope V3, and a 12-fold larger FOV with 2-fold better sensitivity than Miniscope V4. Power and data transmission are handled through a single, flexible coaxial cable down to 0.3 mm in diameter facilitating naturalistic behavior. We validated the MiniLFOV in freely behaving rats by simultaneously imaging &amp;gt;1000 GCaMP7s expressing neurons in the CA1 layer of the hippocampus and in head-fixed mice by simultaneously imaging ∼2000 neurons in the mouse dorsal cortex through a 4 × 4 mm cranial window. For freely behaving experiments, the MiniLFOV supports optional wire-free operation using a 3.5 g wire-free data acquisition expansion board which enables close to 1-hour of wire-free recording with a 400 mAh (7.5 g) on-board single-cell lithium-polymer battery and expands wire-free imaging techniques to larger animal models. We expect this new open-source implementation of the UCLA Miniscope platform will enable researchers to address novel hypotheses concerning brain function in freely behaving animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469394" rel="alternate" title="Miniscope-LFOV: A large field of view, single cell resolution, miniature microscope for wired and wire-free imaging of neural dynamics in freely behaving animals (84 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469166</id><title>Population Imaging of Central Sensitization (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290202+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles Warwick</name></author><author><name>Joseph Salsovic</name></author><author><name>Junichi Hachisuka</name></author><author><name>Kelly M. Smith</name></author><author><name>Haichao Chen</name></author><author><name>James Ibinson</name></author><author><name>H. Richard Koerber</name></author><author><name>Sarah E. Ross</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Capsaicin applied locally to the skin causes central sensitization that results in allodynia, a state in which pain is elicited by innocuous stimuli. Here, we used two-photon calcium imaging of neurons in the dorsal spinal cord to visualize central sensitization across excitatory interneurons and spinal projection neurons. To distinguish among excitatory neuron subtypes, we developed CICADA, a cell profiling approach that leverages the expression of distinct Gq-coupled receptors. We then identified capsaicin-responsive and capsaicin-sensitized neuronal populations. Capsaicin-sensitized neurons showed emergent responses to low threshold input and increased receptive field sizes consistent with the psychophysical phenomenon that allodynia is observed across an extended secondary zone. Finally, we identified spinal projection neurons that showed a shift in tuning toward low threshold input. These experiments provide a population-level view of central sensitization and a framework with which to model somatosensory integration in the dorsal horn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlight&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warwick et al. use two-photon calcium imaging coupled with pharmacological profiling to identify neuronal populations in the spinal dorsal horn that mediate capsaicin-induced central sensitization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469166" rel="alternate" title="Population Imaging of Central Sensitization (36 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.468910</id><title>Sex-specific transcriptomic and epitranscriptomic signatures of PTSD-like fear acquisition (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290348+00:00</updated><author><name>Andre Martins Reis</name></author><author><name>Jillian Hammond</name></author><author><name>Igor Stevanovski</name></author><author><name>Jonathon C Arnold</name></author><author><name>Iain S. McGregor</name></author><author><name>Ira Deveson</name></author><author><name>Anand Gururajan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our understanding of the molecular pathology of posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is rapidly evolving and is being driven by advances in sequencing techniques. Conventional short-read RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) is a central tool in transcriptomics research that enables unbiased gene expression profiling. With the recent emergence of Oxford Nanopore direct RNA-seq (dRNA-seq), it is now also possible to interrogate diverse RNA modifications, collectively known as the ‘epitranscriptome’. Here, we present our analyses of the male and female mouse amygdala transcriptome and epitranscriptome, obtained using parallel Illumina RNA-seq and Oxford Nanopore dRNA-seq, associated with the acquisition of PTSD-like fear induced by Pavlovian cued-fear conditioning. We report significant sex-specific differences in the amygdala transcriptional response during fear acquisition, and a range of shared and dimorphic epitranscriptomic signatures. Differential RNA modifications are enriched among mRNA transcripts associated with neurotransmitter regulation and mitochondrial function, many of which have been previously implicated in PTSD. Very few differentially modified transcripts are also differentially expressed, suggesting an influential, expression-independent role for epitranscriptional regulation in PTSD-like fear-acquisition. Overall, our application of conventional and newly developed methods provides a platform for future work that will lead to new insights into and therapeutics for PTSD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.468910" rel="alternate" title="Sex-specific transcriptomic and epitranscriptomic signatures of PTSD-like fear acquisition (32 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469669</id><title>Alpha power and stimulus-evoked activity dissociate metacognitive reports of attention, visibility and confidence in a visual detection task (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290488+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew James Davidson</name></author><author><name>James Macdonald</name></author><author><name>Nick Yeung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variability in the detection and discrimination of weak visual stimuli has been linked to prestimulus neural activity. In particular, the power of oscillatory activity in the alpha-band (8-12 Hz) has been shown to impact upon the objective likelihood of stimulus detection, as well as measures of subjective visibility, attention, and decision confidence. We aimed to clarify how prestimulus alpha influences performance and phenomenology, by recording simultaneous subjective measures of attention and confidence (Experiment 1), or attention and visibility (Experiment  2) on a trial-by-trial basis in a visual detection task. Across both experiments, prestimulus alpha power was negatively and linearly correlated with the intensity of subjective attention. In contrast to this linear relationship, we observed a quadratic relationship between the strength of prestimulus alpha power and subjective ratings of confidence and visibility. We find that this same quadratic relationship links prestimulus alpha power to the strength of stimulus evoked responses. Visibility and confidence judgements corresponded to the strength of evoked responses, but confidence, uniquely, incorporated information about attentional state. As such, our findings reveal distinct psychological and neural correlates of metacognitive judgements of attentional state, stimulus visibility, and decision confidence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469669" rel="alternate" title="Alpha power and stimulus-evoked activity dissociate metacognitive reports of attention, visibility and confidence in a visual detection task (31 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469613</id><title>Chronic Physical and Vicarious Psychosocial Stress Alter Fentanyl Consumption and Nucleus Accumbens Rho GTPases in Male and Female C57BL/6 Mice (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290605+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniela Franco</name></author><author><name>Andreas B Wulff</name></author><author><name>Mary Kay Lobo</name></author><author><name>Megan E Fox</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chronic stress can increase the risk of developing a substance use disorder in vulnerable individuals. Numerous models have been developed to probe the underlying neurobiological mechanisms, however most prior work has been restricted to male rodents, conducted only in rats, or introduces physical injury that can complicate opioid studies. Here we sought to establish how chronic psychosocial stress influences fentanyl consumption in male and female C57BL/6 mice. We used chronic social defeat stress (CSDS), or the modified vicarious chronic witness defeat stress (CWDS), and used social interaction to stratify mice as stress-susceptible or resilient. We then subjected mice to a 15 day fentanyl drinking paradigm in the home cage that consisted of alternating forced and choice periods with increasing fentanyl concentrations. Male mice susceptible to either CWDS or CSDS consumed more fentanyl relative to unstressed mice, and exhibited increased preference for fentanyl. CWDS-susceptible female mice did not differ from unstressed mice during the forced periods, but showed increased preference for fentanyl. We also found decreased expression of nucleus accumbens Rho GTPases in male, but not female mice following stress and fentanyl drinking. We also compare fentanyl drinking behavior in mice that had free access to plain water throughout. Our results indicate that stress-sensitized fentanyl consumption is dependent on both sex and behavioral outcomes to stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469613" rel="alternate" title="Chronic Physical and Vicarious Psychosocial Stress Alter Fentanyl Consumption and Nucleus Accumbens Rho GTPases in Male and Female C57BL/6 Mice (22 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.468539</id><title>BrainPalmSeq: A curated RNA-seq database of palmitoylating and de-palmitoylating enzyme expression in the mouse brain (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290725+00:00</updated><author><name>AR Wild</name></author><author><name>PW Hogg</name></author><author><name>S Flibotte</name></author><author><name>G Nasseri</name></author><author><name>R Hollman</name></author><author><name>K Haas</name></author><author><name>SX Bamji</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;-palmitoylation is a reversible post translational lipid modification that plays a critical role in neuronal development and plasticity, while dysregulated &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;-palmitoylation underlies a number of severe neurological disorders. Dynamic &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;-palmitoylation is regulated by a large family of ZDHHC palmitoylating enzymes, their accessory proteins, and a small number of known de-palmitoylating enzymes. Here, we curated and analyzed expression data for the proteins that mediate &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;-palmitoylation from publicly available RNAseq datasets, providing a comprehensive overview of their distribution in the mouse nervous system. We developed a web-tool that enables interactive visualization of the expression patterns for these proteins in the nervous system (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brainpalmseq.med.ubc.ca/"&gt;http://brainpalmseq.med.ubc.ca/&lt;/ext-link&gt;), and explored this resource to find region and cell-type specific expression patterns that give insight into the function of palmitoylating and de-palmitoylating enzymes in the brain and neurological disorders. We found coordinated expression of ZDHHC enzymes with their accessory proteins, de-palmitoylating enzymes and other brain-expressed genes that included an enrichment of &lt;italic&gt;S&lt;/italic&gt;-palmitoylation substrates. Finally, we utilized ZDHHC expression patterns to predict and validate palmitoylating enzyme-substrate interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.468539" rel="alternate" title="BrainPalmSeq: A curated RNA-seq database of palmitoylating and de-palmitoylating enzyme expression in the mouse brain (18 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469610</id><title>Electrophysiological correlates of confidence differ across correct and erroneous perceptual decisions (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.290863+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Feuerriegel</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie Murphy</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Konski</name></author><author><name>Vinay Mepani</name></author><author><name>Jie Sun</name></author><author><name>Robert Hester</name></author><author><name>Stefan Bode</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Every decision we make is accompanied by an estimate of the likelihood that our decision is accurate or appropriate. This likelihood estimate is termed our degree of decision confidence. Recent work has uncovered event-related potential (ERP) correlates of confidence both during decision formation and after a decision has been made. However, the interpretation of these findings is complicated by methodological issues related to ERP amplitude measurement that are prevalent across existing studies. To more accurately characterise the neural correlates of confidence, we presented participants with a difficult perceptual decision task that elicited a broad range of confidence ratings. We identified a frontal ERP component within an onset prior to the behavioural response, which exhibited more positive-going amplitudes in trials with higher confidence ratings. This frontal effect also biased measures of the centro-parietal positivity (CPP) component at parietal electrodes via volume conduction. Amplitudes of the error positivity (Pe) component that followed each decision were negatively associated with confidence for trials with decision errors, but not for trials with correct decisions. We provide evidence for both pre- and post-decisional neural correlates of decision confidence that are observed in trials with correct and erroneous decisions, respectively. Our findings suggest that certainty in having made a correct response is associated with frontal activity during decision formation, whereas certainty in having committed an error is instead associated with the post-decisional Pe component. We additionally show that some previously reported associations between decision confidence and CPP/Pe component amplitudes are (at least partly) a consequence of ERP amplitude measurement-related confounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469610" rel="alternate" title="Electrophysiological correlates of confidence differ across correct and erroneous perceptual decisions (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469682</id><title>Categorical encoding of voice in human superior temporal cortex (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291000+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle Rupp</name></author><author><name>Jasmine Hect</name></author><author><name>Madison Remick</name></author><author><name>Avniel Ghuman</name></author><author><name>Bharath Chandrasekaran</name></author><author><name>Lori L. Holt</name></author><author><name>Taylor J. Abel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability to recognize abstract features of voice during auditory perception is a complex, yet poorly understood, feat of human audition. For the listener, this occurs in near-automatic fasion to seamlessly extract complex cues from a highly variable auditory signal. Voice perception depends on specialized regions of auditory cortex, including superior temporal gyrus (STG) and superior temporal sulcus (STS). However, the nature of voice encoding at the cortical level remains poorly understoood. We leverage intracerebral recordings across human auditory cortex during presentation of voice and non-voice acoustic stimuli to examine voice encoding in auditory cortex, in eight patient-participants undergoing epilepsy surgery evaluation. We show that voice-selectivity increases along the auditory hierarchy from supratemporal plane (STP) to the STG and STS. Results show accurate decoding of vocalizations from human auditory cortical activity even in the complete absence of linguistic content. These findings show an early, less-selective temporal window of neural activity in the STG and STS followed by a sustained, strongly voice-selective window. We then developed encoding models that demonstrate divergence in the encoding of acoustic features along the auditory hierarchy, wherein STG/STS responses were best explained by voice category as opposed to the acoustic features of voice stimuli. This is in contrast to neural activity recorded from STP, in which responses were accounted for by acoustic features. These findings support a model of voice perception that engages categorical encoding mechanisms within STG and STS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voice perception occurs via specialized networks in higher order auditory cortex, yet how voice features are encoded remains a central unanswered question. With human intracerebral recordings of auditory cortex, we provide evidence for categorical encoding of voice in STG and STS and occurs in the absence of linguistic content. This selectivity strengthens after an initial onset response and cannot be explained by simple acoustic features. Together, these data support the existence of sites within STG and STS that are specialized for voice perception.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469682" rel="alternate" title="Categorical encoding of voice in human superior temporal cortex (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.469979</id><title>Input to layer 1 of somatosensory cortex: Local input outweighs long-range and can modulate the activity of layer 1 interneurons (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291137+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Ledderose</name></author><author><name>Timothy A Zolnik</name></author><author><name>Maria Toumazou</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Trimbuch</name></author><author><name>Christian Rosenmund</name></author><author><name>Britta J Eickholt</name></author><author><name>Dieter Jaeger</name></author><author><name>Matthew E Larkum</name></author><author><name>Robert Sachdev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neocortical layer (L) 1 is a locus for interactions between long-range inputs, L1 interneurons and apical tuft dendrites of pyramidal neurons. Even though we have a wealth of information about L1, the level and effect of local input to this layer have not been quantified. Here we characterized the input to L1 of mouse somatosensory cortex with fast blue, monosynaptic rabies and optogenetics. Our work shows that most of the input to L1 is local, and that both local and long-range inputs to this layer arise predominantly from L2/3 and L5 neurons. Subtypes of L5 and L6b neurons project to the overlying L1 with different probabilities. VIP and SST interneurons in L2/3 and L5 also innervate L1. A subset of local L5, the intratelencephalic, pyramidal neurons, drive L1 interneurons but have no effect on L5 apical tuft dendrites. Monosynaptic rabies-based retrograde labelling reveals presynaptic boutons covering the entire somato-dendritic axis of pyramidal neurons, including in L1. When fast blue application was combined with rabies virus, we found that only a fraction of local and long-range neurons was both presynaptic to L5 neurons and projected to L1. These results demonstrate that L1 receives a large proportion of its input from local neurons, and that some of these inputs specifically target interneurons. We conclude that L1 is not just a site for interaction between long-range feedback and apical tuft dendrites of pyramidal cells, it is also a site for complex modulation of pyramidal neurons and interneurons by local inputs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.469979" rel="alternate" title="Input to layer 1 of somatosensory cortex: Local input outweighs long-range and can modulate the activity of layer 1 interneurons (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470178</id><title>Couching the brain's multiple-demand and language-specific systems within a macroscale gradient of cortical connectivity (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291287+00:00</updated><author><name>Rocco Chiou</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Jefferies</name></author><author><name>John Duncan</name></author><author><name>Gina F. Humphreys</name></author><author><name>Matthew Lambon Ralph</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cerebrum comprises a set of specialised systems that tile across the cortical sheet, forming a tapestry-like configuration. For example, the multiple-demand and language-specific systems occupy largely separate neural estates and exhibit disparate functional profiles. Although delimiting the boundary between systems informs where cortical sheet functionally fractionates, it remains unclear why different systems' topographical placements are spatially configured in typical manners and how a macroscale architecture arises from this topography. Novel approaches have tackled this challenge by condensing the topography into a principal gradient, which represents the workflow of information processing from sensory-motoric to abstract-cognitive. To understand how the multiple-demand and language-specific systems are accommodated in the gradient framework, here we used fMRI to probe cognitive operations in semantic vs. visuospatial domains and projected functional activities onto the principal gradient. We found that the two systems showed distinct trajectories of distribution along gradient tiers, suggesting different roles in the transition from sensation to cognition. Critically, when semantic processing became difficult, the brain recruited a specialised 'semantic-control' system that was a functional and anatomical 'hybrid' juxtaposed between the multi-demand and language systems. We discuss how the brain's modular division can be better understood through the lens of a dimensionality-reduced gradient-like architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470178" rel="alternate" title="Couching the brain's multiple-demand and language-specific systems within a macroscale gradient of cortical connectivity (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469432</id><title>Patient brain organoids identify a link between the 16p11.2 copy number variant and the RBFOX1 gene (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291412+00:00</updated><author><name>Milos Kostic</name></author><author><name>Joseph J. Raymond</name></author><author><name>Beata Henry</name></author><author><name>Tayfun Tumkaya</name></author><author><name>Jivan Khlghatyan</name></author><author><name>Jill Dvornik</name></author><author><name>Jack S. Hsiao</name></author><author><name>Seon Hye Cheon</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Chung</name></author><author><name>Yishan Sun</name></author><author><name>Ricardo E. Dolmetsch</name></author><author><name>Kathleen A. Worringer</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Ihry</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Copy number variants (CNVs) that delete or duplicate 30 genes within the 16p11.2 genomic region give rise to a range of neurodevelopmental phenotypes with high penetrance in humans. Despite the identification of this small region, the mechanisms by which 16p11.2 CNVs lead to disease are unclear. Relevant models, like human cortical organoids (hCOs), are needed to understand the human-specific mechanisms of neurodevelopmental disease. We generated hCOs from 18 patients and controls, profiling 167,958 cells with single cell (sc)RNA-seq. Analysis revealed neuronal-specific differential expression of genes outside of the 16p11.2 region that were related to cell-cell adhesion, neuronal projection growth, and neurodevelopmental disorders. Furthermore, 16p11.2 deletion syndrome organoids exhibited reduced mRNA and protein levels of RBFOX1, a gene which can also harbor CNVs linked to neurodevelopmental phenotypes. We found that many genes previously shown to be regulated by RBFOX1 are also perturbed in organoids from patients with 16p11.2 deletion syndrome, and thus identified a novel link between independent CNVs associated with neuronal development and autism. Overall, this work suggests convergent signaling, which indicates the possibility of a common therapeutic mechanism across multiple rare neuronal diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469432" rel="alternate" title="Patient brain organoids identify a link between the 16p11.2 copy number variant and the RBFOX1 gene (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469725</id><title>Fecal microbiota transplantation derived from Alzheimer’s disease mice worsens brain trauma outcomes in young C57BL/6 mice (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291589+00:00</updated><author><name>Sirena Soriano</name></author><author><name>Kristen Curry</name></author><author><name>Qi Wang</name></author><author><name>Elsbeth Chow</name></author><author><name>Todd Treangen</name></author><author><name>Sonia Villapol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Traumatic brain injury (TBI) cause neuroinflammation, exaggerated immune response, and, consequently, neurodegeneration. The gut microbiome is an essential modulator of the immune system, impacting in the brain. There are not effective treatments for TBI, therefore, modulating the gut microbiome may shed novel therapeutics for the damaged brain. Also, in patients with Alzheimer’s disease (AD), the microbiota has been associated with a lack of diversity, which negatively modulates the immune system. This study aimed to determine whether the gut microbiota from AD mice exacerbates neurological deficits after TBI in young mice. For this purpose, we performed fecal microbiota transplants from AD (FMT-AD) mice into young C57BL/6 (wild-type, WT) mice following TBI. Thus, FMT-AD and fecal microbiota transplants from healthy controls (FMT-young) were administered orally to young WT mice after the TBI occurred. We first determined the gut microbiota diversity and composition by analyzing fulllength 16S rRNA sequences from mouse fecal samples using the Oxford Nanopore MinION technology. We collected the blood, brain, and gut tissues for protein and immunohistochemical analysis. Our results showed that FMT-AD treatment stimulates a higher relative abundance of &lt;italic&gt;Muribaculum intestinal&lt;/italic&gt; and a decrease in &lt;italic&gt;Lactobacillus johnsonii&lt;/italic&gt; compared FMT-young treatment in WT mice. Furthermore, WT mice exhibited larger lesion volumes, increased the number of activated microglia/macrophages cells, and reduced motor recovery after FMT-AD compared to FMT-young one day after TBI. Thus, the gut microbiota from AD mice not only aggravates the neuroinflammatory response and motor recovery, but also increases the lesion size after TBI in young WT mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469725" rel="alternate" title="Fecal microbiota transplantation derived from Alzheimer’s disease mice worsens brain trauma outcomes in young C57BL/6 mice (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469739</id><title>Long-term potentiation at pyramidal cell to somatostatin interneuron synapses controls hippocampal network plasticity and memory (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291723+00:00</updated><author><name>Azam Asgarihafshejani</name></author><author><name>Ève Honoré</name></author><author><name>François-Xavier Michon</name></author><author><name>Isabel Laplante</name></author><author><name>Jean-Claude Lacaille</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hippocampal somatostatin (SOM) cells are dendrite-projecting inhibitory interneurons. CA1 SOM cells receive major excitatory inputs from pyramidal cells (PC-SOM synapses) which show mGluR1a- and mTORC1-mediated long-term potentiation (LTP). PC-SOM synapse LTP contributes to CA1 network metaplasticity and memory consolidation, but whether it is sufficient to regulate these processes remains unknown. Here we used optogenetic stimulation of CA1 pyramidal cells and whole cell recordings in slices to show that optogenetic theta burst stimulation (TBS&lt;sub&gt;opto&lt;/sub&gt;) produces LTP at PC-SOM synapses. At the network level, we found that TBS&lt;sub&gt;opto&lt;/sub&gt; differentially regulates metaplasticity of pyramidal cell inputs: enhancing LTP at Schaffer collateral synapses and depressing LTP at temporo-ammonic synapses. At the behavioral level, we uncovered that in vivo TBS&lt;sub&gt;opto&lt;/sub&gt; regulates learning-induced LTP at PC-SOM synapses, as well as contextual fear memory. Thus, LTP of PC-SOM synapses is a long-term feedback mechanism controlling pyramidal cell synaptic plasticity, sufficient to regulate memory consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469739" rel="alternate" title="Long-term potentiation at pyramidal cell to somatostatin interneuron synapses controls hippocampal network plasticity and memory (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469851</id><title>Prefrontal, striatal, and VTA subnetwork dynamics during novelty and exploration (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291850+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam J.O. Dede</name></author><author><name>Nader Marzban</name></author><author><name>Ashutosh Mishra</name></author><author><name>Robert Reichert</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Michael X Cohen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple distinct brain areas have been implicated in memory including the prefrontal cortex (PFC), striatum (STR), and ventral tegmental area (VTA). Information-exchange across these widespread networks requires flexible coordination at a fine time-scale. In the present study, we collected high-density recordings from the PFC, STR, and VTA of male rats during baseline, encoding, consolidation, and retrieval stages of memory formation. Novel sub-regional clustering analyses identified patterns of spatially restricted, temporally coherent, and frequency specific signals that were reproducible across days and were modulated by behavioral states. Clustering identified miniscule patches of neural tissue. Generalized eigen decomposition (GED) reduced each cluster to a single time series. Amplitude envelope correlation of the cluster time series was used to assess functional connectivity between clusters. Dense intra- and inter regional functional connectivity characterized the baseline period, with delta oscillations playing an outsized role. There was a dramatic pruning of network connectivity during encoding. Connectivity rebounded during consolidation, but connections in the theta band became stronger, and those in the delta band were weaker. Finally, during retrieval, connections were not as severely reduced as they had been during encoding, and specifically theta and higher-frequency connections were stronger. Underlying these connectivity changes, the anatomical extent of clusters observed in the gamma band in the PFC and in both the gamma and delta bands in the VTA changed markedly across behavioral conditions. These results demonstrate the brain’s ability to reorganize functionally at both the intra- and inter-regional levels during different stages of memory processing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The brain is often thought of as a mosaic of areas each with static functions that activate or deactivate with task demands. Here, we used large-scale recordings (196 simultaneous electrodes) and developed a multivariate analysis approach to analyze data from all our recording locations simultaneously. This analysis revealed that the brain dramatically reorganized itself at both local and long-distance spatial scales during different stages of memory processing. These results demonstrate an extreme degree of flexibility in functional anatomy. Rather than thinking about the brain as a set of static mosaic tiles, it may better be characterized as a quickly moldable piece of clay where each part’s function changes as the whole is reshaped from moment to moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469851" rel="alternate" title="Prefrontal, striatal, and VTA subnetwork dynamics during novelty and exploration (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469689</id><title>Is categorization in visual working memory a way to reduce mental effort? A pupillometry study (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.291980+00:00</updated><author><name>Cherie Zhou</name></author><author><name>Monicque M. Lorist</name></author><author><name>Sebastiaan Mathôt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent studies on visual working memory (VWM) have shown that visual information can be stored in VWM as continuous (e.g., a specific shade of red) as well as categorical representations (e.g., the general category red). It has been widely assumed, yet never directly tested, that continuous representations require more VWM mental effort than categorical representations; given limited VWM capacity, this would mean that fewer continuous, as compared to categorical, representations can be maintained simultaneously. We tested this assumption by measuring pupil size, as a proxy for mental effort, in a delayed estimation task. Participants memorized one to four ambiguous (boundaries between adjacent color categories) or prototypical colors to encourage continuous or categorical representations, respectively; after a delay, a probe indicated the location of the to-be-reported color. We found that, for set size 1, pupil size was larger while maintaining ambiguous as compared to prototypical colors, but without any difference in memory precision; this suggests that participants relied on an effortful continuous representation to maintain a single ambiguous color, thus resulting in pupil dilation while preserving precision. In contrast, for set size 2 and higher, pupil size was equally large while maintaining ambiguous and prototypical colors, but memory precision was now substantially reduced for ambiguous colors; this suggests that participants now also relied on categorical representations for ambiguous colors (which are by definition a poor fit to any category), thus reducing memory precision but not resulting in pupil dilation. Taken together, our results suggest that continuous representations are more effortful than categorical representations, and that very few continuous representations (perhaps only one) can be maintained simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visual working memory (VWM) can store visual information in two more-or-less distinct formats: continuous and categorical representations. It is widely assumed that VWM capacity for continuous representations is more limited than for categorical representations, yet this assumption has never been explicitly tested. Here we address this crucial question of whether continuous representations cost more resources, and as a consequence limits VWM capacity, as compared to categorical representations. To do so, we measured pupil size (as a proxy for mental effort) and memory performance in a delayed estimation task. Crucially, our results suggest that continuous representations are more effortful than categorical representations, and that only one continuous representation can be maintained in VWM at one time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469689" rel="alternate" title="Is categorization in visual working memory a way to reduce mental effort? A pupillometry study (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469580</id><title>Cholinergic control of striatal GABAergic microcircuits (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292094+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Kocaturk</name></author><author><name>F. Shah</name></author><author><name>B. Guven</name></author><author><name>J.M. Tepper</name></author><author><name>M. Assous</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cholinergic interneurons (CINs) are essential elements of striatal circuits and behaviors. While acetylcholine signaling via muscarinic receptors (mAChRs) have been well studied, more recent data indicate that postsynaptic nicotinic receptors (nAChRs) located on GABAergic interneurons (GINs) are equally critical. One demonstration is that CINs stimulation induces large disynaptic inhibition of SPNs mediated by nAChR activation of striatal GINs. While these circuits are ideally positioned to modulate striatal output activity, the neurons involved are not definitively identified due largely to an incomplete mapping of CINs-GINs interconnections. Here, we show that CINs optogenetic activation evokes an intricate dual mechanism involving co-activation of pre- and postsynaptic mAChRs and nAChRs on four GINs populations. Using multi-optogenetics, we demonstrate the participation of tyrosine hydroxylase-expressing GINs in the disynaptic inhibition of SPNs likely via heterotypic electrical coupling with neurogliaform interneurons. Altogether, our results highlight the importance of CINs in regulating GINs microcircuits via complex synaptic/heterosynaptic mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469580" rel="alternate" title="Cholinergic control of striatal GABAergic microcircuits (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.469673</id><title>Does the brain care about averages? A simple test. (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292219+00:00</updated><author><name>Alejandro Tlaie</name></author><author><name>Katharine A Shapcott</name></author><author><name>Paul Tiesinga</name></author><author><name>Marieke Schölvinck</name></author><author><name>Martha N Havenith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trial-averaged metrics, e.g. in the form of tuning curves and population response vectors, are a basic and widely accepted way of characterizing neuronal activity. But how relevant are such trial-averaged responses to neuronal computation itself? Here we present a simple test to estimate whether average responses reflect aspects of neuronal activity that contribute to neuronal processing in a specific context. The test probes two assumptions inherent in the usage of average neuronal metrics: 1) Reliability: Neuronal responses repeat consistently enough across single stimulus instances that the average response template they relate to remains recognizable to downstream regions. 2) Behavioural relevance: If a single-trial response is more similar to the average template, this should make it easier for the animal to identify the correct stimulus or action. We apply this test to a large publicly available data set featuring electrophysiological recordings from 42 cortical areas in behaving mice. In this data set, we show that single-trial responses were less correlated to the average response template than one would expect if they simply represented discrete versions of the template, down-sampled to a finite number of spikes. Moreover, single-trial responses were barely stimulus-specific — they could not be clearly assigned to the average response template of one stimulus. Most importantly, better-matched single-trial responses did not predict accurate behaviour for any of the recorded cortical areas. We conclude that in this data set, average responses do not seem particularly relevant to neuronal computation in a majority of brain areas, and we encourage other researchers to apply similar tests when using trial-averaged neuronal metrics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.469673" rel="alternate" title="Does the brain care about averages? A simple test. (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469461</id><title>Impaired astrocytic Ca2+ signalling in awake Alzheimer’s disease transgenic mice (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292345+00:00</updated><author><name>Knut Sindre Åbjørsbråten</name></author><author><name>Gry H. E. Syverstad Skaaraas</name></author><author><name>Céline Cunen</name></author><author><name>Daniel M. Bjørnstad</name></author><author><name>Kristin M. Gullestad Binder</name></author><author><name>Vidar Jensen</name></author><author><name>Lars N.G. Nilsson</name></author><author><name>Shreyas B. Rao</name></author><author><name>Wannan Tang</name></author><author><name>Gudmund Horn Hermansen</name></author><author><name>Erlend A. Nagelhus</name></author><author><name>Ole Petter Ottersen</name></author><author><name>Reidun Torp</name></author><author><name>Rune Enger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Increased astrocytic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling related to amyloid plaques has been shown in Alzheimer’s disease mouse models, but to date no reports have characterized behaviorally induced astrocytic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signalling in such mice without the confounding effects of anesthesia. Here, we employ an event-based algorithm to assess astrocytic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals in the neocortex of awake-behaving tg-ArcSwe mice and non-transgenic wildtype littermates while monitoring pupil responses and behavior. We demonstrate an attenuated astrocytic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; response to locomotion and an uncoupling of pupil responses and astrocytic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signalling in 15-months old plaque-bearing mice. This points to a potential decoupling of neuromodulatory activation and astrocytic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; activity, which may account for some of the cognitive dysfunctions observed in Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469461" rel="alternate" title="Impaired astrocytic Ca2+ signalling in awake Alzheimer’s disease transgenic mice (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469511</id><title>Adaptive coding of stimulus information in human fronto-parietal cortex during visual classification (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292526+00:00</updated><author><name>David Wisniewski</name></author><author><name>Carlos González-García</name></author><author><name>Silvia Formica</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Woolgar</name></author><author><name>Marcel Brass</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our ability to flexibly adapt to changing demands is supported by flexible coding of task-relevant information in frontal and parietal brain regions. Converging evidence suggest that coding of stimuli and task rules in these regions become stronger as task difficulty increases. Here, we tested whether there is a corresponding change in the representational format as well, an issue that has rarely been addressed directly in past research. Participants performed a visual classification task under varying levels of perceptual difficulty, while we acquired fMRI. Using a model-based representational similarity approach, we tested whether stimulus representations retain exemplar-level information. We expected representations to drop such exemplar-level information as perceptual difficulty increases, which would indicate a focus on representing behaviorally relevant category information. Counter to these expectations, and in contrast to previous research, we found frontal and parietal brain regions contained exemplar-level stimulus information. Interestingly, the anterior intraparietal sulcus (aIPS) retained exemplar-level stimulus information even in perceptually difficult trials, and these representations were directly related to performance. Overall, these findings call for a reassessment of the neural mechanisms underlying human adaptive behavior during visual classification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469511" rel="alternate" title="Adaptive coding of stimulus information in human fronto-parietal cortex during visual classification (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469921</id><title>A fully automated FAIMS-DIA proteomic pipeline for high-throughput characterization of iPSC-derived neurons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292657+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke Reilly</name></author><author><name>Lirong Peng</name></author><author><name>Erika Lara</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ramos</name></author><author><name>Michael Fernandopulle</name></author><author><name>Caroline B. Pantazis</name></author><author><name>Julia Stadler</name></author><author><name>Marianita Santiana</name></author><author><name>Anant Dadu</name></author><author><name>James Iben</name></author><author><name>Faraz Faghri</name></author><author><name>Mike A. Nalls</name></author><author><name>Steven L. Coon</name></author><author><name>Priyanka Narayan</name></author><author><name>Andrew B. Singleton</name></author><author><name>Mark R. Cookson</name></author><author><name>Michael E. Ward</name></author><author><name>Yue A. Qi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fully automated proteomic pipelines have the potential to achieve deep coverage of cellular proteomes with high throughput and scalability. However, it is important to evaluate performance, including both reproducibility and ability to provide meaningful levels of biological insight. Here, we present an approach combining high field asymmetric waveform ion mobility spectrometer (FAIMS) interface and data independent acquisition (DIA) proteomics approach developed as part of the induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) Neurodegenerative Disease Initiative (iNDI), a large-scale effort to understand how inherited diseases may manifest in neuronal cells. Our FAIMS-DIA approach identified more than 8000 proteins per mass spectrometry (MS) acquisition as well as superior total identification, reproducibility, and accuracy compared to other existing DIA methods. Next, we applied this approach to perform a longitudinal proteomic profiling of the differentiation of iPSC-derived neurons from the KOLF2.1J parental line used in iNDI. This analysis demonstrated a steady increase in expression of mature cortical neuron markers over the course of neuron differentiation. We validated the performance of our proteomics pipeline by comparing it to single cell RNA-Seq datasets obtained in parallel, confirming expression of key markers and cell type annotations. An interactive webapp of this temporal data is available for aligned-UMAP visualization and data browsing (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://share.streamlit.io/anant-droid/singlecellumap"&gt;https://share.streamlit.io/anant-droid/singlecellumap&lt;/ext-link&gt;). In summary, we report an extensively optimized and validated proteomic pipeline that will be suitable for large-scale studies such as iNDI.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469921" rel="alternate" title="A fully automated FAIMS-DIA proteomic pipeline for high-throughput characterization of iPSC-derived neurons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469804</id><title>Three heads are better than one: Cooperative learning brains wire together when a consensus is reached (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292855+00:00</updated><author><name>Yafeng Pan</name></author><author><name>Xiaojun Cheng</name></author><author><name>Yi Hu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Theories of human learning converge on the view that individuals working together learn better than do those working alone. Little is known, however, about the neural mechanisms of learning through cooperation. We addressed this research gap by leveraging functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) to record the brain activity of triad members in a group simultaneously. Triads were instructed to analyze an ancient Chinese poem either cooperatively or independently. Four main findings emerged. First, we observed significant within-group neural synchronization (GNS) in the left superior temporal cortex, supramarginal gyrus, and postcentral gyrus during cooperative learning compared to independent learning. Second, the enhancement of GNS in triads was amplified when a consensus was reached (vs. elaboration or argument) during cooperative learning. Third, GNS was predictive of learning outcome at an early stage (156-170 s after learning was initiated). Fourth, social factors such as social closeness (e.g., how much learners liked one other) were reflected in GNS and co-varied with learning engagement. These results provide neurophysiological support for Piaget’s theory of cognitive development and favor the notion that successful learning through cooperation involves dynamic consensus building, which is captured in neural patterns shared across learners in a group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Converging evidence has shown that cooperative learning is more effective than independent learning. An influential pedagogical theory postulates that learners benefit from cooperation through different forms of cognitive elaboration, such as providing elaborated clarifications to others. Alternatively, Piaget’s theory of cognitive development posits that cooperation encourages learners with diverse opinions to reach a consensus during the learning process. Here, we report that unlike individuals who worked alone, the brains of students who worked cooperatively with one another became synchronized. This within-group neural synchronization (GNS) was magnified when learners built mutual consensuses. These findings suggest that successful cooperative learning involves dynamic consensus building, which is reflected in the interpersonal coordination of cerebral activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469804" rel="alternate" title="Three heads are better than one: Cooperative learning brains wire together when a consensus is reached (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469557</id><title>Activation of peripheral neuronal FLT3 promotes exaggerated sensorial and emotional pain-related behaviors facilitating the transition from acute to chronic pain (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.292972+00:00</updated><author><name>Adrien Tassou</name></author><author><name>Maxime Thouaye</name></author><author><name>Damien Gilabert</name></author><author><name>Antoine Jouvenel</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Leyris</name></author><author><name>Corinne Sonrier</name></author><author><name>Lucie Diouloufet</name></author><author><name>Ilana Mechaly</name></author><author><name>Myriam Chentouf</name></author><author><name>Madeline Neiveyans</name></author><author><name>Martine Pugnière</name></author><author><name>Pierre Martineau</name></author><author><name>Bruno Robert</name></author><author><name>Xavier Capdevila</name></author><author><name>Jean Valmier</name></author><author><name>Cyril Rivat</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acute pain events have been associated with persistent pain sensitization of nociceptive pathways increasing the risk of transition from acute to chronic pain. However, it is unclear whether injury-induced persistent pain sensitization can promote long-term mood disorders. The receptor tyrosine kinase FLT3 is causally required for peripheral nerve injury-induced pain chronification, questioning its role in the development of pain-induced mood alterations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a model of paw incisional pain, mice underwent single (SI) or double incision (DI) and went through behavioral and molecular phenotyping with the evaluation of both sensorial and emotional pain components. The role of FLT3 was then investigated either by inhibition using transgenic knock-out mice and functional antibodies or by activation with FLT3 ligand (FL) administrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DI mice showed significant anxiodepressive-like and spontaneous pain behaviors while SI mice did not. DI also promoted and extended mechanical pain hypersensitivity compared to SI. This emotional and sensorial pain exaggeration correlated with a potentiation of spinal microglial activation after DI versus SI. Intrathecal minocycline, a microglial inhibitor, specifically reversed DI induced-mechanical hypersensitivity. Finally, FL injections in naive animals provoked mechanical allodynia and anxiodepressive-like disorders concomitant with a significant microglial activation while FLT3 inhibition blunted the development of persistent pain and depression after DI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results show for the first time that the repetition of a peripheral lesion facilitates not only exaggerated nociceptive behaviors but also anxiodepressive disorders. The inhibition of FLT3 could become a promising therapy in the management of pain sensitization and related mood alterations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469557" rel="alternate" title="Activation of peripheral neuronal FLT3 promotes exaggerated sensorial and emotional pain-related behaviors facilitating the transition from acute to chronic pain (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469670</id><title>Transection injury differentially alters the proteome of the human sural nerve (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.293232+00:00</updated><author><name>Monica J. Chau</name></author><author><name>Jorge E. Quintero</name></author><author><name>Eric Blalock</name></author><author><name>Christopher Samaan</name></author><author><name>Greg Gerhardt</name></author><author><name>Craig van Horne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Regeneration after severe peripheral nerve injury is often poor. Knowledge of human nerve regeneration and the growth microenvironment is greatly lacking. We aimed to identify the regenerative proteins in human peripheral nerve by comparing the proteome before and after a transection injury. In a unique study design, we collected from the same participants, samples from naïve and degenerating sural nerve. Naïve and degenerating (two weeks after injury) samples were analyzed using mass spectrometry and immunoassays. Using a correlation matrix, we found significantly altered levels following the nerve injury. Mass spectrometry revealed that post-injury samples had 672 proteins significantly upregulated and 661 significantly downregulated compared to naïve samples (q &amp;lt; 0.05, |FC| &amp;gt; 2). We used Gene Ontology pathways to highlight groups of proteins that were significantly upregulated or downregulated with injury-induced degeneration and regeneration. Significant protein changes in key pathways were identified including growth factor levels, Schwann cell de-differentiation, myelination downregulation, epithelial-mesenchymal transition, and axonal regeneration pathways. Having proteome signatures of human peripheral nerves of both the uninjured and the degenerating/regenerating state may serve as biomarkers to aid in the future development of repair strategies and in monitoring neural tissue regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469670" rel="alternate" title="Transection injury differentially alters the proteome of the human sural nerve (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470073</id><title>Nociceptive stimuli activate the hypothalamus-habenula circuit to inhibit the mesolimbic reward system (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.293367+00:00</updated><author><name>Hee Young Kim</name></author><author><name>Soo Min Lee</name></author><author><name>Yu Fan</name></author><author><name>Bonghyo Lee</name></author><author><name>Sang Chan Kim</name></author><author><name>Kyle B. Bills</name></author><author><name>Scott C. Steffensen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nociceptive signals interact with various regions of the brain, including those involved in physical sensation, reward, cognition, and emotion. Emerging evidence points to a role of nociception in the modulation of the mesolimbic reward system. The mechanism by which nociception affects dopamine (DA) signaling and reward is unclear. The lateral hypothalamus (LH) and the lateral habenula (LHb) receive somatosensory inputs and are structurally connected with the mesolimbic DA system. Here we show that the LH-LHb pathway is necessary for nociceptive modulation of this system. Our extracellular single-unit recordings and head-mounted microendoscopic calcium imaging revealed that nociceptive stimulation by tail-pinch excited LHb and LH neurons, which was inhibited by chemical lesion of the LH. Tail-pinch decreased extracellular DA release in the nucleus accumbens ventrolateral shell, which was blocked by disruption of the LH. Furthermore, tail-pinch attenuated cocaine-induced locomotor activity, 50-kHz ultrasonic vocalizations and reinstatement of cocaine-seeking behavior, which was inhibited by chemogenetic silencing of the LH-LHb pathway. Our findings suggest that nociceptive stimulation recruits the LH-LHb pathway to inhibit mesolimbic DA system and drug reinstatement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470073" rel="alternate" title="Nociceptive stimuli activate the hypothalamus-habenula circuit to inhibit the mesolimbic reward system (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469760</id><title>Comparison of neuromuscular junction dynamics following ischemic and aged skeletal muscle (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.293505+00:00</updated><author><name>Berna Aliya</name></author><author><name>Mahir Mohiuddin</name></author><author><name>Jeongmoon J. Choi</name></author><author><name>Gunjae Jeong</name></author><author><name>Innie Kang</name></author><author><name>Hannah Castels</name></author><author><name>Cade Jones</name></author><author><name>Young C. Jang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Both aging and neuromuscular diseases lead to significant changes in the morphology and functionality of the neuromuscular synapse. Skeletal muscles display a remarkable regenerative capacity, however, are still susceptible to diseases of aging and peripheral nerve perturbations. In this study, we assessed how neuromuscular synapses differ in aged and injured skeletal muscle using an improved neuromuscular junction (NMJ) staining and imaging method. We found that both aged and ischemic skeletal muscle display Wallerian degeneration of the presynaptic motor axons and fragmentation of postsynaptic acetylcholine receptors (AChRs). Quantifiable measurements of various metrics of the NMJs provide a more concrete idea of the dynamics that are occurring in the muscle microenvironment. We questioned whether neuronal degradation precedes myofiber atrophy or vice versa. Previously, it was shown that a cellular crosstalk exists among the motor neurons, myofibers, vasculature, and mitochondria within the muscle microdomain. It is apparent that lack of blood flow to motor neurons in ischemic skeletal muscle disrupts the structure of NMJs, however it is unclear if the aging condition experiences similar dynamics. We demonstrated that both aged and ischemic skeletal muscle demonstrate similar patterns of degeneration, characterized by a smaller percentage overlap of presynaptic and postsynaptic sides, greater fragmentation of AChRs, and a smaller area of AChR clusters. Together, these results reveal high resolution, precise parallels between the aged and ischemic NMJs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The goal of this study was to assess changes in presynaptic motor neurons and postsynaptic acetylcholine receptors following an ischemic injury model and compare this with an aging model. This was accomplished by characterizing key components of NMJ morphology, including overlap and size of the receptors. There is currently limited research investigating the cellular communication between skeletal muscle fibers and motor neurons. Additionally, there is limited work comparing neuromuscular remodeling in aged and young models. With the substantial prevalence of neuromuscular disorders, especially in the aging population, it is essential to understand nerve-muscle interactions in order to promote increased mobility and improved quality of life in both injury and aging models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469760" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of neuromuscular junction dynamics following ischemic and aged skeletal muscle (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470078</id><title>Reversible brain edema in experimental cerebral malaria is associated with transcellular blood-brain barrier disruption and delayed microhemorrhages (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.293650+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelika Hoffmann</name></author><author><name>Jessica Jin</name></author><author><name>Mame Aida</name></author><author><name>Chi Ho Wai</name></author><author><name>Sanjib Mohanty</name></author><author><name>Praveen K. Sahu</name></author><author><name>Rajyabardham Pattnaik</name></author><author><name>Lukas Pirpamer</name></author><author><name>Manuel Fischer</name></author><author><name>Sabine Heiland</name></author><author><name>Michael Lanzer</name></author><author><name>Friedrich Frischknecht</name></author><author><name>Ann-Kristin Mueller</name></author><author><name>Johannes Pfeil</name></author><author><name>Megharay Majhi</name></author><author><name>Marek Cyrklaff</name></author><author><name>Samuel C. Wassmer</name></author><author><name>Martin Bendszus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain swelling occurs in cerebral malaria (CM) and may either reverse or result in fatal outcome. It is currently unknown how brain swelling in CM reverses, as investigations have been hampered by inadequate animal models. In this study, we show that reversible brain swelling in experimental murine cerebral malaria (ECM) can be induced reliably after single vaccination with radiation-attenuated sporozoites as revealed by  in vivo  high-field (9.4T) magnetic resonance imaging. Our results provide evidence that parenchymal fluid increase and consecutive brain swelling results from transcellular blood-brain barrier disruption (BBBD), as revealed by electron microscopy. This mechanism enables reversal of brain swelling but does not prevent persistent focal brain damage, evidenced by microhemorrhages, in areas of most severe BBBD. In a cohort of 27 pediatric and adult CM patients (n=4 fatal, n=23 non-fatal) two out of four fatal CM patients (50%) and 8 out of 23 non-fatal CM patients (35%) showed microhemorrhages on MRI at clinical field strength of 1.5T, emphasizing the translational potential of the experimental model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470078" rel="alternate" title="Reversible brain edema in experimental cerebral malaria is associated with transcellular blood-brain barrier disruption and delayed microhemorrhages (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469282</id><title>The gendered self: Evidence for differences in whole-brain dynamics (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.293849+00:00</updated><author><name>Carme Uribe</name></author><author><name>Anira Escrichs</name></author><author><name>Eleonora de Filippi</name></author><author><name>Yonatan Sanz-Perl</name></author><author><name>Carme Junque</name></author><author><name>Esther Gomez-Gil</name></author><author><name>Morten L Kringelbach</name></author><author><name>Antonio Guillamon</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Deco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How the brain constructs gender identity is largely unknown, but some neural differences have recently been discovered. Here, we used an intrinsic-ignition framework to investigate if gender identity changes the propagation of the neural activity across the whole-brain network and within resting-state networks. Studying 29 transmen and 17 transwomen with gender incongruence, 22 ciswomen, and 19 cismen, we computed the capability of a given brain area in space to propagate activity to other areas (mean-ignition) and its variability across time (node-metastability). We found that both measures differentiated all four groups across the whole-brain network. Furthermore, at the network level, we found that compared to the other groups, cismen showed higher mean-ignition of the dorsal attention network and node-metastability of the dorsal and ventral attention, executive control, and temporal parietal networks. We also found mean-ignition differences between cismen and ciswomen within the executive control network, but higher in ciswomen than cismen and transmen for the default-mode network. For the node-metastability, this was higher in cismen compared to ciswomen in the somatomotor network, while both mean-ignition and node-metastability were higher for cismen than transmen in the limbic network. Finally, we computed correlations between both measures and their body image scores. Transmen dissatisfaction, cismen, and ciswomen satisfaction towards their own body image were distinctively associated with specific networks per group. Overall, the study of the whole-brain network dynamical complexity discriminates binary gender identity groups, and functional connectivity dynamics approaches are needed to disentangle the complex understanding of the gendered self.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study of sex/gender differences may be enriched by the heterogeneity of other gender minority groups, such as transgender. Functional connectivity measures capturing the spatio-temporal oscillations of the brain can provide insights on how the brain cooperates. This is the first study investigating how the whole-brain network propagates information across the brain, spatially and temporally, in binary gender groups (cisgender and transgender) by means of the intrinsic-ignition framework. We found four whole-brain unique phenotypes pertaining to each gender group, namely cismen, ciswomen, transmen and transwomen. Novel functional connectivity dynamics frameworks can contribute to disentangle the complex experience of a &lt;italic&gt;gendered&lt;/italic&gt;-self.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469282" rel="alternate" title="The gendered self: Evidence for differences in whole-brain dynamics (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469748</id><title>Demyelination induces transcriptional reprograming in proprioceptive and Aβ rapidly adapting low-threshold-mechanoreceptor neurons (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294000+00:00</updated><author><name>Benayahu Elbaz</name></author><author><name>Lite Yang</name></author><author><name>Braesen Lee Rader</name></author><author><name>Riki Kawaguchi</name></author><author><name>Maria Traka</name></author><author><name>Clifford J Woolf</name></author><author><name>William Renthal</name></author><author><name>Brian Popko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Schwann cells, the main glial cell in the peripheral nervous system (PNS), ensheath bundles of small unmyelinated axons or form myelin on larger axons. PNS injuries initiate transcriptional reprograming in both Schwann cells and sensory neurons that promotes regeneration. While the factors that initiate the transcriptional reprograming in Schwann cells are well characterized, the full range of stimuli that initiate this reprograming in sensory neurons remain elusive. Here, using a genetic model of Schwann cell ablation, we find that Schwann cell loss results in transient PNS demyelination without overt axonal loss. By profiling sensory ganglia at single-cell resolution we show that this demyelination induces transcriptional reprogramming preferably in proprioceptive and Aβ RA-LTMR neurons. Transcriptional reprograming is assumed to be a cell autonomous response of sensory neurons to mechanical axonal injury. By identifying similar reprograming in non-injured, demyelinated neurons, our study suggests that this reprograming represents a non-cell autonomous transcriptional response of sensory neurons to the loss of axon-Schwann cell interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ablation of Schwann cells results in transient PNS demyelination, without overt axonal loss.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Schwann cell loss results in transcriptional reprograming in specific sensory neurons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spinal nerve transection (mechanical injury of axons) and demyelination (intact axons) induces similar transcriptional responses in DRG neurons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transcriptional response to demyelination among DRG neurons is specific to the large myelinated proprioceptive and Aβ RA-LTMR neurons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469748" rel="alternate" title="Demyelination induces transcriptional reprograming in proprioceptive and Aβ rapidly adapting low-threshold-mechanoreceptor neurons (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.470186</id><title>Dopamine release in nucleus accumbens is under tonic inhibition by adenosine A1 receptors regulated by astrocytic ENT1 and dysregulated by ethanol (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294144+00:00</updated><author><name>Bradley M Roberts</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Lambert</name></author><author><name>Jessica A Livesey</name></author><author><name>Zhaofa Wu</name></author><author><name>Yulong Li</name></author><author><name>Stephanie J M Cragg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Striatal adenosine A1 receptor (A1R) activation can inhibit dopamine release. A1Rs on other striatal neurons are activated by an adenosine tone that is limited by equilibrative nucleoside transporter 1 (ENT1) that is enriched on astrocytes and is ethanol-sensitive. We explored whether dopamine release in nucleus accumbens core is under tonic inhibition by A1Rs, and is regulated by astrocytic ENT1 and ethanol. In ex vivo striatal slices from male and female mice, A1R agonists inhibited dopamine release evoked electrically or optogenetically and detected using fast-scan cyclic voltammetry, most strongly for lower stimulation frequencies and pulse numbers, thereby enhancing the activity-dependent contrast of dopamine release. Conversely, A1R antagonists reduced activity-dependent contrast but enhanced evoked dopamine release levels, even for single optogenetic pulses indicating an underlying tonic inhibition. The ENT1 inhibitor NBTI reduced dopamine release and promoted A1R-mediated inhibition, and conversely, virally-mediated astrocytic overexpression of ENT1 enhanced dopamine release and relieved A1R-mediated inhibition. By imaging the genetically encoded fluorescent adenosine sensor GRAB-Ado, we identified a striatal extracellular adenosine tone that was elevated by the ENT1 inhibitor and sensitive to gliotoxin fluorocitrate. Finally, we identified that ethanol (50 mM) promoted A1R-mediated inhibition of dopamine release, through diminishing adenosine uptake via ENT1. Together, these data reveal that dopamine output dynamics are gated by a striatal adenosine tone, limiting amplitude but promoting contrast, regulated by ENT1, and promoted by ethanol. These data add to the diverse mechanisms through which ethanol modulates striatal dopamine, and to emerging datasets supporting astrocytic transporters as important regulators of striatal function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.27.470186" rel="alternate" title="Dopamine release in nucleus accumbens is under tonic inhibition by adenosine A1 receptors regulated by astrocytic ENT1 and dysregulated by ethanol (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469495</id><title>The different brain areas occupied for integrating information of hierarchical linguistic units: a study based on EEG and TMS (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294276+00:00</updated><author><name>Changfu Pei</name></author><author><name>Yuan Qiu</name></author><author><name>Fali Li</name></author><author><name>Xunan Huang</name></author><author><name>Yajing Si</name></author><author><name>Yuqin Li</name></author><author><name>Xiabing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Chunli Chen</name></author><author><name>Qiang Liu</name></author><author><name>Zehong Cao</name></author><author><name>Nai Ding</name></author><author><name>Shan Gao</name></author><author><name>Kimmo Alho</name></author><author><name>Dezhong Yao</name></author><author><name>Peng Xu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human linguistic units are hierarchical, and our brain responds differently when processing linguistic units during sentence comprehension, especially when the modality of the received signal is different (auditory, visual, or audio-visual). However, it is unclear how the brain processes and integrates language information at different linguistic units (words, phrases, and sentences) provided simultaneously in audio and visual modalities. To address the issue, we presented participants with sequences of short Chinese sentences through auditory or visual or combined audio- visual modalities, while electroencephalographic responses were recorded. With a frequency tagging approach, we analyzed the neural representations of basic linguistic units (i.e., characters/monosyllabic words) and higher-level linguistic structures (i.e., phrases and sentences) across the three modalities separately. We found that audio-visual integration occurs at all linguistic units, and the brain areas involved in the integration varied across different linguistic levels. In particular, the integration of sentences activated the local left prefrontal area. Therefore, we used continuous theta-burst stimulation (cTBS) to verify that the left prefrontal cortex plays a vital role in the audio-visual integration of sentence information. Our findings suggest the advantage of bimodal language comprehension at hierarchical stages in language-related information processing and provide evidence for the causal role of the left prefrontal regions in processing information of audio-visual sentences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469495" rel="alternate" title="The different brain areas occupied for integrating information of hierarchical linguistic units: a study based on EEG and TMS (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469359</id><title>Visual Attention in The Fovea and The Periphery during Visual Search (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294457+00:00</updated><author><name>Jie Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaocang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Wang</name></author><author><name>Hossein Esteky</name></author><author><name>Yonghong Tian</name></author><author><name>Robert Desimone</name></author><author><name>Huihui Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Visual search depends on both the foveal and peripheral visual system, yet the foveal attention mechanisms is still lack of insights. We simultaneously recorded the foveal and peripheral activities in V4, IT and LPFC, while monkeys performed a category-based visual search task. Feature attention enhanced responses of Face-selective, House-selective, and Non-selective foveal cells in visual cortex. While foveal attention effects appeared no matter the peripheral attention effects, paying attention to the foveal stimulus dissipated the peripheral feature attentional effects, and delayed the peripheral spatial attentional effects. When target features appeared both in the foveal and the peripheral, feature attention effects seemed to occur predominately in the foveal, which might not distribute across the visual field according to common view of distributed feature attention effects. As a result, the parallel attentive process seemed to occur during distractor fixations, while the serial process predominated during target fixations in visual search.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469359" rel="alternate" title="Visual Attention in The Fovea and The Periphery during Visual Search (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469296</id><title>Long-term decreased cannabinoid type-1 receptor activity restores specific neurological phenotypes in the Ts65Dn mouse model of Down syndrome (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294596+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Vázquez-Oliver</name></author><author><name>Silvia Pérez-García</name></author><author><name>Nieves Pizarro</name></author><author><name>Laura Molina-Porcel</name></author><author><name>Rafael de la Torre</name></author><author><name>Rafael Maldonado</name></author><author><name>Andrés Ozaita</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intellectual disability is the most prevalent and limiting hallmark of Down syndrome (DS), without any pharmacological treatment available. Neurodegeneration and neuroinflammation are relevant neurological features of DS reaching to early development of Alzheimer’s disease. Preclinical evidence suggests that the endocannabinoid system, an important neuromodulator on cognition and neuroinflammation, could act as beneficial target in DS. Indeed, cannabinoid type-1 receptor (CB1R) activity was enhanced in the hippocampus of young-adult trisomic Ts65Dn mice, a well-characterized surrogate model of DS. In previous studies, inhibition of CB1R, was able to restore key neurological deficits in this mouse model. To determine the possible clinical relevance of this target, it is mandatory to evaluate the long-term consequences of attenuated CB1R activity and to minimize the possible side-effects associated to this mechanism. We found that CB1R expression was significantly enhanced in the hippocampus brains of aged DS subjects. Similarly, middle-aged trisomic mice showed enhanced CB1R expression. Long-term oral administration of a low dose of the CB1R specific antagonist rimonabant was administered to male and female Ts65Dn trisomic and wild-type mice from the time of weaning to 10 months, an age when signs of neurodegeneration have been described in the model. CB1R inhibition resulted in significant cognitive improvement in novel object-recognition memory in trisomic male and female mice, reaching a similar performance to that of wild-type littermates. Interestingly, this long-term rimonabant treatment modify locomotor activity, anxiety-like behavior, body weight or survival rates. Brain analysis at 10 months of age revealed noradrenergic and cholinergic neurodegeneration signs in trisomic mice that were not modified by the treatment, although the alterations in hippocampal microglia morphology shown by vehicle-treated trisomic mice was normalized in trisomic mice exposed to rimonabant. Altogether, our results demonstrate a sustained pro-cognitive effect of CB1R inhibition at doses that do not produce major side effects that could be associated to an anti-inflammatory action, suggesting a potential interest in this target of to preserve cognitive functionality in DS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469296" rel="alternate" title="Long-term decreased cannabinoid type-1 receptor activity restores specific neurological phenotypes in the Ts65Dn mouse model of Down syndrome (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470102</id><title>Time course of EEG power during creative problem-solving with insight or remote thinking (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294733+00:00</updated><author><name>Theophile Bieth</name></author><author><name>Marcela Ovando-Tellez</name></author><author><name>Alizee Lopez-Persem</name></author><author><name>Beatrice Garcin</name></author><author><name>Laurent Hugueville</name></author><author><name>Katia Lehongre</name></author><author><name>Richard Levy</name></author><author><name>Nathalie George</name></author><author><name>Emmanuelle Volle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Problem-solving often requires creativity and is critical in everyday life. However, the neurocognitive mechanisms underlying creative problem-solving remain poorly understood. Two mechanisms have been highlighted: forming new connections from and between the problem elements and insight solving (with a sudden realization of a solution). We examined EEG activity during an adapted version of a classical insight problem task, the Remote Associates Test, that requires finding a word connecting three words. It allowed us to explore remoteness in semantic connections (by varying the remoteness of the solution word across trials) and insight solving (identified as a "Eureka" moment reported by the participants). Semantic remoteness was associated with a power increase in alpha band (8-12Hz) in a left parieto-temporal cluster, beta band (13-30Hz) in a right fronto-temporal cluster in the early phase of the task, and theta band (3-7Hz) in frontal cluster before the participants responded. Insight solving was associated with power increase preceding the response in alpha and gamma band (31-60Hz) in left temporal clusters and theta band in a frontal cluster. Source reconstructions show the brain regions associated with these clusters. Overall, our findings shed new light on the dynamic of some of the mechanisms involved in creative problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470102" rel="alternate" title="Time course of EEG power during creative problem-solving with insight or remote thinking (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469864</id><title>An exploratory study of EEG connectivity during the first year of life in preterm and full-term infants (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.294880+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduardo Gonzalez-Moreira</name></author><author><name>Deirel Paz-Linares</name></author><author><name>Lourdes Cubero-Rego</name></author><author><name>Ariosky Areces-Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Pedro Antonio Valdes-Sosa</name></author><author><name>Thalia Harmony</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aim: to evaluate EEG connectivity during the first year of age in healthy full-term infants and preterm infants with prenatal and perinatal risk factors for perinatal brain damage.
Methods: Three groups of infants were studied: healthy at full-term infants (n = 71), moderate and late preterm infants (n = 54), and very preterm infants (n = 56). All preterm infants had perinatal or/and perinatal risk factors for brain damage.  EEG was obtained during phase II of natural NREM sleep. EEG analysis was performed in 24 segments of 2.56 s free of artifacts. For the calculation of EEG sources, the spectral Structured Sparse Bayesian Learning (sSSBL) was used. Connectivity was computed by the phase-lag index.
Results: In healthy full-term infants, EEG interhemispheric connectivity in the different frequency bands followed similar trends with age to those reported in each frequency band: delta connectivity decreases, theta increases at the end of the year, in the alpha band, different trends were observed according to the region studied, and beta interhemispheric connectivity decreases with age. EEG connectivity in preterm infants showed differences from the results of the term group.
Discussion: Important structural findings may explain the differences observed in EEG connectivity between the term and preterm groups.
Conclusion: The study of EEG connectivity during the first year of age gives essential information on normal and abnormal brain development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.24.469864" rel="alternate" title="An exploratory study of EEG connectivity during the first year of life in preterm and full-term infants (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469972</id><title>A LRRK2/dLRRK-mediated lysosomal pathway that contributes to glial cell death and DA neuron survival (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295013+00:00</updated><author><name>Linfang Wang</name></author><author><name>Honglei Wang</name></author><author><name>Margaret S. Ho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations in &lt;italic&gt;leucine-rich repeat kinase 2&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;LRRK2&lt;/italic&gt;) are the most common cause of familial and sporadic Parkinson’s disease (PD). A plethora of evidence has indicated a role for LRRK2 in endolysosomal trafficking in neurons, while LRRK2 function in glia, although highly expressed, remains largely unknown. Here we present evidence that LRRK2/dLRRK mediates a glial lysosomal pathway that contributes to the mechanism of PD. Independent of its kinase activity, glial LRRK2/dLRRK knockdown in the immortalized microglial cells or flies results in enlarged and swelling lysosomes fewer in number. These lysosomes are less mobile, wrongly acidified, and exhibit defective membrane permeability and reduced activity of the lysosome hydrolase cathespin B. In addition, microglial LRRK2 depletion causes increased &lt;italic&gt;Caspase&lt;/italic&gt; 3 levels, leading to glial apoptosis, dopaminergic neurodegeneration, and locomotor deficits in an age-dependent manner. Taken together, these findings demonstrate a functional role of LRRK2/dLRRK in regulating the glial lysosomal pathway; deficits in lysosomal biogenesis and function linking to glial apoptosis potentially underlie the mechanism of DA neurodegeneration, contributing to the progression of PD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469972" rel="alternate" title="A LRRK2/dLRRK-mediated lysosomal pathway that contributes to glial cell death and DA neuron survival (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469550</id><title>Human visual gamma for color stimuli: When LGN drive is equalized, red is not special (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295126+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Johannes Stauch</name></author><author><name>Alina Peter</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Ehrlich</name></author><author><name>Zora Nolte</name></author><author><name>Pascal Fries</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Strong gamma-band oscillations in primate early visual cortex can be induced by spatially homogeneous, high-contrast stimuli, such as color surfaces. Compared to other hues, particularly strong gamma oscillations have been reported for red stimuli. However, precortical color processing and the resultant strength of input to V1 has often not been fully controlled for. This leaves the possibility that stronger responses to some hues were due to differences in V1 input strength. We presented stimuli that had equal luminance and color contrast levels in a color coordinate system based on color responses of the lateral geniculate nucleus, the main input source for area V1. With these stimuli, we recorded magnetoencephalography in 30 human subjects. We found narrowband color-induced gamma oscillations in early visual cortex, which, contrary to previous reports, did not differ between red and green stimuli of equal L-M cone contrast. Notably, blue stimuli with contrast exclusively on the S-cone axis induced very weak gamma responses, as well as smaller event-related fields and poorer change detection performance. The strength of human color gamma responses could be well explained by the strength of thalamic input induced by each hue and does not show a clear red bias when this input strength is properly equalized.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469550" rel="alternate" title="Human visual gamma for color stimuli: When LGN drive is equalized, red is not special (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469650</id><title>Astrocytic expression of ALS-causative mutant FUS leads to TNFα-dependent neurodegeneration in vivo (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295252+00:00</updated><author><name>Brigid K. Jensen</name></author><author><name>Kevin J. McAvoy</name></author><author><name>Nicolette M. Heinsinger</name></author><author><name>Angelo C. Lepore</name></author><author><name>Hristelina Ilieva</name></author><author><name>Aaron R. Haeusler</name></author><author><name>Davide Trotti</name></author><author><name>Piera Pasinelli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic mutations that cause Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS), a progressively lethal motor neuron disease, are commonly found in ubiquitously expressed genes. In addition to direct defects within motor neurons, growing evidence suggests that dysfunction of non-neuronal cells is also an important driver of disease. Previously, we demonstrated that mutations in DNA/RNA binding protein Fused in Sarcoma (FUS) induce neurotoxic phenotypes in astrocytes &lt;italic&gt;in vitro,&lt;/italic&gt; via activation of the NF-κB pathway and release of pro-inflammatory cytokine TNFα. Here, we developed an intraspinal cord injection model to test whether astrocyte-specific expression of ALS-causative FUS&lt;sup&gt;R521G&lt;/sup&gt; variant (mtFUS) causes neuronal damage &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. We show that mtFUS expression causes TNFα upregulation, motor function deficits, and spinal motor neuron loss. We further demonstrate a lack of phenotype in TNFα knockout animals expressing mtFUS, and prevention of neurodegeneration in mtFUS-transduced animals through administration of TNFα neutralizing antibodies. Together, these studies strengthen evidence that astrocytes contribute to disease in ALS, establish that FUS-ALS astrocytes induce pathogenic changes to motor neurons &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, and provide insights identifying FUS-ALS specific potential therapeutic targets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469650" rel="alternate" title="Astrocytic expression of ALS-causative mutant FUS leads to TNFα-dependent neurodegeneration in vivo (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470264</id><title>Joint Learning of Full-structure Noise in Hierarchical Bayesian Regression Models (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295394+00:00</updated><author><name>Ali Hashemi</name></author><author><name>Chang Cai</name></author><author><name>Yijing Gao</name></author><author><name>Sanjay Ghosh</name></author><author><name>Klaus-Robert Müller</name></author><author><name>Srikantan Nagarajan</name></author><author><name>Stefan Haufe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We consider the reconstruction of brain activity from electroencephalography (EEG). This inverse problem can be formulated as a linear regression with independent Gaussian scale mixture priors for both the source and noise components. Crucial factors influencing accuracy of source estimation are not only the noise level but also its correlation structure, but existing approaches have not addressed estimation of noise covariance matrices with full structure. To address this shortcoming, we develop hierarchical Bayesian (type-II maximum likelihood) models for observations with latent variables for source and noise, which are estimated jointly from data. As an extension to classical sparse Bayesian learning (SBL), where across-sensor observations are assumed to be independent and identically distributed, we consider Gaussian noise with full covariance structure. Using the majorization-maximization framework and Riemannian geometry, we derive an efficient algorithm for updating the noise covariance along the manifold of positive definite matrices. We demonstrate that our algorithm has guaranteed and fast convergence and validate it in simulations and with real MEG data. Our results demonstrate that the novel framework significantly improves upon state-of-the-art techniques in the real-world scenario where the noise is indeed non-diagonal and fully-structured. Our method has applications in many domains beyond biomagnetic inverse problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470264" rel="alternate" title="Joint Learning of Full-structure Noise in Hierarchical Bayesian Regression Models (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470085</id><title>IL-37 expression reduces acute and chronic neuroinflammation and rescues cognitive impairment in an Alzheimer s disease mouse model (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295533+00:00</updated><author><name>Niklas Lonnemann</name></author><author><name>Shirin Hosseini</name></author><author><name>Melanie Ohm</name></author><author><name>Karsten Hiller</name></author><author><name>Charles A. Dinarello</name></author><author><name>Martin Korte</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The anti-inflammatory cytokine interleukin-37 (IL-37) is a member of the IL-1 family but not expressed in mice. We used a human IL 37 (hIL-37tg) expressing mouse, which has been subjected to various models of local and systemic inflammation as well as immunological challenges. Those studies demonstrate an immune-modulatory role of IL-37 which can be characterized as an important suppressor of innate immunity. We investigated the functions of IL-37 in the CNS and explored the effects of IL-37 on neuronal architecture and function, microglia phenotype, cytokine production and behavior after inflammatory challenge by intraperitoneal LPS-injection. Reduced spine density, activated microglia phenotype and impaired long-term potentiation (LTP) were observed in wild-type mice after LPS injection, whereas hIL-37tg mice showed no impairment. In addition, we crossed the hIL-37tg mouse with an animal model of Alzheimer's disease (APP/PS1) to investigate the anti-inflammatory properties of IL-37 under chronic neuroinflammatory conditions. Our results show that IL-37 is able to limit inflammation in the brain after acute inflammatory events and prevent the loss of cognitive abilities in a mouse model of AD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470085" rel="alternate" title="IL-37 expression reduces acute and chronic neuroinflammation and rescues cognitive impairment in an Alzheimer s disease mouse model (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469578</id><title>Resting state functional connectivity in relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis with mild disability – a data driven, whole brain multivoxel pattern analysis study (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295665+00:00</updated><author><name>Gowthami Nair</name></author><author><name>Sruthi S. Nair</name></author><author><name>K. M. Arun</name></author><author><name>Paul Camacho</name></author><author><name>Elshal Bava</name></author><author><name>Priya Ajayaghosh</name></author><author><name>Ramshekhar N. Menon</name></author><author><name>Muralidharan Nair</name></author><author><name>Chandrasekharan Kesavadas</name></author><author><name>Sheeba Arnold Anteraper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multivoxel pattern analysis (MVPA) has emerged as a powerful unbiased approach for generating seed regions of interest (ROIs) in resting-state functional connectivity (RSFC) analysis in a data-driven manner. The aim of the present study was to investigate RSFC differences between persons with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS) and healthy controls (HCs). We performed a whole-brain connectome-wide MVPA in 50 RRMS patients with expanded disability status scale ≤4 and 50 age and gender-matched HCs. Significant group differences were noted in RSFC in 9 clusters distributed in 7 regions; right middle frontal gyrus, frontal medial cortex, left frontal pole, anterior cingulate gyrus, right middle temporal gyrus, left posterior middle temporal gyrus and right lateral occipital cortex. Whole-brain seed-to-voxel RSFC characterization of these clusters as seed ROIs revealed significantly increased RSFC to the posterior brain regions (bilateral superior lateral occipital cortices, right lingual gyrus and left occipital pole) and reduced connectivity in the anterior and medial regions (right paracingulate gyrus, anterior cingulate gyrus, left amygdala and left frontal orbital cortex) in RRMS compared to HCs. The results of this study agree with the previous reports on abnormalities of RSFC in RRMS, the cognitive and clinical implications of which are discussed herein.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469578" rel="alternate" title="Resting state functional connectivity in relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis with mild disability – a data driven, whole brain multivoxel pattern analysis study (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469706</id><title>High-resolution mapping and digital atlas of subcortical regions in the macaque monkey based on matched MAP-MRI and histology (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295821+00:00</updated><author><name>Kadharbatcha S Saleem</name></author><author><name>Alexandru V Avram</name></author><author><name>Daniel Glen</name></author><author><name>Cecil Chern-Chyi Yen</name></author><author><name>Frank Q Ye</name></author><author><name>Michal Komlosh</name></author><author><name>Peter J Basser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Subcortical nuclei and other deep brain structures are known to play an important role in the regulation of the central and peripheral nervous systems. It can be difficult to identify and delineate many of these nuclei and their finer subdivisions in conventional MRI due to their small size, buried location, and often subtle contrast compared to neighboring tissue. To address this problem, we applied a multi-modal approach in &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; non-human primate (NHP) brain that includes high-resolution mean apparent propagator (MAP)-MRI and five different histological stains imaged with high-resolution microscopy in the brain of the same subject. By registering these high-dimensional MRI data to high-resolution histology data, we can map the location, boundaries, subdivisions, and micro-architectural features of subcortical gray matter regions in the macaque monkey brain. At high spatial resolution, diffusion MRI in general, and MAP-MRI in particular, can distinguish a large number of deep brain structures, including the larger and smaller white matter fiber tracts as well as architectonic features within various nuclei. Correlation with histology from the same brain enables a thorough validation of the structures identified with MAP-MRI. Moreover, anatomical details that are evident in images of MAP-MRI parameters are not visible in conventional T1-weighted images. We also derived subcortical template “SC21” from segmented MRI slices in three-dimensions and registered this volume to a previously published anatomical template with cortical parcellation (Reveley et al., 2017; Saleem and Logothetis, 2012), thereby integrating the 3D segmentation of both cortical and subcortical regions into the same volume. This newly updated three-dimensional D99 digital brain atlas (V2.0) is intended for use as a reference standard for macaque neuroanatomical, functional, and connectional imaging studies, involving both cortical and subcortical targets. The SC21 and D99 digital templates are available as volumes and surfaces in standard NIFTI and GIFTI formats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469706" rel="alternate" title="High-resolution mapping and digital atlas of subcortical regions in the macaque monkey based on matched MAP-MRI and histology (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469596</id><title>Fine-tuning of deep language models as a computational framework of modeling listeners’ perspective during language comprehension (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.295958+00:00</updated><author><name>Refael Tikochinski</name></author><author><name>Ariel Goldstein</name></author><author><name>Yaara Yeshurun</name></author><author><name>Uri Hasson</name></author><author><name>Roi Reichart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Computational Deep Language Models (DLMs) have been shown to be effective in predicting neural responses during natural language processing. This study introduces a novel computational framework, based on the concept of fine-tuning (Hinton, 2007), for modeling differences in interpretation of narratives based on the listeners’ perspective (i.e. their prior knowledge, thoughts, and beliefs). We draw on an fMRI experiment conducted by Yeshurun et al. (2017), in which two groups of listeners were listening to the same narrative but with two different perspectives (cheating versus paranoia). We collected a dedicated dataset of ~3000 stories, and used it to create two modified (fine-tuned) versions of a pre-trained DLM, each representing the perspective of a different group of listeners. Information extracted from each of the two fine-tuned models was better fitted with neural responses of the corresponding group of listeners. Furthermore, we show that the degree of difference between the listeners’ interpretation of the story - as measured both neurally and behaviorally - can be approximated using the distances between the representations of the story extracted from these two fine-tuned models. These models-brain associations were expressed in many language-related brain areas, as well as in several higher-order areas related to the default-mode and the mentalizing networks, therefore implying that computational fine-tuning reliably captures relevant aspects of human language comprehension across different levels of cognitive processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469596" rel="alternate" title="Fine-tuning of deep language models as a computational framework of modeling listeners’ perspective during language comprehension (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470101</id><title>Simultaneous pathway engagement of translation in astrocytes, circadian rhythm in GABAergic neurons and cytoskeleton in glutamatergic neurons precede electroencephalographic changes in neurodegenerative prion disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.296083+00:00</updated><author><name>Lech Tadeusz Kaczmarczyk</name></author><author><name>Melvin Schleif</name></author><author><name>Lars Dittrich</name></author><author><name>Rhiannan Williams</name></author><author><name>Marusa Koderman</name></author><author><name>Vikas Bansal</name></author><author><name>Ashish Rajput</name></author><author><name>Theresa Schulte</name></author><author><name>Maria Jonson</name></author><author><name>Clemens Krost</name></author><author><name>Fabio Testaquadra</name></author><author><name>Stefan Bonn</name></author><author><name>Walker Scot Jackson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Selective vulnerability is an enigmatic feature of neurodegenerative diseases (NDs), whereby a widely expressed protein causes lesions in specific brain regions and cell types. This selectivity may arise from cells possessing varying capacities to regain proteostasis when stressed by cytotoxic protein conformers. Using the RiboTag method in mice, translational responses of five neural subtypes to acquired prion disease (PrD) were measured. Pre-onset and disease onset timepoints were chosen based on longitudinal electroencephalography (EEG) that revealed a gradual increase in theta power between 10- and 18-weeks after prion injection, resembling a clinical feature of human PrD. At disease onset, marked by significantly increased theta power and histopathological lesions, mice had pronounced translatome changes in all five cell types despite having a normal outward appearance. Remarkably, at a pre-onset stage, prior to EEG and neuropathological changes, we found that 1) translatomes of astrocytes indicated a sharply reduced synthesis of ribosomal and mitochondrial components, 2) excitatory neurons showed increased expression of cytoskeletal genes, and 3) inhibitory neurons revealed reduced expression of circadian rhythm network genes. Further assessment for the role of circadian rhythms using a jet lag paradigm modestly exacerbated disease. These data demonstrate that early translatome responses to neurodegeneration emerge prior to other signs of disease and are unique to different cell types. Therapeutic strategies may need to target multiple pathways, each in specific populations of cells, early in the disease process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470101" rel="alternate" title="Simultaneous pathway engagement of translation in astrocytes, circadian rhythm in GABAergic neurons and cytoskeleton in glutamatergic neurons precede electroencephalographic changes in neurodegenerative prion disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469291</id><title>Beamforming seizures from the temporal lobe (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.297333+00:00</updated><author><name>Luis Garcia Dominguez</name></author><author><name>Apameh Tarazi</name></author><author><name>Taufik Valiante</name></author><author><name>Richard Wennberg</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surgical treatment of drug-resistant temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE) depends on proper identification of the seizure onset zone (SOZ), and differentiation of mesial, temporolimbic seizure onsets from temporal neocortical seizure onsets. Non-invasive source imaging using electroencephalography (EEG) and magnetoencephalography (MEG) can provide accurate information on interictal spike localization; however, EEG and MEG have low sensitivity for epileptiform activity restricted to deep temporolimbic structures. Moreover, in mesial temporal lobe epilepsy (MTLE), interictal spikes frequently arise in neocortical foci distant from the SOZ, rendering interictal spike localization potentially misleading for presurgical planning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we used two different beamformer techniques applied to the MEG signal of ictal events acquired during EEG-MEG recordings in six patients with TLE (three neocortical, three MTLE). The ictal source localization results were compared to the patients’ ground truth SOZ localizations determined from intracranial EEG and/or clinical, neuroimaging and postsurgical outcome evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beamformer analysis proved to be highly accurate in all cases and able to reliably identify focal seizure onsets localized to mesial, temporolimbic structures. In three patients, interictal spikes were either absent, too complex for inverse dipole modeling, or localized to anterolateral temporal neocortex distant to a mesial temporal SOZ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report demonstrates the suitability of MEG beamformer analysis of ictal events in TLE, which can supersede or complement the traditional analysis of interictal spikes. The method outlined is applicable to any type of epileptiform event, greatly expanding the information value of MEG and broadening its utility for presurgical recording in epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469291" rel="alternate" title="Beamforming seizures from the temporal lobe (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469678</id><title>KEEPING IN TOUCH WITH OUR HIDDEN SIDE (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.299364+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Mathieu</name></author><author><name>Antonin Abillama</name></author><author><name>Malvina Martinez</name></author><author><name>Laurence Mouchnino</name></author><author><name>Jean Blouin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous studies have shown that the sensory modality used to identify the position of proprioceptive targets hidden from sight, but frequently viewed, influences the type of the body representation employed for reaching them with the finger. The question then arises as to whether this observation also applies to proprioceptive targets which are hidden from sight, and rarely, if ever, viewed. We used an established technique for pinpointing the type of body representation used for the spatial encoding of targets which consisted of assessing the effect of peripheral gaze fixation on the pointing accuracy. More precisely, an exteroceptive, visually dependent, body representation is thought to be used if gaze deviation induces a deviation of the pointing movement. Three light-emitting diodes (LEDs) were positioned at the participants’ eye level at −25 deg, 0 deg and +25 deg with respect to the cyclopean eye. Without moving the head, the participant fixated the lit LED before the experimenter indicated one of the three target head positions: topmost point of the head (vertex) and two other points located at the front and back of the head. These targets were either verbal-cued or tactile-cued. The goal of the subjects (n=27) was to reach the target with their index finger. We analysed the accuracy of the movements directed to the topmost point of the head, which is a well-defined, yet out of view anatomical point. Based on the possibility of the brain to create visual representations of the body areas that remain out of view, we hypothesized that the position of the vertex is encoded using an exteroceptive body representation, both when verbally or tactile-cued. Results revealed that the pointing errors were biased in the opposite direction of gaze fixation for both verbal-cued and tactile-cued targets, suggesting the use of a vision-dependent exteroceptive body representation. The enhancement of the visual body representations by sensorimotor processes was suggested by the greater pointing accuracy when the vertex was identified by tactile stimulation compared to verbal instruction. Moreover, we found in a control condition that participants were more accurate in indicating the position of their own vertex than the vertex of other people. This result supports the idea that sensorimotor experiences increase the spatial resolution of the exteroceptive body representation. Together, our results suggest that the position of rarely viewed body parts are spatially encoded by an exteroceptive body representation and that non-visual sensorimotor processes are involved in the constructing of this representation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469678" rel="alternate" title="KEEPING IN TOUCH WITH OUR HIDDEN SIDE (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469768</id><title>How increased cognitive load affects the dual-task cost in healthy young adults? A randomized, double-blind sham-controlled study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.300454+00:00</updated><author><name>Shabnam Behrangrad</name></author><author><name>Maryam Zoghi</name></author><author><name>Farshad Mansouri</name></author><author><name>Shapour Jaberzadeh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our ability to interact flexibly with the surrounding environment and achieve an adaptive goal-directed response is one of the necessities of balance control. This study aimed to examine the interaction between cognitive demand and the necessity for keeping balance in unstable conditions. We examined the effects of performing two cognitive tasks, namely the Stroop test and Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST), on postural balance in healthy young adults. Stroop and the WCST test assess selective attention and cognitive flexibility in shifting between rules, respectively. Thirty-two healthy adults were included in two experimental conditions (control and treatment) in random order, separated by at least seven days. Standing balance was evaluated by the Sway Medical Mobile application in eyes open (EO) and eyes closed (EC) in different stance positions: feet apart, feet together, semi-tandem, tandem, and single-leg stance (SLS). Balance was evaluated before and after the cognitive test in each experimental condition. Our findings indicate that performing cognitively demanding tasks adversely affected the balance ability in more demanding balance tests such as the SLS with EC (P □ 0.05). However, no significant changes were seen in other balance tests (P □ 0.05). Additionally, no significant changes were seen in balance ability after the Stroop or Wisconsin card sorting test alone. These results confirm that performing cognitively demanding tasks significantly reduced the ability to keep balance in less stable conditions. These findings have significant implications in understanding and preventing falls and incidents resulting from an impaired balance in complex and cognitively demanding conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469768" rel="alternate" title="How increased cognitive load affects the dual-task cost in healthy young adults? A randomized, double-blind sham-controlled study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469734</id><title>Quasi-universal scaling in mouse-brain neuronal activity stems from edge-of-instability critical dynamics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.302580+00:00</updated><author><name>Guillermo B. Morales</name></author><author><name>Serena Di Santo</name></author><author><name>Miguel A. Muñoz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain is in a state of perpetual reverberant neural activity, even in the absence of specific tasks or stimuli. Shedding light on the origin and functional significance of such activity is essential to understanding how the brain transmits, processes, and stores information. An inspiring, albeit controversial, conjecture proposes that some statistical characteristics of empirically observed neuronal activity can be understood by assuming that brain networks operate in a dynamical regime near the edge of a phase transition. Moreover, the resulting critical behavior, with its concomitant scale invariance, is assumed to carry crucial functional advantages. Here, we present a data-driven analysis based on simultaneous high-throughput recordings of the activity of thousands of individual neurons in various regions of the mouse brain. To analyze these data, we construct a unified theoretical framework that synergistically combines cutting-edge methods for the study of brain activity (such as a phenomenological renormalization group approach and techniques that infer the general dynamical state of a neural population), while designing complementary tools. This unified approach allows us to uncover strong signatures of scale invariance that is “quasi-universal” across brain regions and reveal that these areas operate, to a greater or lesser extent, at the edge of instability. Furthermore, this framework allows us to distinguish between quasi-universal background activity and non-universal input-related activity. Taken together, the following study provides strong evidence that brain networks actually operate in a critical regime which, among other functional advantages, provides them with a scale-invariant substrate of activity in which optimal input representations can be sustained.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469734" rel="alternate" title="Quasi-universal scaling in mouse-brain neuronal activity stems from edge-of-instability critical dynamics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469413</id><title>Perceived facial happiness during conversation correlates with insular and hypothalamus activity for humans, not robots: An investigation of the somatic marker hypothesis applied to social interactions (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.302841+00:00</updated><author><name>Thierry Chaminade</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Spatola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The somatic marker hypothesis posits that perceiving emotions entails reenacting markers of self emotions, in particular in the autonomous nervous system. Well studied in decision-making tasks, it has not been tested in a social cognitive neuroscience framework, and in particular for the automatic processing of positive emotions during natural interactions. Here, we address this question using a unique corpus of brain activity recorded during unconstrained conversations between participants and a human or a humanoid robot. fMRI recordings are used to test whether activity in the most important brain regions in relation to the autonomic system, the amygdala, hypothalamus and insula, is affected by the level of happiness expressed by the human and robot agents. Results indicate that for the hypothalamus and the insula, in particular the anterior agranular region strongly involved in processing social emotions, activity in the right hemisphere increases with the level of happiness expressed by the human, but not the robot. Results indicate that perceiving positive emotions in social interactions induces the local brain responses predicted by the somatic marker hypothesis, but only when the interacting agent is a real human.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469413" rel="alternate" title="Perceived facial happiness during conversation correlates with insular and hypothalamus activity for humans, not robots: An investigation of the somatic marker hypothesis applied to social interactions (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469553</id><title>Causal contributions of neural noise to left frontal networks subtending the modulation of conscious visual perception in the human brain (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.303031+00:00</updated><author><name>Chloé Stengel</name></author><author><name>Julià L. Amengual</name></author><author><name>Tristan Moreau</name></author><author><name>Antoni Valero-Cabré</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For several decades, the field of human neurophysiology has focused on the role played by cortical oscillations in enabling brain function underpinning behaviors. In parallel, a less visible but robust body of work on the stochastic resonance phenomenon has also theorized contributions of neural noise − hence more heterogeneous, complex and less predictable activity − in brain coding. The latter notion has received indirect causal support via improvements of visual function during non-regular or random brain stimulation patterns. Nonetheless, direct evidence demonstrating an impact of brain stimulation on direct measures of neural noise is still lacking. Here we evaluated the impact of three &lt;italic&gt;non frequency-specific&lt;/italic&gt; TMS bursts, compared to a control pure high-beta TMS rhythm, delivered to the left FEF during a visual detection task, on the heterogeneity, predictability and complexity of ongoing brain activity recorded with scalp EEG. Our data showed surprisingly that the three &lt;italic&gt;non frequency-specific&lt;/italic&gt; TMS patterns did not prevent a build-up of local high-beta activity. Nonetheless, they increased power across broader or in multiple frequency bands compared to control purely &lt;italic&gt;rhythmic&lt;/italic&gt; high-beta bursts tested along. Importantly, &lt;italic&gt;non frequency-specific&lt;/italic&gt; patterns enhanced signal entropy over multiple time-scales, suggesting higher complexity and an overall induction of higher levels of cortical noise than &lt;italic&gt;rhythmic&lt;/italic&gt; TMS bursts. Our outcomes provide indirect evidence on a potential modulatory role played by sources of stochastic noise on brain oscillations and synchronization. Additionally, they pave the way towards the development of novel neurostimulation approaches to manipulate cortical sources of noise and further investigate their causal role in neural coding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469553" rel="alternate" title="Causal contributions of neural noise to left frontal networks subtending the modulation of conscious visual perception in the human brain (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469555</id><title>Characterizing the short-latency evoked response to intracortical microstimulation across a multi-electrode array (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.303167+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Sombeck</name></author><author><name>Juliet Heye</name></author><author><name>Karthik Kumaravelu</name></author><author><name>Stefan M. Goetz</name></author><author><name>Angel V. Peterchev</name></author><author><name>Warren M. Grill</name></author><author><name>Sliman Bensmaia</name></author><author><name>Lee E. Miller</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Persons with tetraplegia can use brain-machine interfaces to make visually guided reaches with robotic arms. Without somatosensory feedback, these movements will likely be slow and imprecise, like those of persons who retain movement but have lost proprioception. Intracortical microstimulation (ICMS) has promise for providing artificial somatosensory feedback. If ICMS can mimic naturally occurring neural activity, afferent interfaces may be more informative and easier to learn than interfaces that evoke unnaturalistic activity. To develop such biomimetic stimulation patterns, it is important to characterize the responses of neurons to ICMS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Approach&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a Utah multi-electrode array, we recorded activity evoked by single pulses, and short (~0.2 s) and long (~4 s) trains of ICMS at a wide range of amplitudes and frequencies. As the electrical artifact caused by ICMS typically prevents recording for many milliseconds, we deployed a custom rapid-recovery amplifier with nonlinear gain to limit signal saturation on the stimulated electrode. Across all electrodes after stimulation, we removed the remaining slow return to baseline with acausal high-pass filtering of time-reversed recordings. With these techniques, we could record ~0.7 ms after stimulation offset even on the stimulated electrode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recorded likely transsynaptically-evoked activity as early as ~0.7 ms after single pulses of stimulation that was immediately followed by suppressed neural activity lasting 10–150 ms. Instead of this long-lasting inhibition, neurons increased their firing rates for ~100 ms after trains. During long trains, the evoked response on the stimulated electrode decayed rapidly while the response was maintained on non-stimulated channels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The detailed description of the spatial and temporal response to ICMS can be used to better interpret results from experiments that probe circuit connectivity or function of cortical areas. These results can also contribute to the design of stimulation patterns to improve afferent interfaces for artificial sensory feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469555" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing the short-latency evoked response to intracortical microstimulation across a multi-electrode array (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469621</id><title>Age Differences in Diffusivity in the Locus Coeruleus and its Ascending Noradrenergic Tract (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.303318+00:00</updated><author><name>Shai Porat</name></author><author><name>Francesca Sibilia</name></author><author><name>Josephine Yoon</name></author><author><name>Yonggang Shi</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Dahl</name></author><author><name>Markus Werkle-Bergner</name></author><author><name>Sandra Düzel</name></author><author><name>Nils Bodammer</name></author><author><name>Ulman Lindenberger</name></author><author><name>Simone Kühn</name></author><author><name>Mara Mather</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The noradrenergic locus coeruleus (LC) is a small brainstem nucleus that promotes arousal and attention. Recent studies have examined the microstructural properties of the LC using diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging and found unexpected age-related differences in fractional anisotropy - a measure of white matter integrity. Here, we used three datasets (Berlin Aging Study-II, N = 301, the Leipzig Study for Mind-Body-Emotion Interactions, N = 220, and Stockholm Sleepy Brain, N = 49), to replicate published findings and expand them by investigating diffusivity in the LC’s ascending noradrenergic bundle. In younger adults, LC fractional anisotropy was significantly lower, compared to older adults. However, in the LC’s ascending noradrenergic bundle, we observed significantly higher fractional anisotropy in younger adults, relative to older adults. These findings indicate that diffusivity in the LC versus the ascending noradrenergic bundle are both susceptible to microstructural changes in aging that have opposing effects on fractional anisotropy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fractional anisotropy in the locus coeruleus was lower in younger adults&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fractional anisotropy in the noradrenergic bundle was higher in younger adults&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sleep deprivation may affect diffusivity in younger adults more than older adults&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469621" rel="alternate" title="Age Differences in Diffusivity in the Locus Coeruleus and its Ascending Noradrenergic Tract (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>