<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.018820+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463568</id><title>Molecular rhythm alterations in prefrontal cortex and nucleus accumbens associated with opioid use disorder (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.019401+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiangning Xue</name></author><author><name>Wei Zong</name></author><author><name>Jill Glausier</name></author><author><name>Sam-Moon Kim</name></author><author><name>Micah Shelton</name></author><author><name>BaDoi N Phan</name></author><author><name>Chaitanya Srinivasan</name></author><author><name>Andreas R Pfenning</name></author><author><name>George Tseng</name></author><author><name>David A Lewis</name></author><author><name>Marianne Seney</name></author><author><name>Ryan Logan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Severe and persistent disruptions to sleep and circadian rhythms are common features of people with opioid use disorder (OUD). Preclinical findings suggest altered molecular rhythms in the brain are involved in opioid reward and dependence. However, whether molecular rhythms are disrupted in brains of people with OUD remained an open question, critical to understanding the role of circadian rhythms in opioid addiction. We previously used subjects' times of death (TOD) as a marker of time of day to investigate transcriptional rhythm alterations in psychiatric disorders. Using TOD and RNA sequencing, we discovered rhythmic transcripts in both the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) and nucleus accumbens (NAc), key brain areas involved in opioid addiction, were largely distinct between OUD and unaffected comparison subjects. Further, fewer rhythmic transcripts were identified in DLPFC of OUD subjects compared to unaffected subjects, but nearly double the number of rhythmic transcripts were found in the NAc of OUD subjects. In OUD, rhythmic transcripts in the NAc peaked either in the evening or near sunrise, and were associated with dopamine, opioid, and GABAergic neurotransmission. Co-expression network analysis identified several OUD-specific modules in the NAc, enriched for transcripts involved in the modulation of dopamine and GABA synapses, including glutamatergic signaling and extracellular matrices. Integrative analyses with human GWAS revealed that rhythmic transcripts in DLPFC and NAc were enriched for genomic loci associated with sleep duration and insomnia. Overall, our results connect transcriptional rhythm changes in dopamine, opioid, and GABAergic synaptic signaling in human brain to sleep-related phenotypes and OUD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463568" rel="alternate" title="Molecular rhythm alterations in prefrontal cortex and nucleus accumbens associated with opioid use disorder (18 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.463138</id><title>Linking contrast sensitivity to cortical magnification in human primary visual cortex (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.019861+00:00</updated><author><name>Marc M. Himmelberg</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Winawer</name></author><author><name>Marisa Carrasco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The size and organization of primary visual cortex (V1) varies across individuals. Across neurotypical adults, V1 size varies more than twofold. Within individuals, surface area per unit of visual field – cortical magnification – varies with eccentricity and polar angle. Contrast sensitivity and cortical magnification covary with eccentricity, therefore it has been hypothesized that cortical magnification, specifically the number of activated V1 neurons, limits contrast sensitivity. Here, we quantify the relation between contrast sensitivity and V1 cortical magnification across observers and polar angle. We measured contrast sensitivity at four cardinal meridians in 29 observers. We then used fMRI to measure the size of V1 in the same observers, and the amount of surface area representing each of the four meridians (wedge-ROIs within 15° polar angle of the meridians, 1 to 8° eccentricity). We found that: First, an observer’s contrast sensitivity (averaged across polar angles) was predicted by the size of V1. Second, contrast sensitivity at each cardinal meridian was correlated with the surface area of the wedge-ROIs centered at the corresponding meridian. Third, increases in contrast sensitivity and cortical magnification at the horizontal compared to vertical meridian (horizontal-vertical anisotropy, ‘HVA’) were strongly correlated: a larger HVA in contrast sensitivity corresponded to a larger HVA in cortical magnification. These results reveal that contrast sensitivity and cortical magnification co-vary across observers and demonstrate a link between perceptual polar angle asymmetries and cortical anatomy. Broadly, the results show a link between visual perception and the idiosyncratic cortical organization of V1 in neurotypical observers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contrast sensitivity is a fundamental property of the human visual system, which indexes the limits of what one can detect or discriminate – the window of visibility. Contrast sensitivity varies with stimulus location on the retina and across observers. These variations are not well understood. Using psychophysics and magnetic resonance imaging, we tested the hypothesis that contrast sensitivity depends on the amount of responsive tissue in primary visual cortex (V1). Individuals with greater contrast sensitivity had a larger V1. Further, within observers, variation in contrast sensitivity across polar angle locations matched the variation in V1 surface area representing those locations. These findings demonstrate a tight link between visual perception and cortical anatomy, both within and among people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.463138" rel="alternate" title="Linking contrast sensitivity to cortical magnification in human primary visual cortex (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.462913</id><title>Minimal required exposures reveal the primacy of awareness in human face perception (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.020071+00:00</updated><author><name>Renzo C. Lanfranco</name></author><author><name>Andrés Canales-Johnson</name></author><author><name>Axel Cleeremans</name></author><author><name>Hugh Rabagliati</name></author><author><name>David Carmel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human visual system is capable of detecting extremely small light signals, as little as one single photon. But what is the visual system’s minimal exposure threshold to detect meaningful stimuli? Due to hardware limitations, studies examining fast visual processing typically present stimuli for suprathreshold durations and disrupt processing with a mask. Here, we employed a newly developed tachistoscope that enables sub-millisecond presentations. Combining measures of perceptual sensitivity and recordings of neural activity, we find that both the holistic configuration and the emotional expression of a human face have the same minimal required exposure as the minimal required exposure for faces to reach awareness. These findings indicate that conscious awareness is required for processing meaningful visual information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.462913" rel="alternate" title="Minimal required exposures reveal the primacy of awareness in human face perception (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463575</id><title>Light-induced asymmetries in the embryonic retina are mediated by the vascular system and extracellular matrix (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.020281+00:00</updated><author><name>Elisabetta Versace</name></author><author><name>Paola Sgado</name></author><author><name>Julia George</name></author><author><name>Jasmine Loveland</name></author><author><name>Joseph Ward</name></author><author><name>Peter Thorpe</name></author><author><name>Lars Juhl Jensen</name></author><author><name>Karen Spencer</name></author><author><name>Silvia Paracchini</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Vallortigara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Left-right asymmetries in the nervous system (lateralisation) influence a broad range of behaviours, from social responses to navigation and language. The role and pathways of endogenous and environmental mechanisms in the ontogeny of lateralisation remains to be established. The domestic chick is a model of both endogenous and experience-induced lateralisation driven by light exposure. Following the endogenous rightward rotation of the embryo, the asymmetrical position in the egg results in a greater exposure of the right eye to environmental light. To identify the genetic pathways activated by asymmetric light stimulation, and their time course, we exposed embryos to different light regimes: darkness, 6 hours of light and 24 hours of light. We used RNA-seq to compare gene expression in the right and left retinas and telencephalon. As expected, no differential expression between left and right was present in darkness. We detected differential gene expression in right vs left retina after 6 hours of light exposure. This difference disappeared before 24 hours of light exposure, suggesting that light-induced activation is a self-terminating phenomenon. This transient effect of light exposure was associated with a downregulation of the sensitive-period mediator gene DIO2 (iodothyronine deiodinase 2) in the right retina. No differences between genes expressed in the right vs. left telencephalon were detected. Gene networks associated with lateralisation were connected to vascularisation, cell motility, and the extracellular matrix. Interestingly, we know that the extracellular matrix - including the differentially expressed PDGFRB (platelet-derived growth factor receptor β) gene - is involved in both sensitive periods and in the endogenous chiral mechanism of primary cilia, that drives lateralisation. Our data show a similarity between endogenous and experience-driven lateralisation, identifying functional gene networks that affect lateralisation in a specific time window.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463575" rel="alternate" title="Light-induced asymmetries in the embryonic retina are mediated by the vascular system and extracellular matrix (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463524</id><title>Impact of stimulation location relative to grey and white matter on single pulse electrical stimulation responses in the human brain (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.020513+00:00</updated><author><name>Angelique C Paulk</name></author><author><name>Rina Zelmann</name></author><author><name>Britni Crocker</name></author><author><name>Alik S Widge</name></author><author><name>Darin D Dougherty</name></author><author><name>Emad N Eskandar</name></author><author><name>Daniel S Weisholtz</name></author><author><name>Mark Richardson</name></author><author><name>Rees Cosgrove</name></author><author><name>Sydney S Cash</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Electrical neuromodulation is an increasingly common therapy for a wide variety of neuropsychiatric diseases. Unfortunately, therapeutic efficacy is inconsistent, possibly a result of our limited understanding of the mechanisms and the massive stimulation parameter space.
Objective/Hypothesis: To better understand the role different parameters play in inducing a response, we systematically examined single pulse-induced cortico-cortico evoked potentials (CCEP) as a function of stimulation amplitude, duration and location in the brain and relative to grey and white matter. 
Methods: We measured voltage peak amplitudes and area under the curve of intracranially recorded stimulation responses as a function of distance from the stimulation site, pulse width, current injected, location relative to grey and white matter, and brain region stimulated (N=52, n=719 stimulation sites). 
Results: Increasing stimulation pulse width increased response values near the stimulation location. Increasing stimulation amplitude (current) increased responses nonlinearly. Locally (&amp;lt;15 mm from the stimulation site), stimulation closer to the grey matter-white matter boundary induced larger responses. In contrast, for distant sites (&amp;gt;15 mm), white matter stimulation consistently produced larger responses than stimulation in or near grey matter. These relationships were different between cingulate, lateral prefrontal, and lateral temporal cortical stimulation. 
Conclusion: These results demonstrate the importance of location and stimulation parameters in inducing a specific output and indicate that a stronger local response may require stimulation in the grey-white boundary while stimulation in the white matter may be needed for network activation, suggesting that stimulation location can be tailored for a specific outcome, key to informed neuromodulatory therapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463524" rel="alternate" title="Impact of stimulation location relative to grey and white matter on single pulse electrical stimulation responses in the human brain (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.03.462970</id><title>β-amyloid−driven synaptic depression requires PDZ protein interaction at AMPA-receptor subunit GluA3 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.020744+00:00</updated><author><name>Niels R. Reinders</name></author><author><name>Sophie van der Spek</name></author><author><name>Remco V. Klaassen</name></author><author><name>Karin J. Koymans</name></author><author><name>Ka Wan Li</name></author><author><name>August B. Smit</name></author><author><name>Helmut W. Kessels</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soluble oligomeric amyloid-β (Aβ) is a prime suspect to cause cognitive deficits in Alzheimer’s disease and weakens synapses by removing AMPA-type glutamate receptors (AMPARs). We show that synapses of CA1 pyramidal neurons become vulnerable to Aβ when they express AMPAR subunit GluA3. We found that Aβ-oligomers reduce the levels of GluA3 immobilized at spines, indicating they deplete GluA3-containing AMPARs from synapses. These Aβ-driven effects critically depended on the PDZ-binding motif of GluA3. When GluA3 was expressed with a single amino acid mutation in its PDZ-binding motif that prevents GRIP binding, it did not end up at spines and Aβ failed to trigger synaptic depression. GluA3 with a different point mutation in the PDZ-motif that leaves GRIP-binding intact but prevents its endocytosis, was present at spines in normal amounts but was fully resistant to effects of Aβ. Our data indicate that Aβ-mediated synaptic depression requires the removal of GluA3 from synapses. We propose that GRIP-detachment from GluA3 is a critical early step in the cascade of events through which Aβ accumulation causes a loss of synapse.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.03.462970" rel="alternate" title="β-amyloid−driven synaptic depression requires PDZ protein interaction at AMPA-receptor subunit GluA3 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463158</id><title>A spiking neural network model of the Superior Colliculus that is robust to changes in the spatial-temporal input (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.020951+00:00</updated><author><name>Arezoo Alizadeh</name></author><author><name>A. John Van Opstal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous studies have indicated that the location of a large neural population in the Superior Colliculus (SC) motor map specifies the amplitude and direction of the saccadic eye-movement vector, while the saccade trajectory and velocity profile are encoded by the population firing rates. We recently proposed a simple spiking neural network model of the SC motor map, based on linear summation of individual spike effects of each recruited neuron, which accounts for many of the observed properties of SC cells in relation to the ensuing eye movement. However, in the model, the cortical input was kept invariant across different saccades. Electrical microstimulation and reversible lesion studies have demonstrated that the saccade properties are quite robust against large changes in supra-threshold SC activation, but that saccade amplitude and peak eye-velocity systematically decrease at low input strengths. These features are not accounted for by the linear spike-vector summation model. Here we show that the model’s input projection strengths and intra-collicular lateral connections can be tuned to generate saccades that follow the experimental results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The midbrain SC generates fast saccadic eye movements through a large population of cells within a topographically organized motor map, in which the location, spike count and temporal firing patterns of recruited cells determine saccade metrics and kinematics. According to the dynamic ensemble-coding model, each recruited SC cell contributes to the saccade by linear vector summation of all its spike contributions. Our previous spiking neural network model used invariant cortical inputs to the SC cells for all saccades. We here improved the robustness of the model to large spatial-temporal variations in the input patterns, by tuning its top-down and lateral synaptic connections, to generate saccades with properties observed in electrophysiological experiments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.05.463158" rel="alternate" title="A spiking neural network model of the Superior Colliculus that is robust to changes in the spatial-temporal input (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463602</id><title>CCR5 closes the temporal window for memory linking (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.021121+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Shen</name></author><author><name>Miou Zhou</name></author><author><name>Denise Cai</name></author><author><name>Daniel Almeida Filho</name></author><author><name>Giselle Fernandes</name></author><author><name>Ying Cai</name></author><author><name>Nury Kim</name></author><author><name>Deanna Necula</name></author><author><name>Chengbin Zhou</name></author><author><name>Andy Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiaoman Kang</name></author><author><name>Masakazu Kamata</name></author><author><name>Ayal Lavi</name></author><author><name>Shan Huang</name></author><author><name>Tawnie Silva</name></author><author><name>Won Do Heo</name></author><author><name>Alcino J. Silva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Real world memories are formed in a particular context and are not acquired or recalled in isolation. Time is a key variable in the organization of memories, since events experienced close in time are more likely to be meaningfully associated, while those experienced with a longer interval are not. How does the brain segregate events that are temporally distinct? Here, we report that a delayed (12-24h) increase in the expression of the C-C chemokine receptor type 5 (CCR5), an immune receptor well known as a co-receptor for HIV infection, following the formation of a contextual memory, determines the duration of the temporal window for associating or linking that memory with subsequent memories. This delayed CCR5 expression in mouse dorsal CA1 (dCA1) neurons results in a decrease in neuronal excitability, which in turn negatively regulates neuronal memory allocation, thus reducing the overlap between dCA1 memory ensembles. Lowering this overlap affects the ability of one memory to trigger the recall of the other, thus closing the temporal window for memory linking. Remarkably, our findings also show that an age-related increase in CCL5/CCR5 expression leads to impairments in memory linking in aged mice, which could be reversed with a CCR5 knockout and an FDA approved drug that inhibits this receptor, a result with significant clinical implications. All together the findings reported here provide the first insights into the molecular and cellular mechanisms that shape the temporal window for memory linking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463602" rel="alternate" title="CCR5 closes the temporal window for memory linking (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463487</id><title>Self-regulation of the brain's Beta rhythm using a brain-computer interface improves inhibitory control (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.021396+00:00</updated><author><name>Nadja Enz</name></author><author><name>Jemima Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Kate Nolan</name></author><author><name>Matthew Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Sandra Alvarez Gomez</name></author><author><name>Miryam Alkayyali</name></author><author><name>Pierce Cambay</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Gippert</name></author><author><name>Robert Whelan</name></author><author><name>Kathy L Ruddy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural oscillations, or brain rhythms, fluctuate in a manner reflecting ongoing behavior. Whether these fluctuations are instrumental or epiphenomenal to the behavior remains elusive. Attempts to experimentally manipulate neural oscillations exogenously using non-invasive brain stimulation have shown some promise, but difficulty with tailoring stimulation parameters to individuals has hindered progress in this field. We demonstrate here using electroencephalography (EEG) neurofeedback in a brain-computer interface that human participants (n=44) learned over multiple sessions across a 6-day period to self-regulate their Beta rhythm (13-20 Hz) over the right inferior frontal cortex (rIFC). This Beta modulation had observable consequences on cognitive behavior: changes in an individual's inhibitory control performance before and after training were predicted by the magnitude of their training-related change in Beta over rIFC. This was not the case for a control group (n=38) who underwent training of their Alpha rhythm (8-12 Hz). The present data support the view that the right frontal Beta rhythm is a key component of the brain's inhibitory control system. Most importantly, we introduce causality to this relationship for the first time, as experimental modulation of rIFC Beta activity had a measurable impact upon behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463487" rel="alternate" title="Self-regulation of the brain's Beta rhythm using a brain-computer interface improves inhibitory control (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463319</id><title>Harmoni: a Method for Eliminating Spurious Interactions due to the Harmonic Components in Neuronal Data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:03.021627+00:00</updated><author><name>Mina Jamshidi Idaji</name></author><author><name>Juanli Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tilman Stephani</name></author><author><name>Guido Nolte</name></author><author><name>Klaus-Robert Mueller</name></author><author><name>Arno Villringer</name></author><author><name>Vadim Nikulin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cross-frequency synchronization (CFS) has been proposed as a mechanism for integrating spatially and spectrally distributed information in the brain. However, investigating CFS in Magneto- and Electroencephalography (MEG/EEG) is hampered by the presence of spurious neuronal interactions due to the non-sinusoidal waveshape of brain oscillations. Such waveshape gives rise to the presence of oscillatory harmonics mimicking genuine neuronal oscillations. Until recently, however, there has been no methodology for removing these harmonics from neuronal data. In order to address this long-standing challenge, we introduce a novel method (called HARMOnic miNImization - Harmoni) that removes the signal components which can be harmonics of a non-sinusoidal signal. Harmoni's working principle is based on the presence of CFS between harmonic components and the fundamental component of a non-sinusoidal signal. 
We extensively tested Harmoni in realistic EEG simulations. The simulated couplings between the source signals represented genuine and spurious CFS and within-frequency phase synchronization. Using diverse evaluation criteria, including ROC analyses, we showed that the within- and cross-frequency spurious interactions are suppressed significantly, while the genuine activities are not affected. Additionally, we applied Harmoni to real resting-state EEG data revealing intricate remote connectivity patterns which are usually masked by the spurious connections. Given the ubiquity of non-sinusoidal neuronal oscillations in electrophysiological recordings, Harmoni is expected to facilitate novel insights into genuine neuronal interactions in various research fields, and can also serve as a steppingstone towards the development of further signal processing methods aiming at refining within- and cross-frequency synchronization in electrophysiological recordings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.463319" rel="alternate" title="Harmoni: a Method for Eliminating Spurious Interactions due to the Harmonic Components in Neuronal Data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>