<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.768959+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460550</id><title>Intact reading ability in spite of a spatially distributed visual word form ‘area’ in an individual born without the left superior temporal lobe (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.769887+00:00</updated><author><name>Jin Li</name></author><author><name>Evelina Fedorenko</name></author><author><name>Zeynep Saygin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The visual word form area (VWFA) is an experience-dependent brain region in the left ventral temporal cortex of literate adults that responds selectively to visual words. Why does it emerge in this stereotyped location? Past research has shown that the VWFA is preferentially connected to the left-lateralized frontotemporal language network. However, it remains unclear whether the presence of a typical language network and its connections with ventral temporal cortex (VTC) are critical for the VWFA’s emergence, and whether alternative functional architectures may support reading ability. We explored these questions in an individual (EG) born without the left superior temporal lobe but exhibiting normal reading ability. Using fMRI, we recorded brain activation to visual words, objects, faces, and scrambled words in EG and neurotypical controls. We did not observe word selectivity either in EG’s right homotope of the VWFA (rVWFA)—the most expected location given that EG’s language network is right-lateralized—or in her spared left VWFA (lVWFA), in the presence of typical face selectivity in both the right and left fusiform face area (rFFA, lFFA). Interestingly, multivariate pattern analyses revealed voxels in EG’s rVWFA and lVWFA that showed 1) higher within- than between-category correlations for words (e.g., Words-Words&amp;gt;Words-Faces), and 2) higher within-category correlations for words than other categories (e.g., Words-Words&amp;gt;Faces-Faces). These results suggest that a typical left-hemisphere language network may be necessary for the emergence of focal word selectivity within ventral temporal cortex, and that orthographic processing may depend on a distributed neural code, which appears capable of supporting reading ability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460550" rel="alternate" title="Intact reading ability in spite of a spatially distributed visual word form ‘area’ in an individual born without the left superior temporal lobe (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460516</id><title>Long-term Motor Learning in the Wild with High Volume Video Game Data (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.770229+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer B Listman</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Tsay</name></author><author><name>Hyosub E Kim</name></author><author><name>Wayne E Mackey</name></author><author><name>David J Heeger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motor learning occurs over long periods of practice during which motor acuity (the ability to execute actions more accurately, precisely, and within a shorter amount of time) improves. Laboratory-based motor learning studies are typically limited to a small number of participants and a time frame of minutes to several hours per participant. Thus, there is a need to assess the generalizability of theories and findings from lab-based motor learning studies on much larger samples across longer time scales. In addition, laboratory-based studies of motor learning use relatively simple motor tasks which participants are unlikely to be intrinsically motivated to learn, limiting the interpretation of their findings in more ecologically valid settings. We studied the acquisition and longitudinal refinement of a complex sensorimotor skill embodied in a first-person shooter video game scenario, with a large sample size (N = 7174 participants, 682,564 repeats of the 60 sec game) over a period of months. Participants voluntarily practiced the gaming scenario for as much as several hours per day up to 100 days. We found improvement in performance accuracy (quantified as hit rate) was modest over time but motor acuity (quantified as hits per second) improved considerably, with 40-60% retention from one day to the next. We observed steady improvements in motor acuity across multiple days of video game practice, unlike most motor learning tasks studied in the lab that hit a performance ceiling rather quickly. Learning rate was a nonlinear function of baseline performance level, amount of daily practice, and to a lesser extent, number of days between practice sessions. In addition, we found that the benefit of additional practice on any given day was non-monotonic; the greatest improvements in motor acuity were evident with about an hour of practice and 90% of the learning benefit was achieved by practicing 30 minutes per day. Taken together, these results provide a proof-of-concept in studying motor skill acquisition outside the confines of the traditional laboratory and provide new insights into how a complex motor skill is acquired in an ecologically valid setting and refined across much longer time scales than typically explored.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460516" rel="alternate" title="Long-term Motor Learning in the Wild with High Volume Video Game Data (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460484</id><title>Hippocampus maintains a flexible and coherent map under reward flavor-landmark cue conflict. (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.770424+00:00</updated><author><name>Indrajith R Nair</name></author><author><name>Dipanjan Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals predominantly use salient visual cues (landmarks) for efficient navigation over other sensory modalities. When the relative position of the visual cues is altered, the hippocampal population exhibits heterogeneous responses and constructs context-specific spatial maps. Another critical factor that can strongly modulate spatial representation is the presence of reward. Reward features can drive behavior and are known to bias spatial attention. However, it is unclear whether reward flavors are used for spatial reference in the presence of distal cues and how the hippocampus population dynamics changes when the association between reward flavors and distal cues is altered. We investigated these questions by recording place cells from the CA1 while the rats ran in an environment with the conflicting association between reward flavors and distal cues. We report that the hippocampal place cells coherently and dynamically bind to reward flavors or distal cues across sessions, but not simultaneously suggesting the use of a single spatial map. We found that place cells maintained their spatial offset in the cue conflict conditions, thus showing a robust spatial coupling featuring an attractor-like property in the CA1. When the textures were added on the track, the coherency of the CA1 is degraded, as the hippocampus showed a heterogeneous response and weak spatial coupling of co-recorded cells suggesting a break away from the attractor network. These results indicate that reward flavors alone may be used for spatial reference but may not cause sufficient input difference to create context-specific spatial maps in the CA1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.15.460484" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampus maintains a flexible and coherent map under reward flavor-landmark cue conflict. (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460110</id><title>Synthetic amyloid beta does not induce a robust transcriptional response in innate immune cell culture systems (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.770575+00:00</updated><author><name>I.Y. Quiroga</name></author><author><name>A.E. Cruikshank</name></author><author><name>K. S. M. Reed</name></author><author><name>M.L. Bond</name></author><author><name>B.A. Evangelista</name></author><author><name>J.H. Tseng</name></author><author><name>J. V. Ragusa</name></author><author><name>R. B. Meeker</name></author><author><name>H. Won</name></author><author><name>S. Cohen</name></author><author><name>T.J. Cohen</name></author><author><name>D.H. Phanstiel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disease that impacts nearly 400 million people worldwide. The accumulation of amyloid beta (Aβ) in the brain has historically been associated with AD, and recent evidence suggests that neuroinflammation plays a central role in its origin and progression. These observations have given rise to the theory that Aβ is the primary trigger of AD, and induces proinflammatory activation of immune brain cells (i.e. microglia), which culminates in neuronal damage and cognitive decline. In order to test this hypothesis, many in vitro systems have been established to study Aβ-mediated activation of innate immune cells. Nevertheless, the transcriptional resemblance of these models to the microglia in the AD brain has never been comprehensively studied on a genome-wide scale. To address this, we used bulk RNA-seq to assess the transcriptional differences between in vitro cell types used to model neuroinflammation in AD, including several established, primary and iPSC-derived immune cell lines (macrophages, microglia and astrocytes) and their similarities to primary cells in the AD brain. We then analyzed the transcriptional response of these innate immune cells to synthetic Aβ. We found that human induced pluripotent stem cell (hIPSC)-derived microglia (IMGL) are the in vitro cell model that best resembles primary microglia. Surprisingly, synthetic Aβ does not trigger a robust transcriptional response in any of the cellular models analyzed, despite testing a wide variety of Aβ formulations, concentrations, and treatment conditions. Finally, we found that bacterial LPS and INFγ activate microglia and induce transcriptional changes similar to those observed in disease associated microglia present in the AD brain, suggesting the potential suitability of this model to study AD-related neuroinflammation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460110" rel="alternate" title="Synthetic amyloid beta does not induce a robust transcriptional response in innate immune cell culture systems (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.459918</id><title>Impaired KDM2B-mediated PRC1 recruitment to chromatin causes neural stem cell senescence and ASD/ID-like behavioral deficits (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.770779+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuen Gao</name></author><author><name>Natalia Duque-Wilckens</name></author><author><name>Mohammad B Aljazi</name></author><author><name>Adam J Moeser</name></author><author><name>George I Mias</name></author><author><name>Alfred J Robison</name></author><author><name>Yi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jin He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and intellectual disability (ID) are neurodevelopmental diseases associated with various genetic mutations. Recent clinical studies report that chromosomal 12q24.31 microdeletions are associated with human ASD/ID. However, the causality and underlying mechanisms linking 12q24.31 microdeletions to ASD/ID pathogenesis remain undetermined. Here we show &lt;italic&gt;Kdm2b&lt;/italic&gt;, one of the genes located in chromosomal 12q24.31, plays a critical role in maintaining neural stem cells (NSCs) in the developing mouse brain. Loss of the CxxC-ZF domain of KDM2B impairs its function in recruiting Polycomb repressive complex 1 (PRC1) to chromatin, resulting in de-repression of genes involved in cell apoptosis, cell cycle arrest, NSC premature senescence, and leading to the loss of NSC populations in the brain. Importantly, the &lt;italic&gt;Kdm2b&lt;/italic&gt; mutation is sufficient to induce ASD/ID-like social and memory deficits in adult mice. Thus, our study reveals a critical role of an epigenetic factor KDM2B in normal brain development, a causality between the &lt;italic&gt;Kdm2b&lt;/italic&gt; mutation and genesis of ASD/ID-like phenotypes in mice, and potential molecular mechanisms linking the function of KDM2B-PRC1 in transcriptional regulation and NSC senescence to the12q24.31 microdeletion-associated ASD/ID.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.459918" rel="alternate" title="Impaired KDM2B-mediated PRC1 recruitment to chromatin causes neural stem cell senescence and ASD/ID-like behavioral deficits (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460257</id><title>Chronic sodium bromide treatment relieves autistic-like behavioral deficits in three mouse models of autism (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.770957+00:00</updated><author><name>Cécile Derieux</name></author><author><name>Audrey Léauté</name></author><author><name>Agathe Brugoux</name></author><author><name>Déborah Jacaz</name></author><author><name>Jean-Philippe Pin</name></author><author><name>Julie Kniazeff</name></author><author><name>Julie Le Merrer</name></author><author><name>Jerome AJ Becker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD) are neurodevelopmental disorders whose diagnosis relies on deficient social interaction and communication together with repetitive behavior. To date, no pharmacological treatment has been approved that ameliorates social behavior in patients with ASD. Based on the excitation/inhibition imbalance theory of autism, we hypothesized that bromide ions, long used as an antiepileptic medication, could relieve core symptoms of ASD. We evaluated the effects of chronic sodium bromide (NaBr) administration on autistic-like symptoms in three genetic mouse models of autism: &lt;italic&gt;Oprm1&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; , &lt;italic&gt;Fmr1&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Shank3&lt;sup&gt;Δex13-16-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice. We showed that chronic NaBr treatment relieved autistic-like behaviors in these three models. In &lt;italic&gt;Oprm1&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice, these beneficial effects were superior to those of chronic bumetanide administration. At transcriptional level, chronic NaBr in &lt;italic&gt;Oprm1&lt;/italic&gt; null mice was associated with increased expression of genes coding for chloride ions transporters, GABAA receptor subunits, oxytocin and mGlu4 receptor. Lastly, we uncovered synergistic alleviating effects of chronic NaBr and a positive allosteric modulator (PAM) of mGlu4 receptor on autistic-like behavior in &lt;italic&gt;Oprm1&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice. We evidenced in heterologous cells that bromide ions behave as PAMs of mGlu4, providing a molecular mechanism for such synergy. Our data reveal the therapeutic potential of bromide ions, alone or in combination with a PAM of mGlu4 receptor, for the treatment of ASDs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460257" rel="alternate" title="Chronic sodium bromide treatment relieves autistic-like behavioral deficits in three mouse models of autism (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.459937</id><title>Amelioration of L-DOPA-induced dyskinesia with vitamin D3 in Parkinsonian mice model (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.771137+00:00</updated><author><name>Adedamola Aminat Bayo-Olugbami</name></author><author><name>Abdulrazaq Bidemi Nafiu</name></author><author><name>Abdulbasit Amin</name></author><author><name>Olalekan Michael Ogundele</name></author><author><name>Charles C. Lee</name></author><author><name>Bamidele Victor Owoyele</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;L-DOPA Induced Dyskinesia (LID) is associated with prolonged L-DOPA therapy. Vitamin-D receptor modulation improves motor-cognitive deficit in experimental LID Parkinsonism. Therefore, in this study, we investigated the mechanism underlying the anti-dyskinetic potential of Vitamin D3 (VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;). Dyskinesia was induced by chronic L-DOPA administration in 6-OHDA lesioned male C57BL6 mice. The experimental groups (Dyskinesia, Dyskinesia/VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, and Dyskinesia/Amantadine) and controls were challenged with L-DOPA to determine the abnormal involuntary movements (AIMs) score during 14 days of VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (30 mg/kg) or Amantadine (40 mg/kg) treatment. Global behavioral Axial, Limb &amp;amp; Orolingual (ALO) AIMs were scored for 1 min at every 20 mins interval, over a duration of 100 mins on days 1,3,7,11 and 14 of treatment. Thereafter, brain samples were collected and processed for immunoblotting to assess striatal expression of tyrosine hydroxylase (TH), monoamine oxidase (MAO), cathecol-o-methyl transferase (COMT), dopamine decarboxylase (DDC), CD11b, BAX, P47phox, and IL-1β. VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; significantly attenuated ALO AIMs only on days 11 &amp;amp; 14, with maximal reduction of 32.7% compared with dyskinetic mice but had no effect on days 1, 3 &amp;amp; 7, while amantadine decreased AIMs all through days 1 to 14 with maximal reduction of 64.5%. TH and MAO-B expression were not significantly different across the groups. DDC was significantly suppressed in dyskinetic mice &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; control (p&amp;lt;0.001) but remained unchanged in VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; mice &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; dyskinetic mice. COMT was upregulated in the dyskinetic group &lt;italic&gt;vs&lt;/italic&gt; control (p&amp;lt;0.01) and attenuated in VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; mice (p&amp;lt;0.05) compared to the dyskinetic group. Interestingly, VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; inhibited significantly (p&amp;lt;0.01) oxidative stress (p47phox), apoptosis (BAX), inflammation (IL-1β), and microglial activation (CD11b) in dyskinetic mice. Overall, we find that the anti-dyskinetic effects of VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; is associated with modulation of striatal oxidative stress, microglial responses, inflammation, and apoptotic signaling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are evidences showing that VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; supplementation improves motor disorders, including Parkinson’s disease. We hypothesized that VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; could improve LID, an abnormal involuntary movement that results from prolonged L-DOPA therapy in the management of PD. We have demonstrated the novel anti-dyskinetic effect of VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and associated mechanistic factors in a mouse model of L-DOPA Induced Dyskinesia (LID), which identifies promising targets for dyskinesia therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.459937" rel="alternate" title="Amelioration of L-DOPA-induced dyskinesia with vitamin D3 in Parkinsonian mice model (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460803</id><title>CUX2 mutations in temporal lobe epilepsy; increased kainate susceptibility and excitatory input to hippocampus in deficient mice (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.771303+00:00</updated><author><name>Toshimitsu Suzuki</name></author><author><name>Tetsuya Tatsukawa</name></author><author><name>Genki Sudo</name></author><author><name>Caroline Delandre</name></author><author><name>Yun Jin Pai</name></author><author><name>Hiroyuki Miyamoto</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Raveau</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Shimohata</name></author><author><name>Iori Ohmori</name></author><author><name>Shin-ichiro Hamano</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiro Haginoya</name></author><author><name>Mitsugu Uematsu</name></author><author><name>Yukitoshi Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Masafumi Morimoto</name></author><author><name>Shinji Fujimoto</name></author><author><name>Hitoshi Osaka</name></author><author><name>Hirokazu Oguni</name></author><author><name>Makiko Osawa</name></author><author><name>Atsushi Ishii</name></author><author><name>Shinichi Hirose</name></author><author><name>Sunao Kaneko</name></author><author><name>Yushi Inoue</name></author><author><name>Adrian Walton Moore</name></author><author><name>Kazuhiro Yamakawa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt; gene encodes a transcription factor that controls neuronal proliferation, dendrite branching and synapse formation, locating at the epilepsy-associated chromosomal region 12q24 that we previously identified by a genome-wide association study (GWAS) in Japanese population. A &lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt; recurrent &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; variant p.E590K has been described in patients with rare epileptic encephalopathies and the gene is a candidate for the locus, however the mutation may not be enough to generate the genome-wide significance in the GWAS and whether &lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt; variants appear in other types of epilepsies and physiopathological mechanisms are remained to be investigated. Here in this study, we conducted targeted sequencings of &lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt;, a paralog &lt;italic&gt;CUX1&lt;/italic&gt; and its short isoform &lt;italic&gt;CASP&lt;/italic&gt; harboring a unique C-terminus on 271 Japanese patients with a variety of epilepsies, and found that multiple &lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt; missense variants, other than the p.E590K, and some &lt;italic&gt;CASP&lt;/italic&gt; variants including a deletion, predominantly appeared in patients with temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE). Human cell culture and fly dendritic arborization analyses revealed loss-of- function properties for the &lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt; variants. &lt;italic&gt;Cux2&lt;/italic&gt;- and &lt;italic&gt;Casp&lt;/italic&gt;-specific knockout mice both showed high susceptibility to kainate, increased excitatory cell number in the entorhinal cortex, and significant enhancement in glutamatergic synaptic transmission to the hippocampus. CASP and CUX2 proteins physiologically bound to each other and co-expressed in excitatory neurons in brain regions including the entorhinal cortex. These results suggest that &lt;italic&gt;CUX2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;CASP&lt;/italic&gt; variants contribute to the TLE pathology through a facilitation of excitatory synaptic transmission from entorhinal cortex to hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460803" rel="alternate" title="CUX2 mutations in temporal lobe epilepsy; increased kainate susceptibility and excitatory input to hippocampus in deficient mice (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.12.459983</id><title>Transcutaneous auricular vagus nerve stimulation increases eye-gaze on salient facial features and oxytocin release (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.771573+00:00</updated><author><name>Siyu Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yanan Qing</name></author><author><name>Yingying Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaolu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Fangyuan Ding</name></author><author><name>Rong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shuxia Yao</name></author><author><name>Keith Kendrick</name></author><author><name>Weihua Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcutaneous auricular vagus nerve stimulation (taVNS) is a non-invasive neuromodulation technique with promising therapeutic potential in the context of epilepsy, pain, and depression and which may also have beneficial effects on social cognition. However, the underlying mechanisms of taVNS are unclear and evidence regarding its role in social cognition improvement is limited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to investigate the impact of taVNS on social cognition we have studied its effects on gaze towards emotional faces using an eye-tracking task and also on release of the neuropeptide oxytocin which plays a key role in influencing social cognition and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of fifty-four subjects were enrolled in a sham-controlled, participant-blind crossover experiment, consisting of two treatment sessions, separated by one week. In one session participants received 30-min taVNS (tragus), and in the other, they received 30-min sham (earlobe) stimulation with the treatment order counterbalanced across participants. Gaze duration towards the faces and facial features (eyes, nose, and mouth) were measured together with resting pupil size. Additionally, saliva samples were taken for the measurement of oxytocin concentrations by enzyme-linked immunoassay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saliva oxytocin concentrations increased significantly after taVNS compared to sham stimulation, while resting pupil size did not. In addition, taVNS increased fixation time on the nose region irrespective of face emotion, and this was positively correlated with increased saliva oxytocin concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings suggest that taVNS biases visual attention towards socially salient facial features across different emotions and this is associated with its effects on increasing endogenous oxytocin release.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.12.459983" rel="alternate" title="Transcutaneous auricular vagus nerve stimulation increases eye-gaze on salient facial features and oxytocin release (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>