<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.445675+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473349</id><title>All-optical imaging and patterned stimulation with a one-photon endoscope (88 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.446112+00:00</updated><author><name>Jinyong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ryan N. Hughes</name></author><author><name>Namsoo Kim</name></author><author><name>Isabella P. Fallon</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Bakhurin</name></author><author><name>Jiwon Kim</name></author><author><name>Francesco Paolo Ulloa Severino</name></author><author><name>Henry H. Yin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While in vivo calcium imaging makes it possible to record activity in defined neuronal populations with cellular resolution, optogenetics allows selective manipulation of neural activity. Recently, these two tools have been combined to stimulate and record neural activity at the same time, but current approaches often rely on two-photon microscopes that are difficult to use in freely moving animals. To address these limitations, we have developed a new integrated system combining a one-photon endoscope and a digital micromirror device for simultaneous calcium imaging and precise optogenetic photo-stimulation with near cellular resolution (Miniscope with All-optical Patterned Stimulation and Imaging, MAPSI). Using this highly portable system in freely moving mice, we were able to image striatal neurons from either the direct pathway or the indirect pathway while simultaneously activating any neuron of choice in the field of view, or to synthesize arbitrary spatiotemporal patterns of photo-stimulation. We could also select neurons based on their relationship with behavior and recreate the behavior by mimicking the natural neural activity with photo-stimulation. MAPSI thus provides a powerful tool for interrogation of neural circuit function in freely moving animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473349" rel="alternate" title="All-optical imaging and patterned stimulation with a one-photon endoscope (88 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473723</id><title>Striatal dopamine explains novelty-induced behavioral dynamics and individual variability in threat prediction (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.446461+00:00</updated><author><name>Korleki Akiti</name></author><author><name>Iku Tsutsui-Kimura</name></author><author><name>Yudi Xie</name></author><author><name>Alexander Mathis</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Markowitz</name></author><author><name>Rockwell Anyoha</name></author><author><name>Sandeep Robert Datta</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie Weygandt Mathis</name></author><author><name>Naoshige Uchida</name></author><author><name>Mitsuko Watabe-Uchida</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals exhibit diverse behavioral responses, such as exploration and avoidance, to novel cues in the environment. However, it remains unclear how dopamine neuron-related novelty responses influence behavior. Here, we characterized dynamics of novelty exploration using multi-point tracking (DeepLabCut) and behavioral segmentation (MoSeq). Novelty elicits a characteristic sequence of behavior, starting with investigatory approach and culminating in object engagement or avoidance. Dopamine in the tail of striatum (TS) suppresses engagement, and dopamine responses were predictive of individual variability in behavior. Behavioral dynamics and individual variability were explained by a novel reinforcement learning (RL) model of threat prediction, in which behavior arises from a novelty-induced initial threat prediction (akin to “shaping bonus”), and a threat prediction that is learned through dopamine-mediated threat prediction errors. These results uncover an algorithmic similarity between reward- and threat-related dopamine sub-systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Novelty-induced behaviors are analyzed using modern machine-learning methods&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Novelty induces risk assessment which develops into engagement or avoidance&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dopamine in the tail of striatum correlates with individual behavioral variability&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning with shaping bonus and uncertainty explains the data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473723" rel="alternate" title="Striatal dopamine explains novelty-induced behavioral dynamics and individual variability in threat prediction (56 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473863</id><title>Distinct hippocampal network states support theta phase precession and theta sequences in CA1 (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.446699+00:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Guardamagna</name></author><author><name>Federico Stella</name></author><author><name>Francesco P. Battaglia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hippocampus likely uses temporal coding to represent complex memories via mechanisms such as theta phase precession and theta sequences. Theta sequences are rapid sweeps of spikes from multiple place cells, encoding past or planned trajectories or non-spatial information. Phase precession, the correlation between a place cell's theta firing phase and animal position has been suggested to facilitate sequence emergence. We find that CA1 phase precession varies strongly across cells and environmental contingencies. Phase precession depends on the CA1 network state, and is only present when the medium gamma oscillation (60-90 Hz, linked to Entorhinal inputs) dominates. Conversely, theta sequences are most evident for non-precessing cells or with leading slow gamma (20-45 Hz, linked to CA3 inputs). These results challenge the view that phase precession is the mechanism underlying the emergence of theta sequences and point at a 'dual network states' model for hippocampal temporal code, potentially supporting merging of memory and exogenous information in CA1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473863" rel="alternate" title="Distinct hippocampal network states support theta phase precession and theta sequences in CA1 (43 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473899</id><title>Quantifying the inverted U: A meta-analysis of prefrontal dopamine, D1-receptors, and working memory (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.446870+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew A. Weber</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie M. Conlon</name></author><author><name>Hannah R. Stutt</name></author><author><name>Linder Wendt</name></author><author><name>Patrick Ten Eyck</name></author><author><name>Nandakumar S. Narayanan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dopamine in the prefrontal cortex can be disrupted in human disorders that affect cognitive function such as Parkinson's disease (PD), attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), and schizophrenia. Dopamine has a powerful effect on prefrontal circuits via the D1-type dopamine receptor (D1DR). It has been proposed that prefrontal dopamine has "inverted U-shaped" dynamics, with optimal dopamine and D1DR signaling required for optimal cognitive function. However, the quantitative relationship between prefrontal dopamine and cognitive function is not clear. Here, we conducted a meta-analysis of published manipulations of prefrontal dopamine and the effects on working memory, a high-level executive function in humans, primates, and rodents that involves maintaining and manipulating information over seconds to minutes. We reviewed 646 papers and found that 75 studies met criteria for inclusion. Our quantification of effect sizes for dopamine, D1DRs, and behavior revealed a negative quadratic slope. This is consistent with the proposed inverted U-shape of prefrontal dopamine and D1DRs and working memory performance, explaining 10% of the variance. Of note, the inverted quadratic fit was much stronger for prefrontal D1DRs alone, explaining 26% of the variance, compared to prefrontal dopamine alone, explaining 10% of the variance. Taken together, these data, derived from a variety of manipulations and systems, demonstrate that optimal prefrontal dopamine signalling is linked with higher cognitive function. Our results provide insight into the fundamental dynamics of prefrontal dopamine, which could be useful for pharmacological interventions targeting prefrontal dopaminergic circuits, and into the pathophysiology of human brain disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473899" rel="alternate" title="Quantifying the inverted U: A meta-analysis of prefrontal dopamine, D1-receptors, and working memory (27 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473276</id><title>When self comes to a wandering mind: Brain representations and dynamics of self-generated concepts in spontaneous thought (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.447062+00:00</updated><author><name>Byeol Kim</name></author><author><name>Jessica R. Andrews-Hanna</name></author><author><name>Jihoon Han</name></author><author><name>Eunjin Lee</name></author><author><name>Choong-Wan Woo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Self-relevant concepts are major building blocks of spontaneous thought, and their dynamics in a natural stream of thought are likely to reveal one’s internal states important for mental health. Here we conducted an fMRI experiment (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 62) to examine brain representations and dynamics of self-generated concepts in the context of spontaneous thought using a newly developed free association-based thought sampling task. The dynamics of conceptual associations were predictive of individual differences in general negative affectivity, replicating across multiple datasets (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 196). Reflecting on self-generated concepts strongly engaged brain regions linked to autobiographical memory, conceptual processes, emotion, and autonomic regulation, including the medial prefrontal and medial temporal subcortical structures. Multivariate pattern-based predictive modeling revealed that the neural representations of valence became more person-specific as the level of perceived self-relevance increased. Overall, this study provides a hint of how self-generated concepts in spontaneous thought construct inner affective states and idiosyncrasies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473276" rel="alternate" title="When self comes to a wandering mind: Brain representations and dynamics of self-generated concepts in spontaneous thought (24 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473436</id><title>“Prefrontal cortical contributions to working memory loading, maintenance and recall are parsed by hippocampal-prefrontal oscillatory assembly dynamics” (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.447244+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleksander P.F. Domanski</name></author><author><name>Michal T. Kucewicz</name></author><author><name>Eleonora Russo</name></author><author><name>Mark D. Tricklebank</name></author><author><name>Emma S.J. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Durstewitz</name></author><author><name>Matt W. Jones</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Working memory enables incorporation of recent experience into subsequent decision-making. This processing recruits both prefrontal cortex and hippocampus, where neurons encode task cues, rules and outcomes. However, precisely which information is carried when, and by which neurons, remains unclear. Using population decoding of activity in rat medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) and dorsal hippocampal CA1, we confirm that mPFC populations lead in maintaining sample information across delays of an operant nonmatch to sample task, despite individual neurons firing only transiently. During sample encoding, distinct mPFC subpopulations joined distributed CA1-mPFC cell assemblies hallmarked by 4-5Hz rhythmic modulation; CA1-mPFC assemblies re-emerged during choice episodes, but were not 4-5Hz modulated. Delay-dependent errors arose when attenuated rhythmic assembly activity heralded collapse of sustained mPFC encoding; pharmacological disruption of CA1-mPFC assembly rhythmicity impaired task performance. Our results map component processes of memory-guided decisions onto heterogeneous CA1-mPFC subpopulations and the dynamics of physiologically distinct, distributed cell assemblies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473436" rel="alternate" title="“Prefrontal cortical contributions to working memory loading, maintenance and recall are parsed by hippocampal-prefrontal oscillatory assembly dynamics” (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473367</id><title>Cerebellar GABA change during visuomotor adaptation relates to adaptation performance and cerebellar network connectivity: A Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopic Imaging study (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.447522+00:00</updated><author><name>Caroline R Nettekoven</name></author><author><name>Leah Mitchell</name></author><author><name>William T Clarke</name></author><author><name>Uzay Emir</name></author><author><name>Heidi Johansen-Berg</name></author><author><name>Ned Jenkinson</name></author><author><name>Charlotte J Stagg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motor adaptation is crucial for performing accurate movements in a changing environment and relies on the cerebellum. Although cerebellar involvement has been well characterized, the neurochemical changes in the cerebellum that underpin human motor adaptation remain unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used a novel Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopic Imaging (MRSI) technique to measure changes in the major inhibitory neurotransmitter γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA) in the human cerebellum during visuomotor adaptation. Participants used their right hand to adapt to a rotated cursor in the scanner, compared with a control task requiring no adaptation. We were able to spatially resolve adaptation-driven GABA changes at the cerebellar nuclei and in the cerebellar cortex in the left and the right cerebellar hemisphere independently and found that simple movement of the right hand increases GABA in the right cerebellar nuclei and decreases GABA in the left. When isolating adaptation-driven GABA changes, we found an increase in GABA in the left cerebellar nuclei and a decrease in GABA in the right cerebellar nuclei during adaptation. Early adaptation-driven GABA change in the right cerebellar nuclei correlated with adaptation performance: Participants showing greater GABA decrease adapted better, suggesting that this early GABA change is behaviourally relevant. Early GABA change also correlated with functional connectivity change in a cerebellar network: Participants showing a greater decrease in GABA also showed greater strength increase in cerebellar network connectivity. These results were specific to GABA, specific to adaptation and specific to the cerebellar network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the first evidence for plastic changes in cerebellar neurochemistry during a motor adaptation task. Characterising these naturally occurring neurochemical changes may provide a basis for developing therapeutic interventions to facilitate neurochemical changes in the cerebellum that can improve human motor adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite motor adaptation being fundamental to maintaining accurate movements, its neurochemical basis remains poorly understood, perhaps because measuring neurochemicals in the human cerebellum is technically challenging. Using a novel magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging method, this study provides evidence for GABA changes in the left and right cerebellar nuclei driven by both simple movement and motor adaptation. The adaptation-driven GABA change in the right cerebellar nuclei correlated with adaptation performance, and with functional connectivity change in a cerebellar network. These results show the first evidence for plastic changes in cerebellar neurochemistry during a cerebellar learning task. This provides the basis for developing therapeutic interventions that facilitate these naturally occurring changes to amplify cerebellar-dependent learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473367" rel="alternate" title="Cerebellar GABA change during visuomotor adaptation relates to adaptation performance and cerebellar network connectivity: A Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopic Imaging study (20 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474002</id><title>Neurons burdened by DNA double strand breaks incite microglia activation through antiviral-like signaling in neurodegeneration. (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.447723+00:00</updated><author><name>Gwyneth M Welch</name></author><author><name>Carles Adsera Boix</name></author><author><name>Eloi Schmauch</name></author><author><name>Jose Davila-Velderrain</name></author><author><name>Matheus B. Victor</name></author><author><name>Vishnu Dileep</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Bozzelli</name></author><author><name>Jemmie D Cheng</name></author><author><name>Audrey Lee</name></author><author><name>Audrey Lee</name></author><author><name>Qiao Su</name></author><author><name>Andreas R Pfenning</name></author><author><name>Manolis Kellis</name></author><author><name>Li-Huei Tsai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA double strand breaks (DSBs) are linked to aging, neurodegeneration, and senescence. However, the role played by neurons burdened with DSBs in disease-associated neuroinflammation is not well understood. Here, we isolate neurons harboring DSBs from the CK-p25 mouse model of neurodegeneration through fluorescence-activated nuclei sorting (FANS), and characterize their transcriptomes using single-nucleus, bulk, and spatial sequencing techniques. We find that neurons harboring DSBs enter a late-stage DNA damage response marked by the activation of senescent and antiviral-like immune pathways. We identify the NFkB transcription factor as a master regulator of immune gene expression in DSB-bearing neurons, and find that the expression of cytokines like Cxcl10 and Ccl2 develop in DSB-bearing neurons before glial cell types. Alzheimers Disease pathology is significantly associated with immune activation in excitatory neurons, and direct purification of DSB-bearing neurons from Alzheimers Disease brain tissue further validates immune gene upregulation. Spatial transcriptomics reveal that regions of brain tissue dense with DSB-bearing neurons also harbor signatures of inflammatory microglia, which is ameliorated by NFkB knock down in neurons. Inhibition of NFkB or depletion of Ccl2 and Cxcl10 in DSB-bearing neurons also reduces microglial activation in organotypic brain slice culture. In conclusion, we find that in the context of age-associated neurodegenerative disease, DSBs activate immune pathways in neurons, which in turn adopt a senescence associated secretory phenotype to elicit microglia activation. These findings highlight a novel role for neurons in the mechanism of age-associated neuroinflammation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474002" rel="alternate" title="Neurons burdened by DNA double strand breaks incite microglia activation through antiviral-like signaling in neurodegeneration. (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473036</id><title>Electrobehavioral phenotype and seizure pharmacosensitivity in a novel mouse model of patient-derived SLC6A1 S295L mutation-associated neurodevelopmental epilepsy (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.447985+00:00</updated><author><name>Britta E. Lindquist</name></author><author><name>Yuliya Voskobiynyk</name></author><author><name>Jeanne T. Paz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Solute carrier family 6 member 1 (&lt;italic&gt;SLC6A1&lt;/italic&gt;) gene encodes GAT-1, a GABA transporter expressed on glia and presynaptic terminals of inhibitory neurons. Mutations in &lt;italic&gt;SLC6A1&lt;/italic&gt; are associated with myoclonic atonic epilepsy, absence epilepsy, autism, and intellectual disability. However, the mechanisms leading to these defects are unknown. Here, we used a novel mouse model harboring a point mutation (S295L) recently identified in the human &lt;italic&gt;SLC6A1&lt;/italic&gt; gene that results in impaired membrane trafficking of the GAT-1 protein. We performed chronic wireless telemetry recordings of heterozygous (GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;S295L/+&lt;/sup&gt;) mice, and of mice lacking one or both copies of the gene (GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;+/−&lt;/sup&gt; and GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;−/−&lt;/sup&gt;). We assessed their behaviors and pharmacosensitivity, and investigated the relationship between seizure burden and behavioral performance. GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;S295L/+&lt;/sup&gt; mice exhibited frequent spikewave discharges (SWDs) associated with behavioral arrest, and there was a dose-effect relationship between GAT-1 gene copy number and the severity of electrocorticogram (ECoG) abnormalities. Seizure burden was inversely correlated with behavioral performance. Forelimb grip strength was reduced in female mice. Acute administration of GAT-1 antagonist NO-711 induced SWDs in wildtype mice, exacerbated the phenotype in GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;S295L/+&lt;/sup&gt; and GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;+/−&lt;/sup&gt; mice, and had no effect on GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;−/−&lt;/sup&gt; mice lacking the drug target. By contrast, ethosuximide normalized the ECoG in GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;S295L/+&lt;/sup&gt; and GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;+/−&lt;/sup&gt; mice. In conclusion, GAT-1&lt;sup&gt;S295L/+&lt;/sup&gt; mice show haploinsufficiency with evidence of GAT-1 hypofunction. This mouse model reconstitutes major aspects of human disease and thus provides a useful preclinical model for drug screening and gene therapy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;italic&gt;SLC6A1&lt;/italic&gt; gene encodes for GAT-1, a major GABA transporter. Mutations in &lt;italic&gt;SLC6A1&lt;/italic&gt; lead to a spectrum of neurodevelopmental disorders and epilepsies collectively referred to as &lt;italic&gt;SLC6A1&lt;/italic&gt;-related disorders (SRD). A critical contributor to disability in SRD patients is the burden of seizures and their sequelae. There is an urgent need to understand the mechanisms of SRD as they will inform therapeutic interventions. Mouse models can provide critical information allowing both the assessment of candidate therapies and the design of next generations therapies. Here we used behavioral assessments and wireless electrophysiology in a new mouse model of SRD to understand the disease pathogenesis and the association between seizure burden and behavioral deficits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473036" rel="alternate" title="Electrobehavioral phenotype and seizure pharmacosensitivity in a novel mouse model of patient-derived SLC6A1 S295L mutation-associated neurodevelopmental epilepsy (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473901</id><title>Identifying control ensembles for decision-making within the cortico-basal ganglia-thalamic circuit (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.448154+00:00</updated><author><name>Catalina Vich</name></author><author><name>Matthew Clapp</name></author><author><name>Timothy Verstynen</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Rubin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During action selection, mammals exhibit a high degree of flexibility in adapting their decisions in response to environmental changes. Although the cortico-basal ganglia-thalamic (CBGT) network is implicated in this adaptation, it features a synaptic architecture comprising multiple feed-forward, reciprocal, and feedback pathways, complicating efforts to elucidate the roles of specific CBGT populations in the process of evidence accumulation during decision-making. In this paper we apply a strategic sampling approach, based on Latin hypercube sampling, to explore how CBGT network properties, including subpopulation firing rates and synaptic weights, map to parameters of a normative drift diffusion model (DDM) representing algorithmic aspects of information accumulation during decision-making. Through the application of canonical correlation analysis, we find that this relationship can be characterized in terms of three low-dimensional control ensembles impacting specific qualities of the emergent decision policy: responsiveness (associated with overall activity in corticothalamic and direct pathways), pliancy (associated largely with overall activity in components of the indirect pathway of the basal ganglia), and choice (associated with differences in direct and indirect pathways across action channels). These analyses provide key mechanistic predictions about the roles of specific CBGT network elements in shifting different aspects of decision policies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473901" rel="alternate" title="Identifying control ensembles for decision-making within the cortico-basal ganglia-thalamic circuit (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473320</id><title>A mechanistically interpretable model of the retinal neural code for natural scenes with multiscale adaptive dynamics (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.448361+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuehao Ding</name></author><author><name>Dongsoo Lee</name></author><author><name>Satchel Grant</name></author><author><name>Heike Stein</name></author><author><name>Lane McIntosh</name></author><author><name>Niru Maheswaranathan</name></author><author><name>Stephen Baccus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The visual system processes stimuli over a wide range of spatiotemporal scales, with individual neurons receiving input from tens of thousands of neurons whose dynamics range from milliseconds to tens of seconds. This poses a challenge to create models that both accurately capture visual computations and are mechanistically interpretable. Here we present a model of salamander retinal ganglion cell spiking responses recorded with a multielectrode array that captures natural scene responses and slow adaptive dynamics. The model consists of a three-layer convolutional neural network (CNN) modified to include local recurrent synaptic dynamics taken from a linear-nonlinear-kinetic (LNK) model [1]. We presented alternating natural scenes and uniform field white noise stimuli designed to engage slow contrast adaptation. To overcome difficulties fitting slow and fast dynamics together, we first optimized all fast spatiotemporal parameters, then separately optimized recurrent slow synaptic parameters. The resulting full model reproduces a wide range of retinal computations and is mechanistically interpretable, having internal units that correspond to retinal interneurons with biophysically modeled synapses. This model allows us to study the contribution of model units to any retinal computation, and examine how long-term adaptation changes the retinal neural code for natural scenes through selective adaptation of retinal pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.18.473320" rel="alternate" title="A mechanistically interpretable model of the retinal neural code for natural scenes with multiscale adaptive dynamics (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474027</id><title>Pharmacological blockade of muscle afferents and perception of effort: a systematic review with meta-analysis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.448589+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxime Bergevin</name></author><author><name>James Steele</name></author><author><name>Marie Payen de la Garanderie</name></author><author><name>Camille Feral-Basin</name></author><author><name>Samuele M Marcora</name></author><author><name>Pierre Rainville</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey G Caron</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Pageaux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The perception of effort (PE) provides information on task difficulty and influences physical exercise regulation and human behavior. This perception differs from other-exercise related perceptions such as pain. There is no consensus on the role of group III-IV muscle afferents as a signal processed by the brain to generate PE. The aim of this meta-analysis was to investigate the effect of pharmacologically blocking muscle afferents on the PE. Six databases were searched to identify studies measuring the ratings of perceived effort (RPE) during physical exercise, with and without pharmacological blockade of muscle afferents. Articles were coded based on the operational measurement used to distinguish studies in which PE was assessed specifically (effort dissociated) or as a composite experience including other exercise-related perceptions (effort not dissociated). Articles that did not provide enough information for coding were assigned to the unclear group. The effort dissociated group (n=6) demonstrated a slight RPE increase with reduced muscle afferents feedback (standard mean change raw (SMCR), 0.39; 95%CI, 0.13 to 0.64). The group effort not dissociated (n=2) did not reveal conclusive results (SMCR, -0.29; 95%CI, -2.39 to 1.8). The group unclear (n=8) revealed a slight RPE decrease with reduced muscle afferents feedback (SMCR, -0.27; 95%CI, -0.50 to -0.04). The heterogeneity in results between groups reveals that the inclusion of other perceptions than effort in its rating influences the RPE scores reported by the participants. The absence of decreased RPE in the effort dissociated group suggests that muscle afferents feedback is not a sensory signal generating PE.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.474027" rel="alternate" title="Pharmacological blockade of muscle afferents and perception of effort: a systematic review with meta-analysis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473191</id><title>Sensory cortical dynamics during optical microstimulation training (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.448795+00:00</updated><author><name>Ravi Pancholi</name></author><author><name>Lauren Ryan</name></author><author><name>Simon Peron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Primary sensory cortex is a key locus of plasticity during learning. Exposure to novel stimuli often alters cortical activity, but isolating cortex-specific dynamics is challenging due to extensive pre-cortical processing. Here, we employ optical microstimulation of pyramidal neurons in layer (L) 2/3 of mouse primary vibrissal somatosensory cortex (vS1) to study cortical dynamics as mice learn to discriminate microstimulation intensity. Tracking activity over weeks using two-photon calcium imaging, we observe a rapid sparsification of the photoresponsive population, with the most responsive neurons exhibiting the largest declines in responsiveness. Following sparsification, the photoresponsive population attains a stable rate of neuronal turnover. At the same time, the photoresponsive population increasingly overlaps with populations encoding whisker movement and touch. Finally, we find that mice with larger declines in responsiveness learn the task more slowly than mice with smaller declines. Our results reveal that microstimulation-evoked cortical activity undergoes extensive reorganization during task learning and that the dynamics of this reorganization impact perception.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473191" rel="alternate" title="Sensory cortical dynamics during optical microstimulation training (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473671</id><title>A network model of the modulation of gamma oscillations by NMDA receptors in cerebral cortex (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.448963+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduarda Susin</name></author><author><name>Alain Destexhe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Psychotic drugs such as ketamine induce symptoms close to schizophrenia, and stimulates the production of gamma oscillations, as also seen in patients, but the underlying mechanisms are still unclear. Here, we have used computational models of cortical networks generating gamma oscillations, and have integrated the action of drugs such as ketamine to partially block n-methyl-d-Aspartate (NMDA) receptors. The model can reproduce the modulation of gamma oscillations by NMDA-receptor antagonists, assuming that antagonists affect NMDA receptors predominantly on inhibitory interneurons. We next used the model to compare the responsiveness of the network to external stimuli, and found that when NMDA channnels are blocked an increase of Gamma power is observed altogether with an increase of network responsiveness. However, this responsiveness increase applies not only to gamma states, but also to synchronous states with no apparent gamma. We conclude that NMDA antagonists induce increased excitability state, which may or may not produce gamma oscillations, but the response to external inputs is exacerbated, which may explain phenomena such as altered perception or hallucinations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473671" rel="alternate" title="A network model of the modulation of gamma oscillations by NMDA receptors in cerebral cortex (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473905</id><title>Distribution of phosphorylated alpha-synuclein in non-diseased brain implicates olfactory bulb mitral cells in synucleinopathy pathogenesis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.449124+00:00</updated><author><name>Bryan A Killinger</name></author><author><name>Patrik Brundin</name></author><author><name>Jeffery H Kordower</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Mercado</name></author><author><name>Solji G Choi</name></author><author><name>Yaping Chu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synucleinopathies including Parkinsons disease and dementia with Lewy bodies are neurodegenerative diseases characterized by the intracellular accumulation of the protein alpha-synuclein called Lewy pathology.  Alpha-synuclein within Lewy pathology is aggregated into protease resistant filamentous structures and is predominantly phosphorylated at serine 129 (PSER129).  Lewy pathology has been hypothesized to spread throughout the nervous system as the disease progresses. Cross-sectional studies have shown the olfactory bulb and olfactory tract consistently bare LP for common synucleinopathies, making these structures likely starting points for the spreading process, and thus disease. Here we examined the distribution of PSER129 in non-diseased brain. To do this we used a sensitive tyramide signal amplification (TSA) technique to detect low abundance endogenous PSER129 under ideal antibody binding conditions. In wild-type non-diseased mice, PSER129 was detected in the olfactory bulb and several brain regions of the olfactory cortex across the neuroaxis (i.e., olfactory bulb to brain stem). PSER129 was particularly apparent in the mitral cell layer and the outer plexiform layer of the olfactory bulb where it was observed as cytosolic/nuclear puncta or fibers, respectively. PSER129 immunoreactivity in the healthy olfactory bulb was abolished by pretreatment of the tissue with proteinase K, pre-absorption of the primary antibody against the purified PSER129 peptide fragment, or the omission of the PSER129 antibody. Furthermore, PSER129 immunoreactivity was not observed in any brain region of alpha-synuclein knockout mice. Dual labeling for the PSER129 and the mitral cell marker TBX21 showed that PSER129 positive structures of the healthy OB were found in mitral cells. We found evidence of the same PSER129 positive structures in the olfactory bulb of non-diseased rats, non-human primates, healthy humans, but not individuals diagnosed with PD. Results suggest biological pathways responsible for alpha-synuclein phosphorylation are constitutively active in OB mitral cells and alpha-synuclein in these cells may be predisposed to pathological aggregation. Pathological seeds originating in mitral cells may act as a source for alpha-synuclein spread competent assemblies that spreads throughout the brain via fibers of the olfactory tract. Future studies should investigate the normal function of alpha-synuclein in the mitral cells of the olfactory bulb, which may give insight into synucleinopathy disease origins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473905" rel="alternate" title="Distribution of phosphorylated alpha-synuclein in non-diseased brain implicates olfactory bulb mitral cells in synucleinopathy pathogenesis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473383</id><title>Neuronal primary cilia regulate pyramidal cell positioning to the deep and superficial sublayers in the hippocampal CA1 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.449351+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Yang</name></author><author><name>Liyan Qiu</name></author><author><name>Xuanmao Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is well-recognized that primary cilia regulate embryonic neurodevelopment, but little is known about their roles in postnatal neurodevelopment. The striatum pyramidal (SP) of hippocampal CA1 consists of superficial and deep sublayers, however, it is not well understood how early- and late-born pyramidal neurons position to two sublayers postnatally. Here we show that neuronal primary cilia emerge after CA1 pyramidal cells have reached SP, but before final neuronal positioning. The axonemes of primary cilia of early-born neurons point to the stratum oriens (SO), whereas late-born neuronal cilia orient toward the stratum radiatum (SR), reflecting an inside-out lamination pattern. Neuronal primary cilia in SP undergo marked changes in morphology and orientation from postnatal day 5 (P5) to P14, concurrent with pyramidal cell positioning to the deep and superficial sublayers and with neuronal maturation. Transgenic overexpression of Arl13B, a protein regulating ciliogenesis, not only elongates primary cilia and promotes earlier cilia protrusion, but also affects centriole positioning and cilia orientation in SP. The centrioles of late-born neurons migrate excessively to cluster at SP bottom before primary cilia protrusion and a reverse movement back to the main SP. Similarly, this “pull-back” movement of centriole/cilia is also identified on late-born cortical pyramidal neurons, although early- and late-born cortical neurons display the same cilia orientation. Together, this study provides the first evidence demonstrating that late-born pyramidal neurons exhibit a reverse movement for cell positioning, and primary cilia regulate pyramidal neuronal positioning to the deep and superficial sublayers in the hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473383" rel="alternate" title="Neuronal primary cilia regulate pyramidal cell positioning to the deep and superficial sublayers in the hippocampal CA1 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473699</id><title>Directed motor actions and choice signalling drive cortical acetylcholine dynamics. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.449650+00:00</updated><author><name>Jing Zou</name></author><author><name>Simon Trinh</name></author><author><name>Andrew Erskine</name></author><author><name>Miao Jing</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Yao</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Walker</name></author><author><name>Yulong Li</name></author><author><name>Samuel Andrew Hires</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Numerous cognitive functions including attention, learning, and plasticity are influenced by the dynamic patterns of acetylcholine release across the brain. How acetylcholine mediates these functions in cortex remains unclear, as the spatiotemporal relationship between cortical acetylcholine and behavioral events has not been precisely measured across task learning. To dissect this relationship, we quantified motor behavior and sub-second acetylcholine dynamics in primary somatosensory cortex during acquisition and performance of a tactile-guided object localization task. We found that acetylcholine dynamics were spatially homogenous and directly attributable to whisker motion and licking, rather than sensory cues or reward delivery. As task performance improved across training, acetylcholine release to the first lick in a trial became dramatically and specifically potentiated, paralleling the emergence of a choice-signalling basis for this motor action. These results show that acetylcholine dynamics in sensory cortex are driven by directed motor actions to gather information and act upon it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473699" rel="alternate" title="Directed motor actions and choice signalling drive cortical acetylcholine dynamics. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473608</id><title>Gustatory cortex is involved in evidence accumulation during food choice (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.449890+00:00</updated><author><name>Ali Ataei</name></author><author><name>Arash Amini</name></author><author><name>Ali Ghazizadeh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Food choice is one of the most fundamental and most frequent value-based decisions for all animals including humans. However, the neural circuitry involved in food-based decisions is only recently being addressed. Given the relatively fast dynamics of decision formation, EEG-informed fMRI analysis is highly beneficial for localizing this circuitry in humans. Here by using the EEG correlates of evidence accumulation in a simultaneously recorded EEG-fMRI dataset, we found a significant role for the right temporal-parietal operculum (PO) and medial insula including gustatory cortex (GC) in binary choice between food items. These activations were uncovered by using the “EEG energy” (power 2) as the BOLD regressor and were missed if conventional analysis with the EEG signal itself were to be used, in agreement with theoretical predictions for EEG and BOLD relations. No significant positive correlations were found with higher powers of EEG (powers 3 or 4) pointing to specificity and sufficiency of EEG energy as the main correlate of the BOLD response. This finding extends the role of cortical areas traditionally involved in palatability processing to value-based decision making and offers the “EEG energy” as a key regressor of BOLD response in simultaneous EEG-fMRI designs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473608" rel="alternate" title="Gustatory cortex is involved in evidence accumulation during food choice (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473984</id><title>Reward priming differentially modulates enhancement and inhibition in auditory decision-making (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.450065+00:00</updated><author><name>Hidekazu Nagamura</name></author><author><name>Hiroshi Onishi</name></author><author><name>Momoko Hishitani</name></author><author><name>Shota Murai</name></author><author><name>Yuma Osako</name></author><author><name>Kohta I. Kobayasi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In cognitive sciences, rewards, such as money and food, play a fundamental role in individuals' daily lives and well-being. Moreover, rewards that are irrelevant to the task alter individuals' behavior. However, it is unclear whether explicit knowledge of reward irrelevancy has an impact on reward priming enhancements and inhibition. In this study, an auditory change-detection task with task-irrelevant rewards was introduced. The participants were informed explicitly in advance that the rewards would be given randomly. The results revealed that while inhibition related to reward priming only occurred when the participants were explicitly informed about rewards, implicit instruction thereof resulted in enhancement and inhibition associated with reward priming. These findings highlight the contribution of explicit information about rewards associated with auditory decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473984" rel="alternate" title="Reward priming differentially modulates enhancement and inhibition in auditory decision-making (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473708</id><title>How synaptic strength, short-term plasticity, and temporal factors contribute to neuronal spike output (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.450258+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Gastone Guilabert</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Ehret</name></author><author><name>Moritz O. Buchholz</name></author><author><name>Gregor F.P. Schuhknecht</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To compute spiking responses, neurons integrate inputs from thousands of synapses whose strengths span an order of magnitude. Intriguingly, in mouse neocortex, the small minority of 'strong' synapses is found predominantly between similarly tuned cells, suggesting they are the synapses that determine a neuron's spike output. This raises the question of how other computational primitives, such as 'background' activity from the majority of synapses, which are 'weak', short-term plasticity, and temporal synchrony contribute to spiking. First, we combined extracellular stimulation and whole-cell recordings in mouse barrel cortex to map the distribution of excitatory postsynaptic potential (EPSP) amplitudes and paired-pulse ratios of excitatory synaptic connections converging onto individual layer 2/3 (L2/3) neurons. While generally net short-term plasticity was weak, connections with EPSPs &amp;gt; 2 mV displayed pronounced paired-pulse depression. EPSP amplitudes and paired-pulse ratios of connections converging onto the same neurons spanned the full range observed across L2/3 and there was no indication that strong synapses nor those with particular short-term plasticity properties were associated with particular cells, which critically constrains theoretical models of cortical filtering. To investigate how different computational primitives of synaptic information processing interact to shape spiking, we developed a computational model of a pyramidal neuron in the rodent L2/3 circuitry: firing rates and pairwise correlations of presynaptic inputs were constrained by in vivo observations, while synaptic strength and short-term plasticity were set based on our experimental data. Importantly, we found that the ability of strong inputs to evoke spiking critically depended on their high temporal synchrony and high firing rates observed in vivo and on synaptic background activity - and not primarily on synaptic strength, which in turn further enhanced information transfer. Depression of strong synapses was critical for maintaining a neuron's responsivity and prevented runaway excitation. Our results provide a holistic framework of how cortical neurons exploit complex synergies between temporal coding, synaptic properties, and noise in order to transform synaptic inputs into output firing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473708" rel="alternate" title="How synaptic strength, short-term plasticity, and temporal factors contribute to neuronal spike output (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473936</id><title>An in vivo, neuron-specific approach for pairing translational and epigenetic signatures of early-life exercise (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.450439+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Mark Raus</name></author><author><name>Tyson D Fuller</name></author><author><name>Nellie E Nelson</name></author><author><name>David A Valientes</name></author><author><name>Anita Bayat</name></author><author><name>Autumn S Ivy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aerobic exercise promotes physiological and molecular adaptations in neurons to influence brain function and behavior. The most well studied neurobiological consequences of exercise are those which underlie exercise-induced improvements in hippocampal memory, including the expression and regulation of the neurotrophic factor Bdnf. Whether aerobic exercise taking place during early-life periods of postnatal brain maturation has similar impacts on gene expression and its regulation remains to be investigated. Using unbiased next-generation sequencing we characterize gene expression programs and their regulation by specific, memory-associated histone modifications during juvenile-adolescent voluntary exercise (ELE). Traditional transcriptomic and epigenomic sequencing approaches have either used heterogeneous cell populations from whole tissue homogenates or flow cytometry for single cell isolation to distinguish cell types / subtypes. These methods fall short in providing cell-type specificity without compromising sequencing depth or procedure-induced changes to cellular phenotype. In this study, we use simultaneous isolation of translating mRNA and nuclear chromatin from a neuron-enriched cell population to more accurately pair ELE-induced changes in gene expression with epigenetic modifications. We employ a line of transgenic mice expressing the NuTRAP (Nuclear Tagging and Translating Ribosome Affinity Purification) cassette under the Emx1 promoter allowing for brain cell-type specificity. We then developed a technique that combines nuclear isolation using Isolation of Nuclei TAgged in Specific Cell Types (INTACT) with Translating Ribosomal Affinity Purification (TRAP) methods to determine cell type-specific epigenetic modifications influencing gene expression programs from a population of Emx1 expressing hippocampal neurons. Data from RNA-seq and CUT&amp;amp;RUN-seq were coupled to evaluate histone modifications influencing the expression of translating mRNA in neurons after early-life exercise (ELE). We also performed separate INTACT and TRAP isolations for validation of our protocol and demonstrate similar molecular functions and biological processes implicated by gene ontology (GO) analysis. Finally, as prior studies use tissue from opposite brain hemispheres to pair transcriptomic and epigenomic data from the same rodent, we take a bioinformatics approach to compare hemispheric differences in gene expression programs and histone modifications altered by by ELE. Our data reveal transcriptional and epigenetic signatures of ELE exposure and identify novel candidate gene-histone modification interactions for further investigation. Importantly, our novel approach of combined INTACT/TRAP methods from the same cell suspension allows for simultaneous transcriptomic and epigenomic sequencing in a cell-type specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473936" rel="alternate" title="An in vivo, neuron-specific approach for pairing translational and epigenetic signatures of early-life exercise (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473548</id><title>Profiles and Dynamics of the Transcriptome of Microglial Cells Reveal their Inflammatory Status (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.450636+00:00</updated><author><name>Keren Zohar</name></author><author><name>Elyad Lezmi</name></author><author><name>Fanny Reichert</name></author><author><name>Tsiona Eliyahu</name></author><author><name>Shlomo Rotshenker</name></author><author><name>Marta Weinstock</name></author><author><name>Michal Linial</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The primary role of microglia in the maintenance of brain homeostasis is to respond to disturbances in the microenvironment. In this study, we cultured murine neonatal microglia and activated them with lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and benzoyl ATP (bzATP) to characterize changes in the transcriptome in response to various &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; stimuli caused by pathogens, injury, or toxins. Activation by bzATP, an agonist of purinergic receptors, induces a transient wave of transcriptional changes. However, a long-lasting transcriptional profile affecting thousands of genes occurs only following a combination of bzATP and LPS. This profile is dominated by a coordinated induction of cytokines (e.g., IL1-α and IL1-β), chemokines, and their direct regulators. Many of these inflammatory-related genes are up-regulated by several orders of magnitude. We identified the TNF-α and NF-κB pathways as the principal hubs for signaling of interleukin and chemokine induction in this cell system. We propose that primary microglia under controlled activation paradigms can be used for testing reagents that could attenuate their activated state. Such a microglial system could serve as a model for changes occurring in the aging brain and neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlight points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;*&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Primary murine microglia cultures release cytokines following activation with bzATP and LPS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;*&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wave of changes in gene expression by bzATP is transient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;*&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;bzATP+LPS causes a transcription program dominated by the induction of interleukins and chemokines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473548" rel="alternate" title="Profiles and Dynamics of the Transcriptome of Microglial Cells Reveal their Inflammatory Status (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473676</id><title>Understanding Harmonic Structures Through Instantaneous Frequency (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.450859+00:00</updated><author><name>Marco S Fabus</name></author><author><name>Mark W Woolrich</name></author><author><name>Catherine E Warnaby</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Quinn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The analysis of harmonics and non-sinusoidal waveform shape in neurophysiological data is growing in importance. However, a precise definition of what constitutes a harmonic is lacking. In this paper, we propose a rigorous definition of when to consider signals to be in a harmonic relationship based on an integer frequency ratio, constant phase, and a well-defined joint instantaneous frequency. We show this definition is linked to extrema counting and Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD). We explore the mathematics of our definition and link it to results from analytic number theory. This naturally leads to us to define two classes of harmonic structures, termed strong and weak, with different extrema behaviour. We validate our framework using both simulations and real data. Specifically, we look at the harmonics structure in the FitzHugh-Nagumo model and the non-sinusoidal hippocampal theta oscillation in rat local field potential data. We further discuss how our definition helps to address mode splitting in EMD. A clear understanding of when harmonics are present in signals will enable a deeper understanding of the functional and clinical roles of non-sinusoidal neural oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473676" rel="alternate" title="Understanding Harmonic Structures Through Instantaneous Frequency (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473516</id><title>The adolescent pattern of sleep spindle development revealed by HD-EEG polisomnography (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.451059+00:00</updated><author><name>Gábor Bocskai</name></author><author><name>Adrián Pótári</name></author><author><name>Ferenc Gombos</name></author><author><name>Róbert Bódizs</name></author><author><name>Ilona Kovács</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep spindles are developmentally relevant cortical oscillatory patterns; however, they have mostly been studied by considering the entire spindle frequency range (11 to 15 Hz) without a distinction between the functionally and topographically different slow and fast spindles, using relatively few electrodes and analysing wide age-ranges. Here, we employ HD-EEG polysomnography in three age-groups between 12 to 20 years of age, with an equal distribution between the two genders, and analyse the adolescent developmental pattern of the four major parameters of slow and fast sleep spindles. Most of our findings corroborate those very few previous studies that also make a distinction between slow and fast spindles in their developmental analysis. We find spindle frequency increasing with age, although spindle density change is not obvious in our study. We confirm the declining tendencies for amplitude and duration, although within narrower, more specific age-windows than previously. Spindle frequency seems to be higher in females in the oldest age-group. Based on the pattern of our findings, we suggest that HD-EEG, specifically targeting slow and fast spindle ranges and relatively narrow age-ranges would advance the understanding of both adolescent development and the functional relevance of sleep spindles in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473516" rel="alternate" title="The adolescent pattern of sleep spindle development revealed by HD-EEG polisomnography (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473973</id><title>Multimodal lesion network mapping to predict sensorimotor behavior in stroke patients (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.451245+00:00</updated><author><name>Antonio Jimenez-Marin</name></author><author><name>Nele De Bruyn</name></author><author><name>Jolien Gooijers</name></author><author><name>Alberto Llera</name></author><author><name>Sarah Meyer</name></author><author><name>Kaat Alaerts</name></author><author><name>Geert Verheyden</name></author><author><name>Stephan P Swinnen</name></author><author><name>Jesus M Cortes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lesion network mapping (LNM) has proved to be a successful technique to map symptoms to brain networks after acquired brain injury. Beyond the characteristics of a lesion, such as its etiology, size or location, LNM has shown that common symptoms in patients after injury may reflect the effects of their lesions on the same circuits, thereby linking symptoms to specific brain networks. Here, we extend LNM to its multimodal form, using a combination of functional and structural connectivity maps drawn from data from 1000 healthy participants in the Human Connectome Project. We applied the multimodal LNM to a cohort of 54 stroke patients with the aim of predicting sensorimotor behavior, as assessed through a combination of motor and sensory tests. Test scores were predicted using a Canonical Correlation Analysis with multimodal brain maps as independent variables, and cross-validation strategies were employed to overcome overfitting. The results obtained led us to draw three conclusions. First, the multimodal analysis reveals how functional connectivity maps contribute more than structural connectivity maps in the optimal prediction of sensorimotor behavior. Second, the maximal association solution between the behavioral outcome and multimodal lesion connectivity maps suggests an equal contribution of sensory and motor coefficients, in contrast to the unimodal analyses where the sensory contribution dominates in both structural and functional maps. Finally, when looking at each modality individually, the performance of the structural connectivity maps strongly depends on whether sensorimotor performance was corrected for lesion size, thereby eliminating the effect of larger lesions that produce more severe sensorimotor dysfunction. By contrast, the maps of functional connectivity performed similarly irrespective of any correction for lesion size. Overall, these results support the extension of LNM to its multimodal form, highlighting the synergistic and additive nature of different types of imaging modalities, and the influence of their corresponding brain networks on behavioral performance after acquired brain injury.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473973" rel="alternate" title="Multimodal lesion network mapping to predict sensorimotor behavior in stroke patients (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473346</id><title>Spatiotemporal dynamics of molecular expression pattern and intercellular interactions in glial scar responding to spinal cord injury (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.451465+00:00</updated><author><name>Leilei Gong</name></author><author><name>Yun Gu</name></author><author><name>Xiaoxiao Han</name></author><author><name>Chengcheng Luan</name></author><author><name>Xinghui Wang</name></author><author><name>Yufeng Sun</name></author><author><name>Mengya Fang</name></author><author><name>Shuhai Yang</name></author><author><name>Lai Xu</name></author><author><name>Hualin Sun</name></author><author><name>Bin Yu</name></author><author><name>Xiaosong Gu</name></author><author><name>Songlin Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adult regeneration in spinal cord is poor in mammalian but remarkable in the neonatal mammals and some vertebrates, including fish and salamanders. Increasing evidences basis of this interspecies and ontogeny highlighted the pivotal roles of neuron extrinsic factors-the glial scar, which exert confusing inhibiting or promoting regeneration function, but the spatiotemporal ordering of cellular and molecular events that drive repair processes in scar formation remains poorly understood. Here, we firstly constructed tissue-wide gene expression measurements of mouse spinal cords over the course of scar formation using the spatial transcriptomics (ST) technology in Spinal cord injury (SCI) repair. We analyzed the transcriptomes of nearly 15449 spots from 32 samples and distinguished normal and damage response regions. Compared to histological changes, spatial mapping of differentiation transitions in spinal cord injury site delineated the possible trajectory between subpopulations of fibroblast, glia and immune cell more comprehensively and defined the extent of scar boundary and core more accurately. Locally, we identified gene expression gradients from leading edge to the core of scar areas that allow for re-understanding of the scar microenvironment and found some regulators in special cell types, such as Thbs1 and Col1a2 in macrophage, CD36 and Postn in fibroblast, Plxnb2 and Nxpe3 in microglia, Clu in astrocyte and CD74 in oligodendrocyte. Last, we profiled the bidirectional ligand-receptor interactions at the neighbor cluster boundary, contributing to maintain scar architecture during gliosis and fibrosis, and found GPR37L1_PSAP and GPR37_PSAP were top 2 enriched gene-pairs between microglia and fibroblast or microglia and astrocyte. Together, the establishment of these profiles firstly uncovered scar spatial heterogeneity and lineage trajectory, provide an unbiased view of scar and served as a valuable resource for CNS injury treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spatial illustration of gene expression pattern after T10 right lateral hemisection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spatial atlas of scar formation by 21 cell types around damaged area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The origin, trajectory reconstruction and functional diversity of cell types in different stages of scar formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Novel insights for glial scar boundary and potential benefits for recovery intervention after SCI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473346" rel="alternate" title="Spatiotemporal dynamics of molecular expression pattern and intercellular interactions in glial scar responding to spinal cord injury (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473341</id><title>In the back of your mind: Cortical mapping of tactile and proprioceptive paraspinal afferent inputs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.451715+00:00</updated><author><name>David M. Cole</name></author><author><name>Philipp Stämpfli</name></author><author><name>Robert Gandia</name></author><author><name>Louis Schibli</name></author><author><name>Sandro Gantner</name></author><author><name>Philipp Schuetz</name></author><author><name>Michael L. Meier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Persistent pain alters brain-body representations, highlighting their potential pathological significance. In chronic low back pain (LBP), sparse evidence points towards a shift of the cortical representation of sensory afferents of the back. However, systematic investigations of the cortical representation of tactile and proprioceptive paraspinal afferents along the thoracolumbar axis are lacking. Detailed cortical maps of paraspinal afferent input might be crucial to further explore potential relationships between brain changes and the development and maintenance of chronic LBP. We therefore validated a novel and functional magnetic resonance imaging-(fMRI-)compatible method of mapping cortical representations of tactile and proprioceptive afferents of the back, using pneumatic vibrotactile stimulation (“pneuVID”) at varying frequencies and paraspinal locations, in conjunction with high-resolution fMRI. We hypothesised that: (i) high (80 Hz) frequency stimulation would lead to increased postural sway compared to low (20 Hz) stimulation, due to differential evoked mechanoreceptor contributions to postural control (proprioceptive vs tactile); and (ii) that high (80 Hz) versus low (20 Hz) frequency stimulation would be associated with neuronal activity in distinct primary somatosensory (S1) and motor (M1) cortical targets of tactile and proprioceptive afferents (N=15, healthy volunteers). Additionally, we expected neural representations to vary spatially along the thoracolumbar axis. We found significant differences between neural representations of low and high frequency stimulation and between representations of thoracic and lumbar paraspinal locations, in several bilateral sensorimotor cortical regions. Proprioceptive (80 Hz) stimulation preferentially activated sub-regions S1 3a and M1 4p, while tactile (20 Hz) stimulation was more encoded in S1 3b and M1 4a. Moreover, in S1, lower back proprioceptive stimulation activated dorsal-posterior representations, compared to ventral-anterior representations activated by upper back stimulation. As per our hypotheses, we found distinct sensorimotor cortical tactile and proprioceptive representations, with the latter displaying clear topographic differences between the upper and lower back. This thus represents the first behavioural and neurobiological validation of the novel pneuVID method for stimulating muscle spindles and mapping cortical representations of paraspinal afferents. Future investigations of detailed cortical maps will be of major importance in elucidating the role of cortical reorganization in the pathophysiology of chronic LBP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473341" rel="alternate" title="In the back of your mind: Cortical mapping of tactile and proprioceptive paraspinal afferent inputs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473212</id><title>Notch inhibition promotes regeneration and immunosuppression supports cone survival in a zebrafish model of inherited retinal dystrophy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.451914+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Fogerty</name></author><author><name>Ping Song</name></author><author><name>Patrick Boyd</name></author><author><name>Sarah Grabinski</name></author><author><name>Thanh Hoang</name></author><author><name>Adrian Reich</name></author><author><name>Lauren T. Cianciolo</name></author><author><name>Seth Blackshaw</name></author><author><name>Jeff S. Mumm</name></author><author><name>David R. Hyde</name></author><author><name>Brian D. Perkins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Photoreceptor degeneration leads to irreversible vision loss in humans with retinal dystrophies such as Retinitis Pigmentosa. Whereas photoreceptor loss is permanent in mammals, zebrafish possesses the ability to regenerate retinal neurons and restore visual function. Following acute damage, Müller glia (MG) re-enter the cell cycle and produce multipotent progenitors whose progeny differentiate into mature neurons. Both MG reprogramming and proliferation of retinal progenitor cells require reactive microglia and associated inflammatory signaling. Paradoxically, MG in zebrafish models of photoreceptor degeneration fail to re-enter the cell cycle and regenerate lost cells. Here, we used the zebrafish &lt;italic&gt;cep290&lt;/italic&gt; mutant to demonstrate that progressive cone degeneration generates an immune response but does not stimulate MG proliferation. Acute light damage triggered photoreceptor regeneration in &lt;italic&gt;cep290&lt;/italic&gt; mutants but cones were only restored to pre-lesion densities. Using &lt;italic&gt;irf8&lt;/italic&gt; mutant zebrafish, we found that the chronic absence of microglia reduced inflammation and rescued cone degeneration in &lt;italic&gt;cep290&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. Finally, single-cell RNA-sequencing revealed sustained expression of &lt;italic&gt;notch3&lt;/italic&gt; in MG of &lt;italic&gt;cep290&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and inhibition of Notch signaling induced MG to re-enter the cell cycle. Our findings provide new insights on the requirements for MG to proliferate and the potential for immunosuppression to prolong photoreceptor survival.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473212" rel="alternate" title="Notch inhibition promotes regeneration and immunosuppression supports cone survival in a zebrafish model of inherited retinal dystrophy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473353</id><title>Dichotomous Activity and Function of Neurons with Low- and High-Frequency Discharge in the External Globus Pallidus of Non-Human Primates (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.452218+00:00</updated><author><name>Shiran Katabi</name></author><author><name>Avital Adler</name></author><author><name>Marc Deffains</name></author><author><name>Hagai Bergman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To date, there is a consensus that there are at least two neuronal populations in the non-human primate (NHP) external globus pallidus (GPe): the low- and high-frequency discharge (LFD and HFD) neurons. Nevertheless, almost all NHP physiological studies have neglected the functional importance of LFD neurons. This study examined the discharge features of these two GPe neuronal subpopulations recorded in four NHPs engaged in a classical conditioning task with cues predicting reward, neutral and aversive outcomes. The results show that LFD neurons tended to burst, encoded the salience of behavioral cues, and exhibited correlated spiking activity. By contrast, the HFD neurons tended to pause, encoded cue valence, and exhibited uncorrelated spiking activity. Overall, these findings point to the dichotomic organization of the NHP GPe which is likely to be critical to the implementation of normal basal ganglia functions and computations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473353" rel="alternate" title="Dichotomous Activity and Function of Neurons with Low- and High-Frequency Discharge in the External Globus Pallidus of Non-Human Primates (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473590</id><title>Transcriptional signature in microglia isolated from an Alzheimer’s disease mouse model treated with scanning ultrasound (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.452401+00:00</updated><author><name>Gerhard Leinenga</name></author><author><name>Liviu-Gabriel Bodea</name></author><author><name>Jan Schröder</name></author><author><name>Giuzhi Sun</name></author><author><name>Yi Chen</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Grubman</name></author><author><name>Jose M. Polo</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Götz</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Rationale&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intracranial scanning ultrasound combined with intravenously injected microbubbles (SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt;) has been shown to transiently open the blood-brain barrier and reduce amyloid-β (Aβ) pathology in the APP23 mouse model of Alzheimer’s disease (AD). This has been accomplished, at least in part, through the activation of microglial cells; however, their response to the SUS treatment is only incompletely understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wild-type (WT) and APP23 mice were subjected to SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt;, using non-SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt;-treated mice as sham controls. After 48 hours, the APP23 mice were injected with methoxy-XO4 to label Aβ aggregates, followed by microglial isolation into XO4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and XO4&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; populations using flow cytometry. Both XO4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and XO4&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; cells were subjected to RNA sequencing and their transcriptome was analyzed through a bioinformatics pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transcriptomic analysis of the microglial cells revealed a clear segregation depending on genotype (AD model versus WT mice), as well as treatment (SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt; versus sham) and Aβ internalization (XO4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; versus XO4&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; microglia). Differential gene expression analysis detected 278 genes that were significantly changed by SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt; in the XO4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; cells (248 up/30 down) and 242 in XO&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; cells (225 up/17 down). Not surprisingly given previous findings of increased phagocytosis of plaques following SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt;, the pathway analysis highlighted that the treatment induced an enrichment in genes related to the phagosome pathway in XO4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; microglia; however, when comparing SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt; to sham, the analysis revealed an enrichment in genes involved in the cell cycle in both the XO4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and XO4&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; microglial population.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data provide a comprehensive analysis of microglia in an AD mouse model subjected to ultrasound treatment as a function of Aβ internalization, one of the defining hallmarks of AD. Several differentially expressed genes are highlighted, pointing to an ultrasound-induced activation of cell cycle mechanisms in microglial cells isolated from APP23 mice treated with SUS&lt;sup&gt;+MB&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec id="s8"&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="473590v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473590" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional signature in microglia isolated from an Alzheimer’s disease mouse model treated with scanning ultrasound (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473997</id><title>Subject-specific features of excitation/inhibition profiles in neurodegenerative diseases (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.452826+00:00</updated><author><name>Anita Monteverdi</name></author><author><name>Fulvia Palesi</name></author><author><name>Alfredo Costa</name></author><author><name>Paolo Vitali</name></author><author><name>Anna Pichiecchio</name></author><author><name>Matteo Cotta Ramusino</name></author><author><name>Sara Bernini</name></author><author><name>Viktor Jirsa</name></author><author><name>Claudia A.M. Gandini Wheeler-Kingshott</name></author><author><name>Egidio D'Angelo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain pathologies are based on microscopic changes in neurons and synapses that reverberate into large scale networks altering brain dynamics and functional states. An important yet unresolved issue concerns the impact of patients excitation/inhibition profiles on neurodegenerative diseases including Alzheimer's disease, Frontotemporal Dementia and Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis. In this work we used a simulation platform, The Virtual Brain, to simulate brain dynamics in healthy controls and in Alzheimer's disease, Frontotemporal Dementia and Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis patients. The brain connectome and functional connectivity were extracted from 3T-MRI scans and The Virtual Brain nodes were represented by a Wong-Wang neural mass model endowing an explicit representation of the excitatory/inhibitory balance. The integration of cerebro-cerebellar loops improved the correlation between experimental and simulated functional connectivity, and hence The Virtual Brain predictive power, in all pathological conditions. The Virtual Brain biophysical parameters differed between clinical phenotypes, predicting higher global coupling and inhibition in Alzheimer's disease and stronger NMDA (N-methyl-D-aspartate) receptor-dependent excitation in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis. These physio-pathological parameters allowed an advanced analysis of patients' state. In backward regressions, The Virtual Brain parameters significantly contributed to explain the variation of neuropsychological scores and, in discriminant analysis, the combination of The Virtual Brain parameters and neuropsychological scores significantly improved discriminative power between clinical conditions. Eventually, cluster analysis provided a unique description of the excitatory/inhibitory balance in individual patients. In aggregate, The Virtual Brain simulations reveal differences in the excitatory/inhibitory balance of individual patients that, combined with cognitive assessment, can promote the personalized diagnosis and therapy of neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473997" rel="alternate" title="Subject-specific features of excitation/inhibition profiles in neurodegenerative diseases (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473801</id><title>Frequency transfer of the ventriloquism aftereffect (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.453078+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel Ege</name></author><author><name>A. John van Opstal</name></author><author><name>Marc Mathijs van Wanrooij</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ventriloquism aftereffect (VAE) describes the persistent shift of perceived sound location after having been adapted to a ventriloquism condition, in which the sound was repeatedly paired with a displaced visual stimulus. In the latter case, participants consistently mislocalize the sound in the direction of the visual stimulus (ventriloquism effect, VE). Previous studies provide conflicting reports regarding the strength of the VAE, ranging from 0 to nearly 100%. Moreover, there is controversy about its generalization to different sounds than the one inducing the VE, ranging from no transfer at all, to full transfer across different sound spectra. Here, we imposed the VE for three different sounds: a low-frequency and a high-frequency narrow-band noise, and a broadband Gaussian white noise (GWN). In the adaptation phase, listeners generated fast goal-directed head movements to localize the sound, presented across a 70 deg range in the horizontal plane, while ignoring a visual distracter that was consistently displaced 10 deg to the right of the sound. In the post-adaptation phase, participants localized narrow-band sounds with center frequencies from 0.5 to 8 kHz, as well as GWN, without the visual distracter. Our results show that the VAE amounted to approximately 40% of the VE and generalized well across the entire frequency domain. We also found that the strength of the VAE correlated with the pre-adaptation sound-localization performance. We compare our results with previous reports and discuss different hypotheses regarding optimal audio-visual cue integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473801" rel="alternate" title="Frequency transfer of the ventriloquism aftereffect (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473616</id><title>Optineurin deficiency induces patchy hair loss but it is not sufficient to cause amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.453255+00:00</updated><author><name>Shivranjani C Moharir</name></author><author><name>Ghanshyam Swarup</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic alterations and environmental factors contribute towards pathogenesis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), a neurodegenerative disease. Various types of mutations in the autophagy receptor protein optineurin (coded by OPTN gene) including deletions are causatively associated with ALS. To explore the role of OPTN in ALS pathogenesis, we used Optn knockout mice to study the features of ALS. The Optn-deficient mice did not show kyphosis, loss of body weight, weakening of front paw-grip strength or limb muscle strength. However, several Optn-deficient mice showed patchy loss of hair, which increased with age. Our results suggest that optineurin deficiency alone is not sufficient to induce ALS-like symptoms in mice. We suggest that optineurin deficiency may require cooperation with other genetic or environmental factors to cause ALS. Since endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress plays an important role in ALS pathogenesis, and Optn modulates ER stress response signaling, Optn deficiency may contribute to ALS pathogenesis partly by potentiating ER stress response signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473616" rel="alternate" title="Optineurin deficiency induces patchy hair loss but it is not sufficient to cause amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473858</id><title>Type I Interferon Signaling Drives Microglial Dysfunction and Senescence in Human iPSC Models of Down Syndrome and Alzheimers Disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.453425+00:00</updated><author><name>Mengmeng Jin</name></author><author><name>Ranji Xu</name></author><author><name>Mahabub Maraj Alam</name></author><author><name>Ziyuan Ma</name></author><author><name>Sining Zhu</name></author><author><name>Le Wang</name></author><author><name>Alessandra C. Martini</name></author><author><name>Matteo Bernabucci</name></author><author><name>Ping Xie</name></author><author><name>Kelvin Kwan</name></author><author><name>Zhiping P Pang</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth Head</name></author><author><name>Ying Liu</name></author><author><name>Ronald P. Hart</name></author><author><name>Peng Jiang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia are critical for brain development and play a central role in Alzheimers disease (AD) etiology. Down syndrome (DS), also known as trisomy 21, is the most common genetic origin of intellectual disability and the most common risk factor for AD. Surprisingly, little information is available on the impact of trisomy of human chromosome 21 (Hsa21) on microglia in DS brain development and AD in DS (DSAD). Using our new induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC)-based human microglia-containing cerebral organoid and chimeric mouse brain models, here we report that DS microglia exhibit enhanced synaptic pruning function during brain development. Consequently, electrophysiological recordings demonstrate that DS microglial mouse chimeras show impaired synaptic neurotransmission, as compared to control microglial chimeras. Upon being exposed to human brain tissue-derived soluble pathological tau, DS microglia display dystrophic phenotypes in chimeric mouse brains, recapitulating microglial responses seen in human AD and DSAD brain tissues. Further flow cytometry, single-cell RNA-sequencing, and immunohistological analyses of chimeric mouse brains demonstrate that DS microglia undergo cellular senescence and exhibit elevated type I interferon signaling after being challenged by pathological tau. Mechanistically, we find that shRNA-mediated knockdown of Hsa21encoded type I interferon receptor genes, IFNARs, rescues the defective DS microglial phenotypes both during brain development and in response to pathological tau. Our findings provide first in vivo evidence supporting a paradigm shifting theory that human microglia respond to pathological tau by exhibiting accelerated senescence and dystrophic phenotypes. Our results further suggest that targeting IFNARs may improve microglial functions during DS brain development and prevent human microglial senescence in DS individuals with AD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473858" rel="alternate" title="Type I Interferon Signaling Drives Microglial Dysfunction and Senescence in Human iPSC Models of Down Syndrome and Alzheimers Disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473490</id><title>Effectiveness and relationship between biased and unbiased measures of dopamine release and clearance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.453709+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna C. Everett</name></author><author><name>Ben E. Graul</name></author><author><name>J. Kayden Robinson</name></author><author><name>Daniel B. Watts</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo A. España</name></author><author><name>Cody A. Siciliano</name></author><author><name>Jordan T. Yorgason</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fast-scan cyclic voltammetry (FSCV) is an effective tool for measuring dopamine (DA) release and clearance throughout the brain, including the ventral and dorsal striatum. Striatal DA terminals are abundant with signals heavily regulated by release machinery and the dopamine transporter (DAT). Peak height is a common method for measuring release but can be affected by changes in clearance. The Michaelis-Menten model has been a standard in measuring DA clearance, but requires experimenter fitted modeling subject to experimenter bias. The current study presents the use of the first derivative (velocity) of evoked DA signals as an alternative approach for measuring dopamine release and clearance and can be used to distinguish the two measures. Maximal upwards velocity predicts reductions in DA peak height due to D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and GABAB receptor stimulation and by alterations in calcium concentrations. The Michaelis-Menten maximal velocity (V&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;) measure, an approximation for DAT numbers, predicted maximal downward velocity in slices and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Dopamine peak height and upward velocity were similar between wildtype C57 (WT) and DAT knock out (DATKO) mice. In contrast, downward velocity was considerably reduced and exponential decay (tau) was increased in DATKO mice, supporting use of both measures for changes in DAT activity. In slices, the competitive DAT inhibitors cocaine, PTT and WF23 increased peak height and upward velocity differentially across increasing concentrations, with PTT and cocaine reducing these measures at high concentrations. Downward velocity and tau values decreased and increased respectively across concentrations, with greater potency and efficacy observed with WF23 and PTT. In vivo recordings demonstrated similar effects of WF23 and PTT on measures of release and clearance. Tau was a more sensitive measure at low concentrations, supporting its use as a surrogate for the Michaelis-Menten measure of apparent affinity (Km). Together, these results inform on the use of these measures for DA release and clearance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473490" rel="alternate" title="Effectiveness and relationship between biased and unbiased measures of dopamine release and clearance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473469</id><title>Ultra-deep through-skull mouse brain imaging via the combination of skull optical clearing and three-photon microscopy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.453920+00:00</updated><author><name>Mubin He</name></author><author><name>Dongyu Li</name></author><author><name>Zheng Zheng</name></author><author><name>Hequn Zhang</name></author><author><name>Tianxiang Wu</name></author><author><name>Weihang Geng</name></author><author><name>Zhengwu Hu</name></author><author><name>Zhe Feng</name></author><author><name>Shiyi Peng</name></author><author><name>Liang Zhu</name></author><author><name>Wang Xi</name></author><author><name>Dan Zhu</name></author><author><name>Jun Qian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Optical microscopy has enabled in vivo monitoring of brain structures and functions with high spatial resolution. However, the strong optical scattering in turbid brain tissue and skull impedes the observation of microvasculature and neuronal structures at large depth. Herein, we proposed a strategy to overcome the influence induced by the high scattering effect of both skull and brain tissue via the combination of skull optical clearing (SOC) technique and thee-photon fluorescence microscopy (3PM). The Visible-NIR-II compatible Skull Optical Clearing Agents (VNSOCA) we applied reduced the skull scattering and water absorption in long wavelength by refractive index matching and H2O replacement to D2O respectively. 3PM with the excitation in the 1300-nm window reached 1.5 mm cerebrovascular imaging depth in cranial window. Combining the two advanced technologies together, we achieved so far the largest cerebrovascular imaging depth of 1 mm and neuronal imaging depth of &amp;gt;700 μm through intact mouse skull. Dual-channel through-skull imaging of both brain vessels and neurons was also successfully realized, giving an opportunity of non-invasively monitoring the deep brain structures and functions at single-cell level simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473469" rel="alternate" title="Ultra-deep through-skull mouse brain imaging via the combination of skull optical clearing and three-photon microscopy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473450</id><title>Different excitation-inhibition correlations between spontaneous and tone-evoked activity in primary auditory cortex neurons (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.454378+00:00</updated><author><name>Katherine C. M. Chew</name></author><author><name>Vineet Kumar</name></author><author><name>Andrew Y. Y. Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tone-evoked synaptic excitation and inhibition are highly correlated in many neurons with V-shaped tuning curves in the primary auditory cortex of pentobarbital-anesthetized rats. In contrast, there is less correlation between spontaneous excitation and inhibition in visual cortex neurons under the same anesthetic conditions. However, it was not known whether the primary auditory cortex resembles visual cortex in having spontaneous excitation and inhibition that is less correlated than tone-evoked excitation and inhibition. Here we report whole-cell voltage-clamp measurements of spontaneous excitation and inhibition in primary auditory cortex neurons of pentobarbital-anesthetized rats. The larger excursions of both spontaneous excitatory and inhibitory currents appeared to consist of distinct events, with the inhibitory event rate typically lower than the excitatory event rate. We use the ratio of the excitatory event rate to the inhibitory event rate, and the assumption that the excitatory and inhibitory synaptic currents can each be reasonably described as a filtered Poisson process, to estimate the maximum spontaneous excitatory-inhibitory correlation for each neuron. In a subset of neurons, we also measured tone-evoked excitation and inhibition. In neurons with V-shaped tuning curves, although tone-evoked excitation and inhibition were highly correlated, the spontaneous inhibitory event rate was typically sufficiently lower than the spontaneous excitatory event rate to indicate a lower excitatory-inhibitory correlation for spontaneous activity than for tone-evoked responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473450" rel="alternate" title="Different excitation-inhibition correlations between spontaneous and tone-evoked activity in primary auditory cortex neurons (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>