<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.523085+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458230</id><title>Disentangling the flow of signals between populations of neurons (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.523721+00:00</updated><author><name>Evren Gokcen</name></author><author><name>Anna I. Jasper</name></author><author><name>João D. Semedo</name></author><author><name>Amin Zandvakili</name></author><author><name>Adam Kohn</name></author><author><name>Christian K. Machens</name></author><author><name>Byron M. Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Technological advances have granted the ability to record from large populations of neurons across multiple brain areas. These recordings may illuminate how communication between areas contributes to brain function, yet a substantial barrier remains: How do we disentangle the concurrent, bidirectional flow of signals between two populations of neurons? We therefore propose here a novel dimensionality reduction framework: Delayed Latents Across Groups (DLAG). DLAG disentangles signals relayed in both directions; identifies how these signals are represented by each population; and characterizes how they evolve over time and trial-to-trial. We demonstrate that DLAG performs well on synthetic datasets similar in scale to current neurophysiological recordings. Then we study simultaneously recorded populations in primate visual areas V1 and V2, where DLAG reveals signatures of concurrent yet selective communication. Our framework lays the foundation for dissecting the intricate flow of signals across populations of neurons, and how this signaling contributes to cortical computation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.458230" rel="alternate" title="Disentangling the flow of signals between populations of neurons (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.457871</id><title>The Retrieval-related Anterior shift is Moderated by Age and Correlates with Memory Performance (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.524309+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabina Srokova</name></author><author><name>Paul F Hill</name></author><author><name>Michael D Rugg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent research suggests that episodic memory is associated with systematic differences in the localization of neural activity observed during memory encoding and retrieval. The retrieval-related anterior shift is a phenomenon whereby the retrieval of a stimulus event (e.g., a scene image) is associated with a peak neural response which is localized more anteriorly than the response elicited when the stimulus is experienced directly. Here, we examine whether the magnitude of the anterior shift, i.e., the distance between encoding- and retrieval-related response peaks, is moderated by age, and also whether the shift is associated with memory performance. Younger and older human subjects of both sexes underwent fMRI as they completed encoding and retrieval tasks on word-face and word-scene pairs. We localized peak scene- and face-selectivity for each individual participant within the face-selective precuneus (PCU) and in three scene-selective (parahippocampal place area [PPA], medial place area [MPA], occipital place area [OPA]) regions of interest (ROIs). In line with recent findings, we identified an anterior shift in PPA and OPA in both age groups and, in older adults only, in MPA and PCU also. Of importance, the magnitude of the anterior shift was larger in older than in younger adults. The shift within the PPA exhibited an age-invariant across-participant negative correlation with source memory performance, such that a smaller displacement between encoding- and retrieval-related neural activity was associated with better performance. These findings provide novel insights into the functional significance of the anterior shift, especially in relation to memory decline in older age.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.30.457871" rel="alternate" title="The Retrieval-related Anterior shift is Moderated by Age and Correlates with Memory Performance (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458571</id><title>Right fronto-parietal networks mediate the neurocognitive benefits of enriched environments. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-06T09:10:47.524697+00:00</updated><author><name>Meadhbh B Brosnan</name></author><author><name>Nir Shalev</name></author><author><name>Jivesh Ramduny</name></author><author><name>Stamatios Sotiropoulos</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Chechlacz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Exposure to enriched environments (EE) throughout a lifetime, providing so called reserve, protects against cognitive decline in later years. It has been hypothesised that high levels of alertness necessitated by EE might strengthen the right fronto-parietal networks (FPN) to facilitate this neurocognitive resilience. We have previously shown that EE offset age-related deficits in selective attention by preserving grey matter within right fronto-parietal regions. Here, using neurite orientation dispersion and density imaging (NODDI), we examined the relationship between EE, microstructural properties of fronto-parietal white matter association pathways (three branches of the superior longitudinal fasciculus, SLF), structural brain health (atrophy), and attention (alertness, orienting and executive control) in a group of older adults. We show that EE is associated with a lower orientation dispersion index (ODI) within the right SLF1 which in turn mediates the relationship between EE and alertness, as well as grey- and white-matter atrophy. This suggests that EE may induce white matter plasticity (and prevent age-related dispersion of axons) within the right FPN to facilitate the preservation of neurocognitive health in later years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.01.458571" rel="alternate" title="Right fronto-parietal networks mediate the neurocognitive benefits of enriched environments. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>