<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.177754+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470378</id><title>Structural and functional organization of visual responses in the inferior olive of larval zebrafish (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.178402+00:00</updated><author><name>Rita Felix</name></author><author><name>Daniil A Markov</name></author><author><name>Sabine L. Renninger</name></author><author><name>Raquel Tomás</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Laborde</name></author><author><name>Megan R Carey</name></author><author><name>Michael B Orger</name></author><author><name>Ruben Portugues</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The olivo-cerebellar system plays an important role in vertebrate sensorimotor control. According to a classical theory of cerebellar cortex, the inferior olive (IO) provides Purkinje cells with error information which drives motor learning in the cerebellum. Here we investigate the sensory representations in the IO of larval zebrafish and their spatial organization. Using single-cell labeling of genetically identified IO neurons we find that they can be divided into at least two distinct groups based on their spatial location, dendritic morphology, and axonal projection patterns. In the same genetically targeted population, we recorded calcium activity in response to a set of visual stimuli using 2-photon imaging. We found that most IO neurons showed direction selective and binocular responses to visual stimuli and that functional properties were spatially organized within the IO. Light-sheet functional imaging that allowed for simultaneous activity recordings at the soma and axonal level revealed tight coupling between soma location, axonal projections and functional properties of IO neurons. Taken together, our results suggest that anatomically-defined classes of inferior olive neurons correspond to distinct functional types, and that topographic connections between IO and cerebellum contribute to organization of the cerebellum into distinct functional zones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470378" rel="alternate" title="Structural and functional organization of visual responses in the inferior olive of larval zebrafish (44 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470790</id><title>Moving Beyond Processing and Analysis-Related Variation in Neuroscience (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.178997+00:00</updated><author><name>Xinhui Li</name></author><author><name>Lei Ai</name></author><author><name>Steve Giavasis</name></author><author><name>Hecheng Jin</name></author><author><name>Eric Feczko</name></author><author><name>Ting Xu</name></author><author><name>Jon Clucas</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Franco</name></author><author><name>Anibal Solon Heinsfeld</name></author><author><name>Azeez Adebimpe</name></author><author><name>Joshua T. Vogelstein</name></author><author><name>Chao-Gan Yan</name></author><author><name>Oscar Esteban</name></author><author><name>Russell A. Poldrack</name></author><author><name>Cameron Craddock</name></author><author><name>Damien Fair</name></author><author><name>Theodore Satterthwaite</name></author><author><name>Gregory Kiar</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Milham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When fields lack consensus standards and ground truths for their analytic methods, reproducibility tends to be more of an ideal than a reality. Such has been the case for functional neuroimaging, where there exists a sprawling space of tools from which scientists can construct processing pipelines and draw interpretations. We provide a critical evaluation of the impact of differences observed in results across five independently developed functional MRI minimal preprocessing pipelines. We show that even when handling the same exact data, inter-pipeline agreement was only moderate, with the specific steps that contribute to the lack of agreement varying across pipeline comparisons. Using a densely sampled test-retest dataset, we show that the limitations imposed by inter-pipeline agreement mainly become appreciable when the reliability of the underlying data is high. We highlight the importance of comparison among analytic tools and parameters, as both  widely debated (e.g., global signal regression) and commonly overlooked (e.g., MNI template version) decisions were each found to lead to marked variation. We provide recommendations for incorporating tool-based variability in functional neuroimaging analyses and a supporting infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470790" rel="alternate" title="Moving Beyond Processing and Analysis-Related Variation in Neuroscience (28 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470579</id><title>Human ventromedial prefrontal cortex lesions enhance expectation-related pain modulation (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.179527+00:00</updated><author><name>JC Motzkin</name></author><author><name>J Hiser</name></author><author><name>I Carroll</name></author><author><name>R Wolf</name></author><author><name>MK Baskaya</name></author><author><name>M Koenigs</name></author><author><name>LY Atlas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pain is strongly modulated by expectations and beliefs. Research across species indicates that subregions of the ventromedial prefrontal cortex (VMPFC) play a fundamental role in learning and generating predictions about valued outcomes. Consistent with this overarching framework, neuroimaging studies of experimental pain indicate that VMPFC activation tracks expectations of pain relief and statistically mediates expectation-related reductions in responses to painful stimuli across a distributed pain processing network. However, lesion studies in preclinical models and in humans with refractory chronic pain suggest that VMPFC may play a more general role in representing the affective and motivational qualities of pain that contribute to its strong aversive drive. To test whether VMPFC is necessary for pain processing in general, or instead plays a more specific role in the modulation of pain by expectations, we studied responses to experimental heat pain in five adults with bilateral surgical lesions of VMPFC and twenty healthy adults without brain damage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All participants underwent quantitative sensory testing (QST) to characterize pain sensitivity, followed by a pain expectancy task. Participants were instructed that auditory cues would be followed by heat calibrated to elicit low or high pain. Following a conditioning phase, each cue was intermittently paired with a single temperature calibrated to elicit moderate pain. We compared ratings of moderate heat stimuli and subjective expectancy ratings as a function of cue to evaluate whether VMPFC lesions impact cue-based expectancy and expectancy effects on pain intensity and unpleasantness. We also analyzed QST measures to evaluate whether VMPFC lesions were associated with overall shifts in pain sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to adults without brain damage, individuals with VMPFC lesions reported larger differences in expectations as a function of pain-predictive cues, and stronger cue-based modulation of pain ratings, particularly for ratings of pain unpleasantness. There were no group differences in pain sensitivity, nor in the relationship between pain and autonomic arousal, indicating that the impact of VMPFC lesions is specific to expectancy-based modulation of pain unpleasantness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings suggest that the VMPFC is not essential for basic subjective and physiological responses to painful stimuli. Rather, our findings of significantly enhanced cue- related expectancy effects may suggest that VMPFC plays an important role in updating expectations or integrating sensory information with expectations to guide subjective judgements about pain. Taken together, these results expand our understanding VMPFC’s contribution to pain and highlight the role of VMPFC in integrating cognitive representations with sensory information to yield affective responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470579" rel="alternate" title="Human ventromedial prefrontal cortex lesions enhance expectation-related pain modulation (24 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470650</id><title>The enteric nervous system of C. elegans is specified by the Sine Oculis-like homeobox gene ceh-34 (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.179850+00:00</updated><author><name>Berta Vidal</name></author><author><name>Burcu Gulez</name></author><author><name>Wen Xi Cao</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Leyva-Diaz</name></author><author><name>Tessa Tekieli</name></author><author><name>Oliver Hobert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Overarching themes in the terminal differentiation of the enteric nervous system, an autonomously acting unit of animal nervous systems, have so far eluded discovery. We describe here the overall regulatory logic of enteric nervous system differentiation of the nematode &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; that resides within the foregut (pharynx) of the worm. A &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; homolog of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; Sine Oculis homeobox gene, &lt;italic&gt;ceh-34&lt;/italic&gt;, is expressed in all 14 classes of interconnected pharyngeal neurons from their birth throughout their life time, but in no other neuron type of the entire animal. Constitutive and temporally controlled &lt;italic&gt;ceh-34&lt;/italic&gt; removal shows that &lt;italic&gt;ceh-34&lt;/italic&gt; is required to initiate and maintain the neuron type-specific terminal differentiation program of all pharyngeal neuron classes, including their circuit assembly, without affecting panneuronal features. Through additional genetic loss of function analysis, we show that within each pharyngeal neuron class, &lt;italic&gt;ceh-34&lt;/italic&gt; cooperates with different homeodomain transcription factors to individuate distinct pharyngeal neuron classes. Our analysis underscores the critical role of homeobox genes in neuronal identity specification and links them to the control of neuronal circuit assembly of the enteric nervous system. Together with the pharyngeal nervous system simplicity as well as its specification by a Sine Oculis homolog, our findings invite speculations about the early evolution of nervous systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470650" rel="alternate" title="The enteric nervous system of C. elegans is specified by the Sine Oculis-like homeobox gene ceh-34 (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470476</id><title>Synapse-associated astrocyte mitochondria stabilize motor circuits to prevent excitotoxicity (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.180142+00:00</updated><author><name>Sonja A. Zolnoski</name></author><author><name>Emily L. Heckman</name></author><author><name>Chris Q. Doe</name></author><author><name>Sarah D. Ackerman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early stages of the devastating neurodegenerative disease amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) are characterized by motor neuron hyperexcitability. During this phase, peri-synaptic astrocytes are neuroprotective. When reactive, loss of wild-type astrocyte functions results in excitotoxicity. How astrocytes stabilize motor circuit function in early-stage ALS is poorly understood. Here, we used &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; motor neurons to define the role of astrocyte-motor neuron metabolic coupling in a model of ALS: astrocyte knockdown of the ALS-causing gene &lt;italic&gt;tbph/TARDBP&lt;/italic&gt;. In wild-type, astrocyte mitochondria were dynamically trafficked towards active motor dendrites/synapses to meet local metabolic demand. Knockdown of &lt;italic&gt;tbph&lt;/italic&gt; in astrocytes resulted in motor neuron hyperexcitability, reminiscent of early-stage ALS, which was met with a compensatory accumulation of astrocyte mitochondria near motor dendrites/synapses. Finally, we blocked mitochondria-synapse association in &lt;italic&gt;tbph&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown animals and observed locomotor deficits and synapse loss. Thus, synapse-associated astrocyte mitochondria stabilize motor circuits to prevent the transition from hyperexcitability to excitotoxicity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470476" rel="alternate" title="Synapse-associated astrocyte mitochondria stabilize motor circuits to prevent excitotoxicity (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470628</id><title>The Long Noncoding RNA FEDORA is a Cell-Type- and Sex-Specific Regulator of Depression (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.180353+00:00</updated><author><name>Orna Issler</name></author><author><name>Yentl Y van der Zee</name></author><author><name>Aarthi Ramakrishnan</name></author><author><name>Sunhui Xia</name></author><author><name>Alexander K Zinsmaier</name></author><author><name>Chunfeng Tan</name></author><author><name>Wei Li</name></author><author><name>Caleb J Browne</name></author><author><name>Deena M Walker</name></author><author><name>Marine Salery</name></author><author><name>Angélica Torres-Berrío</name></author><author><name>Rita Futamura</name></author><author><name>Julia E Duffy</name></author><author><name>Benoit Labonte</name></author><author><name>Carol A Tamminga</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey L Dupree</name></author><author><name>Yan Dong</name></author><author><name>James W Murrough</name></author><author><name>Li Shen</name></author><author><name>Eric J Nestler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Women suffer from depression at twice the rate of men, but the underlying molecular mechanisms are poorly understood. Here, we identify dramatic baseline sex differences in expression of long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) in human postmortem brain tissue that are profoundly lost in depression. One such lncRNA, RP11-298D21.1 (which we termed FEDORA), is enriched in oligodendrocytes and neurons and upregulated in several cortical regions of depressed females but not males. We found that virally-expressing FEDORA selectively either in neurons or in oligodendrocytes of prefrontal cortex promoted depression-like behavioral abnormalities in female mice only, changes associated with cell-type-specific regulation of synaptic properties, myelin thickness, and gene expression. We also found that blood FEDORA levels have diagnostic significance for depressed women. These findings demonstrate the important role played by lncRNAs, and FEDORA in particular, in shaping the sex-specific landscape of the brain and contributing to sex differences in depression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470628" rel="alternate" title="The Long Noncoding RNA FEDORA is a Cell-Type- and Sex-Specific Regulator of Depression (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470393</id><title>Chronic adolescent exposure to cannabis in mice leads to long-term sex-biased changes in gene expression networks across brain regions (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.180780+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanning Zuo</name></author><author><name>Attilio Iemolo</name></author><author><name>Patricia Montilla-Perez</name></author><author><name>Hairi Li</name></author><author><name>Xia Yang</name></author><author><name>Francesca Telese</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The molecular mechanisms underlying the long-lasting behavioral changes associated with adolescent cannabis use are poorly understood. To this end, we performed gene network analyses of multiple brain regions in adult mice exposed during the entire adolescence to Δ-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC), the major psychoactive component of cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two weeks after the last exposure to THC (10 mg/kg) or vehicle, we measured cognitive behaviors and profiled the transcriptomes of 5 brain regions from 12 female and 12 male mice. We performed differential gene expression analysis and constructed gene coexpression networks (modules) to identify THC-induced transcriptional alterations at the level of individual genes, gene networks, and biological pathways. We integrated the THC-correlated modules with human traits from genomewide association studies to identify potential regulators of disease-associated networks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;THC impaired cognitive behaviors of mice, with memory being more impacted in females than males, which coincided with larger transcriptional changes in the female brain. Modules involved in endocannabinoid signaling and inflammation were correlated with memory deficits in the female dorsal medial striatum and ventral tegmental area, respectively. Converging pathways related to dopamine signaling and addiction were altered in the female amygdala and male nucleus accumbens. Moreover, the connectivity map of THC-correlated modules uncovered intra- and inter-region molecular circuitries influenced by THC. Lastly, modules altered by THC were enriched in genes relevant for human cognition and neuropsychiatric disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings provide novel insights concerning the genes, pathways and brain regions underlying persistent behavioral deficits induced by adolescent exposure to THC in a sex-specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470393" rel="alternate" title="Chronic adolescent exposure to cannabis in mice leads to long-term sex-biased changes in gene expression networks across brain regions (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470560</id><title>Capturing cognitive events embedded in the real-world using mobile EEG and Eye-Tracking (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.181056+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Ladouce</name></author><author><name>Magda Mustile</name></author><author><name>Frédéric Dehais</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The study of cognitive processes underlying natural behaviours implies to depart from computerized paradigms and artificial experimental probes. The aim of the present study is to assess the feasibility of capturing neural markers of visual attention (P300 Event-Related Potentials) in response to objects embedded in a real-world environment. To this end, electroencephalography and eye-tracking data were recorded while participants attended stimuli presented on a tablet and while they searched for books in a library. Initial analyses of the library data revealed P300-like features shifted in time. A Dynamic Time Warping analysis confirmed the presence of P300 ERP in the library condition. Library data were then lag-corrected based on cross-correlation co-efficients. Together these approaches uncovered P300 ERP responses in the library recordings. These findings high-light the relevance of scalable experimental designs, joint brain and body recordings and template-matching analyses to capture cognitive events during natural behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470560" rel="alternate" title="Capturing cognitive events embedded in the real-world using mobile EEG and Eye-Tracking (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470825</id><title>Information flow across the cortical timescales hierarchy during narrative comprehension (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.181398+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire H. C. Chang</name></author><author><name>Samuel A. Nastase</name></author><author><name>Uri Hasson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When listening to spoken narratives, we must integrate information over multiple, concurrent timescales, building up from words to phrases to sentences to a coherent narrative. Recent evidence suggests that the brain relies on a chain of hierarchically organized areas with increasing temporal receptive windows to process naturalistic narratives. In this study, we use inter-subject functional connectivity to reveal a stimulus-driven information flow along the cortical hierarchy. Using cross-correlation analysis to estimate the time lags between six functional networks, we found a fixed temporal sequence of information flow, starting in early auditory areas, followed language areas, the attention network, and lastly the default mode network. This gradient is consistent across eight distinct stories but absent in resting-state and scrambled story data, indicating that the lag gradient reflects the construction of narrative features. Finally, we simulate a variety of narrative integration models and demonstrate that nested narrative structure along with the gradual accumulation of information within the boundaries of linguistic events at each level of the processing hierarchy is sufficient to reproduce the lag gradient. Taken together, this study provides a computational framework for how information flows along the cortical hierarchy during narrative comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470825" rel="alternate" title="Information flow across the cortical timescales hierarchy during narrative comprehension (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470580</id><title>Convergent Cerebrospinal Fluid Proteomes and Metabolic Ontologies in Humans and Animal Models of Rett Syndrome (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.181733+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephanie A. Zlatic</name></author><author><name>Duc Duong</name></author><author><name>Kamal K.E. Gadalla</name></author><author><name>Brenda Murage</name></author><author><name>Lingyan Ping</name></author><author><name>Ruth Shah</name></author><author><name>Omar Khwaja</name></author><author><name>Lindsay C. Swanson</name></author><author><name>Mustafa Sahin</name></author><author><name>Sruti Rayaprolu</name></author><author><name>Prateek Kumar</name></author><author><name>Srikant Rangaraju</name></author><author><name>Adrian Bird</name></author><author><name>Daniel Tarquinio</name></author><author><name>Stuart Cobb</name></author><author><name>Victor Faundez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MECP2 loss-of-function mutations cause Rett syndrome, a disorder that results from a disrupted brain transcriptome. How these transcriptional defects are decoded into a disease proteome remains unknown. We studied the proteome in Rett syndrome cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) across vertebrates. We identified a consensus proteome and ontological categories shared across Rett syndrome cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) from three species, including humans. Rett CSF proteomes enriched proteins annotated to HDL lipoproteins, complement, mitochondria, citrate/pyruvate metabolism, as well as synapse compartments. We used these prioritized and shared ontologies to select analytes for orthogonal quantification. These studies independently validated our proteome and ontologies. Ontologically selected CSF hits had genotypic discriminatory capacity as determined by Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) analysis and distinguished Rett from a related neurodevelopmental disorder, CDKL5 deficiency disorder. We propose that &lt;italic&gt;Mecp2&lt;/italic&gt; mutant CSF proteomes and ontologies inform novel putative mechanisms and biomarkers of disease. We suggest that Rett syndrome is a metabolic disorder impacting synapse function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470580" rel="alternate" title="Convergent Cerebrospinal Fluid Proteomes and Metabolic Ontologies in Humans and Animal Models of Rett Syndrome (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470555</id><title>Multiscale and extended retrieval of associative memory structures in a cortical model of local-global inhibition balance (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.182543+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas F Burns</name></author><author><name>Tatsuya Haga</name></author><author><name>Tomoki Fukai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inhibitory neurons take on many forms and functions. How this diversity contributes to memory function is not completely known. Previous formal studies indicate inhibition differentiated by local and global connectivity in associative memory networks functions to rescale the level of retrieval of excitatory assemblies. However, such studies lack biological details such as a distinction between types of neurons (excitatory and inhibitory), unrealistic connection schemas, and non-sparse assemblies. In this study, we present a rate-based cortical model where neurons are distinguished (as excitatory, local inhibitory, or global inhibitory), connected more realistically, and where memory items correspond to sparse excitatory assemblies. We use this model to study how local-global inhibition balance can alter memory retrieval in associative memory structures, including naturalistic and artificial structures. Experimental studies have reported inhibitory neurons and their sub-types uniquely respond to specific stimuli and can form sophisticated, joint excitatory-inhibitory assemblies. Our model suggests such joint assemblies, as well as a distribution and rebalancing of overall inhibition between two inhibitory sub-populations – one connected to excitatory assemblies locally and the other connected globally – can quadruple the range of retrieval across related memories. We identify a possible functional role for local-global inhibitory balance to, in the context of choice or preference of relationships, permit and maintain a broader range of memory items when local inhibition is dominant and conversely consolidate and strengthen a smaller range of memory items when global inhibition is dominant. This model therefore highlights a biologically-plausible and behaviourally-useful function of inhibitory diversity in memory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470555" rel="alternate" title="Multiscale and extended retrieval of associative memory structures in a cortical model of local-global inhibition balance (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470746</id><title>Interleukin-13 and its receptor are synaptic proteins involved in plasticity and neuroprotection (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.182904+00:00</updated><author><name>Li Shun</name></author><author><name>Florian olde Heuvel</name></author><author><name>Rida Rehman</name></author><author><name>Zhenghui Li</name></author><author><name>Oumayma Aousji</name></author><author><name>Albrecht Froehlich</name></author><author><name>Wanhong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Alison Conquest</name></author><author><name>Sarah Woelfle</name></author><author><name>Michael Schoen</name></author><author><name>Caitlin O Meara</name></author><author><name>Richard Lee Reinhardt</name></author><author><name>David Voehringer</name></author><author><name>Jan Kassubek</name></author><author><name>Albert Ludolph</name></author><author><name>Markus Huber-Lang</name></author><author><name>Bernd Knoell</name></author><author><name>Maria Cristina Morganti-Kossmann</name></author><author><name>Tobias M Boeckers</name></author><author><name>Francesco Roselli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune system molecules are expressed by neurons, often for unknown functions. We have identified IL-13 and its receptor IL-13Ra1 as neuronal, synaptic proteins in mouse, rat, and human brains, whose engagement upregulates the phosphorylation of NMDAR and AMPAR subunits and, in turn, increases synaptic activity and CREB-mediated transcription. We demonstrate that increased IL-13 is a hallmark of traumatic brain injury (TBI) in mice as well as in two distinct cohorts of human patients. We also provide evidence that IL-13 upregulation protects neurons from excitotoxic death. We show IL-13 upregulation occurring in several cohorts of human brain samples and in CSF. Thus, IL-13 is a previously unrecognized physiological modulator of synaptic physiology of neuronal origin, with implications for the establishment of synaptic plasticity and the survival of neurons under injury conditions. Furthermore, we suggest that the neuroprotection afforded through the upregulation of IL-13 represents a new entry point for interventions in the pathophysiology of TBI.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470746" rel="alternate" title="Interleukin-13 and its receptor are synaptic proteins involved in plasticity and neuroprotection (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470494</id><title>Mapping Consistent, Reproducible, and Transcriptionally Relevant Connectome Hubs of the Human Brain (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.183545+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhilei Xu</name></author><author><name>Mingrui Xia</name></author><author><name>Xindi Wang</name></author><author><name>Xuhong Liao</name></author><author><name>Tengda Zhao</name></author><author><name>Yong He</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macroscopic functional connectomic analyses have identified sets of densely connected regions in the human brain, known as connectome hubs, which play a vital role in understanding network communication, cognitive processing, and brain disorders. However, anatomical locations of functional connectome hubs are largely inconsistent and less reproducible among extant reports, partly due to inadequate sample size and differences in image processing and network analysis. Moreover, the genetic signatures underlying the robust connectome hubs remain unknown. Here, we conduct the first worldwide voxelwise meta-connectomic analysis by pooling resting-state functional MRI data of 5,212 healthy young adults across 61 independent international cohorts with harmonized image processing and network analysis protocols. We identify highly consistent and reproducible functional connectome hubs that are spatially distributed in multiple heteromodal and unimodal regions, with the most robust findings mainly located in lateral parietal regions. These connectome hubs show unique, heterogeneous connectivity profiles and are critical for both intra- and inter-network communications. Using transcriptome data from the Allen Human Brain Atlas and BrainSpan Atlas as well as machine learning, we demonstrate that these robust hubs are significantly associated with a transcriptomic pattern dominated by genes involved in the neuropeptide signaling pathway, neurodevelopmental processes, and cellular metabolic processes. This pattern represents microstructural and metabolic substrates underlying the development and functioning of brain hubs. Together, these results highlight robustness of macroscopic connectome hubs of the human brain and their potential cellular and molecular underpinnings and have implications for understanding how brain hubs support the connectome organization in health and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470494" rel="alternate" title="Mapping Consistent, Reproducible, and Transcriptionally Relevant Connectome Hubs of the Human Brain (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470730</id><title>Benchmarking Geometric Deep Learning for Cortical Segmentation and Neurodevelopmental Phenotype Prediction (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.183825+00:00</updated><author><name>Abdulah Fawaz</name></author><author><name>Logan Z. J. Williams</name></author><author><name>Amir Alansary</name></author><author><name>Cher Bass</name></author><author><name>Karthik Gopinath</name></author><author><name>Mariana da Silva</name></author><author><name>Simon Dahan</name></author><author><name>Chris Adamson</name></author><author><name>Bonnie Alexander</name></author><author><name>Deanne Thompson</name></author><author><name>Gareth Ball</name></author><author><name>Christian Desrosiers</name></author><author><name>Hervé Lombaert</name></author><author><name>Daniel Rueckert</name></author><author><name>A. David Edwards</name></author><author><name>Emma C. Robinson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The emerging field of geometric deep learning extends the application of convolutional neural networks to irregular domains such as graphs, meshes and surfaces. Several recent studies have explored the potential for using these techniques to analyse and segment the cortical surface. However, there has been no comprehensive comparison of these approaches to one another, nor to existing Euclidean methods, to date. This paper benchmarks a collection of geometric and traditional deep learning models on phenotype prediction and segmentation of sphericalised neonatal cortical surface data, from the publicly available Developing Human Connectome Project (dHCP). Tasks include prediction of postmenstrual age at scan, gestational age at birth and segmentation of the cortical surface into anatomical regions defined by the M-CRIB-S atlas. Performance was assessed not only in terms of model precision, but also in terms of network dependence on image registration, and model interpretation via occlusion. Networks were trained both on sphericalised and anatomical cortical meshes. Findings suggest that the utility of geometric deep learning over traditional deep learning is highly task-specific, which has implications for the design of future deep learning models on the cortical surface. The code, and instructions for data access, are available from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Abdulah-Fawaz/Benchmarking-Surface-DL"&gt;https://github.com/Abdulah-Fawaz/Benchmarking-Surface-DL&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470730" rel="alternate" title="Benchmarking Geometric Deep Learning for Cortical Segmentation and Neurodevelopmental Phenotype Prediction (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471180</id><title>Microglia Mediate Early Corticostriatal Synapse Loss and Cognitive Dysfunction in Huntingtons Disease Through Complement-Dependent Mechanisms (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.184276+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel K Wilton</name></author><author><name>Kevin J Mastro</name></author><author><name>Molly D Heller</name></author><author><name>Frederick W Gergits</name></author><author><name>Carly Rose Willing</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Frouin</name></author><author><name>Anthony Daggett</name></author><author><name>Xiaofeng Gu</name></author><author><name>Andrea Y Kim</name></author><author><name>Richard Faull</name></author><author><name>Suman Jayadev</name></author><author><name>Ted Yednock</name></author><author><name>Xiangdong William Yang</name></author><author><name>beth stevens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Huntington′s disease (HD) is a devastating monogenic neurodegenerative disease characterized by early, selective pathology in the basal ganglia despite the ubiquitous expression of mutant huntingtin. The molecular mechanisms underlying this region-specific neuronal degeneration and how these relate to the development of early cognitive phenotypes are poorly understood. Here, we show that there is selective loss of synaptic connections between the cortex and striatum in postmortem tissue from HD patients that is associated with the increased activation and localization of complement proteins, innate immune molecules, to markers of these synaptic elements.  We also find that levels of these secreted innate immune molecules are elevated in the CSF of premanifest HD patients and correlate with established measures of disease burden. In preclinical genetic models of HD we show that complement proteins mediate the selective elimination of corticostriatal synapses at an early stage in disease pathogenesis marking them for removal by microglia, the brain′s resident macrophage population. This process requires mutant huntingtin to be expressed in both cortical and striatal neurons and inhibition of this complement-dependent elimination mechanism through administration of a therapeutically relevant C1q function blocking antibody or genetic ablation of a complement receptor on microglia, prevented synapse loss, increased excitatory input to the striatum and rescued the early development of visual discrimination learning and cognitive flexibility deficits in these models. Together, our findings implicate microglia and the complement cascade in the selective, early degeneration of corticostriatal synapses and the development of cognitive deficits in presymptomatic HD, and also provide new preclinical data to support complement as a therapeutic target for early intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471180" rel="alternate" title="Microglia Mediate Early Corticostriatal Synapse Loss and Cognitive Dysfunction in Huntingtons Disease Through Complement-Dependent Mechanisms (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470530</id><title>Targeted memory reactivation in human REM sleep elicits recurrent, temporally compressed reactivation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.184638+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahmoud E. A. Abdellahi</name></author><author><name>Anne C. M. Koopman</name></author><author><name>Matthias S. Treder</name></author><author><name>Penelope A. Lewis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Memories are reactivated during non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep, but the question of whether equivalent reactivation also occurs in rapid eye movement (REM) sleep is hotly debated. To examine this, we used a technique called targeted memory reactivation (TMR) in which sounds are paired with learned material in wake, and then re-presented in subsequent sleep to trigger reactivation. We then used machine learning classifiers to identify TMR-induced reactivation in REM. The reactivation we measured was temporally compressed by approximately five times during REM compared to wakeful performance of the task, and often occurred twice after a single TMR cue. Reactivation strength positively predicted overnight performance improvement and was only apparent in trials with high theta activity. These findings provide strong evidence for memory reactivation in human REM sleep after TMR as well as an initial characterisation of this reactivation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470530" rel="alternate" title="Targeted memory reactivation in human REM sleep elicits recurrent, temporally compressed reactivation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470952</id><title>cacna2d3, a voltage-gated calcium channel subunit, functions in vertebrate habituation learning and the startle sensitivity threshold (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.184884+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas J. Santistevan</name></author><author><name>Jessica C. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Elelbin A. Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Andrew H. Miller</name></author><author><name>Dima Kenj Halabi</name></author><author><name>Zoë A. Sippl</name></author><author><name>Michael Granato</name></author><author><name>Yevgenya Grinblat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability to filter sensory information into relevant versus irrelevant stimuli is a fundamental, conserved property of the central nervous system and is accomplished in part through habituation learning. Synaptic plasticity that underlies habituation learning has been described at the cellular level, yet the genetic regulators of this plasticity remain poorly understood, as do circuits that mediate sensory filtering. A forward genetic screen for zebrafish genes that control habituation learning identified a mutant allele &lt;italic&gt;dory&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;p177&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that caused reduced habituation of the acoustic startle response. Whole-genome sequencing identified the &lt;italic&gt;calcium voltage-gated channel auxiliary subunit alpha-2/delta-&lt;/italic&gt;3 (&lt;italic&gt;cacna2d3&lt;/italic&gt;) as a candidate gene affected in &lt;italic&gt;dory&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;p177&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; mutants. Behavioral characterization of larvae homozygous for two additional, independently derived mutant alleles of &lt;italic&gt;cacna2d3&lt;/italic&gt;, together with failure of these alleles to complement &lt;italic&gt;dory&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;p177&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, confirmed a critical role for &lt;italic&gt;cacna2d3&lt;/italic&gt; in habituation learning. Notably, detailed analyses of the acoustic response in mutant larvae also revealed increased startle sensitivity to acoustic stimuli, suggesting a broader role for &lt;italic&gt;cacna2d3&lt;/italic&gt; in controlling innate response thresholds to acoustic stimuli. Taken together, our data demonstrate a critical role for &lt;italic&gt;cacna2d3&lt;/italic&gt; in sensory filtering, a process that is disrupted in human CNS disorders, e.g. ADHD, schizophrenia, and autism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470952" rel="alternate" title="cacna2d3, a voltage-gated calcium channel subunit, functions in vertebrate habituation learning and the startle sensitivity threshold (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471186</id><title>Long-term labeling and imaging of synaptically-connected neuronal networks in vivo using nontoxic, double-deletion-mutant rabies viruses (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.185168+00:00</updated><author><name>Lei Jin</name></author><author><name>Heather A Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Mulangma Zhu</name></author><author><name>Thomas K Lavin</name></author><author><name>Makoto Matsuyama</name></author><author><name>Nicholas E Lea</name></author><author><name>Ran Xu</name></author><author><name>YuanYuan Hou</name></author><author><name>Luca Rutigliani</name></author><author><name>Maxwell T Pruner</name></author><author><name>Kelsey R Babcock</name></author><author><name>Jacque Pak Kan Ip</name></author><author><name>Ming Hu</name></author><author><name>Tanya L Daigle</name></author><author><name>Hongkui Zeng</name></author><author><name>Mriganka Sur</name></author><author><name>Ian R Wickersham</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The highly specific and complex connectivity between neurons is the hallmark of nervous systems, but techniques for identifying, imaging, and manipulating synaptically-connected networks of neurons are limited. Monosynaptic tracing, or the gated replication and spread of a deletion-mutant rabies virus to label neurons directly connected to a targeted population of starting neurons1, is the most widely-used technique for mapping neural circuitry, but the rapid cytotoxicity of first-generation rabies viral vectors has restricted its use almost entirely to anatomical applications. We recently introduced double-deletion-mutant second-generation rabies viral vectors, showing that they have little or no detectable toxicity and are efficient means of retrogradely targeting neurons projecting to an injection site2, but they have not previously been shown to be capable of gated replication in vivo, the basis of monosynaptic tracing. Here we present a complete second-generation system for labeling direct inputs to genetically-targeted neuronal populations with minimal toxicity, using double-deletion-mutant rabies viruses. Spread of the viruses requires complementation of both of the deleted viral genes in trans in the starting postsynaptic cells; suppressing the expression of these viral genes following an initial period of viral replication, using the Tet-Off system, reduces toxicity to the starting cells without decreasing the efficiency of viral spread. Using longitudinal two-photon imaging of live monosynaptic tracing in visual cortex, we found that 94.4% of all labeled cells, and an estimated 92.3% of starting cells, survived for the full twelve-week course of imaging. Two-photon imaging of calcium responses in labeled networks of neurons in vivo over ten weeks showed that labeled neurons' visual response properties remained stable for as long as we followed them. This nontoxic labeling of inputs to genetically-targeted neurons in vivo is a long-held goal in neuroscience, with transformative applications including nonperturbative transcriptomic and epigenomic profiling, long-term functional imaging and behavioral studies, and optogenetic and chemogenetic manipulation of synaptically-connected neuronal networks over the lifetimes of experimental animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471186" rel="alternate" title="Long-term labeling and imaging of synaptically-connected neuronal networks in vivo using nontoxic, double-deletion-mutant rabies viruses (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470965</id><title>Contextual control of conditioned pain tolerance and endogenous analgesic systems: Evidence for sex-based differences in endogenous opioid engagement (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.185575+00:00</updated><author><name>Sydney Trask</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey S Mogil</name></author><author><name>Fred Helmstetter</name></author><author><name>Cheryl L Stucky</name></author><author><name>Katelyn E Sadler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mechanisms underlying the transition from acute to chronic pain are unclear but may involve the persistence or strengthening of pain memories acquired in part through associative learning. Contextual cues, which comprise the surrounding environment where events occur, were recently described as a critical regulator of pain memory; both rodents and humans exhibit increased pain sensitivity in environments recently associated with a single painful experience. It is unknown, however, how repeated exposure to an acute painful unconditioned stimulus in a distinct context modifies pain sensitivity or the expectation of pain in that environment. To answer this question, we conditioned mice to associate distinct contexts with either repeated administration of a mild visceral pain stimulus (intraperitoneal injection of acetic acid) or vehicle injection over the course of three days. On the final day of experiments animals received either an acid injection or vehicle injection prior to being placed into both contexts. In this way, contextual control of pain sensitivity and pain expectation could be tested respectively. Both male and female mice developed context-dependent conditional pain tolerance, a phenomenon mediated by endogenous opioid signaling. However, when expecting the presentation of a painful stimulus in a given context, males exhibited conditional hypersensitivity whereas females exhibited endogenous opioid-mediated conditional analgesia. Successful determination of the brain circuits involved in this sexually dimorphic anticipatory response may allow for the manipulation of pain memories, which may contribute to the development of chronic pain states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470965" rel="alternate" title="Contextual control of conditioned pain tolerance and endogenous analgesic systems: Evidence for sex-based differences in endogenous opioid engagement (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470970</id><title>Pupillary dynamics of optimal effort (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.185852+00:00</updated><author><name>Ceyda Sayali</name></author><author><name>Emma Heling</name></author><author><name>Roshan Cools</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While a substantial body of work has shown that cognitive effort is aversive and costly, a separate line of research on intrinsic motivation suggests that people spontaneously seek challenging tasks. According to one prominent account of intrinsic motivation, the Learning Progress Motivation theory, the preference for difficult tasks reflects the dynamic range that these tasks yield for minimization of performance accuracy prediction errors (Oudeyer, Kaplan &amp;amp; Hafner, 2007). Here we test this hypothesis, by asking whether greater engagement with intermediately difficult tasks, indexed by subjective ratings and objective pupil measurements, is a function of trial-wise changes in performance prediction error. In a novel paradigm, we determined each individuals capacity for task performance and used difficulty levels that are too low, intermediately challenging or high for that individual. We demonstrated that intermediately challenging tasks resulted in greater liking and engagement scores compared with easy tasks. Task-evoked and baseline pupil size tracked objective task difficulty, where challenging tasks were associated with smaller baseline and greater phasic pupil responses than easy tasks. Most importantly, pupil responses were predicted by trial-to-trial changes in expected accuracy, performance prediction error magnitude and changes in prediction errors (learning progress), whereas smaller baseline pupil responses also predicted greater subjective engagement scores. Together, these results suggest that what is underlying the link between task engagement and intermediate tasks might be the dynamic range that these tasks yield for minimization of performance accuracy prediction errors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470970" rel="alternate" title="Pupillary dynamics of optimal effort (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470765</id><title>Sex-dependent changes in murine striatal dopamine release, sleep, and behavior during spontaneous Δ-9-tetrahydrocannabinol abstinence (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.186109+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew J. Kesner</name></author><author><name>Yolanda Mateo</name></author><author><name>Karina P. Abrahao</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Ramos-Maciel</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Pava</name></author><author><name>Alexa L. Gracias</name></author><author><name>Riley T. Paulsen</name></author><author><name>Hartley B. Carlson</name></author><author><name>David M. Lovinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Withdrawal symptoms are observed upon cessation of cannabis use in humans. Although animal studies have examined withdrawal symptoms following exposure to delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC), difficulties in obtaining objective measures of spontaneous withdrawal using paradigms that mimic cessation of use in humans have slowed research. The neuromodulator dopamine (DA) is known to be affected by chronic THC treatment and plays a role in many behaviors related to human THC withdrawal symptoms. These symptoms include sleep disturbances that often drive relapse, and emotional behaviors, e.g., irritability and anhedonia. We examined THC withdrawal-induced changes in striatal DA release and the extent to which sleep disruption and behavioral maladaptation manifest during withdrawal in a mouse chronic cannabis exposure model. Using a THC treatment regimen known to produce tolerance we measured electrically elicited DA release in acute brain slices from different striatal subregions during early and late THC abstinence. Long-term polysomnographic recordings from mice were used to assess vigilance state and sleep architecture before, during, and after THC treatment. We additionally assessed how behaviors that model human withdrawal symptoms are altered by chronic THC treatment in early and late abstinence. We detected altered striatal DA release, sleep disturbances that mimic clinical observations, and behavioral maladaptation in mice following tolerance inducing THC treatment. Sex differences were observed in nearly all metrics. Altered striatal DA release, sleep and affect-related behaviors associated with spontaneous THC abstinence were more consistently observed in male mice. To our knowledge these findings provide the first model of directly translatable non-precipitated cannabis withdrawal symptoms, in particular, sleep disruption.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470765" rel="alternate" title="Sex-dependent changes in murine striatal dopamine release, sleep, and behavior during spontaneous Δ-9-tetrahydrocannabinol abstinence (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470537</id><title>Temporally stable beta sensorimotor oscillations and cortico–muscular coupling underlie force steadiness (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.186463+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott J. Mongold</name></author><author><name>Harri Piitulainen</name></author><author><name>Thomas Legrand</name></author><author><name>Marc Vander Ghinst</name></author><author><name>Gilles Naeije</name></author><author><name>Veikko Jousmäki</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Bourguignon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As humans, we seamlessly hold objects in our hands, and may even lose consciousness of these objects. This phenomenon raises the unsettled question of the involvement of the cerebral cortex, the core area for voluntary motor control, in dynamically maintaining steady muscle force. To address this issue, we measured magnetoencephalographic brain activity from healthy adults who maintained a steady pinch grip. Using a novel analysis approach, we uncovered fine-grained temporal modulations in the ∼20-Hz sensorimotor brain rhythm and its coupling with muscle activity, with respect to several aspects of muscle force (rate of increase/decrease or plateauing high/low). These modulations preceded changes in force features by ∼40 ms and possessed behavioral relevance, as less salient or absent modulation predicted a more stable force output. These findings have consequences for the existing theories regarding the functional role of cortico-muscular coupling, and suggest that steady muscle contractions are characterized by a stable rather than fluttering involvement of the sensorimotor cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.30.470537" rel="alternate" title="Temporally stable beta sensorimotor oscillations and cortico–muscular coupling underlie force steadiness (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470724</id><title>Pupillometry and the vigilance decrement: Task-evoked but not baseline pupil measures reflect declining performance in visual vigilance tasks (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.186821+00:00</updated><author><name>Joel T. Martin</name></author><author><name>Annalise H. Whittaker</name></author><author><name>Stephen J. Johnston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Baseline and task-evoked pupil measures are known to reflect the activity of the nervous system’s central arousal mechanisms. With the increasing availability, affordability and flexibility of video-based eye tracking hardware, these measures may one day find practical application in real-time biobehavioral monitoring systems to assess performance or fitness for duty in tasks requiring vigilant attention. But real-world vigilance tasks are predominantly visual in their nature and most research in this area has taken place in the auditory domain. Here we explore the relationship between pupil size—both baseline and task-evoked—and behavioral performance measures in two novel vigilance tasks requiring visual target detection: 1) a traditional vigilance task involving prolonged, continuous, and uninterrupted performance (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 28), and 2) a psychomotor vigilance task (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 25). In both tasks, behavioral performance and task- evoked pupil responses declined as time spent on task increased, corroborating previous reports in the literature of a vigilance decrement with a corresponding reduction in task-evoked pupil measures. Also in line with previous findings, baseline pupil size did not show a consistent relationship with performance measures. We discuss our findings considering the adaptive gain theory of locus coeruleus function and question the validity of the assumption that baseline (prestimulus) pupil size and task-evoked (poststimulus) pupil measures correspond to the tonic and phasic firing modes of the LC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470724" rel="alternate" title="Pupillometry and the vigilance decrement: Task-evoked but not baseline pupil measures reflect declining performance in visual vigilance tasks (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470914</id><title>Relationship between high-frequency activity in the sensory and the motor hand areas, and regional myelin content (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.187137+00:00</updated><author><name>Leo Tomasevic</name></author><author><name>Hartwig Roman Siebner</name></author><author><name>Axel Thielscher</name></author><author><name>Fiore Manganelli</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Pontillo</name></author><author><name>Raffaele Dubbioso</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: The human primary sensory (S1) and primary motor (M1) hand areas feature high-frequency neuronal responses. Electrical nerve stimulation evokes high-frequency oscillations (HFO) at around 650 Hz in the contralateral S1. Likewise, paired-pulse transcranial magnetic stimulation of M1 produces short interval intracortical facilitation (SICF) of motor evoked potentials in contralateral hand muscles. SICF features several peaks of facilitation which are separated by inter-peak intervals resembling HFO rhythmicity.
Hypothesis: In this study, we tested the hypothesis that the individual expressions of HFO and SICF are tightly related to each other and to the regional myelin content in the sensorimotor cortex.
Methods: In 24 healthy volunteers, we recorded HFO and SICF, and, in a subgroup of 20 participants, we mapped the cortical myelin content using the ratio between the T1- and T2-weighted MRI signal as read-out.
Results: The individual frequencies and magnitudes of HFO and SICF were tightly correlated: the intervals between the first and second peak of cortical HFO and SICF showed a positive linear relationship (r= 0.703, p&amp;lt; 0.001), while their amplitudes were inversely related (r= -0.613, p= 0.001). The rhythmicity, but not the magnitude of the high-frequency responses, was related to the cortical myelin content: the higher the cortical myelin content, the shorter the inter-peak intervals of HFO and SICF.
Conclusion: The results confirm a tight functional relationship between high-frequency responses in S1 (i.e., HFO) and M1 (i.e., SICF). They also establish a link between the degree of regional cortical myelination and the expression of high-frequency responses in the human cortex, giving further the opportunity to infer their possible generators.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470914" rel="alternate" title="Relationship between high-frequency activity in the sensory and the motor hand areas, and regional myelin content (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>