<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.149968+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458870</id><title>Behavioral state tunes mouse vision to ethological features through pupil dilation (106 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.150188+00:00</updated><author><name>Katrin Franke</name></author><author><name>Konstantin F. Willeke</name></author><author><name>Kayla Ponder</name></author><author><name>Mario Galdamez</name></author><author><name>Taliah Muhammad</name></author><author><name>Saumil Patel</name></author><author><name>Emmanouil Froudarakis</name></author><author><name>Jacob Reimer</name></author><author><name>Fabian Sinz</name></author><author><name>Andreas S. Tolias</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Across animal species, sensory processing dynamically adapts to behavioral context. In the mammalian visual system, sensory neural responses and behavioral performance increase during an active behavioral state characterized by locomotion activity and pupil dilation, whereas preferred stimuli of individual neurons typically remain unchanged. Here, we address how behavioral states modulate stimulus selectivity in the context of colored natural scenes using a combination of large-scale population imaging, behavior, pharmacology, and deep neural network modeling. In visual cortex of awake mice, we identified a consistent shift of individual neuron color preferences towards ultraviolet stimuli during active behavioral periods that was particularly pronounced in the upper visual field. We found that the spectral shift in neural tuning is mediated by pupil dilation, resulting in a dynamic switch from rod-to cone-driven visual responses for constant ambient light levels. We further showed that this shift selectively enhances the discriminability of ultraviolet objects and facilitates the detection of ethological stimuli, such as aerial predators against the ultraviolet background of the twilight sky. Our results suggest a novel functional role for pupil dilation during active behavioral states as a bottom-up mechanism that, together with top-down neuromodulatory mechanisms, dynamically tunes visual representations to different behavioral demands.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458870" rel="alternate" title="Behavioral state tunes mouse vision to ethological features through pupil dilation (106 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.458941</id><title>Mapping electromagnetic networks to haemodynamic networks in the human brain (69 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.150437+00:00</updated><author><name>Golia Shafiei</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Baillet</name></author><author><name>Bratislav Misic</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole-brain neural communication is typically estimated from statistical associations among electromagnetic or haemodynamic time-series. The relationship between functional network architectures recovered from these two types of neural activity remains unknown. Here we map electromagnetic networks (measured using magnetoencephalography; MEG) to haemodynamic networks (measured using functional magnetic resonance imaging; fMRI). We find that the relationship between the two modalities is regionally heterogeneous and systematically follows the cortical hierarchy, with close correspondence in unimodal cortex and poor correspondence in transmodal cortex, potentially reflecting patterns of laminar differentiation, recurrent subcortical input and neurovascular coupling. Correspondence between the two is largely driven by slower rhythms, particularly the delta (2-4 Hz) and beta (15-29 Hz) frequency band. Moreover, haemodynamic connectivity cannot be explained by electromagnetic activity in a single frequency band, but rather arises from the mixing of multiple neurophysiological rhythms. Collectively, these findings demonstrate highly organized but only partly overlapping patterns of connectivity in MEG and fMRI functional networks, opening fundamentally new avenues for studying the relationship between cortical micro-architecture and multi-modal connectivity patterns.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.458941" rel="alternate" title="Mapping electromagnetic networks to haemodynamic networks in the human brain (69 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459546</id><title>Humans reconfigure target and distractor processing to address distinct task demands (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.150749+00:00</updated><author><name>Harrison Ritz</name></author><author><name>Amitai Shenhav</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When faced with distraction, we can focus more on goal-relevant information (targets) or focus less goal-conflicting information (distractors). How people decide to distribute cognitive control across targets and distractors remains unclear. To help address this question, we developed a parametric attentional control task with a graded manipulation to both target discriminability and distractor interference. We find that participants exert independent control over target and distractor processing. We measured control adjustments through the influence of incentives and previous conflict on target and distractor sensitivity, finding that these have dissociable influences on control. Whereas incentives preferentially led to target enhancement, conflict on the previous trial preferentially led to distractor suppression. These distinct drivers of control altered sensitivity to targets and distractors early in the trial, and were promptly followed by reactive reconfiguration towards task-appropriate feature sensitivity. Finally, we provide a process-level account of these findings by show that these control adjustments are well-captured by an evidence accumulation model with attractor dynamics over feature weights. These results help establish a process-level account of control configuration that provides new insights into how multivariate attentional signals are optimized to achieve task goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459546" rel="alternate" title="Humans reconfigure target and distractor processing to address distinct task demands (56 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459829</id><title>Dopamine biases sensitivity to personal goals and social influence in self-control over everyday desires (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.150973+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaime J Castrellon</name></author><author><name>Jacob S Young</name></author><author><name>Linh C Dang</name></author><author><name>Christopher T Smith</name></author><author><name>Ronald L Cowan</name></author><author><name>David H Zald</name></author><author><name>Gregory R Samanez-Larkin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;People regularly give in to daily temptations in spite of conflict with personal goals. To test hypotheses about neuropharmacological influences on self-control, we used positron emission tomography to measure dopamine D2-like receptors (D2R) and experience sampling surveys to naturalistically track daily desires outside the laboratory in everyday life in a sample of 103 adults. Higher D2R availability in the ventral striatum was associated with increased sensitivity to personal goal conflict but not desire strength in deciding whether to attempt to resist a desire. The influence of D2Rs on sensitivity to personal goal conflict depended on whether desires were experienced in a social context. D2R availability in the midbrain (but not the ventral striatum) influenced whether desires were enacted. These findings provide unique evidence that the dopamine system influences decision making and regulatory behavior and provides new insights into how these mechanisms interact with personal goals and social contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459829" rel="alternate" title="Dopamine biases sensitivity to personal goals and social influence in self-control over everyday desires (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459619</id><title>Single-nucleus transcriptomic analyses reveal microglial activation underlying cerebellar degeneration in Ataxia Telangiectasia (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.151172+00:00</updated><author><name>Jenny Lai</name></author><author><name>Junho Kim</name></author><author><name>Ailsa M. Jeffries</name></author><author><name>Allie Tolles</name></author><author><name>Thomas W. Chittenden</name></author><author><name>Patrick G. Buckley</name></author><author><name>Timothy W. Yu</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Lodato</name></author><author><name>Eunjung Alice Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While &lt;italic&gt;ATM&lt;/italic&gt; loss-of-function has long been identified as the genetic cause of Ataxia Telangiectasia (AT), how this genetic mutation leads to selective and progressive cerebellar degeneration of Purkinje and granule cells remains unknown. We performed single-nucleus RNA-sequencing of the human cerebellum and prefrontal cortex from individuals with AT and matched unaffected controls to identify AT-associated transcriptomic changes in a cell-type- and brain-region-specific manner. We provide the largest single-nucleus transcriptomic atlas of the adult human cerebellum to-date (126,356 nuclei), identify upregulation of apoptotic and ER stress pathways in Purkinje and granule neurons, and uncover strong downregulation of calcium ion homeostasis genes in Purkinje neurons. Our analysis reveals prominent inflammation of microglia in AT cerebellum with transcriptional signatures similar to aging and neurodegenerative microglia, and suggests that microglia activation precedes Purkinje and granule neuron death in disease progression. Our data implicates a novel role of microglial activation underlying cerebellar degeneration in AT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459619" rel="alternate" title="Single-nucleus transcriptomic analyses reveal microglial activation underlying cerebellar degeneration in Ataxia Telangiectasia (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.458611</id><title>CaPTure: Calcium PeakToolbox for analysis of in vitro calcium imaging data (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.151367+00:00</updated><author><name>Madhavi Tippani</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Pattie</name></author><author><name>Brittany A. Davis</name></author><author><name>Claudia V. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Yanhong Wang</name></author><author><name>Srinidhi Rao Sripathy</name></author><author><name>Brady J. Maher</name></author><author><name>Keri Martinowich</name></author><author><name>Andrew E. Jaffe</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Cerceo Page</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Calcium imaging is a powerful technique for recording cellular activity across large populations of neurons. However, analysis methods capable of single-cell resolution in cultured neurons, especially for cultures derived from human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs), are lacking. Existing methods lack scalability to accommodate high-throughput comparisons between multiple lines, across developmental timepoints, or across pharmacological manipulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed a scalable, automated Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; imaging analysis pipeline called CaPTure (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/LieberInstitute/CaPTure"&gt;https://github.com/LieberInstitute/CaPTure&lt;/ext-link&gt;). This method detects neurons, classifies and quantifies spontaneous activity, quantifies synchrony metrics, and generates cell- and network-specific metrics that facilitate phenotypic discovery. The method is compatible with parallel processing on computing clusters without requiring significant user input or parameter modification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CaPTure allows for rapid assessment of neuronal activity in cultured cells at cellular resolution, rendering it amenable to high-throughput screening and phenotypic discovery. The platform can be applied to both human- and rodent-derived neurons and is compatible with many imaging systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.458611" rel="alternate" title="CaPTure: Calcium PeakToolbox for analysis of in vitro calcium imaging data (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459211</id><title>Assembly formation is stabilized by Parvalbumin neurons and accelerated by Somatostatin neurons (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.151714+00:00</updated><author><name>Fereshteh Lagzi</name></author><author><name>Martha Canto Bustos</name></author><author><name>Anne-Marie Oswald</name></author><author><name>Brent Doiron</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Learning entails preserving the features of the external world in the neuronal representations of the brain, and manifests itself in the form of strengthened interactions between neurons within assemblies. Hebbian synaptic plasticity is thought to be one mechanism by which correlations in spiking promote assembly formation during learning. While spike timing dependent plasticity (STDP) rules for excitatory synapses have been well characterized, inhibitory STDP rules remain incomplete, particularly with respect to sub-classes of inhibitory interneurons. Here, we report that in layer 2/3 of the orbitofrontal cortex of mice, inhibition from parvalbumin (PV) interneurons onto excitatory (E) neurons follows a symmetric STDP function and mediates homeostasis in E-neuron firing rates. However, inhibition from somatostatin (SOM) interneurons follows an asymmetric, Hebbian STDP rule. We incorporate these findings in both large scale simulations and mean-field models to investigate how these differences in plasticity impact network dynamics and assembly formation. We find that plasticity of SOM inhibition builds lateral inhibitory connections and increases competition between assemblies. This is reflected in amplified correlations between neurons within assembly and anti-correlations between assemblies. An additional finding is that the emergence of tuned PV inhibition depends on the interaction between SOM and PV STDP rules. Altogether, we show that incorporation of differential inhibitory STDP rules promotes assembly formation through competition, while enhanced inhibition both within and between assemblies protects new representations from degradation after the training input is removed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459211" rel="alternate" title="Assembly formation is stabilized by Parvalbumin neurons and accelerated by Somatostatin neurons (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458917</id><title>Strategy-dependent effects of working-memory limitations on human perceptual decision-making (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.151923+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyra Schapiro</name></author><author><name>Krešimir Josić</name></author><author><name>Zachary P. Kilpatrick</name></author><author><name>Joshua I. Gold</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deliberative decisions based on an accumulation of evidence over time depend on working memory, and working memory has limitations, but how these limitations affect deliberative decision-making is not understood. We used human psychophysics to assess the impact of working-memory limitations on the fidelity of a continuous decision variable. Participants decided the average location of multiple visual targets. This computed, continuous decision variable degraded with time and capacity in a manner that depended critically on the strategy used to form the decision variable. This dependence reflected whether the decision variable was computed either: 1) immediately upon observing the evidence, and thus stored as a single value in memory; or 2) at the time of the report, and thus stored as multiple values in memory. These results provide important constraints on how the brain computes and maintains temporally dynamic decision variables.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458917" rel="alternate" title="Strategy-dependent effects of working-memory limitations on human perceptual decision-making (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459766</id><title>Combining CRISPR/Cas9 and brain imaging: from genes to proteins to networks (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.152166+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabina Marciano</name></author><author><name>Tudor M. Ionescu</name></author><author><name>Ran Sing Saw</name></author><author><name>Rachel Y. Cheong</name></author><author><name>Deniz Kirik</name></author><author><name>Andreas Maurer</name></author><author><name>Bernd J. Pichler</name></author><author><name>Kristina Herfert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding how functional connections between brain regions are arranged and influenced by genes, in the healthy and diseased states, is a major goal in neuroscience. Functional connectivity alterations are linked to molecular changes in several neurodegenerative disorders and could serve as early markers of pathology. Yet, the underlying molecular signatures driving the functional alterations remain largely unknown. Here, we combine CRISPR/Cas9 gene-editing with in vivo positron emission tomography (PET) and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to investigate the direct link between genes, proteins, and the brain connectome. The extensive knowledge of the Slc18a2 gene encoding the vesicular monoamine transporter (VMAT2), involved in the storage and release of dopamine, makes it an excellent basis for studying the gene networks relationships. We edited Slc18a2 into the substantia nigra pars compacta of adult rats and used in vivo molecular imaging, behavioral, histological, and biochemical assessments to characterize the CRISPR/Cas9-mediated VMAT2 knockdown. Simultaneous PET/fMRI was performed to inspect the functional brain adaptations, beyond the predicted dopaminergic changes. Further, [11C]flumazenil PET was carried out to investigate the dopamine-GABA interplay. We found a regional increase in postsynaptic dopamine receptor availability, preceded by a reorganization of brain networks that adapt to reduced dopamine transmission states by becoming functionally connected and organized. The hyperconnectivity within and between brain networks spreads from the contralateral thalamus and prefrontal cortical regions to the striata and hippocampi. Additionally, impaired striatal dopamine release reduces GABA-A receptor availability, complementing the increased synchrony and functional connectivity between networks observed at rest. Our study reveals that recruiting different brain networks may be an early response to the dopaminergic dysfunction preceding neuronal cell loss, postsynaptic changes, and motor impairment in neurodegenerative disorders such as Parkinson's disease. We anticipate our combinatorial approach to be a starting point to investigate the impact of specific genes on brain molecular and functional dynamics, aiding in the identification of early neurobiological markers and promising therapeutic interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459766" rel="alternate" title="Combining CRISPR/Cas9 and brain imaging: from genes to proteins to networks (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459353</id><title>Concurrent Multimodal Data Acquisition During Brain Scanning is within Reach (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.152374+00:00</updated><author><name>Rosa Sola Molina</name></author><author><name>Gemma Lamp</name></author><author><name>Laila Hugrass</name></author><author><name>Russell Beaton</name></author><author><name>Marten de Man</name></author><author><name>Lisa Wise</name></author><author><name>David Crewther</name></author><author><name>Melvyn Goodale</name></author><author><name>Sheila Crewther</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous brain-scanning research exploring the neural mechanisms underpinning visuomotor planning and control has mostly been done without simultaneous motion-tracking and eye-tracking. Employing concurrent methodologies would enhance understanding of the brain mechanisms underlying visuomotor integration of cognitive, visual, ocular, and motor aspects of reaching and grasping behaviours. Therefore, this work presents the methods and validation for a high-speed, multimodal and synchronized system to holistically examine neural processes that are involved in visually-guided movement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The multimodal methods included high speed 3D motion tracking (Qualisys), 2D eye-tracking (SR Research), and magnetoencephalography (MEG; Elekta) that were synchronized to millisecond precision. Previous MRIs were taken to provide improved spatial localization. The methods section describes the system layout and acquisition parameters to achieve multimodal synchronization. Pilot results presented here are preliminary data from a larger study including 29 participants. Using a pincer grip, five people (3 male, 2 female, ages 30-32) reached for and grasped a translucent dowel 50 times, after it was pseudorandomly illuminated. The object illumination was the Go cue. Seven discrete time points (events) throughout the task were chosen for investigation of simultaneous brain, hand and eye activity associated with specific visual (Go cue), oculomotor (1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; saccade after Go), motor (Reaction Time; RT, Maximum Velocity: MV, Maximum Grip Width; MGW) or cognitive (Ready, End) mechanisms. Time-frequency analyses were performed on the MEG data sourced from the left precentral gyrus to explore task-related changes time-locked to these chosen events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Pilot results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Basic kinematic parameters including RT, MV, MGW, Movement Time, and Total Time were similar to previous, seminal research by Castiello, Paulignan and Jeannerod, (1991), using a similar task. Although no gaze instructions were given, eye-tracking results indicated volunteers mostly gazed at or near the target object when Ready (72%), and then hardly looked away throughout the rest of the task at the important events sampled here (92% - 98%). At the End event, when lifting the dowel, on average, participants gazed at or near the target object 100% of the time. Although saccades &amp;gt; 100 ms after Go, but prior to RT were made on average in about one fourth (&lt;italic&gt;M&lt;/italic&gt; = 13, &lt;italic&gt;SD&lt;/italic&gt; = 6) of trials, a mixed model (REML) indicated their latency in timing after the Go was significantly (&lt;italic&gt;F&lt;/italic&gt; = 13.376, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; = .001) associated with RT scores on those trials (&lt;italic&gt;AIC&lt;/italic&gt; = 724, &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;m&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.407, &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;c&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;= 0.420). Neural activity relative to baseline in the beta band was desynchronized for the visually guided reach periods, beginning prior to Go, and remaining sustained until beyond End, after the grasp and lift were executed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study presents the layout, acquisition parameters and validation for a multimodal, synchronized system designed to record data from the hand, eye and brain simultaneously, with millisecond precision during an ecologically-valid prehension task with physical, 3D objects. The pilot results align with previous research made with single or bimodal data recordings. This multimodal method enables full-brain modelling that can holistically map the precise location and timing of neural activity involved in the visual, oculomotor, motor and cognitive aspects of reach-to-grasp planning and control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459353" rel="alternate" title="Concurrent Multimodal Data Acquisition During Brain Scanning is within Reach (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459678</id><title>The Cortical Spectrum: a robust structural continuum in primate cerebral cortex revealed by histological staining and magnetic resonance imaging (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.152594+00:00</updated><author><name>Yohan J. John</name></author><author><name>Basilis Zikopoulos</name></author><author><name>Miguel Ángel García-Cabezas</name></author><author><name>Helen Barbas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High-level characterizations of the primate cerebral cortex sit between two extremes: on one end the cortical mantle is seen as a mosaic of structurally and functionally unique areas, and on the other it is seen as a uniform six-layered structure in which functional differences are defined solely by extrinsic connections. Neither of these extremes captures the crucial neuroanatomical finding: that the cortex exhibits systematic gradations in architectonic structure. These gradations have been shown to predict cortico-cortical connectivity, which in turn suggests powerful ways to ground connectomics in anatomical structure, and by extension cortical function. A challenge to more widespread use of this concept is the labor-intensive and invasive nature of histological staining, which is the primary means of recognizing anatomical gradations. Here we show that a novel computational analysis technique can be used to derive a coarse-grained picture of cortical variation. For each of 78 cortical areas spanning the entire cortical mantle of the rhesus macaque, we created a high dimensional set of anatomical features derived from captured images of cortical tissue stained for myelin and SMI-32. The method involved semi-automated de-noising of images, and enabled comparison of brain areas without hand-labeling of features such as layer boundaries. We applied nonmetric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) to the dataset to visualize similarity among cortical areas. This analysis shows a systematic variation between weakly laminated (limbic) cortices and sharply laminated (eulaminate) cortices. We call this smooth continuum the ‘cortical spectrum’. We also show that this spectrum is visible within subsystems of the cortex: the occipital, parietal, temporal, motor, prefrontal, and insular cortices. We compared the NMDS-derived spectrum with a spectrum produced using T1- and T2-weighted magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) data derived from macaque, and found close agreement of the two coarse-graining methods. This evidence suggests that T1/T2 data, routinely obtained in human MRI studies, can be used as an effective proxy for data derived from high-resolution histological methods. More generally, this approach shows that the cortical spectrum is robust to the specific method used to compare cortical areas, and is therefore a powerful tool to understand the principles of organization of the primate cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459678" rel="alternate" title="The Cortical Spectrum: a robust structural continuum in primate cerebral cortex revealed by histological staining and magnetic resonance imaging (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.459906</id><title>PV neurons improve cortical complex scene analysis by enhancing timing-based coding (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.152779+00:00</updated><author><name>Jian Carlo Nocon</name></author><author><name>Howard J Gritton</name></author><author><name>Nicholas M James</name></author><author><name>Xue Han</name></author><author><name>Kamal Sen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cortical representations underlying a wide range of cognitive abilities, which employ both rate and spike timing-based coding, emerge from underlying cortical circuits with a tremendous diversity of cell types. However, cell-type specific contributions to cortical coding are not well-understood. Here, we investigate the role of parvalbumin (PV) neurons in cortical complex scene analysis. Many complex scenes contain sensory stimuli, e.g., natural sounds, images, odors or vibrations, which are highly dynamic in time, competing with stimuli at other locations in space. PV neurons are thought to play a fundamental role in sculpting cortical temporal dynamics; yet their specific role in encoding complex scenes via timing-based codes, and the robustness of such temporal representations to spatial competition, have not been investigated. Here, we address these questions in auditory cortex using a cocktail party-like paradigm; integrating electrophysiology, optogenetic manipulations, and a family of novel spike-distance metrics, to dissect the contributions of PV neurons towards rate and timing-based coding. We find that PV neurons improve cortical discrimination of dynamic naturalistic sounds in a cocktail party-like setting by enhancing rapid temporal modulations in rate and spike timing reproducibility. Moreover, this temporal representation is maintained in the face of competing stimuli at other spatial locations, providing a robust code for complex scene analysis. These findings provide novel insights into the specific contributions of PV neurons in cortical coding of complex scenes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.11.459906" rel="alternate" title="PV neurons improve cortical complex scene analysis by enhancing timing-based coding (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458926</id><title>Supervised Phenotype Discovery fromMultimodal Brain Imaging (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.152970+00:00</updated><author><name>Weikang Gong</name></author><author><name>Song Bai</name></author><author><name>Ying-Qiu Zheng</name></author><author><name>Stephen M. Smith</name></author><author><name>Christian F. Beckmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Data-driven discovery of image-derived phenotypes (IDPs) from large-scale multimodal brain imaging data has enormous potential for neuroscientific and clinical research by linking IDPs to subjects’ demographic, behavioural, clinical and cognitive measures (i.e., non-imaging derived phenotypes or nIDPs). However, current approaches are primarily based on unsupervised approaches, without use of information in nIDPs. In this paper, we proposed Supervised BigFLICA (SuperBigFLICA), a semi-supervised, multimodal, and multi-task fusion approach for IDP discovery, which simultaneously integrates information from multiple imaging modalities as well as multiple nIDPs. SuperBigFLICA is computationally efficient and largely bypasses the need for parameter tuning. Using the UK Biobank brain imaging dataset with around 40,000 subjects and 47 modalities, along with more than 17,000 nIDPs, we showed that SuperBigFLICA enhances the prediction power of nIDPs, bench-marked against IDPs derived by conventional expert-knowledge and unsupervised-learning approaches (with average nIDP prediction accuracy improvements of up to 46%). It also enables learning of generic imaging features that can predict new nIDPs. Further empirical analysis of the SuperBigFLICA algorithm demonstrates its robustness in different prediction tasks and the ability to derive biologically meaningful IDPs in predicting health outcomes and cognitive nIDPs, such as fluid intelligence and hypertension scores.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458926" rel="alternate" title="Supervised Phenotype Discovery fromMultimodal Brain Imaging (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459532</id><title>The Temporal Pattern of Spiking Activity of a Thalamic Neuron are Related to the Amplitude of the Cortical Local Field Potential (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.153152+00:00</updated><author><name>Hiroshi Tamura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuron activity in the sensory cortices mainly depends on feedforward thalamic inputs. High-frequency activity of a thalamic input can be temporally integrated by a neuron in the sensory cortex and is likely to induce larger depolarization. However, feedforward inhibition (FFI) and depression of excitatory synaptic transmission in thalamocortical pathways attenuate depolarization induced by the latter part of high-frequency spiking activity and the temporal summation may not be effective. The spiking activity of a thalamic neuron in a specific temporal pattern may circumvent FFI and depression of excitatory synapses. The present study determined the relationship between the temporal pattern of spiking activity of a single thalamic neuron and the degree of cortical activation as well as that between the firing rate of spiking activity of a single thalamic neuron and the degree of cortical activation. Spiking activity of a thalamic neuron was recorded extracellularly from the lateral geniculate nucleus (LGN) in male Long-Evans rats. Degree of cortical activation was assessed by simultaneous recording of local field potential (LFP) from the visual cortex. A specific temporal pattern appearing in three consecutive spikes of an LGN neuron induced larger cortical LFP modulation than high-frequency spiking activity during a short period. These findings indicate that spiking activity of thalamic inputs is integrated by a synaptic mechanism sensitive to an input temporal pattern.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.459532" rel="alternate" title="The Temporal Pattern of Spiking Activity of a Thalamic Neuron are Related to the Amplitude of the Cortical Local Field Potential (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459856</id><title>Deficits in decision-making induced by parietal cortex inactivation are compensated at two time scales (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.153298+00:00</updated><author><name>Danique Jeurissen</name></author><author><name>S Shushruth</name></author><author><name>Yasmine El-Shamayleh</name></author><author><name>Gregory D Horwitz</name></author><author><name>Michael N Shadlen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perceptual decisions arise through the transformation of samples of evidence into a commitment to a proposition or plan of action. Such transformation is thought to involve cortical circuits capable of computation over time scales associated with working memory, attention, and planning. Neurons in the lateral intraparietal area (LIP) are thought to play a role in all of these functions, and much of what is known about the neurobiology of decision making has been influenced by studies of LIP and its network of cortical and subcortical connections. However a causal role of neurons in LIP remains controversial. We used pharmacological and chemogenetic methods to inactivate LIP in one hemisphere of four rhesus monkeys. Inactivation produced clear biases in decisions, but the effects dissipated despite the persistence  of neural inactivation, implying compensation by other unaffected areas. Compensation occurs on a rapid times scale, within an experimental session, and more gradually, across sessions. The findings resolve disparate studies and inform interpretation of focal perturbations of brain function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459856" rel="alternate" title="Deficits in decision-making induced by parietal cortex inactivation are compensated at two time scales (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459569</id><title>Spontaneous alpha-band oscillations bias subjective contrast perception (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.153488+00:00</updated><author><name>Elio Balestrieri</name></author><author><name>Niko A. Busch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perceptual decisions depend both on the features of the incoming stimulus and on the ongoing brain activity at the moment the stimulus is received. Specifically, trial-to-trial fluctuations in cortical excitability have been linked to fluctuations in the amplitude of pre-stimulus alpha oscillations (~8-13 Hz), which are in turn are associated with fluctuations in subjects' tendency to report the detection of a stimulus. It is currently unknown whether alpha oscillations bias post-perceptual decision making, or even bias subjective perception itself. To answer this question, we used a contrast discrimination task in which subjects reported which of two gratings -- one in each hemifield -- was perceived as having a stronger contrast. Our EEG analysis showed that subjective contrast was reduced for the stimulus in the hemifield represented in the hemisphere with relatively stronger pre-stimulus alpha amplitude, reflecting reduced cortical excitability. Furthermore, the strength of this spontaneous hemispheric lateralization was strongly correlated with the magnitude of individual subjects' biases, suggesting that the spontaneous patterns of alpha lateralization play a role in explaining the inter-subject variability in contrast perception. These results indicate that spontaneous fluctuations in cortical excitability, indicted by patterns of pre-stimulus alpha amplitude, affect perceptual decisions by altering the phenomenological perception of the visual world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459569" rel="alternate" title="Spontaneous alpha-band oscillations bias subjective contrast perception (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>