<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.218527+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465012</id><title>Hippocampal spatio-temporal cognitive maps adaptively guide reward generalization (96 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.218986+00:00</updated><author><name>Mona M Garvert</name></author><author><name>Tankred Saanum</name></author><author><name>Eric Schulz</name></author><author><name>Nicolas W Schuck</name></author><author><name>Christian F. Doeller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain forms cognitive maps of relational knowledge, an organizing principle thought to underlie our ability to generalize and make inferences. However, how can a relevant map be selected in situations where a stimulus is embedded in multiple relational structures? Here, we find that both spatial and temporal cognitive maps influence generalization in a choice task, where spatial location determines reward magnitude. Mirroring behavior, the hippocampus not only builds a map of spatial relationships but also encodes temporal distances. As the task progresses, participants' choices become more influenced by spatial relationships, reflected in a strengthening of the spatial and a weakening of the temporal map. This change is driven by orbitofrontal cortex, which represents the evidence that an observed outcome is generated from the spatial rather than the temporal map and updates hippocampal representations accordingly. Taken together, this demonstrates how hippocampal cognitive maps are used and updated flexibly for inference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465012" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal spatio-temporal cognitive maps adaptively guide reward generalization (96 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465374</id><title>Neural knowledge assembly in humans and deep networks (41 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.219379+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephanie M Nelli</name></author><author><name>Lukas Braun</name></author><author><name>Tsvetomira Dumbalska</name></author><author><name>Andrew Saxe</name></author><author><name>Christopher Summerfield</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human understanding of the world can change rapidly when new information comes to light, such as when a plot twist occurs in a work of fiction. This flexible knowledge assembly requires few-shot reorganisation of neural codes for relations among objects and events. However, existing computational theories are largely silent about how this could occur. Here, participants learned a transitive ordering among novel objects within two distinct contexts, before exposure to new knowledge revealing how the contexts were linked. BOLD signals in dorsal frontoparietal cortical areas revealed that objects were rapidly and dramatically rearranged on the neural manifold after minimal exposure to the linking information. We then adapt stochastic online gradient descent to permit similar rapid knowledge assembly in a neural network model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465374" rel="alternate" title="Neural knowledge assembly in humans and deep networks (41 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465514</id><title>E-Cannula reveals anatomical diversity in sharp-wave ripples as a driver for the recruitment of distinct hippocampal assemblies (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.219705+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Liu</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Terada</name></author><author><name>Jeonghoon Kim</name></author><author><name>Yichen Lu</name></author><author><name>Mehrdad Ramezani</name></author><author><name>Andres D Grosmark</name></author><author><name>Attila Losonczy</name></author><author><name>Duygu Kuzum</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hippocampus plays a critical role in spatial navigation and episodic memory. However, research on in vivo hippocampal activity dynamics has mostly relied on single modalities such as electrical recordings or optical imaging, with respectively limited spatial and temporal resolution. This technical difficulty greatly impedes multi-level investigations into network state-related changes in cellular activity. To overcome these limitations, we developed the E-Cannula integrating fully transparent graphene microelectrodes with imaging-cannula. The E-Cannula enables the simultaneous electrical recording and two-photon calcium imaging from the exact same population of neurons across an anatomically extended region of the mouse hippocampal CA1 stably across several days. These large-scale simultaneous optical and electrical recordings showed that local hippocampal sharp wave ripples (SWRs) are associated with synchronous calcium events involving large neural populations in CA1. We show that SWRs exhibit spatiotemporal wave patterns along multiple axes in 2D space with different spatial extents (local or global) and temporal propagation modes (stationary or travelling). Notably, distinct SWR wave patterns were associated with, and decoded from, the selective recruitment of orthogonal CA1 cell assemblies. These results suggest that the diversity in the anatomical progression of SWRs may serve as a mechanism for the selective activation of the unique hippocampal cell assemblies extensively implicated in the encoding of distinct memories. Through these results we demonstrate the utility of the E-Cannula as a versatile neurotechnology with the potential for future integration with other optical components such as green lenses, fibers or prisms enabling the multi-modal investigation of cross-time scale population-level neural dynamics across brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465514" rel="alternate" title="E-Cannula reveals anatomical diversity in sharp-wave ripples as a driver for the recruitment of distinct hippocampal assemblies (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.464802</id><title>Microglia remodel the synaptic signaling required for context-dependent cognitive performance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.220097+00:00</updated><author><name>Renato Socodato</name></author><author><name>Tiago O. Almeida</name></author><author><name>Camila C. Portugal</name></author><author><name>Evelyn C. S. Santos</name></author><author><name>Joana Tedim-Moreira</name></author><author><name>Teresa Canedo</name></author><author><name>Filipa I. Baptista</name></author><author><name>Ana Magalhães</name></author><author><name>António F. Ambrósio</name></author><author><name>Cord Brakebusch</name></author><author><name>Boris Rubinstein</name></author><author><name>Irina Moreira</name></author><author><name>Teresa Summavielle</name></author><author><name>Inês Mendes Pinto</name></author><author><name>João B. Relvas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia modulate synaptic activity, essential for context-dependent cognitive performance, allowing organism-level adaptations to different environmental scenarios. Yet, the microglial molecular drivers required for synaptic remodeling related to cognitive performance remain largely elusive. Here, combining conditional gene targeting, single-cell live imaging, RNA-seq, high-throughput proteomics, systems biology, and animal behavior, we mapped a molecular nexus between microglia and synapses that instructs cognitive performance. Specifically, we found that microglia use the RhoGTPase Rac1 as a relay switch to sense the brain microenvironment and drive synaptic remodeling required for experience-dependent sociability and learning related to memory. Targeting this microglial relay modifies context-dependent cognitive performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.18.464802" rel="alternate" title="Microglia remodel the synaptic signaling required for context-dependent cognitive performance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465238</id><title>Automated and parallelized spike collision tests to identify spike signal projections (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.220577+00:00</updated><author><name>Keita Mitani</name></author><author><name>Masanori Kawabata</name></author><author><name>Yoshikazu Isomura</name></author><author><name>Yutaka Sakai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spike collision test is a highly reliable technique to identify axonal projection of a neuron recorded electrophysiologically for investigating functional spike information among brain areas. It is potentially applicable to more neuronal projections by combining multi-channel recording with optogenetic stimulation. Yet, it remains inefficient and laborious because an experimenter must visually select spikes in every channel and manually repeat spike collision tests for each neuron serially. Here, we established a novel technique to automatically perform spike collision tests for all channels in parallel (Multi-Linc analysis), employing two distinct protocols implemented in a multi-channel real-time processing system. The rat cortical neurons identified with this technique displayed physiological spike features consistent with excitatory projection neurons. Their antidromic spikes were similar in shape but slightly larger in amplitude compared with spontaneous spikes. In addition, we demonstrated simultaneous identification of reciprocal or bifurcating projections among cortical areas. Thus, our Multi-Linc analysis will be a powerful research approach to elucidate interareal spike communication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465238" rel="alternate" title="Automated and parallelized spike collision tests to identify spike signal projections (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>