<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.377288+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461872</id><title>KLC4 shapes axon arbors during development and mediates adult behavior (118 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.378747+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth M. Haynes</name></author><author><name>Jiaye “Henry” He</name></author><author><name>Marcel Jean-Pierre</name></author><author><name>Kevin W. Eliceiri</name></author><author><name>Jan Huisken</name></author><author><name>Mary C. Halloran</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Development of elaborate and polarized neuronal morphology requires precisely regulated transport of cellular cargos by motor proteins such as kinesin-1. Kinesin-1 has numerous cellular cargos which must be delivered to unique neuronal compartments. The process by which this motor selectively transports and delivers cargo to regulate neuronal morphogenesis is poorly understood. Our work implicates one kinesin light chain subunit, KLC4, as an essential regulator of axon branching and arborization pattern of sensory neurons during development. Using several live imaging approaches in &lt;italic&gt;klc4&lt;/italic&gt; mutant zebrafish, we show that KLC4 is required for stabilization of nascent axon branches and for proper microtubule (MT) dynamics. Furthermore, KLC4 is required for the contact repulsion necessary for tiling of peripheral axon arbors: in &lt;italic&gt;klc4&lt;/italic&gt; mutants, peripheral axons showed abnormal fasciculation, a behavior characteristic of central axons, suggesting that KLC4 patterns axonal compartments and helps define axon identity. Finally, we find that &lt;italic&gt;klc4&lt;/italic&gt; mutant adults show anxiety-like behavior in a novel tank test, implicating &lt;italic&gt;klc4&lt;/italic&gt; as a novel gene involved in stress response circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461872" rel="alternate" title="KLC4 shapes axon arbors during development and mediates adult behavior (118 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462148</id><title>Adeno-associated virus (AAV) reduces cortical dendritic complexity in a TLR9-dependent manner (106 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.396473+00:00</updated><author><name>Christos M. Suriano</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Verpeut</name></author><author><name>Neerav Kumar</name></author><author><name>Jie Ma</name></author><author><name>Caroline Jung</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Boulanger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recombinant adeno-associated viruses (AAVs) allow rapid and efficient gene delivery in the nervous system. AAVs are widely used in research and are the basis of multiple FDA-approved gene therapies. Here, we find that the immune response to AAV’s genome reduces dendritic complexity in mammalian cortex. Dendritic loss associated with AAV-mediated gene delivery occurs at experimentally-relevant titers, cannot be explained by responses to transgene expression or surgery, and is not restricted to a particular capsid serotype, encoded transgene, promoter, or production facility. AAV-associated dendritic loss is accompanied by a decrease in the frequency and amplitude of miniature excitatory postsynaptic currents (mEPSCs) and upregulation of immune molecules that can limit dendritic complexity and synaptic transmission. Blocking detection of unmethylated CpG-rich DNA via Toll-like receptor 9 (TLR9) protects dendritic complexity, suggesting that immunodetection of a core feature of the AAV genome triggers dendritic loss. These results reveal previously unsuspected impacts of AAV on neuronal structure and function and identify TLR9 inhibitors as important tools to improve the safety and efficacy of AAV-mediated gene delivery in the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462148" rel="alternate" title="Adeno-associated virus (AAV) reduces cortical dendritic complexity in a TLR9-dependent manner (106 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461548</id><title>A rise-to-threshold signal for a relative value deliberation (69 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.397593+00:00</updated><author><name>Vikram Vijayan</name></author><author><name>Fei Wang</name></author><author><name>Kaiyu Wang</name></author><author><name>Arun Chakravorty</name></author><author><name>Atsuko Adachi</name></author><author><name>Hessameddin Akhlaghpour</name></author><author><name>Barry J. Dickson</name></author><author><name>Gaby Maimon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whereas progress has been made in identifying neural signals related to rapid, cued decisions&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;, less is known about how brains guide and terminate more ethologically relevant deliberations, where an animal’s own behavior governs the options experienced over minutes&lt;sup&gt;5–8&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; search for many seconds to minutes for egg-laying sites with high relative value&lt;sup&gt;9, 10&lt;/sup&gt; and neurons, called &lt;italic&gt;oviDNs&lt;/italic&gt;, exist whose activity fulfills necessity and sufficiency criteria for initiating the egg-deposition motor program&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we show that oviDNs express a calcium signal that rises over seconds to minutes as a fly deliberates whether to lay an egg. The calcium signal dips when an egg is internally prepared (ovulated), rises at a rate related to the relative value of the current substrate being experienced, and reaches a consistent peak just prior to the abdomen bend for egg deposition. We provide perturbational evidence that the egg-deposition motor program is initiated once this signal hits a threshold and that sub-threshold variation in the signal regulates the time spent deliberating and, ultimately, the option chosen. These results argue that a rise-to-threshold signal guides &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; to lay eggs on substrate options with high relative value, with each egg-laying event representing a self-paced decision similar to real-world decisions made by humans and other mammals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461548" rel="alternate" title="A rise-to-threshold signal for a relative value deliberation (69 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461717</id><title>Topological insights into the neural basis of flexible behavior (69 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.398070+00:00</updated><author><name>Tevin C. Rouse</name></author><author><name>Amy M. Ni</name></author><author><name>Chengcheng Huang</name></author><author><name>Marlene R. Cohen</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that there is an inextricable link between neural computations, biological mechanisms, and behavior, but there exists no framework that can simultaneously explain all three. Here, we show that topological data analysis (TDA) provides that necessary bridge. We demonstrate that cognitive processes change the topological description of the shared activity of populations of visual neurons. These topological changes provide uniquely strong constraints on a mechanistic model, explain behavior, and, via a link with network control theory, reveal a tradeoff between improving sensitivity to subtle visual stimulus changes and increasing the chance that the subject will stray off task. These discoveries provide a blueprint for using TDA to uncover the biological and computational mechanisms by which cognition affects behavior in health and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461717" rel="alternate" title="Topological insights into the neural basis of flexible behavior (69 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461354</id><title>Leveling up: improving power in fMRI by moving beyond cluster-level inference (54 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.398730+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephanie Noble</name></author><author><name>Amanda F. Mejia</name></author><author><name>Andrew Zalesky</name></author><author><name>Dustin Scheinost</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inference in neuroimaging commonly occurs at the level of “clusters” of neighboring voxels or connections, thought to reflect functionally specific brain areas. Yet increasingly large studies reveal effects that are shared throughout the brain, suggesting that reported clusters may only reflect the “tip of the iceberg” of underlying effects. Here, we empirically compare power of traditional levels of inference (edge and cluster) with broader levels of inference (network and whole-brain) by resampling functional connectivity data from the Human Connectome Project (n=40, 80, 120). Only network- and whole brain-level inference attained or surpassed “adequate” power (&lt;italic&gt;β&lt;/italic&gt;=80%) to detect an average effect, with almost double the power for network-compared with cluster-level procedures at more typical sample sizes. Likewise, effects tended to be widespread, and more widespread pooling resulted in stronger magnitude effects. Power also substantially increased when controlling FDR rather than FWER. Importantly, there may be similar implications for task-based activation analyses where effects are also increasingly understood to be widespread. However, increased power with broader levels of inference may diminish the specificity to localize effects, especially for non-task contexts. These findings underscore the benefit of shifting the scale of inference to better capture the underlying signal, which may unlock opportunities for discovery in human neuroimaging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461354" rel="alternate" title="Leveling up: improving power in fMRI by moving beyond cluster-level inference (54 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461209</id><title>The influence of objecthood on the representation of natural images in the visual cortex (51 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.399260+00:00</updated><author><name>Paolo Papale</name></author><author><name>Wietske Zuiderbaan</name></author><author><name>Rob R.M. Teeuwen</name></author><author><name>Amparo Gilhuis</name></author><author><name>Matthew W. Self</name></author><author><name>Pieter R. Roelfsema</name></author><author><name>Serge O. Dumoulin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurons in early visual cortex are not only sensitive to the image elements in their receptive field but also to the context determining whether the elements are part of an object or background. We here assessed the effect of objecthood in natural images on neuronal activity in early visual cortex, with fMRI in humans and electrophysiology in monkeys. We report that boundaries and interiors of objects elicit more activity than the background. Boundary effects occur remarkably early, implying that visual cortical neurons are tuned to features characterizing object boundaries in natural images. When a new image is presented the influence of the object interiors on neuronal activity occurs during a late phase of neuronal response and earlier when eye movements shift the image representation, implying that object representations are remapped across eye-movements. Our results reveal how object perception shapes the representation of natural images in early visual cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461209" rel="alternate" title="The influence of objecthood on the representation of natural images in the visual cortex (51 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461002</id><title>Fluctuations in Neural Complexity During Wakefulness Relate To Conscious Level and Cognition (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.399622+00:00</updated><author><name>Pedro A.M. Mediano</name></author><author><name>Aleksi Ikkala</name></author><author><name>Rogier A. Kievit</name></author><author><name>Sridhar R. Jagannathan</name></author><author><name>Thomas F. Varley</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel A. Stamatakis</name></author><author><name>Tristan A. Bekinschtein</name></author><author><name>Daniel Bor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There has been considerable recent progress in measuring conscious level using neural complexity measures. For instance, such measures can reliably distinguish healthy awake from asleep subjects and vegetative state patients. However, this line of research has never explored the dynamics of conscious level during normal wakefulness. Being able to capture meaningful differences in conscious level during wakefulness may provide a vital new insight into the nature of consciousness, by demonstrating what biological, behavioural and cognitive factors relate to such differences. Here we take advantage of a large MEG and fMRI dataset of healthy adults, to examine within-subject conscious level fluctuations during resting state and tasks, by using a range of complexity measures. We first establish the validity of this approach in both neuroimaging domains by relating neural complexity measures to pre-existing techniques for capturing transitions of consciousness from full wakefulness into drowsiness and the earliest stages of sleep, finding decreased complexity as participants become increasingly drowsy. We further demonstrate that neural complexity measures in both MEG and fMRI change both within and between tasks, and relate to performance on an executive task, with higher complexity associated with better performance and faster reaction times. This approach provides a powerful new route to further explore the cognitive and neural underpinnings of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461002" rel="alternate" title="Fluctuations in Neural Complexity During Wakefulness Relate To Conscious Level and Cognition (45 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461751</id><title>Endotaxis: A Universal Algorithm for Mapping, Goal-Learning, and Navigation (43 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.399923+00:00</updated><author><name>Tony Zhang</name></author><author><name>Matthew Rosenberg</name></author><author><name>Pietro Perona</name></author><author><name>Markus Meister</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;An animal entering a new environment typically faces three challenges: explore the space for resources, memorize their locations, and navigate towards those targets as needed. Experimental work on exploration, mapping, and navigation has mostly focused on simple environments – such as an open arena, a pond [1], or a desert [2] – and much has been learned about neural signals in diverse brain areas under these conditions [3, 4]. However, many natural environments are highly constrained, such as a system of burrows, or of paths through the underbrush. More generally, many cognitive tasks are equally constrained, allowing only a small set of actions at any given stage in the process. Here we propose an algorithm that learns the structure of an arbitrary environment, discovers useful targets during exploration, and navigates back to those targets by the shortest path. It makes use of a behavioral module common to all motile animals, namely the ability to follow an odor to its source [5]. We show how the brain can learn to generate internal “virtual odors” that guide the animal to any location of interest. This &lt;italic&gt;endotaxis&lt;/italic&gt; algorithm can be implemented with a simple 3-layer neural circuit using only biologically realistic structures and learning rules. Several neural components of this scheme are found in brains from insects to humans. Nature may have evolved a general mechanism for search and navigation on the ancient backbone of chemotaxis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461751" rel="alternate" title="Endotaxis: A Universal Algorithm for Mapping, Goal-Learning, and Navigation (43 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461232</id><title>Neural signatures of compression in the retelling of past events (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.400313+00:00</updated><author><name>Elizabeth Musz</name></author><author><name>Janice Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When we retell our past experiences, we aim to reproduce some version of the original events; this reproduced version is often temporally compressed relative to the original. How does such compression of memories manifest in brain activity? One possibility is that a compressed retrieved memory manifests as a neural pattern which is more dissimilar to the original, relative to a more detailed or vivid memory. However, we argue that measuring raw dissimilarity alone is insufficient, as it confuses a variety of interesting and uninteresting changes. To address this problem, we examine brain pattern changes that are consistent across people. We show that temporal compression in individuals’ retelling of past events predicts systematic encoding-to-recall transformations in a number of higher associative regions. These findings elucidate how neural representations are not simply reactivated, but can also be transformed due to temporal compression during a universal form of human memory expression: verbal retelling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461232" rel="alternate" title="Neural signatures of compression in the retelling of past events (38 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462008</id><title>Convergent coding of recent and remote fear memory in the basolateral amygdala (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.402571+00:00</updated><author><name>Jianfeng Liu</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Totty</name></author><author><name>Laila Melissari</name></author><author><name>Stephen Maren</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animals must learn to anticipate recently encountered threats as well as dangers experienced long ago. In both rodents and humans, the basolateral amygdala (BLA) is essential for the encoding and retrieval conditioned fear memories. Although the BLA is a putative storage site for aversive memory, recent evidence suggests that these memories undergo time-dependent reorganization and no longer require the BLA after the passage of time. To explore this question, we systematically examined the role for the BLA in recent and remote fear memory using optogenetic, electrophysiological, and calcium imaging methods in male and female Long-Evans rats. Critically, we used a behavioral design that permits within-subjects comparison of recent and remote memory at the same time point. We found that BLA c-Fos expression was similar after the retrieval of recent (1 day) or remote (2 weeks) fear memories. Extracellular recordings in awake, behaving animals revealed that the majority of BLA neurons encoded both recent and remote memories, suggesting substantial overlap in the allocation of temporally distinct events. Fiber photometric recordings of BLA principal neurons also revealed similar patterns of CS-evoked activity to recent and remote CSs. Consistent with these results, continuous or CS-specific optogenetic inhibition of BLA principal neurons impaired conditioned freezing to both recent and remote CSs. Collectively, these data reveal that single BLA neurons encode both recent and remote fear memories. This may underlie the broad generalization of fear memories across both space and time. Ultimately, these results provide robust evidence that the BLA is a long-term storage site for emotional memories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462008" rel="alternate" title="Convergent coding of recent and remote fear memory in the basolateral amygdala (35 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461722</id><title>Regulation of membrane homeostasis by TMC1 mechanoelectrical transduction channels is essential for hearing (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.402897+00:00</updated><author><name>Angela Ballesteros</name></author><author><name>Kenton J. Swartz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mechanoelectrical transduction (MET) channel complex of auditory hair cells converts sound into electrical signals, allowing us to hear. After decades of research, the transmembrane-like channel 1 and 2 (TMC1 and TMC2) have been recently identified as pore-forming subunits of the MET channels, but the molecular peculiarity that differentiates these two proteins and makes TMC1 essential for hearing remains elusive. Here, we show that TMC1, but not TMC2, is essential for membrane remodeling triggered by a decrease in intracellular calcium concentration. We demonstrate that inhibition of MET channels or buffering of intracellular calcium lead to pronounced phosphatidylserine externalization, membrane blebbing and ectosome release at the hair cell sensory organelle, culminating in the loss of TMC1 protein. Moreover, three TMC1 deafness-causing mutations cause constitutive phosphatidylserine externalization that correlates with the deafness phenotype, suggesting that the mechanisms of hearing loss involve alterations in membrane homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461722" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of membrane homeostasis by TMC1 mechanoelectrical transduction channels is essential for hearing (33 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461152</id><title>Distinct ground state and activated state modes of firing in forebrain neurons (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.403122+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Levenstein</name></author><author><name>Gabrielle Girardeau</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Gornet</name></author><author><name>Andres Grosmark</name></author><author><name>Roman Huszár</name></author><author><name>Adrien Peyrache</name></author><author><name>Yuta Senzai</name></author><author><name>Brendon Watson</name></author><author><name>John Rinzel</name></author><author><name>György Buzsáki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuronal firing patterns have significant spatiotemporal variety with no agreed upon theoretical framework. Using a combined experimental and modeling approach, we found that spike interval statistics can be described by discrete modes of activity. A “ground state” (GS) mode of low-rate spiking is universal among forebrain excitatory neurons and characterized by irregular spiking at a cell-specific rate. In contrast, “activated state” (AS) modes consist of spiking at characteristic timescales and regularity and are specific to neurons in a given region and brain state. We find that the majority of spiking is contributed by GS mode, while neurons can transiently switch to AS spiking in response to stimuli or in coordination with population activity patterns. We hypothesize that GS spiking serves to maintain a persistent backbone of neuronal activity while AS modes support communication functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461152" rel="alternate" title="Distinct ground state and activated state modes of firing in forebrain neurons (32 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461591</id><title>Satellite glia are essential modulators of sympathetic neuron survival, activity, and autonomic function (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.403422+00:00</updated><author><name>Aurelia A. Mapps</name></author><author><name>Erica Boehm</name></author><author><name>Corrine Beier</name></author><author><name>William T. Keenan</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Langel</name></author><author><name>Michael Liu</name></author><author><name>Samer Hattar</name></author><author><name>Haiqing Zhao</name></author><author><name>Emmanouil Tampakakis</name></author><author><name>Rejji Kuruvilla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Satellite glia are the major glial cells in sympathetic ganglia, enveloping neuronal cell bodies. Despite this intimate association, how satellite glia contribute to sympathetic functions remain unclear. Here, we show that satellite glia are critical for metabolism, survival, and activity of sympathetic neurons and modulate autonomic behaviors in mice. Adult ablation of satellite glia results in impaired mTOR signaling, soma atrophy, reduced noradrenergic enzymes, and loss of sympathetic neurons. However, persisting neurons have elevated activity, and satellite glia-ablated mice show increased pupil dilation and heart rate, indicative of enhanced sympathetic tone. Satellite glia-specific deletion of Kir4.1, an inward-rectifying potassium channel, largely recapitulates the cellular defects observed in glia-ablated mice, suggesting that satellite glia act in part via extracellular K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; buffering. These findings highlight neuron-satellite glia as functional units in regulating sympathetic output, with implications for disorders linked to sympathetic hyper-activity such as cardiovascular disease and hypertension.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461591" rel="alternate" title="Satellite glia are essential modulators of sympathetic neuron survival, activity, and autonomic function (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461599</id><title>Pyramidal cell types drive functionally distinct cortical activity patterns during decision-making (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.405842+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Musall</name></author><author><name>Xiaonan R. Sun</name></author><author><name>Hemanth Mohan</name></author><author><name>Xu An</name></author><author><name>Steven Gluf</name></author><author><name>Anne K. Churchland</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To understand how cortical circuits generate complex behavior, it is crucial to investigate the cell types that comprise them. Functional differences across pyramidal neuron (PyN) types have been observed in sensory and frontal cortex, but it is not known whether these differences are the rule across all cortical areas or if different PyN types mostly follow the same cortex-wide dynamics. We used genetic and retrograde labeling to target pyramidal tract (PT), intratelencephalic (IT) and corticostriatal projection neurons and measured their cortex-wide activity. Each PyN type drove unique neural dynamics at a cortex-wide and within-area scale. Cortical activity and optogenetic inactivation during an auditory discrimination task also revealed distinct functional roles: all PyNs in parietal cortex were recruited during sensory stimulation but, surprisingly, PT neurons were most important for perception. In frontal cortex, all PyNs were required for accurate choices but showed distinct choice-tuning. Our results reveal that rich, cell-type-specific cortical dynamics shape perceptual decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461599" rel="alternate" title="Pyramidal cell types drive functionally distinct cortical activity patterns during decision-making (27 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461138</id><title>Emotion Down- and Up-Regulation Act on Spatially Distinct Brain Areas: Interoceptive Regions to Calm Down and Other Affective Regions to Amp Up (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.406362+00:00</updated><author><name>Jungwon Min</name></author><author><name>Kaoru Nashiro</name></author><author><name>Hyun Joo Yoo</name></author><author><name>Christine Cho</name></author><author><name>Padideh Nasseri</name></author><author><name>Shelby L. Bachman</name></author><author><name>Shai Porat</name></author><author><name>Julian F. Thayer</name></author><author><name>Catie Chang</name></author><author><name>Tae-ho Lee</name></author><author><name>Mara Mather</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prior studies on emotion regulation identified a set of brain regions specialized for generating and controlling affect. Researchers generally agree that when up- and down-regulating emotion, control regions in the prefrontal cortex turn up or down activity in affect-generating areas. However, the assumption that turning up and down emotions produces opposite effects in the same affect-generating regions is untested. We call this assumption the ‘affective dial hypothesis.’ Our study tested this hypothesis by examining the overlap between the sets of regions activated during up-regulation and those deactivated during down-regulation in a large number of participants (N=105). We found that up- and down-regulation both recruit regulatory regions such as the inferior frontal gyrus and dorsal anterior cingulate gyrus but act on distinct affect-generating regions. While up-regulation increases BOLD signal in regions associated with emotion such as the amygdala, anterior insula, striatum and anterior cingulate gyrus as well as in regions associated with sympathetic vascular activity such as periventricular white matter, down-regulation decreases signal in regions receiving interoceptive input such as the posterior insula and postcentral gyrus. These findings indicate that up- and down-regulation do not generally exert opposing effects on the same affect-generating regions. Instead, they target different brain circuits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many contexts require modulating one’s own emotions. Identifying the brain areas implementing these regulatory processes should advance understanding emotional disorders and designing potential interventions. The emotion regulation field has an implicit assumption we call the affective dial hypothesis: that both emotion up- and down-regulation modulate the same emotion-generating brain areas. Countering the hypothesis, our findings indicate that up- and down-modulating emotions target different brain areas. Thus, the mechanisms underlying emotion regulation differ more than previously appreciated for up- versus down-regulation. In addition to their theoretical importance, these findings are critical for researchers attempting to target activity in particular brain regions during an emotion regulation intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461138" rel="alternate" title="Emotion Down- and Up-Regulation Act on Spatially Distinct Brain Areas: Interoceptive Regions to Calm Down and Other Affective Regions to Amp Up (25 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461804</id><title>Flygenvectors: The spatial and temporal structure of neural activity across the fly brain (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.406716+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan S. Schaffer</name></author><author><name>Neeli Mishra</name></author><author><name>Matthew R. Whiteway</name></author><author><name>Wenze Li</name></author><author><name>Michelle B. Vancura</name></author><author><name>Jason Freedman</name></author><author><name>Kripa B. Patel</name></author><author><name>Venkatakaushik Voleti</name></author><author><name>Liam Paninski</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth M.C. Hillman</name></author><author><name>L.F. Abbott</name></author><author><name>Richard Axel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;What are the spatial and temporal scales of brainwide neuronal activity, and how do activities at different scales interact? We used SCAPE microscopy to image a large fraction of the central brain of adult &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; with high spatiotemporal resolution while flies engaged in a variety of behaviors, including running, grooming and flailing. This revealed neural representations of behavior on multiple spatial and temporal scales. The activity of most neurons across the brain correlated (or, in some cases, anticorrelated) with running and flailing over timescales that ranged from seconds to almost a minute. Grooming elicited a much weaker global response. Although these behaviors accounted for a large fraction of neural activity, residual activity not directly correlated with behavior was high dimensional. Many dimensions of the residual activity reflect the activity of small clusters of spatially organized neurons that may correspond to genetically defined cell types. These clusters participate in the global dynamics, indicating that neural activity reflects a combination of local and broadly distributed components. This suggests that microcircuits with highly specified functions are provided with knowledge of the larger context in which they operate, conferring a useful balance of specificity and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461804" rel="alternate" title="Flygenvectors: The spatial and temporal structure of neural activity across the fly brain (24 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462005</id><title>Feature-reweighted RSA: A method for improving the fit between computational models, brains, and behavior (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.407363+00:00</updated><author><name>Philipp Kaniuth</name></author><author><name>Martin N. Hebart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Representational Similarity Analysis (RSA) has emerged as a popular method for relating representational spaces from human brain activity, behavioral data, and computational models. RSA is based on the comparison of representational dissimilarity matrices (RDM), which characterize the pairwise dissimilarities of all conditions across all features (e.g. fMRI voxels or units of a model). However, classical RSA treats each feature as equally important. This ‘equal weights’ assumption contrasts with the flexibility of multivariate decoding, which reweights individual features for predicting a target variable. As a consequence, classical RSA may lead researchers to underestimate the correspondence between a model and a brain region and, for model comparison, it may lead to selecting the inferior model. While previous work has suggested that reweighting can improve model selection in RSA, it has remained unclear to what extent these results generalize across datasets and data modalities. To fill this gap, the aim of this work is twofold: First, utilizing a range of publicly available datasets and three popular deep neural networks (DNNs), we seek to broadly test feature-reweighted RSA (FR-RSA) applied to computational models and reveal the extent to which reweighting model features improves RDM correspondence and affects model selection. Second, we propose voxel-reweighted RSA, a novel use case of FR-RSA that reweights fMRI voxels, mirroring the rationale of multivariate decoding of optimally combining voxel activity patterns. We find that reweighting individual model units (1) markedly improves the fit between model RDMs and target RDMs derived from several fMRI and behavioral datasets and (2) affects model selection, highlighting the importance of considering FR-RSA. For voxel-reweighted RSA, improvements in RDM correspondence were even more pronounced, demonstrating the utility of this novel approach. We additionally demonstrate that classical noise ceilings can be exceeded when FR-RSA is applied and propose an updated approach for their computation. Taken together, our results broadly validate the use of FR-RSA for improving the fit between computational models, brain and behavioral data, possibly allowing us to better adjudicate between competing computational models. Further, our results suggest that FR-RSA applied to brain measurement channels could become an important new method to assess the match between representational spaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462005" rel="alternate" title="Feature-reweighted RSA: A method for improving the fit between computational models, brains, and behavior (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461551</id><title>Vertex-wise characterization of Non-Human Primate cortical development with prenatal insights (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.408093+00:00</updated><author><name>Julian S.B. Ramirez</name></author><author><name>Robert Hermosillo</name></author><author><name>Elina Thomas</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Y. Zhu</name></author><author><name>Darrick Sturgeon</name></author><author><name>Emma Schifsky</name></author><author><name>Anthony Galassi</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline R. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L. Bagley</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Milham</name></author><author><name>Oscar Miranda-Dominguez</name></author><author><name>Samantha Papadakis</name></author><author><name>Muhammed Bah</name></author><author><name>AJ Mitchell</name></author><author><name>Ting Xu</name></author><author><name>Alice M. Graham</name></author><author><name>Eric Feczko</name></author><author><name>Elinor L. Sullivan</name></author><author><name>Damien A. Fair</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Characterization of the interwoven complexities of early cortical thickness development has been an ongoing undertaking in neuroscience research. Longitudinal studies of Non-Human Primates (NHP) offer unique advantages to categorizing the diverse patterns of cortical growth trajectories. Here, we used latent growth models to characterize the trajectories of typical cortical thickness development in Japanese macaques at each cortical surface vertex (i.e. grayordinate). Cortical thickness from 4 to 36 months showed regional specific linear and non-linear trajectories and distinct maturation timing across the cortex. Intriguingly, we revealed a “accumulation/ablation phenomenon” of cortical maturation where the most profound development changes in cortical thickness occur in the accumulation or ablation zones surrounding the focal points (i.e., a center of a delineated regions where cortical thickness is thickest or thinnest) throughout the brain. We further examined maternal diet and inflammation in the context of these typical brain trajectories and known network architecture. A well-controlled NHP model of a maternal “Western-style” diet was used alongside measures of inflammatory cytokine interleukin-6 (IL-6) in the mothers during gestation. We observed that these accumulation and ablation zones of variable change might be most susceptible to environmental effects. The maternal factors, diet and inflammation during pregnancy were distinctively associated with different aspects of offspring cortical development reflected in regions related to distinctive functional networks. Our findings characterize the versatile intricacies of typical cortical thickness development and highlight how the maternal environment plays a role in offspring cortical development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461551" rel="alternate" title="Vertex-wise characterization of Non-Human Primate cortical development with prenatal insights (20 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461355</id><title>Identification of touch neurons underlying dopaminergic pleasurable touch and sexual receptivity (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.408608+00:00</updated><author><name>Leah Middleton</name></author><author><name>Melanie Schaffler</name></author><author><name>Isabella Succi</name></author><author><name>William Foster</name></author><author><name>Mark Gradwell</name></author><author><name>Manon Bohic</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Ejoh</name></author><author><name>Victoria Abraira</name></author><author><name>Ishmail Abdus-Saboor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pleasurable touch during social behavior is the key to building familial bonds and meaningful connections. One form of social touch occurs during sex. Although sexual behavior is initiated in part by touch, and touch is ongoing throughout copulation, the identity and role of sensory neurons that transduce sexual touch remain unknown. A population of sensory neurons labeled by the G-protein coupled receptor Mrgprb4 detect stroking touch in mice&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, we study the social relevance of this population by genetically engineering mice to allow activation or ablation of Mrgprb4-lineage neurons and reveal that these neurons are required for sexual receptivity and sufficient to activate reward circuitry. Even in social isolation, optogenetic stimulation of Mrgprb4-lineage neurons through the back skin is sufficient to induce a conditioned place preference and a striking dorsoflexion resembling the lordotic copulatory posture in females. In the absence of Mrgprb4-lineage neurons, female mice no longer find male mounts rewarding: sexual receptivity is supplanted by aggression and a coincident decline in dopaminergic release in the mesolimbic reward pathway. In addition to sexual behavior, Mrgprb4-lineage neurons are also required for social postures induced by female-to-female back touch. Together, these findings establish that Mrgprb4-lineage neurons are the first neurons of a skin-to-brain circuit encoding the rewarding quality of social touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461355" rel="alternate" title="Identification of touch neurons underlying dopaminergic pleasurable touch and sexual receptivity (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461425</id><title>State-dependent linearisation of mixture representations by the olfactory bulb (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.412122+00:00</updated><author><name>Aliya Mari Adefuin</name></author><author><name>Janine Kristin Reinert</name></author><author><name>Sander Lindeman</name></author><author><name>Izumi Fukunaga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sensory systems are often tasked to analyse complex signals from the environment, to separate relevant from irrelevant parts. This process of decomposing signals is challenging when component signals interfere with each other. For example, when a mixture of signals does not equal the sum of its parts, this leads to an unpredictable corruption of signal patterns, making the target recognition harder. In olfaction, nonlinear summation is prevalent at various stages of sensory processing, from stimulus transduction in the nasal epithelium to higher areas, including the olfactory bulb (OB) and the piriform cortex. Here, we investigate how the olfactory system deals with binary mixtures of odours, using two-photon imaging with several behavioural paradigms. Unlike previous studies using anaesthetised animals, we found the mixture summation to be substantially more linear when using awake, head-fixed mice performing an odour detection task. This linearisation was also observed in awake, untrained mice, in both engaged and disengaged states, revealing that the bulk of the difference in mixture summation is explained by the brain state. However, in the apical dendrites of M/T cells, mixture representation is dominated by sublinear summation. Altogether, our results demonstrate that the property of mixture representation in the primary olfactory area likely reflects state-dependent differences in sensory processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461425" rel="alternate" title="State-dependent linearisation of mixture representations by the olfactory bulb (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461430</id><title>Modulation of sensory perception by hydrogen peroxide enables Caenorhabditis elegans to find a niche that provides both food and protection from hydrogen peroxide (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.413530+00:00</updated><author><name>Jodie A. Schiffer</name></author><author><name>Stephanie V. Stumbur</name></author><author><name>Maedeh Seyedolmohadesin</name></author><author><name>Yuyan Xu</name></author><author><name>William T. Serkin</name></author><author><name>Natalie G McGowan</name></author><author><name>Oluwatosin Banjo</name></author><author><name>Mahdi Torkashvand</name></author><author><name>Albert Lin</name></author><author><name>Ciara N. Hosea</name></author><author><name>Adrien Assié</name></author><author><name>Buck S. Samuel</name></author><author><name>Michael P. O’Donnell</name></author><author><name>Vivek Venkatachalam</name></author><author><name>Javier Apfeld</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hydrogen peroxide (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) is the most common chemical threat that organisms face. Here, we show that H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; alters the bacterial food preference of &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt;, enabling the nematodes to find a safe environment with food. H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; induces the nematodes to leave food patches of laboratory and microbiome bacteria when those bacterial communities have insufficient H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-degrading capacity. The nematode’s behavior is directed by H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-sensing neurons that promote escape from H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and by bacteria-sensing neurons that promote attraction to bacteria. However, the input for H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-sensing neurons is removed by bacterial H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-degrading enzymes and the bacteria-sensing neurons’ perception of bacteria is prevented by H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. The resulting cross-attenuation provides a general mechanism that ensures the nematode’s behavior is faithful to the lethal threat of hydrogen peroxide, increasing the nematode’s chances of finding a niche that provides both food and protection from hydrogen peroxide.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461430" rel="alternate" title="Modulation of sensory perception by hydrogen peroxide enables Caenorhabditis elegans to find a niche that provides both food and protection from hydrogen peroxide (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461477</id><title>Self-Administration of entactogen psychostimulants dysregulates GABA and Kappa Opioid Receptor signaling in the central nucleus of the amygdala of female Wistar rats (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.415052+00:00</updated><author><name>Sophia Khom</name></author><author><name>Jacques D. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Sophia A. Vandewater</name></author><author><name>Yanabel Grant</name></author><author><name>Marisa Roberto</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Taffe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Male rats escalate intravenous self-administration of entactogen psychostimulants, 3,4-methylenedioxymethcathinone (methylone) and 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA) under extended access conditions, as with typical psychostimulants. Here, we investigated whether female rats escalate self-administration of methylone, 3,4-methylenedioxypentedrone (pentylone), and MDMA and then studied consequences of MDMA and pentylone self-administration on GABA&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt; receptor and kappa opioid receptor (KOR) signaling in the central nucleus of the amygdala (CeA), a brain area critically dysregulated by extended access self-administration of alcohol or cocaine. Adult female Wistar rats were trained to self-administer methylone, pentylone, MDMA (0.5 mg/kg/infusion), or saline-vehicle using a fixed-ratio 1 response contingency in 6-hour sessions (long-access: LgA) followed by progressive ratio (PR) dose-response testing. The effects of pentylone-LgA, MDMA-LgA and saline on basal GABAergic transmission (miniature postsynaptic inhibitory currents, mIPSCs) and the modulatory role of KOR at CeA GABAergic synapses were determined in acute brain slices using whole-cell patch-clamp. Methylone-LgA and pentylone-LgA rats similarly escalated their drug intake (both obtained more infusions compared to MDMA-LgA rats) however, pentylone-LgA rats reached higher breakpoints in PR tests. At the cellular level, baseline CeA GABA transmission was markedly elevated in pentylone-LgA and MDMA-LgA rats compared to saline-vehicle. Specifically, pentylone-LgA was associated with increased CeA mIPSC frequency (GABA release) and amplitude (postsynaptic GABAA receptor function), while mIPSC amplitudes (but not frequency) was larger in MDMA-LgA rats compared to saline rats. In addition, pentylone-LgA and MDMA-LgA profoundly disrupted CeA KOR signaling such as both KOR agonism (1mM U50488) and KOR antagonism (200nM nor-binaltorphimine) decreased mIPSC frequency suggesting recruitment of non-canonical KOR signaling pathways. This study confirms escalated self-administration of entactogen psychostimulants under LgA conditions in female rats which is accompanied by increased CeA GABAergic inhibition and altered KOR signaling. Collectively, our study suggests that CeA GABA and KOR mechanisms play a critical role in entactogen self-administration like those observed with escalation of alcohol or cocaine self-administration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461477" rel="alternate" title="Self-Administration of entactogen psychostimulants dysregulates GABA and Kappa Opioid Receptor signaling in the central nucleus of the amygdala of female Wistar rats (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461045</id><title>Multi-locus transcranial magnetic stimulation system for electronically targeted brain stimulation (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.415912+00:00</updated><author><name>Jaakko O. Nieminen</name></author><author><name>Heikki Sinisalo</name></author><author><name>Victor H. Souza</name></author><author><name>Mikko Malmi</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Yuryev</name></author><author><name>Aino E. Tervo</name></author><author><name>Matti Stenroos</name></author><author><name>Diego Milardovich</name></author><author><name>Juuso T. Korhonen</name></author><author><name>Lari M. Koponen</name></author><author><name>Risto J. Ilmoniemi</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) allows non-invasive stimulation of the cortex. In multi-locus TMS (mTMS), the stimulating electric field (E-field) is controlled electronically without coil movement by adjusting currents in the coils of a transducer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop an mTMS system that allows adjusting the location and orientation of the E-field maximum within a cortical region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We designed and manufactured a planar 5-coil mTMS transducer to allow controlling the maximum of the induced E-field within a cortical region approximately 30 mm in diameter. We developed electronics with a design consisting of independently controlled H-bridge circuits to drive up to six TMS coils. To control the hardware, we programmed software that runs on a field-programmable gate array and a computer. To induce the desired E-field in the cortex, we developed an optimization method to calculate the currents needed in the coils. We characterized the mTMS system and conducted a proof-of-concept motor-mapping experiment on a healthy volunteer. In the motor mapping, we kept the transducer placement fixed while electronically shifting the E-field maximum on the precentral gyrus and measuring electromyography from the contralateral hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transducer consists of an oval coil, two figure-of-eight coils, and two four-leaf-clover coils stacked on top of each other. The technical characterization indicated that the mTMS system performs as designed. The measured motor evoked potential amplitudes varied consistently as a function of the location of the E-field maximum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developed mTMS system enables electronically targeted brain stimulation within a cortical region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461045" rel="alternate" title="Multi-locus transcranial magnetic stimulation system for electronically targeted brain stimulation (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462068</id><title>Here’s the twist: How the brain updates naturalistic event memories as our understanding of the past changes (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.418610+00:00</updated><author><name>Asieh Zadbood</name></author><author><name>Samuel A. Nastase</name></author><author><name>Janice Chen</name></author><author><name>Kenneth A. Norman</name></author><author><name>Uri Hasson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain actively reshapes past memories in light of new incoming information. In the current study, we ask how the brain supports this updatinge process during the encoding and recall of naturalistic stimuli. One group of participants watched a movie (“The Sixth Sense”) with a cinematic “twist” at the end that dramatically changed the interpretation of previous events. Next, participants were asked to verbally recall the movie events, taking into account the new “twist” information. Most participants updated their recall to incorporate the twist. Two additional groups recalled the movie without having to update their memories during recall: one group never saw the twist; another group was exposed to the twist prior to the beginning of the movie, and thus the twist information was incorporated both during encoding and recall. We found that providing participants with information about the twist beforehand altered neural response patterns during movie-viewing in the default mode network (DMN). Moreover, presenting participants with the twist at the end of the movie changed the neural representation of the previously-encoded information during recall in a subset of DMN regions. Further evidence for this transformation was obtained by comparing the neural activation patterns during encoding and recall and correlating them with behavioral signatures of memory updating. Our results demonstrate that neural representations of past events encoded in the DMN are dynamically integrated with new information that reshapes our memory in natural contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462068" rel="alternate" title="Here’s the twist: How the brain updates naturalistic event memories as our understanding of the past changes (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461606</id><title>Unrestricted eye movements strengthen causal connectivity from hippocampal to oculomotor regions during scene construction (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.419205+00:00</updated><author><name>Natalia Ladyka-Wojcik</name></author><author><name>Zhong-Xu Liu</name></author><author><name>Jennifer D. Ryan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Scene construction is a key component of memory recall, navigation, and future imagining, and relies on the medial temporal lobes (MTL). A parallel body of work suggests that eye movements may enable the imagination and construction of scenes, even in the absence of external visual input. There are vast structural and functional connections between regions of the MTL and those of the oculomotor system. However, the directionality of connections between the MTL and oculomotor control regions, and how it relates to scene construction, has not been studied directly in human neuroimaging. In the current study, we used dynamic causal modeling (DCM) to investigate this relationship at a mechanistic level using a scene construction task in which participants’ eye movements were either restricted (&lt;italic&gt;fixed-viewing&lt;/italic&gt;) or unrestricted (&lt;italic&gt;free-viewing&lt;/italic&gt;). By omitting external visual input, and by contrasting free-versus fixed-viewing, the directionality of neural connectivity during scene construction could be determined. As opposed to when eye movements were restricted, allowing free viewing during construction of scenes strengthened top-down connections from the MTL to the frontal eye fields, and to lower-level cortical visual processing regions, suppressed bottom-up connections along the visual stream, and enhanced vividness of the constructed scenes. Taken together, these findings provide novel, non-invasive evidence for the causal architecture between the MTL memory system and oculomotor system associated with constructing vivid mental representations of scenes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461606" rel="alternate" title="Unrestricted eye movements strengthen causal connectivity from hippocampal to oculomotor regions during scene construction (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461733</id><title>Tuning in scene-preferring cortex for mid-level visual features gives rise to selectivity across multiple levels of stimulus complexity (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.419663+00:00</updated><author><name>Shi Pui Donald Li</name></author><author><name>Michael F. Bonner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The scene-preferring portion of the human ventral visual stream, known as the parahippocampal place area (PPA), responds to scenes and landmark objects, which tend to be large in real-world size, fixed in location, and inanimate. However, the PPA also exhibits preferences for low-level contour statistics, including rectilinearity and cardinal orientations, that are not directly predicted by theories of scene- and landmark-selectivity. It is unknown whether these divergent findings of both low- and high-level selectivity in the PPA can be explained by a unified computational theory. To address this issue, we fit hierarchical computational models of mid-level tuning to the image-evoked fMRI responses of the PPA, and we performed a series of high-throughput experiments on these models. Our findings show that hierarchical encoding models of the PPA exhibit emergent selectivity across multiple levels of complexity, giving rise to high-level preferences along dimensions of real-world size, fixedness, and naturalness/animacy as well as low-level preferences for rectilinear shapes and cardinal orientations. These results reconcile disparate theories of PPA function in a unified model of mid-level visual representation, and they demonstrate how multifaceted selectivity profiles naturally emerge from the hierarchical computations of visual cortex and the natural statistics of images.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visual neuroscientists characterize cortical selectivity by identifying stimuli that drive regional responses. A perplexing finding is that many higher-order visual regions exhibit selectivity spanning multiple levels of complexity: they respond to highly complex categories, such as scenes and landmarks, but also to surprisingly simplistic features, such as specific contour orientations. Using large-scale computational analyses and human brain imaging, we show how multifaceted selectivity in scene-preferring cortex can emerge from the coding of mid-level visual features, whose complexity is neither as simple as local contours nor as complex as scenes or objects. Our work reconciles seemingly divergent findings of selectivity in scene-preferring cortex and suggests that mid-level features may be central to understanding the category-selective organization of the human visual system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461733" rel="alternate" title="Tuning in scene-preferring cortex for mid-level visual features gives rise to selectivity across multiple levels of stimulus complexity (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461634</id><title>Alpha oscillations link action to cognition: An oculomotor account of the brain’s dominant rhythm (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.420096+00:00</updated><author><name>Tzvetan Popov</name></author><author><name>Gregory A. Miller</name></author><author><name>Brigitte Rockstroh</name></author><author><name>Ole Jensen</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Langer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Power modulations in alpha oscillations (8-14Hz) have been associated with most human cognitive functions and psychopathological conditions studied. These reports are often inconsistent with the prevailing view of a specific relationship of alpha oscillations to attention and working memory (WM). We propose that conceptualizing the role of alpha oscillations in oculomotor control resolves this inconsistency. This proposition is based on a review of results across species (human N&lt;sub&gt;pooled&lt;/sub&gt;=295, one non-human primate, honey bee N=5), experimental conditions (rest, attention, and working memory), and recording techniques (EEG, ECOG, eye-tracking, and MEG) that encourage the following relationships between alpha oscillations and eye-movement control: (i) saccade initiation prompts power decrease in brain circuits associated with saccadic control; (ii) the direction of a saccade is consistent with alpha lateralization, both during task and resting conditions; (iii) the phase of alpha activity informs saccade occurrence and biases miniature eye movements during fixation (e.g. fixational tremor); and (iv) oculomotor action differentiates WM load. A new theory on how alpha oscillations link oculomotor action to cognition is proposed. Generalizing across tasks and species: low oculomotor activity is associated with high alpha power and vice versa. Alpha oscillations regulate &lt;italic&gt;how long&lt;/italic&gt; to look at a given target and &lt;italic&gt;how fast&lt;/italic&gt; to saccade to a next. By ensuring steady gaze position, any potential input outside foveal vision is “suppressed”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461634" rel="alternate" title="Alpha oscillations link action to cognition: An oculomotor account of the brain’s dominant rhythm (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461505</id><title>Not all that is gold glitters: PV-IRES-Cre mouse line shows low efficiency of labeling of parvalbumin interneurons in the perirhinal cortex (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.420368+00:00</updated><author><name>Maximiliano José Nigro</name></author><author><name>Hinako Kirikae</name></author><author><name>Kasper Kjelsberg</name></author><author><name>Rajeevkumar Raveendran Nair</name></author><author><name>Menno P. Witter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The wide diversity of cortical inhibitory neuron types populating the cortex allows the assembly of diverse microcircuits and endows these circuits with different computational properties. Thus, characterizing neuronal diversity is fundamental to describe the building blocks of cortical microcircuits and probe their function. To this purpose, the mouse has emerged as a powerful tool to genetically label and manipulate specific inhibitory cell-types in the mammalian brain. Among these cell-types, the parvalbumin-expressing interneuron type (PV-INs) is perhaps the most characterized. Several mouse lines have been generated to target PV-INs. Among these mouse lines, the PV-IRES-Cre lines is the most widely used and demonstrated a high specificity and efficiency in targeting PV-INs in different cortical areas. However, a characterization of the performance across cortical regions is still missing. Here we show that the PV-IRES-Cre mouse line labels only a fraction of parvalbumin immunoreactive neurons in perirhinal cortex and other association areas. Our results point to a yet uncharacterized diversity within the PV-INs and emphasize the need to characterize these tools in specific cortical areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461505" rel="alternate" title="Not all that is gold glitters: PV-IRES-Cre mouse line shows low efficiency of labeling of parvalbumin interneurons in the perirhinal cortex (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462517</id><title>Hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells do not receive monosynaptic input from thalamic nucleus reuniens (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.420605+00:00</updated><author><name>Lilya Andrianova</name></author><author><name>Erica S Brady</name></author><author><name>Gabriella Margetts-Smith</name></author><author><name>Shivali Kohli</name></author><author><name>Chris J McBain</name></author><author><name>Michael T Craig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thalamic nucleus reuniens (NRe) is located on the midline and acts as a hub to mediate interactions between hippocampal, entorhinal and prefrontal areas although these connections are poorly defined at the cellular and synaptic level. Using electrophysiology and monosynaptic circuit-tracing, we found that pyramidal cells in CA1 receive no direct input from NRe. This contrasts starkly with prefrontal cortex, subiculum and entorhinal cortex, and indicates that NRe inputs to CA1 primarily drive local inhibition and not excitation they do in the other regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462517" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells do not receive monosynaptic input from thalamic nucleus reuniens (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461769</id><title>Post-trauma behavioral phenotype predicts vulnerability to fear relapse after extinction (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.420972+00:00</updated><author><name>Fanny Demars</name></author><author><name>Ralitsa Todorova</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Makdah</name></author><author><name>Antonin Forestier</name></author><author><name>Marie-Odile Krebs</name></author><author><name>Bill P. Godsil</name></author><author><name>Thérèse M. Jay</name></author><author><name>Sidney I. Wiener</name></author><author><name>Marco N. Pompili</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Current treatments for trauma-related disorders remain ineffective for many patients. Here, we modeled interindividual differences in post-therapy fear relapse with a novel ethologically relevant trauma recovery paradigm. After traumatic fear conditioning, rats underwent fear extinction while foraging in a large enriched arena, permitting the expression of a wide spectrum of behaviors, assessed by an automated pipeline. This multidimensional behavioral assessment revealed that post-conditioning fear response profiles clustered into two groups, respectively characterized by active vs. passive fear responses. After trauma, some animals expressed fear by freezing, while others darted, as if fleeing from danger. Remarkably, belonging to the darters or freezers group predicted differential vulnerability to fear relapse after extinction. Moreover, genome-wide transcriptional profiling revealed that these groups differentially regulated specific sets of genes, some of which have previously been implicated in anxiety and trauma-related disorders. Our results suggest that post-trauma behavioral phenotypes and the associated epigenetic landscapes can serve as markers of fear relapse susceptibility, and thus may be instrumental for future development of more effective treatments for psychiatric patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461769" rel="alternate" title="Post-trauma behavioral phenotype predicts vulnerability to fear relapse after extinction (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461936</id><title>Distinct neural representations for prosocial and self-benefitting effort (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.421416+00:00</updated><author><name>Patricia L. Lockwood</name></author><author><name>Marco Wittmann</name></author><author><name>Hamed Nili</name></author><author><name>Mona Matsumoto-Ryan</name></author><author><name>Ayat Abdurahman</name></author><author><name>Jo Cutler</name></author><author><name>Masud Husain</name></author><author><name>Matthew A. J. Apps</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prosocial behaviours – actions that benefit others – are central to individual and societal well-being. Most prosocial acts are effortful. Yet, how the brain encodes effort costs when actions benefit others is unknown. Here, using a combination of multivariate representational similarity analysis and model-based univariate analysis during fMRI, we reveal how the costs of prosocial efforts are processed. Strikingly, we identified a unique neural signature of effort in the anterior cingulate gyrus for prosocial acts both when choosing to help others and when exerting force for their benefit. This pattern was absent for similar self-benefitting behaviour and correlated with individual levels of empathy. In contrast, the ventral tegmental area and the ventral insula signalled subjective value preferentially when choosing whether to exert effort to benefit oneself. These findings demonstrate partially distinct brain areas guide the evaluation and exertion of effort costs when acts are prosocial or self-benefitting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461936" rel="alternate" title="Distinct neural representations for prosocial and self-benefitting effort (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462379</id><title>Modeling spatial, developmental, physiological, and topological constraints on human brain connectivity (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.422870+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Oldham</name></author><author><name>B. D. Fulcher</name></author><author><name>K. Aquino</name></author><author><name>A. Arnatkevičiūtė</name></author><author><name>C. Paquola</name></author><author><name>R. Shishegar</name></author><author><name>A. Fornito</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The complex connectivity of nervous systems is thought to have been shaped by competitive selection pressures to minimize wiring costs and support adaptive function. Accordingly, recent modeling work indicates that stochastic processes, shaped by putative trade-offs between the cost and value of each connection, can successfully reproduce many topological properties of macroscale human connectomes measured with diffusion magnetic resonance imaging. Here, we derive a new formalism with the aim to more accurately capture the competing pressures of wiring cost minimization and topological complexity. We further show that model performance can be improved by accounting for developmental changes in brain geometry and associated wiring costs, and by using inter-regional transcriptional or microstructural similarity rather than topological wiring-rules. However, all models struggled to capture topologies spatial embedding. Our findings highlight an important role for genetics in shaping macroscale brain connectivity and indicate that stochastic models offer an incomplete account of connectome organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462379" rel="alternate" title="Modeling spatial, developmental, physiological, and topological constraints on human brain connectivity (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461801</id><title>Distinct brainstem to spinal cord noradrenergic pathways differentially regulate spinal neuronal activity (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.423418+00:00</updated><author><name>Mateusz Wojciech Kucharczyk</name></author><author><name>Francesca Di Domenico</name></author><author><name>Kirsty Bannister</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brainstem to spinal cord pathways modulate spinal neuronal activity. We implemented locus coeruleus (LC) targeting strategies by microinjecting CAV-PRS-ChR2 virus in the spinal cord (LC:SC module) or LC (LC:LC module). While activation of both modules inhibited evoked spinal neuronal firing via α&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-adrenoceptor-mediated actions, LC:SC opto-activation abolished diffuse noxious inhibitory controls. The LC as a pain generator is likely mechanistically underpinned by maladaptive communication with discrete descending modulatory pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461801" rel="alternate" title="Distinct brainstem to spinal cord noradrenergic pathways differentially regulate spinal neuronal activity (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461220</id><title>Knowledge-driven perceptual organization reshapes information sampling via eye movements (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.424117+00:00</updated><author><name>Marek A. Pedziwiatr</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth von dem Hagen</name></author><author><name>Christoph Teufel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humans constantly move their eyes to explore the environment and obtain information. Competing theories of gaze guidance consider the factors driving eye movements within a dichotomy between low-level visual features and high-level object representations. However, recent developments in object perception indicate a complex and intricate relationship between features and objects. Specifically, image-independent object-knowledge can generate objecthood by dynamically reconfiguring how feature space is carved up by the visual system. Here, we adopt this emerging perspective of object perception, moving away from the simplifying dichotomy between features and objects in explanations of gaze guidance. We recorded eye movements in response to stimuli that appear as meaningless patches on initial viewing but are experienced as coherent objects once relevant object-knowledge has been acquired. We demonstrate that gaze guidance differs substantially depending on whether observers experienced the same stimuli as meaningless patches or organized them into object representations. In particular, fixations on identical images became object-centred, less dispersed, and more consistent across observers once exposed to relevant prior object-knowledge. Observers’ gaze behaviour also indicated a shift from exploratory information-sampling to a strategy of extracting information mainly from selected, object-related image areas. These effects were evident from the first fixations on the image. Importantly, however, eye-movements were not fully determined by object representations but were best explained by a simple model that integrates image-computable features and high-level, knowledge-dependent object representations. Overall, the results show how information sampling via eye-movements in humans is guided by a dynamic interaction between image-computable features and knowledge-driven perceptual organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461220" rel="alternate" title="Knowledge-driven perceptual organization reshapes information sampling via eye movements (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461562</id><title>Chronic THC vapor rescues inflammation-related thermal hyperalgesia and causes cell type-specific modifications in vlPAG neurons (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.424412+00:00</updated><author><name>Leslie K. Kelley</name></author><author><name>Savannah H.M. Lightfoot</name></author><author><name>Matthew N. Hill</name></author><author><name>Nicholas W. Gilpin</name></author><author><name>Jason W. Middleton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To reduce reliance on opioids for the treatment of pain in the clinic, ongoing work is testing the utility of cannabinoid drugs as a potential alternative for treatment of chronic pain and/or as a strategy for reducing opioid drug dosage and duration of treatment (i.e., so-called opioid-sparing effects). Previous preclinical work has shown robust anti-hyperalgesic effects of systemic THC and acute anti-hyperalgesic effects of vaporized THC. Here, we used a vapor inhalation model in rats to test chronic THC vapor inhalation effects on thermal nociception and mechanical sensitivity, as well as midbrain (i.e., periaqueductal gray [PAG]) neuronal function, in adult male rats with chronic inflammatory pain. We report that chronic THC vapor inhalation produces a robust anti-hyperalgesic effect in rats with chronic inflammatory pain, and that this effect persists 24 hours after cessation of THC exposure. We demonstrate that chronic THC vapor inhalation also modulates intrinsic and synaptic properties of ventrolateral PAG (vlPAG) neurons, including reductions in action potential firing rate and reductions in spontaneous inhibitory synaptic transmission, and that these effects occur specifically in neurons that respond to current input with a delayed firing phenotype. Finally, we show that the suppressive effect of the bath-applied mu-opioid receptor (MOR) agonist DAMGO on synaptic inhibition in the vlPAG is enhanced in slices taken from rats with a history of chronic THC vapor inhalation. Collectively, these data show that chronic THC vapor inhalation produces lasting attenuation of thermal hyperalgesia and reduces synaptic inhibition in the vlPAG of rats with chronic inflammatory pain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many adults in the U.S. with pain self-medicate with THC and cannabis, and many cannabis users are increasingly using e-cigarette type devices filled with cannabis extracts to self-administer THC and other constituents of the marijuana plant. Until recently, most rodent studies of THC effects on brain and behavior have not used vapor inhalation techniques. Here, we designed a series of studies to test the effect of chronic THC vapor inhalation on pain-related behaviors and midbrain neural circuit function in adult male Wistar rats. We hypothesized that chronic THC vapor would have anti-hyperalgesic effects in rats with chronic inflammatory pain, and that it would produce disinhibition of midbrain pain modulation neurons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461562" rel="alternate" title="Chronic THC vapor rescues inflammation-related thermal hyperalgesia and causes cell type-specific modifications in vlPAG neurons (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461214</id><title>Neural oscillation coupling selectively predicts speech reception in young children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.424685+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoyue Wang</name></author><author><name>Jaime Delgado</name></author><author><name>Silvia Marchesotti</name></author><author><name>Nada Kojovic</name></author><author><name>Holger Franz Sperdin</name></author><author><name>Tonia A. Rihs</name></author><author><name>Marie Schaer</name></author><author><name>Anne-Lise Giraud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Communication difficulties in autism spectrum disorder (ASD) involve a speech reception deficit, whose biological causes are not yet identified. This deficit could denote atypical neuronal ensemble activity, as reflected by neural oscillations. Atypical &lt;italic&gt;cross-frequency oscillation coupling&lt;/italic&gt; in particular could disrupt the possibility to jointly track and predict dynamic acoustic stimuli, a dual process that is essential for speech comprehension. Whether such oscillation anomalies can already be found in very young children with ASD, and with what specificity they relate to individual language reception capacity is unknown. In this study, neural activity was collected using EEG in 64 very young children with and without ASD (mean age 3) while they were exposed to naturalistic-continuous speech via an age-appropriate cartoon. EEG power typically associated with phrase-level chunking (delta, 1-3Hz), phonemic encoding (low-gamma, 25-35Hz) and top-down control (beta, 12-20Hz) was markedly reduced in ASD relative to typically developing (TD) children. Speech neural-tracking by delta and theta oscillations was also weaker in ASD than TD children. Critically, children with ASD exhibited slightly atypical theta/gamma coupling (PAC) involving a higher-than-normal gamma frequency, and markedly atypical beta/gamma PAC. Even though many oscillation features were atypical in our sample of 31 very young children with ASD, the beta/gamma coupling anomaly was the single best predictor of individual speech reception difficulties. These findings suggest that early interventions targeting the normalization of low-gamma and low-beta activity, might help young children with ASD to engage more in oral interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very young children diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder already present marked alterations of neural oscillatory activity in response to natural speech.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hierarchical processing of phonemic- and syllabic-range information (theta/gamma coupling) is atypical in young ASD children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speech reception deficit in children with ASD is indexed by abnormal bottom-up (low-gamma) and top-down (low-beta) coordination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461214" rel="alternate" title="Neural oscillation coupling selectively predicts speech reception in young children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461491</id><title>Model-based dynamic off-resonance correction for improved accelerated fMRI in awake behaving non-human primates (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.425027+00:00</updated><author><name>Mo Shahdloo</name></author><author><name>Urs Schüffelgen</name></author><author><name>Daniel Papp</name></author><author><name>Karla L. Miller</name></author><author><name>Mark Chiew</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To estimate dynamic off-resonance due to vigorous body motion in accelerated fMRI of awake behaving non-human primates (NHPs) using the standard EPI 3-line navigator, in order to attenuate the effects of time-varying off-resonance on the reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In NHP fMRI the animal’s head is usually head-posted, and the dynamic off-resonance is mainly caused by motion in body parts that are distant from the brain and have low spatial frequency. Hence, off-resonance at each frame can be approximated as a spatially linear perturbation of the off-resonance at a reference frame, and is manifested as a relative linear shift in k-space. Using GRAPPA operators, we estimated these shifts by comparing the 3-line navigator at each time frame with that at the reference frame. Estimated shifts were then used to correct the data at each frame. The proposed method was evaluated in phantom scans, simulations, and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed method is shown to successfully estimate low-spatial order dynamic off-resonance perturbations, including induced linear off-resonance perturbations in phantoms, and is able to correct retrospectively corrupted data in simulations. Finally, it is shown to reduce ghosting artifacts and geometric distortions by up to 20% in simultaneous multi-slice &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; acquisitions in awake-behaving NHPs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A method is proposed that does not need any sequence modification or extra acquisitions and makes accelerated awake behaving NHP imaging more robust and reliable, reducing the gap between what is possible with NHP protocols and state-of-the-art human imaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461491" rel="alternate" title="Model-based dynamic off-resonance correction for improved accelerated fMRI in awake behaving non-human primates (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461560</id><title>White matter hyperintensities may be an early marker for age-related cognitive decline in the ADNI cohort (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.425332+00:00</updated><author><name>Cassandra Morrison</name></author><author><name>Mahsa Dadar</name></author><author><name>Sylvia Villeneuve</name></author><author><name>D. Louis Collins</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous research suggests that white matter hyperintensities, amyloid, and tau contribute to age-related cognitive decline. It remains unknown as to how these factors relate to one another and how they jointly contribute to cognitive decline in normal aging. This project examines the association between these pathologies and their relationship to cognitive decline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cognitively normal older adult data from the Alzheimer’s Disease Neuroimaging Initiative were examined. Participants were included if they had no subjective cognitive decline, had baseline white matter hyperintensity, CSF Aß42/40, CSF pTau181, and cognitive scores. Of the 102 participants included, only 79 had follow-up cognitive scores. Linear regressions examined the influence of white matter hyperintensities, amyloid, and tau on baseline and follow-up cognitive scores. Linear regressions also examined the association of amyloid and tau on white matter hyperintensities and between tau and amyloid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Increased white matter hyperintensity load was associated with lower baseline memory (ß= -0.20, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; =.046), follow-up executive functioning (ß= -0.32, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001), and follow-up ADAS-13 (ß=2.69, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;&amp;lt;.001) scores. White matter hyperintensities were not related to pTau or Aß42/40. Lower Aß42/40 was associated with increased pTau (&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;=.025). pTau was not associated with decline in any cognitive score. Lower Aß42/40 was associated with lower baseline (&lt;italic&gt;p=&lt;/italic&gt;.015) but not follow-up executive function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;White matter hyperintensities may be one of the earliest pathologies observed in healthy older adults that contribute to cognitive decline. The inclusion of white matter hyperintensities as an additional marker for early cognitive decline may improve our current understanding of age-related changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461560" rel="alternate" title="White matter hyperintensities may be an early marker for age-related cognitive decline in the ADNI cohort (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460906</id><title>Periodic attention operates faster during more complex visual search (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.425576+00:00</updated><author><name>Garance Merholz</name></author><author><name>Laetitia Grabot</name></author><author><name>Rufin VanRullen</name></author><author><name>Laura Dugué</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Attention has been found to sample visual information periodically, in a wide range of frequencies below 20 Hz. This periodicity may be supported by brain oscillations at corresponding frequencies. We propose that part of the discrepancy in periodic frequencies observed in the literature is due to differences in attentional demands, resulting from heterogeneity in tasks performed. To test this hypothesis, we used visual search and manipulated task complexity, i.e., target discriminability (high, medium, low) and number of distractors (set size), while electro-encephalography was simultaneously recorded. We replicated previous results showing that the phase of pre-stimulus low-frequency oscillations predicts search performance. Crucially, such effects were observed at increasing frequencies within the theta-alpha range (6-18 Hz) for decreasing target discriminability. In medium and low discriminability conditions, correct responses were further associated with higher post-stimulus phase-locking than incorrect ones, in increasing frequency and latency. Finally, the larger the set size, the later the post-stimulus effect peaked. Together, these results suggest that increased complexity (lower discriminability or larger set size) requires more attentional cycles to perform the task, partially explaining discrepancies between reports of attentional sampling. Low-frequency oscillations structure the temporal dynamics of neural activity and aid top-down, attentional control for efficient visual processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.460906" rel="alternate" title="Periodic attention operates faster during more complex visual search (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461550</id><title>Parallel systems for social and spatial reasoning within the cortical apex (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.425805+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben Deen</name></author><author><name>Winrich A. Freiwald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;What is the cognitive and neural architecture of systems for high-level reasoning and memory in humans? We ask this question using deep neuroimaging of individual human brains on various tasks involving reasoning and memory about familiar people, places, and objects. We find that thinking about people and places elicits responses in distinct but parallel networks within high-level association cortex, spanning the frontal, parietal, and temporal lobes. Person- and place-preferring brain regions were systematically yoked across multiple cortical zones. These regions were strongly category-selective, across visual, semantic, and episodic tasks, and were specifically functionally connected to other parts of association cortex with similar category preferences. These results demonstrate that selectivity for content domain is a widespread feature of high-level association cortex in humans. They support a theoretical model in which reasoning about people and places are supported by parallel cognitive and neural mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461550" rel="alternate" title="Parallel systems for social and spatial reasoning within the cortical apex (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461278</id><title>Extrasynaptic signaling enables an asymmetric juvenile motor circuit to produce a symmetric gait (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.426344+00:00</updated><author><name>Yangning Lu</name></author><author><name>Tosif Ahamed</name></author><author><name>Ben Mulcahy</name></author><author><name>Daniel Witvliet</name></author><author><name>Sihui Asuka Guan</name></author><author><name>Wesley Hung</name></author><author><name>Jun Meng</name></author><author><name>Quan Wen</name></author><author><name>Aravinthan DT Samuel</name></author><author><name>Mei Zhen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bilaterians generate motor patterns with symmetries that correspond to their body plans. This is thought to arise from wiring symmetries in their motor circuits. We show that juvenile &lt;italic&gt;C. elegans&lt;/italic&gt; larva has an asymmetrically wired motor circuit, but still generates a bending pattern with dorsal-ventral symmetry. In the juvenile circuit, wiring between excitatory and inhibitory motor neurons coordinates contraction of dorsal muscles with relaxation of ventral muscles, producing dorsal bends. Ventral bending is not driven by analogous wiring. Instead, ventral muscles are excited uniformly by premotor interneurons through extrasynaptic signaling. Ventral bends occur in entrainment to the activity of the same motor neurons that drive dorsal bends. During maturation, the juvenile motor circuit is replaced by two homologous motor circuits that separately drive dorsal and ventral bending. Modeling reveals that the juvenile’s immature motor circuit provides an adequate solution to generate an adult-like gait long before the animal matures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461278" rel="alternate" title="Extrasynaptic signaling enables an asymmetric juvenile motor circuit to produce a symmetric gait (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461656</id><title>A neurocomputational model of the basal ganglia for the analysis of motor deficits after dopaminergic loss in Parkinson’s disease (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.426802+00:00</updated><author><name>Ilaria Gigi</name></author><author><name>Rosa Senatore</name></author><author><name>Angelo Marcelli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The basal ganglia (BG) are part of a basic feedback circuit, regulating cortical function, such as voluntary movement control, via their influence on thalamocortical projections. BG disorders, namely Parkinson’s disease (PD), characterized by the loss of neurons in the substantia nigra (SN), involve the progressive loss of motor functions. The process that leads to these neural alterations is still unknown. At the present, PD cannot be cured, but an early diagnosis (ED) could allow to better manage its symptoms and evolution. A branch of neuroscience research is currently investigating the possibility of using motor alterations, e.g. handwriting, caused by the disease as diagnostic signs in the early stage of the disease, expression of small entity of SN lesion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the present work, we propose a neurocomputational model to investigate the behaviour of the simulated neural system after several degrees of lesion, with the aim of evaluating, if possible, which is the smallest lesion compromising motor learning. The performance of the network in learning a novel motor task has been analyzed, in physiological and pathological conditions. The proposed neural network proves that there may exist abnormalities of motor learning process, due to alterations in the BG, which do not yet involve the presence of symptoms typical of the confirmed diagnosis, since the network shows having some difficulties in motor learning already with 20% DA depletion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461656" rel="alternate" title="A neurocomputational model of the basal ganglia for the analysis of motor deficits after dopaminergic loss in Parkinson’s disease (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.460970</id><title>The HDAC inhibitor CI-994 acts as a molecular memory aid by facilitating synaptic and intra-cellular communication after learning (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.427037+00:00</updated><author><name>Allison M Burns</name></author><author><name>Mélissa Farinelli-Scharly</name></author><author><name>Sandrine Hugues-Ascery</name></author><author><name>Jose Vicente Sanchez-Mut</name></author><author><name>Giulia Santoni</name></author><author><name>Johannes Gräff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long-term memory formation relies on synaptic plasticity, activity-dependent transcription and epigenetic modifications. Multiple studies have shown that HDAC inhibitor (HDACi) treatments can enhance individual aspects of these processes, and thereby act as putative cognitive enhancers. However, their mode of action is not fully understood. In particular, it is unclear how systemic application of HDACis, which are devoid of substrate specificity, can target pathways that promote memory formation. In this study, we explore the electrophysiological, transcriptional and epigenetic responses that are induced by CI-994, a class I HDAC inhibitor, combined with contextual fear conditioning (CFC) in mice. We show that CI-994-mediated improvement of memory formation is accompanied by enhanced long-term potentiation in the hippocampus, a brain region recruited by CFC, but not in the striatum, a brain region not primarily implicated in contextual memory formation. Furthermore, using a combination of bulk and single cell RNA sequencing, we find that synaptic plasticity-promoting gene expression cascades are more strongly engaged in the hippocampus than in the striatum, but only when HDACi treatment co-occurred with CFC, and not by either treatment alone. Lastly, using ChIP-sequencing, we show that the combined action of HDACi application and conditioning is required to elicit enhancer histone acetylation in pathways that may underlie improved memory performance. Together, our results indicate that systemic HDACi administration amplifies brain-region specific processes that are naturally induced by learning. These findings shed light onto the mode of action of HDACis as cognitive enhancers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Memory formation relies on a plethora of functions, including epigenetic modifications. Over the past years, multiple studies have indicated the potential of HDAC inhibitors (HDACi) to act as cognitive enhancers, but their mode of action is not fully understood. Here, we tested whether HDACi treatment improves memory formation via “cognitive epigenetic priming”, stipulating that HDACis – without inherent target specificity – specifically enhance plasticity-related processes. We found that combining HDACi with fear learning, but not either treatment alone, enhances synaptic plasticity as well as memory-promoting transcriptional signaling in the hippocampus, a brain area known to be recruited by fear learning, but not in others. These results lend experimental support to the theory of “cognitive epigenetic priming”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.460970" rel="alternate" title="The HDAC inhibitor CI-994 acts as a molecular memory aid by facilitating synaptic and intra-cellular communication after learning (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461333</id><title>Altered synaptic connectivity in an in vitro human model of STXBP1 encephalopathy (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.431587+00:00</updated><author><name>Faye McLeod</name></author><author><name>Anna Dimtsi</name></author><author><name>David Lewis-Smith</name></author><author><name>Rhys Thomas</name></author><author><name>Gavin J Clowry</name></author><author><name>Andrew J Trevelyan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early infantile epileptic encephalopathies are devastating conditions, generally of genetic origin, but the pathological mechanisms often remain obscure. A major obstacle in this field of research is the difficulty of studying cortical brain development in humans, &lt;italic&gt;in utero&lt;/italic&gt;. To address this, we established an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; assay to study the impact of gene variants on the developing human brain, using living organotypic cultures of the human subplate and neighbouring cortical regions, prepared from ethically sourced, 14-17 post conception week brain tissue (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hdbr.org"&gt;www.hdbr.org&lt;/ext-link&gt;). We were able to maintain cultures for several months, during which time, the gross anatomical structures of the cortical plate, subplate and marginal zone persisted, while neurons continued to develop morphologically, and form new synaptic networks. This preparation thus permits the study of genetic manipulations, and their downstream effects, upon an intact developing human cortical network. We focused upon STXBP1 haploinsufficiency, which is among the most common genetic causes of infantile epileptic encephalopathy. This was induced using shRNA interference, leading to impaired synaptic function and a drop in the number of glutamatergic synapses. We thereby provide a critical proof-of-principle for how to study the impact of any gene of interest on the development of the human cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461333" rel="alternate" title="Altered synaptic connectivity in an in vitro human model of STXBP1 encephalopathy (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461046</id><title>Narcolepsy with cataplexy is caused by epigenetic silencing of hypocretin neurons (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.432205+00:00</updated><author><name>Ali Seifinejad</name></author><author><name>Almar Neiteler</name></author><author><name>Sha Li</name></author><author><name>Corinne Pfister</name></author><author><name>Rolf Fronczek</name></author><author><name>Ling Shan</name></author><author><name>Lee A. Garrett-Sinha</name></author><author><name>David Frieser</name></author><author><name>Makoto Honda</name></author><author><name>Yoan Arribat</name></author><author><name>Dogan Grepper</name></author><author><name>Francesca Amati</name></author><author><name>Marie Picot</name></author><author><name>Christian Iseli</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Chartrel</name></author><author><name>Gert J. Lammers</name></author><author><name>Roland Liblau</name></author><author><name>Anne Vassalli</name></author><author><name>Mehdi Tafti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Narcolepsy with cataplexy is a chronic sleep disorder characterized by hypocretin deficiency. The condition is believed to result from autoimmune destruction of hypocretin (HCRT) neurons, although direct evidence is lacking and mere &lt;italic&gt;Hcrt&lt;/italic&gt; gene inactivation causes full-blown narcolepsy in mice. Here we show that the expression of another hypothalamic neuropeptide, QRFP, is lost in mouse models with HCRT cell-ablation, but tends to be even increased in &lt;italic&gt;Hcrt&lt;/italic&gt; gene knockout mice, suggesting that QRFP expression can be used as a proxy for the presence or absence of HCRT neurons. Similar to &lt;italic&gt;Hcrt&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mice, narcolepsy patients show intact hypothalamic &lt;italic&gt;QRFP&lt;/italic&gt; expression, and cerebrospinal fluid levels of QRFP peptide are increased, suggesting their HCRT neurons are intact. We show that the human &lt;italic&gt;HCRT&lt;/italic&gt; gene promoter is methylation-sensitive &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, and is hypermethylated in the hypothalamus of patients selectively at a putative PAX5:ETS1 binding site within the proximal &lt;italic&gt;HCRT&lt;/italic&gt; promoter. Ets1-KO mice display downregulated &lt;italic&gt;Hcrt&lt;/italic&gt; expression, while &lt;italic&gt;pax5-ets1&lt;/italic&gt; knockdown in zebrafish causes decreased &lt;italic&gt;hcrt&lt;/italic&gt; expression, decreased activity and sleep fragmentation, similar to narcolepsy patients. Our results suggest that HCRT neurons are alive, but epigenetically silenced, in the hypothalamus of narcolepsy patients, opening the possibility to reverse or cure narcolepsy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461046" rel="alternate" title="Narcolepsy with cataplexy is caused by epigenetic silencing of hypocretin neurons (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462468</id><title>Distance estimation from monocular cues in an ethological visuomotor task (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.432756+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip R. L. Parker</name></author><author><name>Elliott T. T. Abe</name></author><author><name>Natalie T. Beatie</name></author><author><name>Emmalyn S. P. Leonard</name></author><author><name>Dylan M. Martins</name></author><author><name>Shelby L. Sharp</name></author><author><name>David G. Wyrick</name></author><author><name>Luca Mazzucato</name></author><author><name>Cristopher M. Niell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In natural contexts, sensory processing and motor output are closely coupled, which is reflected in the fact that many brain areas contain both sensory and movement signals. However, standard reductionist paradigms decouple sensory decisions from their natural motor consequences, and head-fixation prevents the natural sensory consequences of self-motion. In particular, movement through the environment provides a number of depth cues beyond stereo vision that are poorly understood. To study the integration of visual processing and motor output in a naturalistic task, we investigated distance estimation in freely moving mice. We found that mice use vision to accurately jump across a variable gap, thus directly coupling a visual computation to its corresponding ethological motor output. Monocular eyelid suture did not affect performance, thus mice can use cues that do not depend on binocular disparity and stereo vision. Under monocular conditions, mice performed more vertical head movements, consistent with the use of motion parallax cues, and optogenetic suppression of primary visual cortex impaired task performance. Together, these results show that mice can use monocular cues, relying on visual cortex, to accurately judge distance. Furthermore, this behavioral paradigm provides a foundation for studying how neural circuits convert sensory information into ethological motor output.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462468" rel="alternate" title="Distance estimation from monocular cues in an ethological visuomotor task (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462361</id><title>Higher-order olfactory neurons in the lateral horn supports odor valence and odor identity coding in Drosophila (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.433873+00:00</updated><author><name>Sudeshna Das Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Hetan Chang</name></author><author><name>Bill S. Hansson</name></author><author><name>Silke Sachse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding neuronal representations of odor-evoked activities and their progressive transformation from the sensory level to higher brain centers features one of the major aims in olfactory neuroscience. Here, we investigated how odor information is transformed and represented in higher-order neurons of the lateral horn, one of the higher olfactory centers implicated in determining innate behavior, using &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. We focused on a subset of third-order glutamatergic lateral horn neurons (LHNs) and characterized their odor coding properties in relation to their presynaptic partner neurons, the projection neurons (PNs) by two-photon functional imaging. We found that odors evoke reproducible, stereotypic and odor-specific response patterns in LHNs. Notably, odor-evoked responses in these neurons are valence-specific in a way that their response amplitude is positively correlated with innate odor preferences. We postulate that this valence-specific activity is the result of integrating inputs from multiple olfactory channels through second-order neurons. GRASP and micro-lesioning experiments provide evidence that glutamatergic LHNs obtain their major excitatory input from uniglomerular PNs, while they receive an odor-specific inhibition through inhibitory multiglomerular PNs. In summary, our study indicates that odor representations in glutamatergic LHNs encode hedonic valence and odor identity and primarily retain the odor coding properties of second-order neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462361" rel="alternate" title="Higher-order olfactory neurons in the lateral horn supports odor valence and odor identity coding in Drosophila (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.459010</id><title>A whole-brain monosynaptic input connectome to neuron classes in mouse visual cortex (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.434809+00:00</updated><author><name>Shenqin Yao</name></author><author><name>Quanxin Wang</name></author><author><name>Karla E. Hirokawa</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Ouellette</name></author><author><name>Ruweida Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Jasmin Bomben</name></author><author><name>Krissy Brouner</name></author><author><name>Linzy Casal</name></author><author><name>Shiella Caldejon</name></author><author><name>Andy Cho</name></author><author><name>Nadezhda I. Dotson</name></author><author><name>Tanya L. Daigle</name></author><author><name>Tom Egdorf</name></author><author><name>Rachel Enstrom</name></author><author><name>Amanda Gary</name></author><author><name>Emily Gelfand</name></author><author><name>Melissa Gorham</name></author><author><name>Fiona Griffin</name></author><author><name>Hong Gu</name></author><author><name>Nicole Hancock</name></author><author><name>Robert Howard</name></author><author><name>Leonard Kuan</name></author><author><name>Sophie Lambert</name></author><author><name>Eric Kenji Lee</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Luviano</name></author><author><name>Kyla Mace</name></author><author><name>Michelle Maxwell</name></author><author><name>Marty T. Mortrud</name></author><author><name>Maitham Naeemi</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Nayan</name></author><author><name>Nhan-Kiet Ngo</name></author><author><name>Thuyanh Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Kat North</name></author><author><name>Shea Ransford</name></author><author><name>Augustin Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Sam Seid</name></author><author><name>Jackie Swapp</name></author><author><name>Michael J Taormina</name></author><author><name>Wayne Wakeman</name></author><author><name>Thomas Zhou</name></author><author><name>Philip R. Nicovich</name></author><author><name>Ali Williford</name></author><author><name>Lydia Potekhina</name></author><author><name>Medea McGraw</name></author><author><name>Lydia Ng</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Groblewski</name></author><author><name>Bosiljka Tasic</name></author><author><name>Stefan Mihalas</name></author><author><name>Julie A Harris</name></author><author><name>Ali Cetin</name></author><author><name>Hongkui Zeng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identification of the structural connections between neurons is a prerequisite to understanding brain function. We developed a pipeline to systematically map brain-wide monosynaptic inputs to specific neuronal populations using Cre-driver mouse lines and the recombinant rabies tracing system. We first improved the rabies virus tracing strategy to accurately identify starter cells and to efficiently quantify presynaptic inputs. We then mapped brain-wide presynaptic inputs to different excitatory and inhibitory neuron subclasses in the primary visual cortex and seven higher visual areas. Our results reveal quantitative target-, layer- and cell-class-specific differences in the retrograde connectomes, despite similar global input patterns to different neuronal populations in the same anatomical area. The retrograde connectivity we define is consistent with the presence of the ventral and dorsal visual information processing streams and reveals further subnetworks within the dorsal stream. The hierarchical organization of the entire visual cortex can be derived from intracortical feedforward and feedback pathways mediated by upper- and lower-layer input neurons, respectively. This study expands our knowledge of the brain-wide inputs regulating visual areas and demonstrates that our improved rabies virus tracing strategy can be used to scale up the effort in dissecting connectivity of genetically defined cell populations in the whole mouse brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.459010" rel="alternate" title="A whole-brain monosynaptic input connectome to neuron classes in mouse visual cortex (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462081</id><title>Performance-optimized neural networks as an explanatory framework for decision confidence (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.435599+00:00</updated><author><name>Taylor W. Webb</name></author><author><name>Kiyofumi Miyoshi</name></author><author><name>Tsz Yan So</name></author><author><name>Sivananda Rajananda</name></author><author><name>Hakwan Lau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous work has sought to understand decision confidence as a prediction of the probability that a decision will be correct, leading to debate over whether these predictions are optimal, and whether they rely on the same decision variable as decisions themselves. This work has generally relied on idealized, low-dimensional modeling frameworks, such as signal detection theory or Bayesian inference, leaving open the question of how decision confidence operates in the domain of high-dimensional, naturalistic stimuli. To address this, we developed a deep neural network model optimized to assess decision confidence directly given high-dimensional inputs such as images. The model naturally accounts for a number of puzzling dissociations between decisions and confidence, suggests a principled explanation of these dissociations in terms of optimization for the statistics of sensory inputs, and makes the surprising prediction that, despite these dissociations, decisions and confidence depend on a common decision variable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462081" rel="alternate" title="Performance-optimized neural networks as an explanatory framework for decision confidence (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462028</id><title>Fast resupply of synaptic vesicles requires Synaptotagmin-3 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.436029+00:00</updated><author><name>Dennis J. Weingarten</name></author><author><name>Amita Shrestha</name></author><author><name>Sarah A. Kissiwaa</name></author><author><name>Evan Spruston</name></author><author><name>Skyler L. Jackman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sustained neuronal activity demands quick resupply of synaptic vesicles in order to maintain reliable synaptic transmission. Such vesicle replenishment is accelerated by sub-micromolar presynaptic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals by an as yet unidentified high-affinity Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; sensor&lt;sup&gt;1-4&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we identify a novel presynaptic role for the high-affinity Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; sensor Synaptotagmin-3 (SYT3)&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; in driving vesicle replenishment and short-term synaptic plasticity. Synapses in &lt;italic&gt;Syt3&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mice exhibit enhanced short-term depression, and recovery is slower and insensitive to presynaptic residual Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;. During sustained neuronal firing, SYT3 speeds vesicle replenishment and increases the size of the readily releasable pool of vesicles. SYT3 also mediates a second form of short-term enhancement called facilitation, under conditions of low vesicle release probability. Models of vesicle trafficking suggest that SYT3 could combat synaptic depression by accelerating vesicle docking at active zones. Our results reveal a critical role for presynaptic SYT3 in maintaining reliable high-frequency synaptic transmission in neural circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462028" rel="alternate" title="Fast resupply of synaptic vesicles requires Synaptotagmin-3 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.460342</id><title>Region-specific KCC2 rescue by rhIGF-1 and oxytocin in a mouse model of Rett syndrome (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.436582+00:00</updated><author><name>Valentina Gigliucci</name></author><author><name>Jasper Teutsch</name></author><author><name>Marc Woodbury-Smith</name></author><author><name>Mirko Luoni</name></author><author><name>Marta Busnelli</name></author><author><name>Bice Chini</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Banerjee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rett syndrome (RTT) is characterized by dysfunction in neuronal excitation/inhibition (E/I) balance, potentially impacting seizure susceptibility via deficits in K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;/Cl&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; cotransporter 2 (KCC2) function. Mice lacking the Methyl-CpG binding protein 2 (MeCP2) recapitulate many symptoms of RTT, and recombinant human insulin-like growth factor-1 (rhIGF-1) restores KCC2 expression and E/I balance in MeCP2 KO mice. However, clinical trial outcomes of rhIGF-1 in RTT have been variable, and increasing its therapeutic efficacy is highly desirable. To this end, the neuropeptide oxytocin (OXT) is promising, as it also critically modulates KCC2 function during early postnatal development. We measured basal KCC2 expression levels in MeCP2 KO mice and identified three key frontal brain regions showing KCC2 alterations in young adult mice but not in postnatal P10 animals. We thus hypothesized that deficits in an IGF-1/OXT signaling crosstalk modulating KCC2 may occur in RTT during postnatal development. Consistently, we detected alterations of IGF-1 receptor (IGF-1R) and OXT receptor (OXTR) levels in those brain areas. rhIGF-1 and OXT treatments in KO mice rescued KCC2 expression in a region-specific and complementary manner. These results suggest that region-selective combinatorial pharmacotherapeutic strategies could be the most effective at normalizing E/I balance in key brain regions subtending the RTT pathophysiology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.460342" rel="alternate" title="Region-specific KCC2 rescue by rhIGF-1 and oxytocin in a mouse model of Rett syndrome (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461034</id><title>Real-time audio processing of real-life soundscapes for EEG analysis: ERPs based on natural sound onsets (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.437056+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Hölle</name></author><author><name>Sarah Blum</name></author><author><name>Sven Kissner</name></author><author><name>Stefan Debener</name></author><author><name>Martin G. Bleichner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With smartphone-based mobile electroencephalography (EEG), we can investigate sound perception beyond the lab. To understand sound perception in the real world, we need to relate naturally occurring sounds to EEG data. For this, EEG and audio information need to be synchronized precisely, only then it is possible to capture fast and transient evoked neural responses and relate them to individual sounds. We have developed Android applications (AFEx and Record-a) that allow for the concurrent acquisition of EEG data and audio features, i.e., sound onsets, average signal power (RMS) and power spectral density (PSD) on smartphone. In this paper, we evaluate these apps by computing event-related potentials (ERPs) evoked by everyday sounds. One participant listened to piano notes (played live by a pianist) and to a home-office soundscape. Timing tests showed that the temporal precision of the system is very good. We calculated ERPs to sound onsets and observed the typical P1-N1-P2 complex of auditory processing. Furthermore, we show how to relate information on loudness (RMS) and spectra (PSD) to brain activity. In future studies, we can use this system to study sound processing in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461034" rel="alternate" title="Real-time audio processing of real-life soundscapes for EEG analysis: ERPs based on natural sound onsets (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461723</id><title>Normative and mechanistic model of an adaptive circuit for efficient encoding and feature extraction (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.437587+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikolai M. Chapochnikov</name></author><author><name>Cengiz Pehlevan</name></author><author><name>Dmitri B. Chklovskii</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;One major question in neuroscience is how to relate connectomes to neural activity, circuit function, and learning. We offer an answer in the peripheral olfactory circuit of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; larva, composed of olfactory receptor neurons (ORNs) connected through feedback loops with interconnected inhibitory local neurons (LNs). We combine structural and activity data and, using a holistic normative framework based on similarity-matching, we propose a biologically plausible mechanistic model of the circuit. Our model predicts the ORN → LN synaptic weights found in the connectome and demonstrate that they reflect correlations in ORN activity patterns. Additionally, our model explains the relation between ORN → LN and LN – LN synaptic weight and the arising of different LN types. This global synaptic organization can autonomously arise through Hebbian plasticity, and thus allows the circuit to adapt to different environments in an unsupervised manner. Functionally, we propose LNs extract redundant input correlations and dampen them in ORNs, thus partially whitening and normalizing the stimulus representations in ORNs. Our work proposes a comprehensive framework to combine structure, activity, function, and learning, and uncovers a general and potent circuit motif that can learn and extract significant input features and render stimulus representations more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The brain represents information with patterns of neural activity. At the periphery, due to the properties of the external world and of encoding neurons, these patterns contain correlations, which are detrimental for stimulus discrimination. We study the peripheral olfactory neural circuit of the Drosophila larva, that preprocesses neural representations before relaying them to higher brain areas. A comprehensive understanding of this preprocessing is, however, lacking. Here, we propose a mechanistic and normative framework describing the function of the circuit and predict the circuit’s synaptic organization based on the circuit’s input neural activity. We show how the circuit can autonomously adapt to different environments, extracts stimulus features, and decorrelate and normalize input representations, which facilitates odor discrimination downstream.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461723" rel="alternate" title="Normative and mechanistic model of an adaptive circuit for efficient encoding and feature extraction (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461367</id><title>Assessing the relationships between neurological and psychiatric diseases with astrocyte subtypes and psychotropic medications (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.439634+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaolu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Alyssa Wolfinger</name></author><author><name>Rammohan Shukla</name></author><author><name>Anna Lundh</name></author><author><name>Xiaojun Wu</name></author><author><name>Mackenzie Abel</name></author><author><name>Robert E. McCullumsmith</name></author><author><name>Sinead M. O’Donovan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Astrocytes have many important functions in the brain, but their roles in CNS disorders and their responses to psychotropic medications are still being elucidated. In this study, we used gene enrichment analysis to assess the relationships between different astrocyte subtypes, neurological and psychiatric diseases, and psychotropic medications. We also carried out qPCR analyses and “look-up” studies to further assess the chronic effects of these drugs on astrocyte marker gene expression. Our bioinformatic analysis identified differential gene enrichment of different astrocyte subtypes in CNS disorders. The “common” astrocyte subtype was the most frequently enriched across disorders, but the highest level of enrichment was found in depression, supporting a role for astrocytes in this disorder. We also identified common enrichment of metabolic and signal transduction-related biological processes in astrocyte subtypes and CNS disorders. However, enrichment of different psychotropic medications, including antipsychotics, antidepressants, and mood stabilizers, was limited in astrocyte subtypes. These results were confirmed by “look-up” studies and qPCR analysis, which also reported little effect of common psychotropic medications on astrocyte marker gene expression, suggesting that astrocytes are not a primary target of these medications. Overall, this study provides a unique view of astrocyte subtypes and the effect of medications on astrocytes in disease, which will contribute to our understanding of their role in CNS disorders and offers insights into targeting astrocytes therapeutically.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461367" rel="alternate" title="Assessing the relationships between neurological and psychiatric diseases with astrocyte subtypes and psychotropic medications (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461829</id><title>Computing personalized brain functional networks from fMRI using self-supervised deep learning (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.440305+00:00</updated><author><name>Hongming Li</name></author><author><name>Srinivasan Dhivya</name></author><author><name>Zaixu Cui</name></author><author><name>Chuanjun Zhuo</name></author><author><name>Raquel E. Gur</name></author><author><name>Ruben C. Gur</name></author><author><name>Desmond J. Oathes</name></author><author><name>Christos Davatzikos</name></author><author><name>Theodore D. Satterthwaite</name></author><author><name>Yong Fan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A novel self-supervised deep learning (DL) method is developed for computing bias-free, personalized brain functional networks (FNs) that provide unique opportunities to better understand brain function, behavior, and disease. Specifically, convolutional neural networks with an encoder-decoder architecture are employed to compute personalized FNs from resting-state fMRI data without utilizing any external supervision by optimizing functional homogeneity of personalized FNs in a self-supervised setting. We demonstrate that a DL model trained on fMRI scans from the Human Connectome Project can identify canonical FNs and generalizes well across four different datasets. We further demonstrate that the identified personalized FNs are informative for predicting individual differences in behavior, brain development, and schizophrenia status. Taken together, self-supervised DL allows for rapid, generalizable computation of personalized FNs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461829" rel="alternate" title="Computing personalized brain functional networks from fMRI using self-supervised deep learning (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461758</id><title>‘Wanting’ versus ‘Needing’ related value: an fMRI meta-analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.441538+00:00</updated><author><name>J Bosulu</name></author><author><name>M.-A. Allaire</name></author><author><name>L. Tremblay-Grénier</name></author><author><name>Y. Luo</name></author><author><name>S. Eickhoff</name></author><author><name>S. Hétu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Consumption and its excesses are sometimes explained by imbalance of need or lack of control over ‘wanting’. ‘Wanting’ assigns value to cues that predict rewards, whereas ‘needing’ assigns value to biologically significant stimuli that one is deprived of. Here we aimed at studying how the brain activation patterns related to value of ‘wanted’ stimuli differs from that of ‘needed’ stimuli using ALE neuroimaging meta-analysis approaches. We used the perception of a cue predicting a reward for ‘wanting’ related value and the perception of food stimuli in a hungry state as a model for ‘needing’ related value. We carried out separate, contrasts, and conjunction meta-analyses to identify differences and similarities between ‘wanting’ and ‘needing’ values. Our overall results for ‘wanting’ related value show consistent activation of the ventral tegmental area, striatum and pallidum, regions that both activate behaviour and direct choice; while for ‘needing’ related value we found an overall consistent activation of the middle insula and to some extent the caudal-ventral putamen, regions that only direct choice. Our study suggests that wanting has more control on consumption, and a needed stimuli must become wanted in order to be pursued.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461758" rel="alternate" title="‘Wanting’ versus ‘Needing’ related value: an fMRI meta-analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461710</id><title>Aging reduces calreticulin expression and alters spontaneous calcium signals in astrocytic endfeet of the mouse dorsolateral striatum (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.442144+00:00</updated><author><name>Sara M. Zarate</name></author><author><name>Taylor E. Huntington</name></author><author><name>Pooneh Bagher</name></author><author><name>Rahul Srinivasan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging-related impairment of the blood brain barrier (BBB) and neurovascular unit (NVU) increases risk for neurodegeneration. Among the various cells participating in BBB and NVU function, spontaneous Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals in astrocytic endfeet are crucial for maintaining BBB and NVU integrity. To assess if aging is associated with changes in spontaneous Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals within astrocytic endfeet of the dorsolateral striatum (DLS), we expressed a genetically encoded Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; indicator, Lck-GCaMP6f in DLS astrocytes of young (3-4 month) and aging (20-24 month) mice. Compared to young mice, endfeet in the DLS of aging mice demonstrated a decrease in calreticulin (CALR) expression, and dramatic alterations in the dynamics of endfoot membrane-associated and mitochondrial Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals. While young mice required both extracellular and endoplasmic reticulum (ER) Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; sources for generating endfoot Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals, aging mice showed exclusive dependence on ER Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;. These data suggest that aging is associated with significant changes in Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; buffers and Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals within astrocytic endfeet, which has important implications for understanding mechanisms involved in aging-related impairment of the BBB and NVU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461710v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aging mice show reduced calreticulin expression in astrocytic endfeet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aging astrocytic endfeet show dramatic changes in spontaneous Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; activity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals in aging endfeet depend exclusively on endoplasmic reticulum Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461710" rel="alternate" title="Aging reduces calreticulin expression and alters spontaneous calcium signals in astrocytic endfeet of the mouse dorsolateral striatum (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462203</id><title>Numb reduces Tau levels and prevents neurodegeneration in mouse models of tauopathy in an isoform-specific manner (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.442350+00:00</updated><author><name>Marine Lacomme</name></author><author><name>Sarah C. Hales</name></author><author><name>Katarina Stevanovic</name></author><author><name>Christine Jolicoeur</name></author><author><name>Therence Bois</name></author><author><name>Jenny Cai</name></author><author><name>Melissa Desrosiers</name></author><author><name>Deniz Dalkara</name></author><author><name>Michel Cayouette</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accumulation of the microtubule-associated protein Tau is linked to neuronal cell death in tauopathies, but how exactly intraneuronal Tau levels are regulated in health and disease remains unclear. Here we identify the trafficking adaptor protein Numb as an essential regulator of Tau homeostasis. Conditional inactivation of Numb in retinal ganglion cells (RGCs) increases monomeric and oligomeric Tau levels, leading to axonal blebbing followed by neuronal cell loss in aged mice. Moreover, in a mouse model of tauopathy, inactivation of Numb in RGCs and spinal motoneurons accelerates neurodegeneration, and leads to precocious hindlimb paralysis. Conversely, overexpression of the long isoform of Numb (Numb-72), but not other isoforms, decreases intracellular Tau levels by promoting the extracellular release of monomeric Tau, and AAV-mediated delivery of Numb-72 in RGCs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; prevents neurodegeneration in two different mouse models of tauopathy. Taken together, these results uncover Numb as a modulator of intracellular Tau levels and identify Numb-72 as a novel therapeutic factor for tauopathies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462203" rel="alternate" title="Numb reduces Tau levels and prevents neurodegeneration in mouse models of tauopathy in an isoform-specific manner (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462032</id><title>Mapping Spatial Frequency Preferences Across Human Primary Visual Cortex (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.442556+00:00</updated><author><name>William F. Broderick</name></author><author><name>Eero P. Simoncelli</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Winawer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurons in primate visual cortex (area V1) are tuned for spatial frequency, in a manner that depends on their position in the visual field. Several studies have examined this dependency using fMRI, reporting preferred spatial frequencies (tuning curve peaks) of V1 voxels as a function of eccentricity, but their results differ by as much as two octaves, presumably due to differences in stimuli, measurements, and analysis methodology. Here, we characterize spatial frequency tuning at a millimeter resolution within human primary visual cortex, across stimulus orientation and visual field locations. We measured fMRI responses to a novel set of stimuli, constructed as sinusoidal gratings in log-polar coordinates, which include circular, radial, and spiral geometries. For each individual stimulus, the local spatial frequency varies inversely with eccentricity, and for any given location in the visual field, the full set of stimuli span a broad range of spatial frequencies and orientations. Over the measured range of eccentricities, the preferred spatial frequency is well-fit by a function that varies as the inverse of the eccentricity plus a small constant. We also find small but systematic effects of local stimulus orientation, defined in both absolute coordinates and relative to visual field location. Specifically, peak spatial frequency is higher for tangential than radial orientations and for horizontal than vertical orientations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462032" rel="alternate" title="Mapping Spatial Frequency Preferences Across Human Primary Visual Cortex (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461926</id><title>The role of complex IV activity in the axonal response of mitochondria to demyelination in experimental disease models of multiple sclerosis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.443342+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Licht-Mayer</name></author><author><name>Graham R. Campbell</name></author><author><name>Arpan R. Mehta</name></author><author><name>Katie McGill</name></author><author><name>Alex Symonds</name></author><author><name>Sarah Al-Azki</name></author><author><name>Gareth Pryce</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Zandee</name></author><author><name>Chao Zhao</name></author><author><name>Markus Kipp</name></author><author><name>Kenneth J Smith</name></author><author><name>David Baker</name></author><author><name>Daniel Altmann</name></author><author><name>Stephen M. Anderton</name></author><author><name>Yolanda S. Kap</name></author><author><name>Jon D. Laman</name></author><author><name>Bert A. ‘t Hart</name></author><author><name>Moses Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Robin J.M. Franklin</name></author><author><name>Siddharthan Chandran</name></author><author><name>Hans Lassmann</name></author><author><name>Bruce D. Trapp</name></author><author><name>Don J. Mahad</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Axon loss is a cardinal neuropathological feature of multiple sclerosis (MS). Axonal injury in MS and experimental disease models is most frequently detected in acutely demyelinating regions. Furthermore, acute axonal injury consistently correlates with the extent of inflammatory demyelination. Following lysolecithin-induced demyelination, we recently reported a compensatory response in neurons, where mitochondria move from the cell body to the acutely demyelinated axon and increase the mitochondrial content. We termed this energetics phenomenon, that is also evident in MS, the axonal response of mitochondria to demyelination (ARMD). In the present study, we assessed axonal mitochondrial content as well as axonal mitochondrial respiratory chain complex IV activity (COX) of axons and related these to axonal injury in nine different experimental disease models. We consistently found ARMD in all experimental disease models. However, the increase in mitochondrial content within demyelinated axons was not always accompanied by a proportionate increase in COX activity, particularly in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE). Axonal COX activity inversely correlated with the extent of axonal injury in experimental disease models. Our findings indicate that ARMD is a consistent and prominent finding and emphasises the need to preserve axonal mitochondrial COX activity in inflammatory demyelination, paving the way for the development of novel neuroprotective therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461926" rel="alternate" title="The role of complex IV activity in the axonal response of mitochondria to demyelination in experimental disease models of multiple sclerosis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461600</id><title>UCHL1 inhibited by A1 astrocytes facilitates aggregates clearance to promote neural stem cells activation after spinal cord injury (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.443831+00:00</updated><author><name>Lu Ding</name></author><author><name>Weiwei Chu</name></author><author><name>Yu Xia</name></author><author><name>Tian Li</name></author><author><name>Ming Shi</name></author><author><name>Feng-Quan Zhou</name></author><author><name>David Y.B. Deng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinal cord injury (SCI) is a devastating central nervous system (CNS) disease with no satisfying therapies available. Mobilizing endogenous neural stem cells (NSCs) to trigger intrinsic regeneration exhibits promising potentials for SCI repair. However, neurogenesis from endogenous NSCs is extremely restricted in the non-neurogenic spinal cord after SCI. Accumulation of protein aggregates has been shown to impede quiescent NSCs activation and the subsequent neurogenesis. Here, we found that ubiquitin c-terminal hydrolase l-1 (UCHL1), a deubiquitinating enzyme, functioned to regulate NSCs activation and neurogenesis by reducing protein aggregations through ubiquitin-proteasome pathway (UPP) in vitro. Upregulation of UCHL1 in spinal cord NSCs of rats with complete transection SCI efficiently enhanced NSCs proliferation and neurogenesis, leading to significantly improved functional outcomes. Based on protein microarray analysis of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), our results revealed that A1 reactive astrocytes acted to restrict NSCs neurogenesis by negatively regulating UCHL1-depentdent protein aggregates removal via the C3/Nrf2 signaling. Indeed, blockade of A1 astrocytes using neutralizing antibodies after SCI also led to NSCs activation, increased neurogenesis and remarkably enhanced motor function recovery. This study not only revealed a novel mechanism regulating NSCs-medicated neurogenesis in the spinal cord, but also provided new molecular targets for neural repair strategies after SCI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461600v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;UCHL1 facilitates NSCs activation by clearing intracellular protein aggregates through ubiquitin-proteasome approach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A1 reactive astrocytes result in down-regulation of UCHL1 to inhibit spinal NSCs activation by C3 after SCI&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overexpression of UCHL1 or blockade of A1 astrocytes lead to NSCs activation and neurons formation to promote SCI repair via UCHL1-proteasome pathway&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461600" rel="alternate" title="UCHL1 inhibited by A1 astrocytes facilitates aggregates clearance to promote neural stem cells activation after spinal cord injury (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461281</id><title>Urethane Anesthesia Exhibits Neurophysiological Correlates of Unconsciousness and is Distinct from Sleep (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.444472+00:00</updated><author><name>Alejandra Mondino</name></author><author><name>Joaquín González</name></author><author><name>Duan Li</name></author><author><name>Diego Mateos</name></author><author><name>Lucía Osorio</name></author><author><name>Matías Cavelli</name></author><author><name>Alicia Costa</name></author><author><name>Giancarlo Vanini</name></author><author><name>George Mashour</name></author><author><name>Pablo Torterolo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Urethane is a general anesthetic widely used in animal research. It is unique among anesthetics because urethane anesthesia alternates between macroscopically distinct electrographic states: a slow-wave state that resembles NREM sleep (NREMure), and an activated state with features of both REM sleep and wakefulness (REMure). However, the relationship between urethane anesthesia and physiological sleep is still unclear. In this study, electroencephalography (EEG) and electromyography were recorded in chronically prepared rats during natural sleep-wake states and during urethane anesthesia. We subsequently analyzed the EEG signatures associated with the loss of consciousness and found that, in comparison to natural sleep-wake states, the power, coherence, directed connectivity and complexity of brain oscillations are distinct during urethane. We also demonstrate that both urethane states have clear EEG signatures of general anesthesia. Thus, despite superficial similarities that have led others to conclude that urethane is a model of sleep, the electrocortical traits of depressed and activated states during urethane anesthesia differ from physiological sleep states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461281" rel="alternate" title="Urethane Anesthesia Exhibits Neurophysiological Correlates of Unconsciousness and is Distinct from Sleep (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461534</id><title>The structural basis of huntingtin (Htt) fibril polymorphism, revealed by cryo-EM of exon 1 Htt fibrils (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.444749+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergey Nazarov</name></author><author><name>Anass Chiki</name></author><author><name>Driss Boudeffa</name></author><author><name>Hilal A. Lashuel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The lack of detailed insight into the structure of aggregates formed by the huntingtin protein has hampered efforts to develop therapeutics and diagnostics targeting pathology formation in the brain of patients with Huntington’s disease. To address this knowledge gap, we investigated the structural properties of in vitro generated fibrils from exon1 of the huntingtin protein by electron cryo-microscopy and single-particle analysis. We show that wildtype and mutant exon1 of the huntingtin protein form non-helical fibrils with a polygultamine amyloid core composed of β-hairpins with unique characteristics that have not been previously observed with other amyloid filaments. The stacks of β-hairpins form long planar β- sheets (protofilaments) with variable stacking angle and occasional out-of-register state of individual β-hairpins. These features and the propensity of protofilament to undergo lateral association results in a high degree of fibril polymorphism, including fibrils composed of varying numbers of protofilaments. Our results also represent the first direct observation of how the flanking domains are organized around the polyglutamine core of the fibril and provide insight into how they might affect huntingtin fibril structure, polymorphism, and stacking of β-hairpins within its core structure. Removal of the first 17 amino acids at the N-terminus resulted in surprising intra-fibril structural heterogeneity and reduced fibril’s propensity to lateral associations. Overall, this work provides valuable insights that could guide future mechanistic studies to elucidate the sequence and structural determinants of huntingtin aggregation, as well as cryo-EM and structural studies of fibrils derived from huntingtin proteins and other disease-associated polyglutamine-containing proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461534" rel="alternate" title="The structural basis of huntingtin (Htt) fibril polymorphism, revealed by cryo-EM of exon 1 Htt fibrils (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461408</id><title>Blind cavefish retain functional connectivity in the tectum despite loss of retinal input (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.445021+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Brittnee McDole</name></author><author><name>Martin Privat</name></author><author><name>James B. Jaggard</name></author><author><name>Erik Duboué</name></author><author><name>German Sumbre</name></author><author><name>Alex Keene</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sensory systems display remarkable plasticity and are under strong evolutionary selection. The Mexican cavefish, &lt;italic&gt;Astyanax mexicanus&lt;/italic&gt;, consists of eyed river-dwelling surface populations, and multiple independent cave populations which have converged on eye loss, providing the opportunity to examine the evolution of sensory circuits in response to environmental perturbation. Functional analysis across multiple transgenic populations expressing GCaMP6s showed that functional connectivity of the optic tectum largely did not differ between populations, except for the selective loss of negatively correlated activity within the cavefish tectum, suggesting positively correlated neural activity is resistant to an evolved loss of input from the retina. Further, analysis of surface-cave hybrid fish reveals that changes in the tectum are genetically distinct from those encoding eye-loss. Together, these findings uncover the independent evolution of multiple components of the visual system and establish the use of functional imaging in &lt;italic&gt;A. mexicanus&lt;/italic&gt; to study neural circuit evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461408" rel="alternate" title="Blind cavefish retain functional connectivity in the tectum despite loss of retinal input (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461236</id><title>A Purkinje cell to parabrachial nucleus pathway enables broad cerebellar influence over the forebrain and emotional valence (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.445336+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher H. Chen</name></author><author><name>Leannah N. Newman</name></author><author><name>Amanda P. Stark</name></author><author><name>Katherine E. Bond</name></author><author><name>Dawei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Kefiloe Mutume</name></author><author><name>Isabella Flaquer</name></author><author><name>Wade G. Regehr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In addition to its well-known contributions to motor control and motor learning, the cerebellum is involved in language, emotional regulation, anxiety, and affect&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;. We found that suppressing the firing of cerebellar Purkinje cells (PCs) rapidly excites forebrain areas that could contribute to such functions, including the amygdala, basal forebrain, and septum, but that the classic cerebellar outputs, the deep cerebellar nuclei (DCN), do not project to these regions. Here we show that parabrachial nuclei (PBN) neurons that receive direct PC input, project to and influence all of these forebrain regions and many others. Furthermore, the function of this pathway is distinct from the canonical pathway: suppressing PC to PBN activity is aversive, whereas suppressing the PC to DCN pathway is rewarding. Therefore, the PBN pathway allows the cerebellum to influence the entire spectrum of valence, modulate the activity of forebrain regions known to regulate diverse nonmotor behaviors, and may be the substrate for many nonmotor disorders related to cerebellar dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461236" rel="alternate" title="A Purkinje cell to parabrachial nucleus pathway enables broad cerebellar influence over the forebrain and emotional valence (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462177</id><title>Towards real-world neuroscience using mobile EEG and augmented reality (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.445605+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Krugliak</name></author><author><name>Alex Clarke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our visual environment impacts multiple aspects of cognition including perception, attention and memory, yet most studies traditionally remove or control the external environment. As a result, we have a limited understanding of neurocognitive processes beyond the controlled lab environment. Here, we aim to study neural processes in real-world environments, while also maintaining a degree of control over perception. To achieve this, we combined mobile EEG (mEEG) and augmented reality (AR), which allows us to place virtual objects into the real world. We validated this AR and mEEG approach using a well-characterised cognitive response - the face inversion effect. Participants viewed upright and inverted faces in three EEG tasks (1) a lab-based computer task, (2) walking through an indoor environment while seeing face photographs, and (3) walking through an indoor environment while seeing virtual faces. We find greater low frequency EEG activity for inverted compared to upright faces in all experimental tasks, demonstrating that cognitively relevant signals can be extracted from mEEG and AR paradigms. This was established in both an epoch-based analysis aligned to face events, and a GLM-based approach that incorporates continuous EEG signals and face perception states. Together, this research helps pave the way to exploring neurocognitive processes in real-world environments while maintaining experimental control using AR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462177" rel="alternate" title="Towards real-world neuroscience using mobile EEG and augmented reality (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462800</id><title>Molecular structure and conformation of stereocilia tip-links elucidated by cryo-electron tomography (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.470917+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes Elferich</name></author><author><name>Sarah Clark</name></author><author><name>Jingpeng Ge</name></author><author><name>April Goehring</name></author><author><name>Aya Matsui</name></author><author><name>Eric Gouaux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanosensory transduction (MT), the conversion of mechanical stimuli into electrical signals, underpins hearing and balance and is carried out within hair cells in the inner ear. Hair cells harbor actin-filled stereocilia, arranged in rows of descending heights, where the tips of stereocilia are connected to their taller neighbors by a filament composed of protocadherin 15 (PCDH15) and cadherin 23 (CDH23), deemed the ‘tip-link’. Tension exerted on the tip-link opens an ion channel at the tip of the shorter stereocilia, thus converting mechanical force into an electrical signal. While biochemical and structural studies have provided insights into the molecular composition and structure of isolated portions of the tip-link, the architecture, location and conformational states of intact tip-links, on stereocilia, remains unknown. Here we report &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; cryo-electron microscopy imaging of the tip-link in mouse stereocilia. We observe individual PCDH15 molecules at the tip and shaft of stereocilia and determine their stoichiometry, conformational heterogeneity, and their complexes with CDH23. The PCDH15/CDH23 complexes occur in clusters, frequently with more than one copy of PCDH15 at the tip of stereocilia, suggesting that tip-links might consist of more than one copy of the PCDH15/CDH23 heterotetramer and by extension, might include multiple MT complexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462800" rel="alternate" title="Molecular structure and conformation of stereocilia tip-links elucidated by cryo-electron tomography (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462410</id><title>Moderate prenatal alcohol exposure modifies sex-specific CRFR1 activity in the central amygdala and anxiety-like behavior in adolescent offspring (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.472025+00:00</updated><author><name>Siara Kate Rouzer</name></author><author><name>Marvin R. Diaz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anxiety disorders are highly prevalent among individuals with a history of prenatal alcohol exposure (PAE), and adolescent rodents demonstrate anxiety-like behavior following moderate PAE on Gestational Day (G) 12. A likely systemic target of PAE is the stress peptide corticotrophin-releasing factor (CRF), as activation of CRF receptor 1 (CRFR1) in the medial nucleus of the central amygdala (CeM) is known to increase anxiety-like behavior in adults. To determine if CRF-CRFR1 interactions underly PAE-induced anxiety, functional changes in CRF system activity were investigated in adolescent male and female Sprague Dawley rats following G12 PAE. Compared to air-exposed controls, PAE increased basal spontaneous (s) inhibitory post-synaptic current (IPSC) frequency in the CeM of males, but not females. Furthermore, PAE blunted CRFR1-regulated miniature (m) IPSCs in a sex- and dose-specific manner, and only PAE males demonstrated tonic CRFR1 activity in the CeM. It was further determined that G12 PAE decreased CRFR1 mRNA in the CeM of males while increasing regional expression in females. Finally, infusion of a CRFR1 agonist into the CeM of adolescents produced a blunted expression of CRFR1-induced anxiety-like behavior exclusively in PAE males, mirroring the blunted physiology demonstrated by PAE males. Cumulatively, these data suggest that CRFR1 function within the CeM is age- and sex-specific, and PAE not only increases the expression of anxiety-like behavior, but may reduce the efficacy of treatment for PAE-induced anxiety through CRFR1-associated mechanisms. Therefore, future research will be necessary to develop targeted treatment of anxiety disorders in individuals with a history of PAE.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462410" rel="alternate" title="Moderate prenatal alcohol exposure modifies sex-specific CRFR1 activity in the central amygdala and anxiety-like behavior in adolescent offspring (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461520</id><title>On the edge of criticality: strength-dependent perturbation unveils delicate balance between fluctuation and oscillation in brain dynamics (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.473816+00:00</updated><author><name>Yonatan Sanz Perl</name></author><author><name>Anira Escrichs</name></author><author><name>Enzo Tagliazucchi</name></author><author><name>Morten L. Kringelbach</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Deco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Going beyond previous research, we use strength-dependent perturbation to obtain a deeper understanding of the mechanisms underlying the emergence of large-scale brain activity. Despite decades of research, we still have a shallow understanding of the role and generating mechanisms of the ubiquitous fluctuations and oscillations found in recordings of brain dynamics. Here, we used global strength-dependent perturbation to give a causal mechanistic description of human brain function providing a delicate balance between fluctuation and oscillation on the edge of criticality. After application of precise local strength-dependent perturbations and measuring the well-known perturbative complexity index, we demonstrated that the overall balance is shifted towards a fluctuating regime which is superior in terms of enhancing different functional networks compared to the oscillatory regime. This framework can generate specific, testable empirical predictions to be tested in human stimulation studies with strength-dependent rather than constant perturbation. Overall, our novel strength-dependent perturbation framework demonstrates that the human brain is poised on the edge of criticality, between fluctuations to oscillations, allowing for maximal flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461520" rel="alternate" title="On the edge of criticality: strength-dependent perturbation unveils delicate balance between fluctuation and oscillation in brain dynamics (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461464</id><title>Neonatal multi-modal cortical profiles predict 18-month developmental outcomes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.474813+00:00</updated><author><name>Daphna Fenchel</name></author><author><name>Ralica Dimitrova</name></author><author><name>Emma C. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Dafnis Batalle</name></author><author><name>Andrew Chew</name></author><author><name>Shona Falconer</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Kyriakopoulou</name></author><author><name>Chiara Nosarti</name></author><author><name>Jana Hutter</name></author><author><name>Daan Christiaens</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Pietsch</name></author><author><name>Jakki Brandon</name></author><author><name>Emer J. Hughes</name></author><author><name>Joanna Allsop</name></author><author><name>Camilla O’Keeffe</name></author><author><name>Anthony N. Price</name></author><author><name>Lucilio Cordero-Grande</name></author><author><name>Andreas Schuh</name></author><author><name>Antonios Makropoulos</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Passerat-Palmbach</name></author><author><name>Jelena Bozek</name></author><author><name>Daniel Rueckert</name></author><author><name>Joseph V. Hajnal</name></author><author><name>Grainne McAlonan</name></author><author><name>A. David Edwards</name></author><author><name>Jonathan O’Muircheartaigh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Developmental delays in infanthood often persist, turning into life-long difficulties, and coming at great cost for the individual and community. By examining the developing brain and its relation to developmental outcomes we can start to elucidate how the emergence of brain circuits is manifested in variability of infant motor, cognitive and behavioural capacities. In this study, we examined if cortical structural covariance at birth, indexing coordinated development, is related to later infant behaviour. We included 193 healthy term-born infants from the Developing Human Connectome Project (dHCP). An individual cortical connectivity matrix derived from morphological and microstructural features was computed for each subject (morphometric similarity networks, MSNs) and was used as input for prediction of behavioural scores at 18 months using Connectome-Based Predictive Modeling (CPM). Neonatal MSNs successfully predicted language and social-emotional performance. Predictive edges were distributed between and within known functional cortical divisions with a specific important role for primary and posterior cortical regions. These results reveal that multi-modal neonatal cortical profiles showing coordinated maturation are related to developmental outcomes and that network organization at birth provides an early infrastructure for future functional skills.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461464" rel="alternate" title="Neonatal multi-modal cortical profiles predict 18-month developmental outcomes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461864</id><title>A Neuromuscular Model of Human Locomotion Combines Spinal Reflex Circuits with Voluntary Movements (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.476692+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachid Ramadan</name></author><author><name>Hartmut Geyer</name></author><author><name>John J. Jeka</name></author><author><name>Gregor Schöner</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Reimann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Existing models of human walking use low-level reflexes or neural oscillators to generate movement. While appropriate to generate the stable, rhythmic movement patterns of steady-state walking, these models lack the ability to change their movement patterns or spontaneously generate new movements in the specific, goal-directed way characteristic of voluntary movements. Here we present a neuromuscular model of human locomotion that bridges this gap and combines the ability to execute goal directed movements with the generation of stable, rhythmic movement patterns that are required for robust locomotion. The model represents goals for voluntary movements of the swing leg on the task level of swing leg joint kinematics. Smooth movements plans towards the goal configuration are generated on the task level and transformed into descending motor commands that execute the planned movements, using internal models. The movement goals and plans are updated in real time based on sensory feedback and task constraints. On the spinal level, the descending commands during the swing phase are integrated with a generic stretch reflex for each muscle. Stance leg control solely relies on dedicated spinal reflex pathways. Spinal reflexes stimulate Hill-type muscles that actuate a biomechanical model with eight internal joints and six free-body degrees of freedom. The model is able to generate voluntary, goal-directed reaching movements with the swing leg and combine multiple movements in a rhythmic sequence. During walking, the swing leg is moved in a goal-directed manner to a target that is updated in real-time based on sensory feedback to maintain upright balance, while the stance leg is stabilized by low-level reflexes and a behavioral organization switching between swing and stance control for each leg. With this combination of reflexive stance leg and voluntary, goal-directed control of the swing leg, the model controller generates rhythmic, stable walking patterns in which the swing leg movement can be flexibly updated in real-time to step over or around obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461864" rel="alternate" title="A Neuromuscular Model of Human Locomotion Combines Spinal Reflex Circuits with Voluntary Movements (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461996</id><title>Rapid parameter estimation for selective inversion recovery myelin imaging using an open-source Julia toolkit (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.477067+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas J. Sisco</name></author><author><name>Ping Wang</name></author><author><name>Ashley Stokes</name></author><author><name>Richard Dortch</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is used extensively to quantify myelin content, however computational bottlenecks remain challenging for advanced imaging techniques in clinical settings. We present a fast, open-source toolkit for processing quantitative magnetization transfer derived from selective inversion recovery (SIR) acquisitions that allows parameter map estimation, including the myelin-sensitive macromolecular pool size ratio (&lt;italic&gt;PSR&lt;/italic&gt;). Significant progress has been made in reducing SIR acquisition times to improve clinically feasibility. However, parameter map estimation from the resulting data remains computationally expensive. To overcome this computational limitation, we developed a computationally efficient, open-source toolkit implemented in the Julia language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To test the accuracy of this toolkit, we simulated SIR images with varying &lt;italic&gt;PSR&lt;/italic&gt; and spin-lattice relaxation time of the free water pool (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1f&lt;/sub&gt;) over a physiologically meaningful scale from 5 to 20% and 0.5 to 1.5 s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively. Rician noise was then added, and the parameter maps were estimated using our Julia toolkit. Probability density histogram plots and Lin’s concordance correlation coefficients (LCCC) were used to assess accuracy and precision of the fits to our known simulation data. To further mimic biological tissue, we generated five cross-linked bovine serum albumin (BSA) phantoms with concentrations that ranged from 1.25 to 20%. The phantoms were imaged at 3T using SIR, and data were fit to estimate &lt;italic&gt;PSR&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1f&lt;/sub&gt;. Similarly, a healthy volunteer was imaged at 3T, and SIR parameter maps were estimated to demonstrate the reduced computational time for a real-world clinical example.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Estimated SIR parameter maps from our Julia toolkit agreed with simulated values (LCCC&amp;gt; 0.98). This toolkit was further validated using BSA phantoms and a whole brain scan at 3T. In both cases, SIR parameter estimates were consistent with published values using MATLAB. However, compared to earlier work using MATLAB, our Julia toolkit provided an approximate 20-fold reduction in computational time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presented here, we developed a fast, open-source, toolkit for rapid and accurate SIR MRI using Julia. The reduction in computational cost should allow SIR parameters to be accessible in clinical settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461996" rel="alternate" title="Rapid parameter estimation for selective inversion recovery myelin imaging using an open-source Julia toolkit (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461242</id><title>A Comparison of Methods to Harmonize Cortical Thickness Measurements Across Scanners and Sites (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.477430+00:00</updated><author><name>Delin Sun</name></author><author><name>Gopalkumar Rakesh</name></author><author><name>Courtney C. Haswell</name></author><author><name>Mark Logue</name></author><author><name>C. Lexi Baird</name></author><author><name>Brian M. O’Leary</name></author><author><name>Andrew S. Cotton</name></author><author><name>Hong Xie</name></author><author><name>Marijo Tamburrino</name></author><author><name>Tian Chen</name></author><author><name>Emily L. Dennis</name></author><author><name>Neda Jahanshad</name></author><author><name>Lauren E. Salminen</name></author><author><name>Sophia I. Thomopoulos</name></author><author><name>Faisal Rashid</name></author><author><name>Christopher R. K. Ching</name></author><author><name>Saskia B. J. Koch</name></author><author><name>Jessie L. Frijling</name></author><author><name>Laura Nawijn</name></author><author><name>Mirjam van Zuiden</name></author><author><name>Xi Zhu</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Suarez-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Anika Sierk</name></author><author><name>Henrik Walter</name></author><author><name>Antje Manthey</name></author><author><name>Jennifer S. Stevens</name></author><author><name>Negar Fani</name></author><author><name>Sanne J.H. van Rooij</name></author><author><name>Murray Stein</name></author><author><name>Jessica Bomyea</name></author><author><name>Inga K. Koerte</name></author><author><name>Kyle Choi</name></author><author><name>Steven J.A. van der Werff</name></author><author><name>Robert R. J. M. Vermeiren</name></author><author><name>Julia Herzog</name></author><author><name>Lauren A. M. Lebois</name></author><author><name>Justin T. Baker</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth A. Olson</name></author><author><name>Thomas Straube</name></author><author><name>Mayuresh S. Korgaonkar</name></author><author><name>Elpiniki Andrew</name></author><author><name>Ye Zhu</name></author><author><name>Gen Li</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Ipser</name></author><author><name>Anna R. Hudson</name></author><author><name>Matthew Peverill</name></author><author><name>Kelly Sambrook</name></author><author><name>Evan Gordon</name></author><author><name>Lee Baugh</name></author><author><name>Gina Forster</name></author><author><name>Raluca M. Simons</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey S. Simons</name></author><author><name>Vincent Magnotta</name></author><author><name>Adi Maron-Katz</name></author><author><name>Stefan du Plessis</name></author><author><name>Seth G. Disner</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Davenport</name></author><author><name>Daniel W. Grupe</name></author><author><name>Jack B. Nitschke</name></author><author><name>Terri A. deRoon-Cassini</name></author><author><name>Jacklynn M. Fitzgerald</name></author><author><name>John H. Krystal</name></author><author><name>Ifat Levy</name></author><author><name>Miranda Olff</name></author><author><name>Dick J. Veltman</name></author><author><name>Li Wang</name></author><author><name>Yuval Neria</name></author><author><name>Michael D. De Bellis</name></author><author><name>Tanja Jovanovic</name></author><author><name>Judith K. Daniels</name></author><author><name>Martha Shenton</name></author><author><name>Nic J.A. van de Wee</name></author><author><name>Christian Schmahl</name></author><author><name>Milissa L. Kaufman</name></author><author><name>Isabelle M. Rosso</name></author><author><name>Scott R. Sponheim</name></author><author><name>David Bernd Hofmann</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Bryant</name></author><author><name>Kelene A. Fercho</name></author><author><name>Dan J. Stein</name></author><author><name>Sven C. Mueller</name></author><author><name>Bobak Hosseini</name></author><author><name>K. Luan Phan</name></author><author><name>Katie A. McLaughlin</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Davidson</name></author><author><name>Christine L. Larson</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey May</name></author><author><name>Steven M. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Chadi G. Abdallah</name></author><author><name>Hassaan Gomaa</name></author><author><name>Amit Etkin</name></author><author><name>Soraya Seedat</name></author><author><name>Ilan Harpaz-Rotem</name></author><author><name>Israel Liberzon</name></author><author><name>Theo G.M. van Erp</name></author><author><name>Xin Wang</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Rajendra A. Morey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Results of neuroimaging datasets aggregated from multiple sites may be biased by site- specific profiles in participants’ demographic and clinical characteristics, as well as MRI acquisition protocols and scanning platforms. We compared the impact of four different harmonization methods on results obtained from analyses of cortical thickness data: (1) linear mixed-effects model (LME) that models site-specific random intercepts (LME&lt;sub&gt;INT&lt;/sub&gt;), (2) LME that models both site-specific random intercepts and age-related random slopes (LME&lt;sub&gt;INT+SLP&lt;/sub&gt;), (3) ComBat, and (4) ComBat with a generalized additive model (ComBat-GAM). Our test case for comparing harmonization methods was cortical thickness data aggregated from 29 sites, which included 1,343 cases with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) (6.2-81.8 years old) and 2,067 trauma-exposed controls without PTSD (6.3-85.2 years old). We found that, compared to the other data harmonization methods, data processed with ComBat-GAM were more sensitive to the detection of significant case-control differences in regional cortical thickness (&lt;italic&gt;X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;(3) = 34.339, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; &amp;lt; 0.001), and case-control differences in age-related cortical thinning (&lt;italic&gt;X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;(3) = 15.128, &lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt; = 0.002). Specifically, ComBat-GAM led to larger effect size estimates of cortical thickness reductions (corrected &lt;italic&gt;p-values &amp;lt; 0.001&lt;/italic&gt;), smaller age-appropriate declines (corrected &lt;italic&gt;p-values &amp;lt; 0.001&lt;/italic&gt;), and lower female to male contrast (corrected &lt;italic&gt;p-values &amp;lt; 0.001&lt;/italic&gt;) in cases compared to controls relative to other harmonization methods. Harmonization with ComBat-GAM also led to greater estimates of age-related declines in cortical thickness (corrected &lt;italic&gt;p-values &amp;lt; 0.001&lt;/italic&gt;) in both cases and controls compared to other harmonization methods. Our results support the use of ComBat-GAM for harmonizing cortical thickness data aggregated from multiple sites and scanners to minimize confounds and increase statistical power.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461242" rel="alternate" title="A Comparison of Methods to Harmonize Cortical Thickness Measurements Across Scanners and Sites (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461383</id><title>NMDAr BLOCKING BY MK801 ALTERS HIPPOCAMPAL AND PREFRONTAL CORTEX OSCILLATIONS AND IMPAIRS SPATIAL WORKING MEMORY IN MICE (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.478531+00:00</updated><author><name>P. Abad-Perez</name></author><author><name>L. Martínez-Otero</name></author><author><name>V. Borrell</name></author><author><name>R. Redondo</name></author><author><name>J.R. Brotons-Mas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abnormal NMDAr function has been linked to rhythmopathies, psychosis, and cognitive dysfunction in schizophrenia. Here, we investigate the role of NMDAr hypofunction in pathological oscillations and behavior. We implanted mice with tetrodes in the dorsal hippocampus and medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) and administered them with the NMDAr antagonist MK801, recording oscillations during spontaneous exploration in an open field and in the y-maze spatial working memory test. Our results show that NMDAr blockade increased locomotor activity and impaired spatial working memory. The administration of MK801 disrupted the correlation between oscillations and speed of movement, crucial for internal representations of distance. In the hippocampus, MK801 impaired gamma oscillations and theta/gamma coupling, while in the mPFC, it increased the power of theta, gamma, and generated high-frequency oscillations (HFO 155-185 Hz). Spatial working memory tests in the y-maze revealed that theta/gamma coupling was consistently higher in correct trials. Theta/gamma co-modulation mediated by NMDAr function might be key to explain various of schizophrenia’s cognitive symptoms. Further investigating NMDAr hypofunction’s role in the emergence of aberrant oscillatory activity will improve our understanding of schizophrenia and inspire new treatments of psychiatric disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;–&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;NMDAr blockade increases motor behavior and impairs spatial working memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;–&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;NMDAr hypofunction differentially alters oscillatory activity in the hippocampus and PFC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;–&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;NMDAr blockade generates locally modulated high-frequency oscillations in the PFC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;–&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;Theta/gamma modulation, but also long-range theta/gamma modulation across CA1 and the PFC is involved in spatial working memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;label&gt;–&lt;/label&gt;&lt;p&gt;NMDAr blockade disrupts the correlation between theta/gamma co-modulation and spatial working memory performances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461383" rel="alternate" title="NMDAr BLOCKING BY MK801 ALTERS HIPPOCAMPAL AND PREFRONTAL CORTEX OSCILLATIONS AND IMPAIRS SPATIAL WORKING MEMORY IN MICE (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461384</id><title>Live Monitoring of Inflammation Reveals Tissue and Sex-specific Responses to Western Diet and Butyrate treatment (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.478711+00:00</updated><author><name>Raiza Bonomo</name></author><author><name>Sarah Talley</name></author><author><name>Jomana Hatahet</name></author><author><name>Chaitanya Gavini</name></author><author><name>Tyler Cook</name></author><author><name>Ben Chun</name></author><author><name>Pete Kekenes-Huskey</name></author><author><name>Gregory Aubert</name></author><author><name>Edward Campbell</name></author><author><name>Virginie Mansuy-Aubert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Obesity is a current epidemic, affecting millions of individuals worldwide. Chronic obesity is characterized by a low-grade systemic inflammation besides not being a classic inflammatory disease. Many studies have tried to identify inflammatory insults dysregulated by a Westernized diet – consisted of high fat, high sucrose, and high cholesterol –mainly focusing on production and secretion of inflammatory cytokines. The gut microbiome and derived metabolites, including the short-chain fatty acid butyrate, have received increased attention as underlying some of the obesogenic features. In the present work, we utilized a novel biosensor mouse model capable of monitoring in vivo inflammation. We observed tissue- and sex- specific caspase-1 activation patterns in obese mice and treated with butyrate. Our work utilizing a caspase-1 biosensor mouse model, flow cytometry and computational analyses and offers new mechanistic insights underlying the effect of butyrate in obesity and its complications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461384" rel="alternate" title="Live Monitoring of Inflammation Reveals Tissue and Sex-specific Responses to Western Diet and Butyrate treatment (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461385</id><title>Characterizing pupil dynamics coupling to brain state fluctuation based on lateral hypothalamic activity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.478927+00:00</updated><author><name>Kengo Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Filip Sobczak</name></author><author><name>Patricia Pais-Roldán</name></author><author><name>Xin Yu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pupil dynamics presents varied correlation features with brain activity under different vigilant levels. The modulation of brain state changes can arise from the lateral hypothalamus (LH), where diverse neuronal cell types contribute to arousal regulation in opposite directions via the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC). However, the relationship of the LH and pupil dynamics has seldom been investigated. Here, we performed local field potential (LFP) recordings at the LH and ACC, and the whole brain fMRI with simultaneous fiber photometry Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; recording in the ACC, to evaluate their correlation with brain state-dependent pupil dynamics. Both LFP and functional MRI (fMRI) data showed opposite correlation features to pupil dynamics, demonstrating an LH activity-dependent manner. Our results demonstrate that the correlation of pupil dynamics with ACC LFP and whole-brain fMRI signals depends on LH activity, indicating a role of the latter in brain state regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461385" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing pupil dynamics coupling to brain state fluctuation based on lateral hypothalamic activity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461935</id><title>The activities of LRRK2 and GCase are positively correlated in clinical biospecimens and experimental models of Parkinson’s disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.481103+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Kedariti</name></author><author><name>Emanuele Frattini</name></author><author><name>Pascale Baden</name></author><author><name>Susanna Cogo</name></author><author><name>Laura Civiero</name></author><author><name>Elena Ziviani</name></author><author><name>Massimo Aureli</name></author><author><name>Alice Kaganovich</name></author><author><name>Mark R Cookson</name></author><author><name>Leonidas Stefanis</name></author><author><name>Matthew Surface</name></author><author><name>Michela Deleidi</name></author><author><name>Alessio Di Fonzo</name></author><author><name>Roy N. Alcalay</name></author><author><name>Hardy Rideout</name></author><author><name>Elisa Greggio</name></author><author><name>Nicoletta Plotegher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;LRRK2 is a kinase involved in different cellular functions, including autophagy, endolysosomal pathways and vesicle trafficking. Mutations in &lt;italic&gt;LRRK2&lt;/italic&gt; cause autosomal dominant forms of Parkinson’s disease (PD). Heterozygous mutations in &lt;italic&gt;GBA1&lt;/italic&gt;, the gene encoding the lysosomal enzyme glucocerebrosidase (GCase), are the most common genetic risk factors for PD. Moreover, GCase function is altered in idiopathic PD and in other genetic forms of the disease. Recent work suggests that LRRK2 kinase activity can regulate GCase function. However, both a positive and a negative correlation have been described. To gain insights into the impact of LRRK2 on GCase, we investigated GCase levels and activity in &lt;italic&gt;LRRK2&lt;/italic&gt; G2019S knockin mice, in clinical biospecimens from PD patients carrying this mutation and in patient-derived cellular models. In these models we found a positive correlation between the activities of LRRK2 and GCase, which was further confirmed in cell lines with genetic and pharmacological manipulation of LRRK2 kinase activity. Overall, our study indicates that LRRK2 kinase activity affects both the levels and the catalytic activity of GCase.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461935" rel="alternate" title="The activities of LRRK2 and GCase are positively correlated in clinical biospecimens and experimental models of Parkinson’s disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461922</id><title>Cell and circuit origins of fast network oscillations in the mammalian main olfactory bulb (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.482321+00:00</updated><author><name>Shawn D. Burton</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel N. Urban</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural synchrony generates fast network oscillations throughout the brain, including the main olfactory bulb (MOB), the first processing station of the olfactory system. Identifying the mechanisms synchronizing neurons in the MOB will be key to understanding how network oscillations support the coding of a high-dimensional sensory space. Here, using paired recordings and optogenetic activation of glomerular sensory inputs in MOB slices, we uncovered profound differences in principal mitral cell (MC) vs. tufted cell (TC) spike-time synchrony: TCs robustly synchronized across fast- and slow-gamma frequencies, while MC synchrony was weaker and concentrated in slow-gamma frequencies. Synchrony among both cell types was enhanced by shared glomerular input but was independent of intraglomerular lateral excitation. Cell-type differences in synchrony could also not be traced to any difference in the synchronization of synaptic inhibition. Instead, greater TC than MC synchrony paralleled the more periodic firing among resonant TCs than MCs and emerged in patterns consistent with densely synchronous network oscillations. Collectively, our results thus reveal a mechanism for parallel processing of sensory information in the MOB via differential TC vs. MC synchrony, and further contrast mechanisms driving fast network oscillations in the MOB from those driving the sparse synchronization of irregularly-firing principal cells throughout cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461922" rel="alternate" title="Cell and circuit origins of fast network oscillations in the mammalian main olfactory bulb (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461495</id><title>Pathological and metabolic underpinnings of energetic inefficiency in temporal lobe epilepsy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.482725+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaosong He</name></author><author><name>Lorenzo Caciagli</name></author><author><name>Linden Parkes</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Stiso</name></author><author><name>Teresa M. Karrer</name></author><author><name>Jason Z. Kim</name></author><author><name>Zhixin Lu</name></author><author><name>Tommaso Menara</name></author><author><name>Fabio Pasqualetti</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Sperling</name></author><author><name>Joseph I. Tracy</name></author><author><name>Dani S. Bassett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human brain consumes a disproportionate amount of energy to generate neural dynamics. Yet precisely how energetic processes are altered in neurological disorders remains far from understood. Here, we use network control theory to profile the brain’s energy landscape, describing the rich dynamical repertoire supported by the structural connectome. This approach allows us to estimate the energy required to activate a circuit, and determine which regions most support that activation. Focusing on temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE), we show that patients require more control energy to activate the limbic network than healthy volunteers, especially ipsilateral to the seizure focus. Further, greater energetic costs are largely localized to the ipsilateral temporo-limbic regions. Importantly, the energetic imbalance between ipsilateral and contralateral temporo-limbic regions is tracked by asymmetric metabolic patterns, which in turn are explained by asymmetric gray matter volume loss. In TLE, failure to meet the extra energy demands may lead to suboptimal brain dynamics and inadequate activation. Broadly, our investigation provides a theoretical framework unifying gray matter integrity, local metabolism, and energetic generation of neural dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461495" rel="alternate" title="Pathological and metabolic underpinnings of energetic inefficiency in temporal lobe epilepsy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461943</id><title>Overcoming the effect of ASH1L haploinsufficiency on stem cells amenability to genome editing and differentiation into the neuronal lineage – a technical report (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.483085+00:00</updated><author><name>Seon Hye Cheon</name></author><author><name>Foster D. Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Janay M. Vacharasin</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Marinelli</name></author><author><name>Collin Cheatle</name></author><author><name>Mikayla M. McCord</name></author><author><name>Kaitlin Cox</name></author><author><name>Sofia B. Lizarraga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome editing and neuronal differentiation protocols have proliferated in the last decade. Mutations in genes that control pluripotency could lead to a potential obstacle with regards to the survival and differentiation potential of the genome-edited cell lines. Here we describe a protocol for the generation, and differentiation, of cell lines containing CRISPR/Cas9 induced mutations in the histone methyl transferase ASH1L. This chromatin modifier was previously implicated in hematopoietic stem cell pluripotency and is a major genetic risk factor for autism spectrum disorders (ASD). We find that haploinsufficiency of ASH1L leads to decreased NANOG gene expression leading to reduce cell survival and increased spontaneous differentiation. We report a method that provides improved single-cell survival with higher colony formation efficiency in ASH1L mutant stem cells. Additionally, we describe a modified dual-SMAD inhibition neuronal induction methodology that permits the successful generation of human neurons with mutations in ASH1L, in a smaller scale than previously reported methods. With our modified CRISPR-genome editing and neuronal differentiation protocols, it is possible to generate genome-edited stem cells containing mutations in genes that impact pluripotency and could affect subsequent cell lineage specific differentiation. Our detailed technical report presents cost-effective strategies that will benefit researchers focusing on both translational and basic science using stem cell experimental systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461943" rel="alternate" title="Overcoming the effect of ASH1L haploinsufficiency on stem cells amenability to genome editing and differentiation into the neuronal lineage – a technical report (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462159</id><title>Light regulated SIK1 remodels the synaptic phosphoproteome to induce sleep (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.483738+00:00</updated><author><name>Lewis Taylor</name></author><author><name>Teele Palumaa</name></author><author><name>Paul K Reardon</name></author><author><name>Steven Walsh</name></author><author><name>Bradley H Johnson</name></author><author><name>Sabrina Liberatori</name></author><author><name>Sibah Hasan</name></author><author><name>Kristopher Clark</name></author><author><name>Philip Cohen</name></author><author><name>Sridhar Vasudevan</name></author><author><name>Stuart Peirson</name></author><author><name>Shabaz Mohammed</name></author><author><name>Vladyslav Vyazovskiy</name></author><author><name>Russell G Foster</name></author><author><name>Aarti Jagannath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The sleep and circadian systems act in concert to regulate sleep-wake timing, yet the molecular mechanisms that underpin their interaction to induce sleep remain unknown. Synaptic protein phosphorylation, driven by the kinase SIK3, correlates with sleep pressure, however it is unclear whether these phosphoproteome changes are causally responsible for inducing sleep. Here we show that the light-dependent activity of SIK1 controls the phosphorylation of a subset of the brain phosphoproteome to induce sleep in a manner that is independent of sleep pressure. By uncoupling phosphorylation and sleep induction from sleep pressure, we establish that synaptic protein phosphorylation provides a causal mechanism for the induction of sleep under different environmental contexts. Furthermore, we propose a framework that details how the salt-inducible kinases regulate the synaptic phosphoproteome to integrate exogenous and endogenous stimuli, thereby providing the molecular basis upon which the sleep and circadian systems interact to control the sleep-wake cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462159" rel="alternate" title="Light regulated SIK1 remodels the synaptic phosphoproteome to induce sleep (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462143</id><title>Hippocampal-prefrontal theta coupling develops as mice become proficient in associative odorant discrimination learning (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.484172+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Ramirez-Gordillo</name></author><author><name>Andrew A. Parra</name></author><author><name>K. Ulrich Bayer</name></author><author><name>Diego Restrepo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Learning and memory requires coordinated activity between different regions of the brain. Here we studied the interaction between medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) and hippocampal dorsal CA1 during associative odorant discrimination learning in the mouse. We found that as the animal learns to discriminate odorants in a go-no go task the coupling of high frequency neural oscillations to the phase of theta oscillations (phase-amplitude coupling or PAC) changes in a manner that results in divergence between rewarded and unrewarded odorant-elicited changes in the theta-phase referenced power (tPRP) for beta and gamma oscillations. In addition, in the proficient animal there was a decrease in the coordinated oscillatory activity between CA1 and mPFC in the presence of the unrewarded odorant. Furthermore, the changes in PAC resulted in a marked increase in the accuracy for decoding odorant identity from tPRP when the animal became proficient. Finally, we studied the role of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase II α (CaMKIIα), a protein involved in learning and memory, in oscillatory neural processing in this task. We find that the accuracy for decoding the odorant identity from tPRP decreases in CaMKIIα knockout mice and that this accuracy correlates with behavioral performance. These results implicate a role for PAC and CaMKIIα in olfactory go-no go associative learning in the hippocampal-prefrontal circuit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462143" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal-prefrontal theta coupling develops as mice become proficient in associative odorant discrimination learning (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.460866</id><title>Individual differences in behavioral flexibility predict future volitional ethanol consumption in mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.484366+00:00</updated><author><name>Ellen M Rodberg</name></author><author><name>Elena M Vazey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cognitive control is key to regulating alcohol intake and preventing relapse. Behavioral inflexibility can prevent adaptive strategies such as mindfulness or other relapse-prevention behaviors. In a mouse model we investigated whether individual variability in behavioral flexibility (using attentional set-shifting task; ASST) predicts future alcohol intake. Adult male and female C57BL/6J mice were subjected to ASST using a bowl digging paradigm where mice identify a baited bowl based on compound odor and textural cues. This was completed prior to any alcohol exposure. Individual performance across mice varied within the group. We integrated several metrics, specifically ASST stage completed, trials to completion and errors performed to produce an individual performance index measure of behavioral flexibility. After, ASST mice were trained to drink ethanol (15%, v/v, 1hr/day) for 3-4 weeks until intake stabilized. Using this prospective approach, we identified an inverse relationship between behavioral flexibility and drinking - less flexible mice had a propensity to consume more alcohol. Similar relationships have been identified previously in non-human primates and rats. Our results show that the relationship between alcohol and cognitive flexibility is a robust trait that is conserved across species and can be used in mice to study neural substrates underlying these behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="simple"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- ASST can be used to examine individual differences in cognitive function in mice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Behavioral inflexibility is related to future higher alcohol consumption&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Executive function can be used as a predictive risk factor for alcohol intake&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;- This relationship in mice supports previous findings across species&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.460866" rel="alternate" title="Individual differences in behavioral flexibility predict future volitional ethanol consumption in mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462075</id><title>Lip movements enhance speech representations and effective connectivity in speech dorsal stream and its relationship with neurite architecture (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.484515+00:00</updated><author><name>Lei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yi Du</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lip movements facilitate speech comprehension, especially under adverse listening conditions, but the neural mechanisms of this perceptual benefit at the phonemic and feature levels remain unclear. This fMRI study addresses this question by quantifying regional multivariate representation and network organization underlying audiovisual speech-in-noise perception. We found that valid lip movements enhanced neural representations of phoneme, place of articulation, or voicing feature of speech differentially in dorsal stream regions, including frontal speech motor areas and supramarginal gyrus. Such local changes were accompanied by strengthened dorsal stream effective connectivity. Moreover, the neurite orientation dispersion of left arcuate fasciculus, a structural basis of speech dorsal stream, predicted the visual enhancements of neural representations and effective connectivity. Our findings provide novel insight to speech science that lip movements promote both local phonemic and feature encoding and network connectivity in speech dorsal pathway and the functional enhancement is mediated by the microstructural architecture of the circuit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462075" rel="alternate" title="Lip movements enhance speech representations and effective connectivity in speech dorsal stream and its relationship with neurite architecture (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461912</id><title>GABAB receptor/HCN channel complexes in VTA dopamine neurons limit synaptic inhibition and prevent anxiety-like behavior (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.484659+00:00</updated><author><name>Enrique Pérez-Garci</name></author><author><name>Giorgio Rizzi</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Fritzius</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Porcu</name></author><author><name>Valerie Besseyrias</name></author><author><name>Martin Gassmann</name></author><author><name>Kelly R. Tan</name></author><author><name>Bernhard Bettler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aversive stimuli inhibiting dopamine neurons in the ventral tegmental area (DA&lt;sup&gt;VTA&lt;/sup&gt; neurons) induce anxiety-like behaviors. The inhibition of DA&lt;sup&gt;VTA&lt;/sup&gt; neurons is prolonged by GABA&lt;sub&gt;B&lt;/sub&gt; receptor (GBR)-activated K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-currents, which exhibit a rapid desensitization of unknown physiological relevance. We now report that GBRs associate via auxiliary KCTD16 subunits with HCN channels, which facilitates activation of hyperpolarization- activated currents (&lt;italic&gt;I&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt;) by GBR-activated K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; currents. Activation of &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; underlies rapid K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; current desensitization in DA&lt;sup&gt;VTA&lt;/sup&gt; neurons and limits GBR-mediated inhibition. Disruption of the GBR/HCN complex in &lt;italic&gt;KCTD16&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice or blockade of &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; prolongs optogenetically driven inhibition of DA&lt;sup&gt;VTA&lt;/sup&gt; neuron firing. &lt;italic&gt;KCTD16&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; mice exhibit an increased anxiety-like behavior in response to stressful stimuli, which is reproduced by &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; CRISPR/Cas9-mediated &lt;italic&gt;KCTD16&lt;/italic&gt; ablation in DA&lt;sup&gt;VTA&lt;/sup&gt; neurons or intra-VTA infusion of HCN antagonist to wild-type mice. Our data reveal that GBR-induced &lt;italic&gt;I&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; protect DA&lt;sup&gt;VTA&lt;/sup&gt; neurons from prolonged GBR- mediated inhibition in response to stressors, which moderates anxiety-like behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461912" rel="alternate" title="GABAB receptor/HCN channel complexes in VTA dopamine neurons limit synaptic inhibition and prevent anxiety-like behavior (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.458716</id><title>Astrocytic C-X-C motif chemokine ligand-1 mediates β-amyloid-induced synaptotoxicity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.484836+00:00</updated><author><name>Beatriz Gomez Perez-Nievas</name></author><author><name>Louisa Johnson</name></author><author><name>Paula Beltran-Lobo</name></author><author><name>Martina M. Hughes</name></author><author><name>Luciana Gammallieri</name></author><author><name>Francesca Tarsitano</name></author><author><name>Monika A Myszczynska</name></author><author><name>Irina Vazquez-Villasenor</name></author><author><name>Maria Jimenez-Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Claire Troakes</name></author><author><name>Stephen B. Wharton</name></author><author><name>Laura Ferraiuolo</name></author><author><name>Wendy Noble</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pathological interactions between β-amyloid (Aβ) and tau drive the synapse loss that underlies neural circuit disruption and cognitive decline in Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Reactive astrocytes, displaying altered functions, are also a prominent feature of AD brain. This large and heterogeneous population of cells are increasingly recognised as contributing to early phases of disease. However, the contribution of astrocytes to detrimental Aβ-tau interactions in AD is not well understood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mouse and human astrocyte cultures were stimulated with concentrations and species of human Aβ that mimic those in human AD brain. Astrocyte conditioned medium was collected and immunodepleted of Aβ before being added to rodent or human neuron cultures. Cytokines, identified in unbiased screens were also applied to neurons, including following the pre-treatment of neurons with chemokine receptor antagonists. Tau mislocalisation, synaptic markers and dendritic spine numbers were measured in cultured neurons and organotypic brain slice cultures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conditioned medium from astrocytes stimulated with Aβ induces tau mislocalisation and exaggerated synaptotoxicity that is recapitulated following spiking of neuron culture medium with recombinant C-X-C motif chemokine ligand-1 (CXCL1), a chemokine we show to be upregulated in Alzheimer’s disease brain. Antagonism of neuronal C-X-C motif chemokine receptor 2 (CXCR2) prevented tau mislocalisation and synaptotoxicity in response to CXCL1 and Aβ-stimulated astrocyte secretions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our data indicate that astrocytes exacerbate tau mislocalisation and the synaptotoxic effects of Aβ via interactions of astrocytic CXCL1 and neuronal CXCR2 receptors, highlighting this chemokine-receptor pair as a novel target for therapeutic intervention in AD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.458716" rel="alternate" title="Astrocytic C-X-C motif chemokine ligand-1 mediates β-amyloid-induced synaptotoxicity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461263</id><title>LXR agonist Prevents Peripheral Neuropathy and modifies PNS immune cells in Aged Mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.485053+00:00</updated><author><name>Chaitanya K. Gavini</name></author><author><name>Nadia Elshareif</name></author><author><name>Anand V. Germanwala</name></author><author><name>Gregory Aubert</name></author><author><name>Nigel A. Calcutt</name></author><author><name>Virginie Mansuy-Aubert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Peripheral neuropathy is a common and progressive disorder in the elderly that interferes with daily activities and increases the risk of injury. It is of importance to find efficient treatments to treat or delay this age-related neurodegeneration. We previously demonstrated that activation of the cholesterol sensor Liver X receptor (LXR) with the potent agonist GW3965, alleviates pain in a diet-induced obesity model. Because cholesterol had also been linked to neuropathy during aging, we sought to test whether LXR activation may improve neuropathy and pain in aged mice by treating 21-month-old mice for 3 months with GW3965. Treatment resulted in a significant increase in nerve fibers of the sub-basal plexus, accompanied by a change in polarization, metabolism, and cholesterol content of macrophages in the sciatic nerve. These results suggest that activation of the LXR may block the progression of neuropathy associated with aging by modifying nerve-immune cell cholesterol, thereby providing new pathways to target in efforts to delay neuropathy during aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461263" rel="alternate" title="LXR agonist Prevents Peripheral Neuropathy and modifies PNS immune cells in Aged Mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461119</id><title>Mitophagy enhancers against phosphorylated Tau-induced mitochondrial and synaptic toxicities in Alzheimer disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.485274+00:00</updated><author><name>Sudhir Kshirsagar</name></author><author><name>Neha Sawant</name></author><author><name>Hallie Morton</name></author><author><name>Arubala P. Reddy</name></author><author><name>P. Hemachandra Reddy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of our study is to determine the protective effects of mitophagy enhancers against phosphorylated tau (P-tau)-induced mitochondrial and synaptic toxicities in Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Mitochondrial abnormalities, including defective mitochondrial dynamics, biogenesis, axonal transport and impaired clearance of dead mitochondria are linked to P-tau in AD. Mitophagy enhancers are potential therapeutic candidates to clear dead mitochondria and improve synaptic and cognitive functions in AD. We recently optimized the doses of mitophagy enhancers urolithin A, actinonin, tomatidine, nicotinamide riboside in immortalized mouse primary hippocampal (HT22) neurons. In the current study, we treated mutant Tau expressed in HT22 (mTau-HT22) cells with mitophagy enhancers and assessed mRNA and protein levels of mitochondrial/synaptic genes, cell survival and mitochondrial respiration. We also assessed mitochondrial morphology in mTau-HT22 cells treated and untreated with mitophagy enhancers. Mutant Tau-HT22 cells showed increased fission, decreased fusion, synaptic &amp;amp; mitophagy genes, reduced cell survival and defective mitochondrial respiration. However, these events were reversed in mitophagy enhancers treated mTau-HT22 cells. Cell survival was increased, mRNA and protein levels of mitochondrial fusion, synaptic and mitophagy genes were increased, and mitochondrial fragmentation is reduced in mitophagy enhancers treated mTau-HT22 cells. Further, urolithin A showed strongest protective effects among all enhancers tested in AD. Our combination treatments of urolithin A + EGCG, addition to urolithin A and EGCG individual treatment revealed that combination treatments approach is even stronger than urolithin A treatment. Based on these findings, we cautiously propose that mitophagy enhancers are promising therapeutic drugs to treat mitophagy in patients with AD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461119" rel="alternate" title="Mitophagy enhancers against phosphorylated Tau-induced mitochondrial and synaptic toxicities in Alzheimer disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461167</id><title>Preparing for a second attack: a lesion simulation study on network resilience after stroke (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.485447+00:00</updated><author><name>Mitsouko van Assche</name></author><author><name>Julian Klug</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Dirren</name></author><author><name>Jonas Richiardi</name></author><author><name>Emmanuel Carrera</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does the brain become more resilient after a first stroke to reduce the consequences of a new lesion? Although recurrent strokes are a major clinical issue, whether and how the brain prepares for a second attack is unknown. This is due to the difficulties to obtain an appropriate dataset of stroke patients with comparable lesions, imaged at the same interval after onset. Furthermore, timing of the recurrent event remains unpredictable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we used a novel clinical lesion simulation approach to test the hypothesis that resilience in brain networks increases during stroke recovery. 16 patients with a lesion restricted to the primary motor cortex were recruited. At 3 time points of the index event (10 days, 3 weeks, 3 months), we mimicked recurrent infarcts by deletion of nodes in brain networks (resting-state fMRI). Graph measures were applied to determine resilience (global efficiency) and wiring cost (mean degree) of the network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;At 10 days and 3 weeks after stroke, resilience was similar in patients and controls. However, at 3 months, while motor function had fully recovered, resilience to clinically representative simulated lesions was higher compared to controls (cortical lesion p=0.012; subcortical: p=0.009; cortico-subcortical: p=0.009). Similar results were found after random (p=0.012) and targeted (p=0.015) attacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results suggest that, after a lesion, brain networks reconfigure to increase resilience to future insults. Lesion simulation is an innovative approach, which may have major implications for stroke therapy. Individualized neuromodulation strategies could be developed to foster resilient network reconfigurations after a first stroke to limit the consequences of future attacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461167" rel="alternate" title="Preparing for a second attack: a lesion simulation study on network resilience after stroke (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461189</id><title>High permeability of the CSF flow in the juvenile mouse brain by brain-wide DCE-MRI (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.485608+00:00</updated><author><name>Yayoi Wada</name></author><author><name>Hirohiko Imai</name></author><author><name>Yuki Yamawaki</name></author><author><name>Md Sorwer Alam Parvez</name></author><author><name>Sae Matsui</name></author><author><name>Gen Ohtsuki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The vasculature system with a lymphatic function in the brain is manifested as meningeal lymphatic vessels and the glymphatic system, which drain waste products from cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and produce interstitial fluid. Invasion of stimulated immune cells or inflammatory cytokines during the maturation is regarded as a sign of the disruption of brain functions through excessive immune stresses. However, it is unclear when the lymphatic system is functionally completed and in which parts of the organ the brain immunity is privileged (&lt;italic&gt;i.e&lt;/italic&gt;., the blood-brain barrier is fully established). Here, we visualized the whole-head signal of gadolinium (Gd) contrast agents in mouse brains to investigate the CSF flow from the signals of Gd-contrast agents using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in the course of developmental stages. We found higher Gd-signals in the olfactory bulbs, prefrontal cortex, parietal surface regions of the neocortex along with dorsal meningeal lymphatic vessels, ventral midbrain, and a part of cerebellum, as well as in the basal brain regions, at the immature stage of postnatal (P) 4 weeks, compared to the P8-12 weeks. Our results suggest that the barrier of the vasculature system in mouse brains is still permeable until P1-month and small molecules can leak into the parenchyma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461189" rel="alternate" title="High permeability of the CSF flow in the juvenile mouse brain by brain-wide DCE-MRI (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461513</id><title>Novel microRNA-455-3p mouse models to study Alzheimer’s disease pathogenesis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.485773+00:00</updated><author><name>Subodh Kumar</name></author><author><name>Hallie Mortan</name></author><author><name>Neha Sawant</name></author><author><name>Erika Orlov</name></author><author><name>Lloyd Bunquin</name></author><author><name>Jangampalli Adi Pradeepkiran</name></author><author><name>P. Hemachandra Reddy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MicroRNA-455-3p is one of the highly conserved miRNAs involved in several human diseases but newly explored by our lab in Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Our past studies unveiled the biomarker and therapeutic potentials of miR-455-3p in AD. Our &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; study exhibited the protective role of miR-455-3p against AD toxicities in reducing full-length APP and amyloid-β (Aβ) protein levels, and also reducing defective mitochondrial biogenesis, impaired mitochondrial dynamics and synaptic deficiencies. Next, we sought to determine the essential roles of miR-455-3p in AD using mouse models. Therefore, for the first time we generated both transgenic (TG) and knockout (KO) mouse models of miR-455-3p. We determined the positive and negative effects of miR-455-3p on mice cognitive function, mitochondrial biogenesis, mitochondrial dynamics, mitochondrial number &amp;amp; length, dendritic spine density, synapse numbers and synaptic activity in 12-month-old miR-455-3p TG and KO mice. MiR-455-3p TG mice lived 5 months longer than wild-type (WT) mice, whereas KO mice lived 4 months shorter than their WT counter parts. Morris water maze test showed improved cognitive behavior, spatial learning and memory in miR-455-3p TG mice relative to age-matched WT mice and miR-455-3p KO mice. Further, mitochondrial biogenesis, dynamics and synaptic activities were enhanced in miR-455-3p TG mice, while these were reduced in KO mice. Overall, miR-455-3p TG mice displayed protective effects and miR-455-3p KO mice exhibited deleterious effects in relation to AD pathogenesis. Both mouse models could be ideal research tools to understand the molecular mechanism of miR-455-3p in AD and other human diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461513" rel="alternate" title="Novel microRNA-455-3p mouse models to study Alzheimer’s disease pathogenesis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460810</id><title>Educational Attainment Polygenic Scores, Socioeconomic Factors, and Cortical Structure in Children and Adolescents (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.485944+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily C. Merz</name></author><author><name>Jordan Strack</name></author><author><name>Hailee Hurtado</name></author><author><name>Uku Vainik</name></author><author><name>Michael Thomas</name></author><author><name>Alan Evans</name></author><author><name>Budhachandra Khundrakpam</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide polygenic scores for educational attainment (PGS-EA) and socioeconomic factors, which are correlated with each other, have been consistently associated with academic achievement and general cognitive ability in children and adolescents. Yet, the independent associations of PGS-EA and socioeconomic factors with specific underlying factors at the neural and neurocognitive levels are not well understood. The goal of this study was to examine the unique contributions of PGS-EA and parental education to cortical thickness (CT), cortical surface area (SA), and neurocognitive skills in children and adolescents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participants were typically developing children and adolescents (3-21 years of age; 53% male; &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; = 391). High-resolution, T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging data were acquired. PGS-EA were computed based on the most recent genome-wide association study of educational attainment. Sustained attention, inhibitory control, working memory, vocabulary, and episodic memory were measured.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PGS-EA and parental education were independently and significantly associated with SA, vocabulary, and attention outcomes but were not associated with CT. Vertex-wise analyses indicated that higher PGS-EA was significantly associated with greater SA in the left medial orbitofrontal gyrus and inferior frontal gyrus after accounting for parental education. Higher parental education was significantly associated with greater SA in the left parahippocampal gyrus after accounting for PGS-EA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest that education-linked genetics may influence SA, particularly in certain frontal regions, leading to variability in academic achievement. Results suggested genetic confounding in associations between parental education and SA in children and adolescents, with these associations remaining significant after controlling for PGS-EA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.17.460810" rel="alternate" title="Educational Attainment Polygenic Scores, Socioeconomic Factors, and Cortical Structure in Children and Adolescents (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461726</id><title>Express Arm Responses Appear Bilaterally on Upper-limb Muscles in Arm Choice Reaching Task (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.486132+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah L. Kearsley</name></author><author><name>Aaron L. Cecala</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Kozak</name></author><author><name>Brian D. Corneil</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When required, humans can generate very short latency reaches towards a visual target, like catching a phone falling off a desk. During such rapid reaches, express arm responses are the first wave of upper limb muscle recruitment, occurring within ~80-100 ms of target appearance. There is accumulating evidence that express arm responses arise from signaling along the tecto-reticulo-spinal tract, but the involvement of the reticulo-spinal tract has not been well-studied. Since the reticulospinal tract projects bilaterally, we studied whether express arm responses would be expressed bilaterally. Human participants (n = 14; 7 female) performed visually guided reaches in a modified emerging target paradigm where either arm could be used to intercept a target once it emerged below a barrier. We recorded electromyographic activity bilaterally from the pectoralis major muscle. Our analysis focused on target locations where participants reached with the right arm on some trials, and the left arm on others. In support of the involvement of the reticulospinal tract, the express arm response persisted bilaterally regardless of which arm reached to the target. While the latency of the express arm response was the same on the reaching vs non-reaching arm, the response magnitude was slightly larger on the reaching arm, in part due to anticipatory muscle recruitment related to arm choice. Our results support the involvement of the reticulo-spinal tract in mediating the express arm response, and we surmise that the increased magnitude on the arm chosen to move arises from convergence of cortically derived signals with the largely independent express arm response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;New and Noteworthy&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Express arm responses have been proposed to arise from the tecto-reticulo-spinal tract. These responses have been linked to the superior colliculus, but the involvement of the reticulo-spinal tract has not been well studied. Here we show these responses appear bilaterally regardless of arm choice when either arm can be used to intercept a newly appearing stimulus, supporting involvement of the reticulo-spinal tract. We propose this response is mediated largely independent of the volitional cortical related activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461726" rel="alternate" title="Express Arm Responses Appear Bilaterally on Upper-limb Muscles in Arm Choice Reaching Task (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461637</id><title>Rapamycin attenuated zinc-induced tau phosphorylation and oxidative stress in animal model: Involvement of dual mTOR/p70S6K and Nrf2/HO-1 pathways (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.486293+00:00</updated><author><name>Chencen Lai</name></author><author><name>Yuanting Ding</name></author><author><name>Qian Chen</name></author><author><name>Songbai Su</name></author><author><name>Heng Liu</name></author><author><name>Ruiqing Ni</name></author><author><name>Zhi Tang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease is pathologically featured by abnormal accumulation of amyloid-beta plaque, neurofibrillary tangles, oxidative stress, neuroinflammation, and neurodegeneration. Metal dysregulation including excessive zinc released by presynaptic neurons plays an important role in tau pathology and oxidase activation. The activities of mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR)/ ribosomal S6 protein kinase (p70S6K) are elevated in the brains of patients with Alzheimer’s disease. Zinc induces tau hyperphosphorylation via mTOR/P70S6K activation &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. However, the involvement of mTOR/P70S6K pathway in zinc-induced oxidative stress, tau degeneration, synaptic and cognitive impairment, has not been fully elucidated &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Here we assessed in the effect of pathological concentration of zinc in SH-SY5Y cells by using biochemical assays and immunofluorescence staining. Rats (n = 18, male) were lateral ventricularly-injected with zinc and treated with rapamycin (intraperitoneal injection) for one week and assessed using Morris water maze. Evaluation of the oxidative stress, tau phorsphylation and synaptic impairment were performed using the hippocampus tissue of the rats by biochemical assays and immunofluorescence staining. Results from Morris water maze showed that the capacity of spatial memory is impaired in zinc-treated rats. Zinc sulfate significantly increased the levels of P-mTOR Ser2448, P-p70S6K Thr389, and P-tau Ser356, and decreased levels of Nrf2 and HO□1 in SH-SY5Y cells and in zinc-treated rats compared with control groups. Increased expressions of reactive oxygen species were observed in zinc sulfate-induced SH-SY5Y cells as well as in the hippocampus of zinc-injected rats. Rapamycin, an inhibitor of mTOR, rescued the zinc-induced increases in mTOR/p70S6K activations, tau phosphorylation and oxidative stress, as well as Nrf2/HO□1 inactivation, cognitive impairment and synaptic impairment reduced the expression of synapse-related proteins in zinc-injected rats. In conclusion, our findings imply that rapamycin prevents zinc-induced cognitive impairment and protects neurons from tau pathology, oxidative stress and synaptic impairment, by decreasing mTOR/p70S6K hyperactivity and increasing Nrf2/HO □ 1 activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461637" rel="alternate" title="Rapamycin attenuated zinc-induced tau phosphorylation and oxidative stress in animal model: Involvement of dual mTOR/p70S6K and Nrf2/HO-1 pathways (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.460811</id><title>Compartment-specific tuning of hippocampal dendritic feature selectivity by intracellular Ca2+ release (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.486469+00:00</updated><author><name>Justin K. O’Hare</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Hirabayashi</name></author><author><name>Victoria L. Hewitt</name></author><author><name>Heike Blockus</name></author><author><name>Miklos Szoboszlay</name></author><author><name>Sebi V. Rolotti</name></author><author><name>Tristan C. Geiller</name></author><author><name>Adrian Negrean</name></author><author><name>Vikas Chelur</name></author><author><name>Attila Losonczy</name></author><author><name>Franck Polleux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Dendritic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling is central to neural plasticity mechanisms allowing animals to adapt to the environment. Intracellular Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; release (ICR) from endoplasmic reticulum has long been thought to shape these mechanisms. However, ICR has not been investigated in mammalian neurons &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. We combined electroporation of single CA1 pyramidal neurons, simultaneous imaging of dendritic and somatic activity during spatial navigation, optogenetic place field induction, and acute genetic augmentation of ICR cytosolic impact to reveal that ICR supports the establishment of dendritic feature selectivity and shapes integrative properties determining output-level receptive fields. This role for ICR was more prominent in apical than in basal dendrites. Thus, ICR cooperates with circuit-level architecture &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; to promote the emergence of behaviorally-relevant plasticity in a compartment-specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.460811" rel="alternate" title="Compartment-specific tuning of hippocampal dendritic feature selectivity by intracellular Ca2+ release (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461583</id><title>Mice With Monoallelic GNAO1 Loss Exhibit Reduced Inhibitory Synaptic Input To Cerebellar Purkinje Cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.486676+00:00</updated><author><name>Huijie Feng</name></author><author><name>Yukun Yuan</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Williams</name></author><author><name>Alex J. Roy</name></author><author><name>Jeffery Leipprandt</name></author><author><name>Richard R. Neubig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;GNAO1&lt;/italic&gt; encodes Gα&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt;, a heterotrimeric G protein alpha subunit in the G&lt;sub&gt;i/o&lt;/sub&gt; family. In this report, we used a &lt;italic&gt;Gnao1&lt;/italic&gt; mouse model “G203R” previously described as a “gain-of-function” &lt;italic&gt;Gnao1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant with movement abnormalities and enhanced seizure susceptibility. Here, we report an unexpected second mutation resulting in a loss-of-function Gα&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt; protein and describe alterations in central synaptic transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whole cell patch clamp recordings from Purkinje cells (PCs) in acute cerebellar slices from &lt;italic&gt;Gnao1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant mice showed significantly lower frequencies of spontaneous and miniature inhibitory postsynaptic currents (sIPSCs and mIPSCs) compared to WT mice. There was no significant change in sEPSCs or mEPSCs. Whereas mIPSC frequency was reduced, mIPSC amplitudes were not affected, suggesting a presynaptic mechanism of action. A modest decrease in the number of molecular layer interneurons was insufficient to explain the magnitude of IPSC suppression. Paradoxically, G&lt;sub&gt;i/o&lt;/sub&gt; inhibitors (pertussis toxin), enhanced the mutant-suppressed mIPSC frequency and eliminated the difference between WT and &lt;italic&gt;Gnao1&lt;/italic&gt; mice. While GABA&lt;sub&gt;B&lt;/sub&gt; receptor regulates mIPSCs, neither agonists nor antagonists of this receptor altered function in the mutant mouse PCs. This study is the first electrophysiological investigation of the role of G&lt;sub&gt;i/o&lt;/sub&gt; protein in cerebellar synaptic transmission using an animal model with a loss-of-function G&lt;sub&gt;i/o&lt;/sub&gt; protein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first report on the electrophysiological mechanisms of a movement disorder animal model with monoallelic &lt;italic&gt;Gnao1&lt;/italic&gt; loss. This study illustrates the role of Gα&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt; protein in regulating GABA release in mouse cerebellum. This study could also facilitate the discovery of new drugs or drug repurposing for &lt;italic&gt;GNAO1&lt;/italic&gt;-associated disorders. Moreover, since &lt;italic&gt;GNAO1&lt;/italic&gt; shares pathways with other genes related to movement disorders, developing drugs for the treatment of &lt;italic&gt;GNAO1&lt;/italic&gt;-associated movement disorders could further the pharmacological intervention for other monogenic movement disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461583" rel="alternate" title="Mice With Monoallelic GNAO1 Loss Exhibit Reduced Inhibitory Synaptic Input To Cerebellar Purkinje Cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461780</id><title>Kinetic and thermodynamic modeling of a voltage-gated sodium channel (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.486964+00:00</updated><author><name>Mara Almog</name></author><author><name>Nurit Degani-Katzav</name></author><author><name>Alon Korgnreen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Like all biological and chemical reactions, ion channel kinetics are highly sensitive to changes in temperature. Therefore, it is prudent to investigate channel dynamics at physiological temperatures. However, most ion channel investigations are performed at room temperature due to practical considerations, such as recording stability and technical limitations. This problem is especially severe for the fast voltage-gated sodium channel, whose activation kinetics are faster than the time constant of the standard patch-clamp amplifier at physiological temperatures. Thus, biologically detailed simulations of the action potential generation evenly scale the kinetic models of voltage-gated channels acquired at room temperature. To quantitatively study voltage-gated sodium channels’ temperature sensitivity, we recorded sodium currents from nucleated patches extracted from the rat’s layer five neocortical pyramidal neurons at several temperatures from 13.5 to 30oC. We use these recordings to model the kinetics of the voltage-gated sodium channel as a function of temperature. We show that the temperature dependence of activation differs from that of inactivation. Furthermore, we show that the sustained current has a different temperature dependence than the fast current. Our kinetic and thermodynamic analysis of the current provided a numerical model spanning the entire temperature range. This model reproduced vital features of channel activation and inactivation. Furthermore, the model also reproduced action potential dependence on temperature. Thus, we provide an essential building block for the generation of biologically detailed models of cortical neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461780" rel="alternate" title="Kinetic and thermodynamic modeling of a voltage-gated sodium channel (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461827</id><title>Role of type I interferon signaling and microglia in the abnormal long term potentiation and object place recognition deficits of male mice with a mutation of the Tuberous Sclerosis 2 gene (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.487229+00:00</updated><author><name>Manuel F. López-Aranda</name></author><author><name>Gayle M. Boxx</name></author><author><name>Miranda Phan</name></author><author><name>Karen Bach</name></author><author><name>Rochelle Mandanas</name></author><author><name>Isaiah Herrera</name></author><author><name>Sunrae Taloma</name></author><author><name>Chirag Thadani</name></author><author><name>Odilia Lu</name></author><author><name>Raymond Bui</name></author><author><name>Shuhan Liu</name></author><author><name>Nan Li</name></author><author><name>Yu Zhou</name></author><author><name>Genhong Cheng</name></author><author><name>Alcino J. Silva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tuberous Sclerosis Complex (TSC) is a genetic disorder associated with high rates of intellectual disability and autism. Although previous studies focused on the role of neuronal deficits in the memory phenotypes of rodent models of TSC, the results presented here demonstrate a role for microglia in these deficits. Mice with a heterozygous null mutation of the Tsc2 gene (Tsc2&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt;), show deficits in hippocampal dependent tasks, as well as abnormal long-term potentiation (LTP) in the hippocampal CA1 region. Here, we show that microglia and type I interferon signaling (IFN1) have a key role in the object place recognition (OPR; a hippocampal dependent task) deficits and abnormal LTP of Tsc2&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt; male mice. Unexpectedly, we demonstrate that male, but not female, Tsc2&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice showed OPR deficits. Importantly, these deficits can be rescued by depletion of microglia, as well as by a genetic manipulation of a signaling pathway known to modulate microglia function (interferon-alpha/beta receptor alpha chain null mutation). In addition to rescuing the OPR deficits, depletion of microglia also reversed the abnormal LTP of the Tsc2&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice. Altogether, our results suggest that altered IFN1 signaling in microglia cause the abnormal LTP and OPR deficits of male Tsc2&lt;sup&gt;+/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461827" rel="alternate" title="Role of type I interferon signaling and microglia in the abnormal long term potentiation and object place recognition deficits of male mice with a mutation of the Tuberous Sclerosis 2 gene (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>