<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.882476+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466453</id><title>Invariant neural subspaces maintained by feedback modulation (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.883977+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Bella Naumann</name></author><author><name>Joram Keijser</name></author><author><name>Henning Sprekeler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sensory systems reliably process incoming stimuli in spite of changes in context. Most recent models accredit this context invariance to an extraction of increasingly complex sensory features in hierarchical feedforward networks. Here, we study how context-invariant representations can be established by feedback rather than feedforward processing. We show that feedforward neural networks modulated by feedback can dynamically generate invariant sensory representations. The required feedback can be implemented as a slow and spatially diffuse gain modulation. The invariance is not present on the level of individual neurons, but emerges only on the population level. Mechanistically, the feedback modulation dynamically reorients the manifold of neural activity and thereby maintains an invariant neural subspace in spite of contextual variations. Our results highlight the importance of population-level analyses for understanding the role of feedback in flexible sensory processing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466453" rel="alternate" title="Invariant neural subspaces maintained by feedback modulation (33 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466434</id><title>Multilevel neural gradients reflect transdiagnostic effects of major psychiatric conditions on cortical morphology (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.884453+00:00</updated><author><name>Bo-yong Park</name></author><author><name>Valeria Kebets</name></author><author><name>Sara Larivière</name></author><author><name>Meike D. Hettwer</name></author><author><name>Casey Paquola</name></author><author><name>Daan van Rooij</name></author><author><name>Jan Buitelaar</name></author><author><name>Barbara Franke</name></author><author><name>Martine Hoogman</name></author><author><name>Lianne Schmaal</name></author><author><name>Dick J. Veltman</name></author><author><name>Odile van den Heuvel</name></author><author><name>Dan J. Stein</name></author><author><name>Ole A. Andreassen</name></author><author><name>Christopher R. K. Ching</name></author><author><name>Jessica Turner</name></author><author><name>Theo G. M. van Erp</name></author><author><name>Alan C. Evans</name></author><author><name>Alain Dagher</name></author><author><name>Sophia I. Thomopoulos</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Sofie L. Valk</name></author><author><name>Matthias Kirschner</name></author><author><name>Boris C. Bernhardt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is increasingly recognized that multiple psychiatric conditions are underpinned by shared neural pathways, affecting similar brain systems. Here, we assessed &lt;italic&gt;i)&lt;/italic&gt; shared dimensions of alterations in cortical morphology across six major psychiatric conditions (autism spectrum disorder, attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder, major depression, obsessive-compulsive disorder, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia) and &lt;italic&gt;ii)&lt;/italic&gt; carried out a multiscale neural contextualization, by cross-referencing shared anomalies against cortical myeloarchitecture and cytoarchitecture, as well as connectome and neurotransmitter organization. Pooling disease-related effects on MRI-based cortical thickness measures across six ENIGMA working groups, including a total of 28,546 participants (12,876 patients and 15,670 controls), we computed a shared disease dimension on cortical morphology using principal component analysis that described a sensory-fugal pattern with paralimbic regions showing the most consistent abnormalities across conditions. The shared disease dimension was closely related to cortical gradients of microstructure and intrinsic connectivity, as well as neurotransmitter systems, specifically serotonin and dopamine. Our findings embed the shared effects of major psychiatric conditions on brain structure in multiple scales of brain organization and may provide novel insights into neural mechanisms into transdiagnostic vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466434" rel="alternate" title="Multilevel neural gradients reflect transdiagnostic effects of major psychiatric conditions on cortical morphology (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466884</id><title>Retinal OFF ganglion cells allow detection of quantal shadows at starlight (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.885297+00:00</updated><author><name>Johan Westö</name></author><author><name>Nataliia Martyniuk</name></author><author><name>Sanna Koskela</name></author><author><name>Tuomas Turunen</name></author><author><name>Santtu Pentikäinen</name></author><author><name>Petri Ala-Laurila</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perception of light in darkness requires no more than a handful of photons and this remarkable behavioral performance can be directly linked to a particular retinal circuit – the retinal ON pathway. However, the neural limits to shadow detection in very dim light have remained unresolved. Here, we unravel the neural mechanisms that determine the sensitivity of mice to the dimmest light decrements by measuring signals from the most sensitive ON and OFF retinal ganglion cell types and by correlating their signals with visually guided behavior. We show that mice can detect shadows when only a few photon absorptions are missing among thousands of rods. Behavioral detection of “quantal” shadows relies only on the retinal OFF pathway and is limited by noise and losses of single-photon signals in retinal processing. Thus, in the dim-light regime, light increments and decrements are encoded separately via the ON and OFF retinal pathways, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466884" rel="alternate" title="Retinal OFF ganglion cells allow detection of quantal shadows at starlight (26 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466363</id><title>Distinct representation of cue-outcome association by D1 and D2 neurons in the olfactory striatum (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.885595+00:00</updated><author><name>Nuné Martiros</name></author><author><name>Spencer E. Kim</name></author><author><name>Vikrant Kapoor</name></author><author><name>Venkatesh N. Murthy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Positive and negative associations acquired through olfactory experience are thought to be especially strong and long-lasting. The conserved direct olfactory sensory input to the ventral striatal olfactory tubercle (OT) and its convergence with dense dopaminergic input to the OT could underlie this privileged form of associative memory, but how this process occurs is not well understood. We imaged the activity of the two canonical types of striatal neurons, expressing D1 or D2 type dopamine receptors, in the OT at cellular resolution while mice learned odor-outcome associations ranging from aversive to rewarding. D1 and D2 neurons both responded to rewarding and aversive odors. D1 neurons in the OT robustly and bidirectionally represented odor valence, responding similarly to odors predicting similar outcomes regardless of odor identity. This valence representation persisted even in the absence of an instrumental response to the odors and in the absence of the outcomes, indicating a true transformation of odor sensory information by D1 OT neurons. In contrast, D2 neuronal representation of the odor-outcome associations was weaker, contingent on an instrumental response by the mouse, and D2 neurons were more selective for odor identity than valence. Stimulus valence coding in the OT was not modality invariant, with separate sets of D1 neurons responding to odors and sounds predicting the same outcomes, suggesting that integration of multimodal valence information happens downstream of the OT. Our results point to distinct representation of identity and valence of odor stimuli by D1 and D2 neurons in the OT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466363" rel="alternate" title="Distinct representation of cue-outcome association by D1 and D2 neurons in the olfactory striatum (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.466530</id><title>Consequences of endogenous and virally-induced hyperphosphorylated tau on behavior and cognition in a rat model of Alzheimer’s disease (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.885826+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael A. Kelberman</name></author><author><name>Claire R. Anderson</name></author><author><name>Eli Chlan</name></author><author><name>Jacki M. Rorabaugh</name></author><author><name>Katharine E. McCann</name></author><author><name>David Weinshenker</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The locus coeruleus (LC) is one of the earliest brain regions to accumulate hyperphosphorylated tau, but a lack of animal models that recapitulate this pathology has hampered our ability to understand its contributions to the pathophysiology of Alzheimer’s disease (AD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We previously reported that TgF344-AD rats, which overexpress mutant human amyloid precursor protein and presenilin-1, accumulate early endogenous hyperphosphorylated tau in the LC. Here, we used TgF344-AD rats and a wild-type (WT) human tau virus to interrogate the effects of endogenous hyperphosphorylated rat tau and human tau in the LC on AD-related neuropathology and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two-month old TgF344-AD and WT rats received bilateral LC infusions of WT human tau or mCherry control virus driven by the noradrenergic-specific PRSx8 promoter. Rats were subsequently assessed at 6 and 12 months for arousal (sleep latency), anxiety-like behavior (open field, elevated plus maze, novelty-suppressed feeding), passive coping (forced swim task), and learning and memory (Morris water maze and fear conditioning). Hippocampal microglia, astrocyte, and AD pathology were evaluated using immunohistochemistry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In general, the effects of age were more pronounced than genotype or treatment; older rats displayed greater hippocampal pathology, took longer to fall asleep, had reduced locomotor activity, floated more, and had impaired cognition compared to younger animals. TgF344-AD rats showed increased anxiety-like behavior and impaired learning and memory. The tau virus had negligible influence on most measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Effects of hyperphosphorylated tau on AD-like neuropathology and behavioral symptoms were subtle. Further investigation of different forms of tau is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.466530" rel="alternate" title="Consequences of endogenous and virally-induced hyperphosphorylated tau on behavior and cognition in a rat model of Alzheimer’s disease (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466347</id><title>Dorsal striatum coding for the timely execution of action sequences (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.888153+00:00</updated><author><name>María Cecilia Martinez</name></author><author><name>Camila Lidia Zold</name></author><author><name>Mario Gustavo Murer</name></author><author><name>Mariano Andrés Belluscio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The automatic initiation of actions can be highly functional. But occasionally these actions cannot be withheld and are released at inappropriate times, impulsively. Striatal activity has been shown to participate in the timing of action sequence initiation and it has been linked to impulsivity. Using a self- initiated task, we trained adult rats to withhold a rewarded action sequence until a waiting time interval has elapsed. By analyzing neuronal activity we show that the striatal response preceding the initiation of the learned sequence is strongly modulated by the time subjects wait before eliciting the sequence. Interestingly, the modulation is steeper in adolescent rats, which show a strong prevalence of impulsive responses compared to adults. We hypothesize this anticipatory striatal activity reflects the animals’ subjective reward expectation, based on the elapsed waiting time, while its steeper waiting modulation in adolescence reflects age-related differences in temporal discounting, internal urgency states or explore- exploit balance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466347" rel="alternate" title="Dorsal striatum coding for the timely execution of action sequences (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466818</id><title>Behavioral context affects social signal representations within single primate prefrontal cortex neurons (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.888583+00:00</updated><author><name>Vladimir Jovanovic</name></author><author><name>Adam R. Fishbein</name></author><author><name>Lisa de la Mothe</name></author><author><name>Kuo-Fen Lee</name></author><author><name>Cory T. Miller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We tested whether social signal processing in more traditional, head-restrained contexts is representative of the putative natural analog – social communication – by comparing responses to vocalizations within individual neurons in marmoset prefrontal cortex (PFC) across a series of behavioral contexts ranging from traditional to naturalistic. Although vocalization responsive neurons were evident in all contexts, cross-context consistency was notably limited. A response to these social signals when subjects were head-restrained was not predictive of a comparable neural response to the identical vocalizations during natural communication, even within the same neuron. Neural activity at the population level followed a similar pattern, as PFC activity could be reliably decoded for the context in which vocalizations were heard. This suggests that neural representations of social signals in primate PFC are not static, but highly flexible and likely reflect how nuances of the dynamic behavioral contexts affect the perception of these signals and what they communicate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466818" rel="alternate" title="Behavioral context affects social signal representations within single primate prefrontal cortex neurons (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466926</id><title>Learning from ingroup experiences changes intergroup impressions (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.889393+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuqing Zhou</name></author><author><name>Björn Lindström</name></author><author><name>Alexander Soutschek</name></author><author><name>Pyungwon Kang</name></author><author><name>Philippe N. Tobler</name></author><author><name>Grit Hein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Living in multicultural societies, humans form impressions towards individuals of their own social groups (ingroup members) and of different social groups (outgroup members). Some psychological theories predict that intergroup impressions are mainly shaped by experiences with outgroup individuals (“outgroup focused theories”), while other theories predict that ingroup experiences play a dominant role (“ingroup focused theories”). Here we test predictions from these two psychological theories by estimating how intergroup impressions are dynamically shaped when people learn from both ingroup and outgroup experiences. Participants expected to receive painful shocks but were saved from pain by different ingroup or outgroup members in 75% of all trials. We measured neural responses using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), and participants rated their social closeness as well as impressions towards the ingroup and the outgroup. Behavioral results showed an initial ingroup bias in impression ratings which was significantly reduced over the course of learning. Computational learning models revealed that these changes in intergroup impressions were predicted by the weight given to ingroup prediction errors. The weight of the ingroup prediction error and its effect on intergroup impression change was stronger the more individuals identified with their ingroup. On the neural level, the left inferior parietal lobule (IPL) encoded more negative prediction errors for the ingroup compared to the outgroup. Moreover, stronger weight for ingroup prediction errors was related to increased neural coupling between the left IPL and the anterior insula (AI). This coupling further predicted learning-related changes in intergroup impressions. Together, our work provides computational and neural evidence for “ingroup focused theories”, highlighting the importance of ingroup experiences in shaping social impressions in intergroup settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466926" rel="alternate" title="Learning from ingroup experiences changes intergroup impressions (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467135</id><title>Prefrontal-amygdalar oscillations related to social interaction behavior in mice (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.889960+00:00</updated><author><name>Nahoko Kuga</name></author><author><name>Reimi Abe</name></author><author><name>Kotomi Takano</name></author><author><name>Yuji Ikegaya</name></author><author><name>Takuya Sasaki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The medial prefrontal cortex and amygdala are involved in the regulation of social behavior and associated with psychiatric diseases but their detailed neurophysiological mechanisms at a network level remain unclear. We recorded local field potentials (LFPs) from the dorsal medial PFC (dmPFC) and basolateral amygdala (BLA) while mice engaged on social behavior. We found that in wild-type mice, both the dmPFC and BLA increased 4–7 Hz oscillation power and decreased 30–60 Hz power when they needed to attend to another target mouse. In mouse models with reduced social interactions, dmPFC 4–7 Hz power further increased especially when they exhibited social avoidance behavior. In contrast, dmPFC and BLA decreased 4–7 Hz power when wild-type mice socially approached a target mouse. Frequency-specific optogenetic manipulations of replicating social approach-related LFP patterns restored social interaction behavior in socially deficient mice. These results demonstrate a neurophysiological substrate of the prefrontal cortex and amygdala related to social behavior and provide a unified pathophysiological understanding of neuronal population dynamics underlying social behavioral deficits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467135" rel="alternate" title="Prefrontal-amygdalar oscillations related to social interaction behavior in mice (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466751</id><title>Penalized generalized estimating equations for relative risk regression with applications to brain lesion data (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.890396+00:00</updated><author><name>Petya Kindalova</name></author><author><name>Michele Veldsman</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Nichols</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Kosmidis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivated by a brain lesion application, we introduce penalized generalized estimating equations for relative risk regression for modelling correlated binary data. Brain lesions can have varying incidence across the brain and result in both rare and high incidence outcomes. As a result, odds ratios estimated from generalized estimating equations with logistic regression structures are not necessarily directly interpretable as relative risks. On the other hand, use of log-link regression structures with the binomial variance function may lead to estimation instabilities when event probabilities are close to 1. To circumvent such issues, we use generalized estimating equations with log-link regression structures with identity variance function and unknown dispersion parameter. Even in this setting, parameter estimates can be infinite, which we address by penalizing the generalized estimating functions with the gradient of the Jeffreys prior.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings from extensive simulation studies show significant improvement over the standard log-link generalized estimating equations by providing finite estimates and achieving convergence when boundary estimates occur. The real data application on UK Biobank brain lesion maps further reveals the instabilities of the standard log-link generalized estimating equations for a large-scale data set and demonstrates the clear interpretation of relative risk in clinical applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466751" rel="alternate" title="Penalized generalized estimating equations for relative risk regression with applications to brain lesion data (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466768</id><title>Coherent theta oscillations in the cerebellum and supplementary motor area mediate visuomotor adaptation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.891058+00:00</updated><author><name>Elinor Tzvi</name></author><author><name>Leila Gajiyeva</name></author><author><name>Laura Bindel</name></author><author><name>Gesa Hartwigsen</name></author><author><name>Joseph Classen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The cerebellum and its interaction with cortical areas play a key role in our ability to flexibly adapt a motor program in response to sensory input. Current knowledge about specific neural mechanisms underlying the process of visuomotor adaptation is however lacking. Using a novel placement of EEG electrodes to record electric activity from the cerebellum, we studied local cerebellar activity, as well as its coupling with neocortical activity to obtain direct neurophysiological markers of visuomotor adaptation in humans. We found increased theta (4-8Hz) power in “cerebellar” as well as cortical electrodes, when subjects first encountered a visual perturbation. Theta power decreased as subjects adapted to the perturbation, and rebounded when the perturbation was suddenly removed. This effect was observed in two distinct locations: a cerebellar cluster and a central cluster, which were localized in left cerebellar crus I (lCB) and right supplementary motor area (rSMA) using linear constrained minimum variance beamforming. Importantly, we found that better adaptation was associated with increased theta power in left cerebellar electrodes and a right sensorimotor cortex electrode. Finally, increased rSMA –&amp;gt; lCB connectivity was significantly decreased with adaptation. These results demonstrate that: (1) cerebellar theta power is markedly modulated over the course of visuomotor adaptation and (2) theta oscillations could serve as a key mechanism for communication within a cortico-cerebellar loop.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466768" rel="alternate" title="Coherent theta oscillations in the cerebellum and supplementary motor area mediate visuomotor adaptation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466459</id><title>Finger representations in primary somatosensory cortex are modulated during vibrotactile working memory (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.892523+00:00</updated><author><name>Finn Rabe</name></author><author><name>Sanne Kikkert</name></author><author><name>Nicole Wenderoth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is well-established that vibrotactile stimulations elicit Blood-oxygen-level-dependent (BOLD) responses in somatotopically organized brain regions. Whether these somatotopic maps are modulated by working memory (WM) is still unknown. In our WM experiment, participants had to compare frequencies that were separated by a delay period. Vibrotactile stimuli were sequentially applied to either their right index or little finger. Using functional MRI, we investigated whether vibrotactile WM modulated neural activity in primary somatosensory (S1), an area that is known to contain individual finger representations. Our mass-univariate results revealed the well-described network of brain regions involved in WM. Interestingly, our mass-univariate results did not demonstrate S1 to be part of this network. However, when we parametrically modulated the time-binned regressors in our GLM we found that the delay activity in S1 and secondary somatosensory cortex (S2) was reflected in a U-shaped manner. Using multi-voxel pattern analysis (MVPA), an analysis technique that is more sensitive to subtle activity differences, we found finger-specific patterns of activation in the S1 hand area during the WM delay period. These results indicate that processes underlying WM modulate finger-specific representations during our discrimination task.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466459" rel="alternate" title="Finger representations in primary somatosensory cortex are modulated during vibrotactile working memory (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467391</id><title>Organizing Principles of Astrocytic Nanoarchitecture in the Mouse Cerebral Cortex (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.892859+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher K Salmon</name></author><author><name>Tabish A Syed</name></author><author><name>J Benjamin Kacerovsky</name></author><author><name>Nensi Alivodej</name></author><author><name>Alexandra L Schober</name></author><author><name>Michael T Pratte</name></author><author><name>Michael P Rosen</name></author><author><name>Miranda Green</name></author><author><name>Adario Chirgwin-Dasgupta</name></author><author><name>Hojatollah Vali</name></author><author><name>Craig A Mandato</name></author><author><name>Kaleem Siddiqi</name></author><author><name>Keith K Murai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Astrocytes have complex roles in central nervous system (CNS) health and disease. Underlying these roles is an elaborate architecture based on frequent, extremely fine, but seemingly haphazard branches, as well as prominent features including tripartite synaptic complexes and perivascular endfeet. While broad categories of structures in astrocytes are known, the fundamental building blocks that compose them and their organizing principles have yet to be adequately defined. This is largely due to the absence of high-resolution datasets that can reveal nanoscopic features of astrocytes (i.e. 10-20nm diameter in x, y, and z) and a lack of computational approaches that can effectively interrogate astrocyte shape, organization, and nanoarchitecture. Here, we produced and analyzed multiple, high-resolution datasets of layer 2/3 mouse somatosensory cortex using focused ion beam scanning electron microscopy (8nm intervals) and computer vision approaches to provide a principled, quantitative analysis of astrocytic nanoarchitecture. A decomposition of astrocytes into fundamental "parts" led to the discovery of unique structural components, recurring structural motifs, and assembly of parts into an organized hierarchy. New relationships were also discerned between astrocytic processes and other CNS microanatomy including mitochondria, tripartite synapses, and cerebrovasculature. By deploying computational resources to quantitatively understand the organizing principles and nanoarchitecture of astrocytes, this study reveals the specialized anatomical adaptations of these complex cells within the CNS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467391" rel="alternate" title="Organizing Principles of Astrocytic Nanoarchitecture in the Mouse Cerebral Cortex (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467191</id><title>miR-409-3p represses Cited2 at the evolutionary emergence of the callosal and corticospinal projections (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.893829+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikolaus R Wagner</name></author><author><name>Ashis Sinha</name></author><author><name>Verl B Siththanandan</name></author><author><name>Angelica N Kowalchuk</name></author><author><name>Jessica MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Suzanne Tharin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Callosal projection neurons are a broad population of interhemispheric projection neurons that extend an axon across the corpus callosum to connect the two cerebral hemispheres. The corticospinal tract, comprised of the axons of corticospinal projection neurons, is unique to mammals, and its full extension to the lumbar segments that control walking is, like the corpus callosum, unique to placental mammals. The emergence of these two distinct axonal tracts is thought to underpin the evolutionary expansion of complex motor and cognitive abilities. The molecular mechanisms regulating the divergence of corticospinal and callosal projection neurons are incompletely understood. Our recent work identifies a genomic cluster of microRNAs (12qF1/Mirg) unique to placental mammals. These clustered miRNAs are specifically expressed by corticospinal vs. callosal projection neurons during the molecular refinement of corticospinal vs. callosal projection neuron fate (1). One of these, miR-409-3p, can convert layer V callosal into corticospinal projection neurons, acting in part through repression of the callosal-expressed transcriptional regulator Lmo4. This conversion is partial, however, suggesting that miR-409-3p represses multiple callosal projection neuron control genes in order to specify corticospinal projection neurons. One potential additional target of miR-409-3p repression is the callosal-expressed transcriptional co-activator Cited2. Cited2 interacts genetically with Lmo4, and Lmo4 can partially functionally compensate for Cited2 in thymus development(2). Further, Cited2 and Lmo4 function as opposing molecular controls over specific areal identity within superficial layer callosal projection neurons of the somatosensory and motor cortices, respectively (3). Cited2 is highly expressed by callosal, relative to corticospinal, projection neurons from the earliest stages of neurogenesis. Cited2 is necessary for the expansion of intermediate progenitor cells (IPCs) in the subventricular zone (SVZ), and the resulting generation of superficial layer callosal projection neurons. Here we show that miR-409-3p and Cited2 interact in IPCs and in corticospinal vs. deep layer callosal projection neuron development. miR-409-3p represses the Cited2 3UTR in luciferase assays. Mirg, which encodes miR-409-3p, and Cited2, are reciprocally expressed in IPCs at e15.5 by qPCR.  Furthermore, miR-409-3p gain-of-function results in a phenocopy of established Cited2 loss-of-function in IPCs. Later on, miR-409-3p and Cited2 exert opposing effects on the adoption of corticospinal vs. callosal projection neuron subtype identity. Taken together, our work suggests that miR-409-3p, and possibly other 12qF1 miRNAs, represses Cited2 in IPCs to limit their proliferation, and in developing corticospinal and deep layer callosal projection neurons to favor corticospinal fate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467191" rel="alternate" title="miR-409-3p represses Cited2 at the evolutionary emergence of the callosal and corticospinal projections (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466361</id><title>A retrograde mechanism coordinates memory allocation across brain regions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.894250+00:00</updated><author><name>Ayal Lavi</name></author><author><name>Megha Sehgal</name></author><author><name>Fardad Sisan</name></author><author><name>Anna Okabe</name></author><author><name>Donara Ter-Mkrtchyan</name></author><author><name>Alcino J Silva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Memories engage ensembles of neurons across different brain regions within a memory system. However, it is unclear whether the allocation of a memory to these ensembles is coordinated across brain regions. To address this question, we used CREB expression to bias memory allocation in one brain region, and rabies retrograde tracing to test memory allocation in connected presynaptic neurons in the other brain regions. We find that biasing allocation of CTA memory in the basolateral amygdala (BLA) also biases memory allocation in presynaptic neurons of the insular cortex (IC). By manipulating the allocation of CTA memory to specific neurons in both BLA and IC, we found that we increased their connectivity and enhanced CTA memory performance. These results – which are corroborated by mathematical simulations, and by studies with auditory fear conditioning – demonstrate that a retrograde mechanism coordinates the allocation of memories across different brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466361" rel="alternate" title="A retrograde mechanism coordinates memory allocation across brain regions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467325</id><title>Glioma synapses recruit mechanisms of adaptive plasticity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.894637+00:00</updated><author><name>Kathryn R Taylor</name></author><author><name>Tara Barron</name></author><author><name>Helena Zhang</name></author><author><name>Alexa C Hui</name></author><author><name>Griffin G Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Lijun Ni</name></author><author><name>Humsa S Venkatesh</name></author><author><name>Peter Du</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Mancusi</name></author><author><name>Belgin Yalcin</name></author><author><name>Isabelle J Chau</name></author><author><name>Anitha Ponnuswami</name></author><author><name>Razina Aziz-Bose</name></author><author><name>Michelle Monje</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The nervous system plays an increasingly appreciated role in the regulation of cancer. In malignant gliomas, neuronal activity drives tumor progression not only through paracrine signaling factors such as neuroligin-3 and brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), but also through electrophysiologically functional neuron-to-glioma synapses. Malignant synapses are mediated by calcium-permeable AMPA (α-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole propionic acid) receptors in both pediatric and adult high-grade gliomas, and consequent depolarization of the glioma cell membrane drives tumor proliferation. The nervous system exhibits plasticity of both synaptic connectivity and synaptic strength, contributing to neural circuit form and functions. In health, one factor that promotes plasticity of synaptic connectivity and strength is activity-regulated secretion of the neurotrophin BDNF. Here, we show that malignant synapses exhibit similar plasticity regulated by BDNF-TrkB (tropomyosin receptor kinase B) signaling. Signaling through the receptor TrkB, BDNF promotes AMPA receptor trafficking to the glioma cell membrane, resulting in increased amplitude of glutamate-evoked currents in the malignant cells. This potentiation of malignant synaptic strength shares mechanistic features with the long-term potentiation (LTP) that is thought to contribute to memory and learning in the healthy brain. BDNF-TrkB signaling also regulates the number of neuron-to-glioma synapses. Abrogation of activity-regulated BDNF secretion from the brain microenvironment or loss of TrkB in human glioma cells exerts growth inhibitory effects in vivo and in neuron:glioma co-cultures that cannot be explained by classical growth factor signaling alone. Blocking TrkB genetically or pharmacologically abrogates these effects of BDNF on glioma synapses and substantially prolongs survival in xenograft models of pediatric glioblastoma and diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma (DIPG). Taken together, these findings indicate that BDNF-TrkB signaling promotes malignant synaptic plasticity and augments tumor progression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467325" rel="alternate" title="Glioma synapses recruit mechanisms of adaptive plasticity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466989</id><title>Validating the wearable MUSE headset for EEG spectral analysis and Frontal Alpha Asymmetry (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.895134+00:00</updated><author><name>Cedric Cannard</name></author><author><name>Helane Wahbeh</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Delorme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;EEG power spectral density (PSD), the individual alpha frequency (IAF) and the frontal alpha asymmetry (FAA) are all EEG spectral measures that have been widely used to evaluate cognitive and attentional processes in experimental and clinical settings, and that can be used for real-world applications (e.g., remote EEG monitoring, brain-computer interfaces, neurofeedback, neuromodulation, etc.). Potential applications remain limited by the high cost, low mobility, and long preparation times associated with high-density EEG recording systems. Low-density wearable systems address these issues and can increase access to larger and diversified samples. The present study tested whether a low-cost, 4-channel wearable EEG system (the MUSE) could be used to quickly measure continuous EEG data, yielding similar frequency components compared to research a grade EEG system (the 64-channel BIOSEMI Active Two). We compare the spectral measures from MUSE EEG data referenced to mastoids to those from BIOSEMI EEG data with two different references for validation. A minimal amount of data was deliberately collected to test the feasibility for real-world applications (EEG setup and data collection being completed in under 5 min). We show that the MUSE can be used to examine power spectral density (PSD) in all frequency bands, the individual alpha frequency (IAF; i.e., peak alpha frequency and alpha center of gravity), and frontal alpha asymmetry. Furthermore, we observed satisfying internal consistency reliability in alpha power and asymmetry measures recorded with the MUSE. Estimating asymmetry on PAF and CoG frequencies did not yield significant advantages relative to the traditional method (whole alpha band). These findings should advance human neurophysiological monitoring using wearable neurotechnologies in large participant samples and increase the feasibility of their implementation in real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466989" rel="alternate" title="Validating the wearable MUSE headset for EEG spectral analysis and Frontal Alpha Asymmetry (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467014</id><title>Age-dependent increased sag current in human pyramidal neurons dampens baseline cortical activity (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.895411+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandre Guet-McCreight</name></author><author><name>Homeira Moradi Chameh</name></author><author><name>Sara Mahallati</name></author><author><name>Margaret Wishart</name></author><author><name>Shreejoy J Tripathy</name></author><author><name>Taufik A Valiante</name></author><author><name>Etay Hay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aging involves various neurobiological changes, although their effect on brain function in humans remains poorly understood. The growing availability of human neuronal and circuit data provides opportunities for uncovering age-dependent changes of brain networks and for constraining models to predict consequences on brain activity. Here we found increased sag current in human layer 5 pyramidal neurons from older subjects, and captured this effect in biophysical models of younger and older pyramidal neurons. We used these models to simulate detailed layer 5 microcircuits and found lower baseline firing in older pyramidal neuron microcircuits, with minimal effect on response. We then validated the predicted reduced baseline firing using extracellular multi-electrode recordings from human brain slices of different ages. Our results thus report changes in human pyramidal neuron input integration properties that can sufficiently account for age-dependent decreases in cortical resting state activity and may underpin a clinical relevance in aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467014" rel="alternate" title="Age-dependent increased sag current in human pyramidal neurons dampens baseline cortical activity (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466479</id><title>Cycles of transcription and local translation consolidate Arc protein at dendritic sites (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.895836+00:00</updated><author><name>Sulagna Das</name></author><author><name>Pablo J. Lituma</name></author><author><name>Pablo E. Castillo</name></author><author><name>Robert H. Singer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maintenance of long-term memory requires transcription and translation of activity-regulated genes. Many of these are immediate early genes (IEGs) with short-lived mRNAs and proteins, often decaying rapidly after stimulation. It remains unknown how an IEG with rapid mRNA and protein turnover can impact long-lasting changes at the synapses. Here, we imaged the long-term transcription and translation dynamics of an IEG, &lt;italic&gt;Arc&lt;/italic&gt;, important for memory consolidation, after stimulation in individual neurons. We demonstrated that the gene underwent reactivation in the same neuron without an additional stimulus, often at the same allele. The cycling of &lt;italic&gt;Arc&lt;/italic&gt; transcription required protein synthesis. Indeed, phases of &lt;italic&gt;Arc&lt;/italic&gt; translation were coordinated with the transcription cycles. &lt;italic&gt;Arc&lt;/italic&gt; mRNAs from later cycles preferentially localized at dendritic sites marked by previous Arc protein, thereby creating hubs of local protein enrichment, potentially maintained by cycles of dendritic translation. These results identify novel characteristics of an IEG and provide insights into how unstable proteins may be sustained over the long-time scale of memory consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466479" rel="alternate" title="Cycles of transcription and local translation consolidate Arc protein at dendritic sites (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466879</id><title>Biological Factors and Self-Perception of Stress Predict Human Freeze-Like Responses in the Context of Self-Defence Training and Personal Experience with Violence (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.896139+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter Lenart</name></author><author><name>Michal Vit</name></author><author><name>Klara Mareckova</name></author><author><name>Jan Novak</name></author><author><name>Filip Zlamal</name></author><author><name>Michal Mikl</name></author><author><name>Zdenko Reguli</name></author><author><name>Martin Bugala</name></author><author><name>Jitka Cihounkova</name></author><author><name>Pavel Precechtel</name></author><author><name>Vojtech Malcik</name></author><author><name>Tomas Vojtisek</name></author><author><name>Jan Kucera</name></author><author><name>Jana Fialova Kucerova</name></author><author><name>Veronika Hajnova</name></author><author><name>Marie Tomandlova</name></author><author><name>Radek Sip</name></author><author><name>Lucie Rackova</name></author><author><name>Marketa Grulichova</name></author><author><name>Josef Tomandl</name></author><author><name>Milan Brazdil</name></author><author><name>Julie Bienertova-Vasku</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many animals react to threatening stimuli such as a predator attacks by freezing. However, little experimental research investigated freeze response in humans. Here, we have employed practices commonly used in self-defence training to create two unique scenarios simulating armed physical attacks. Sixty healthy men volunteers divided into three groups of twenty (untrained, trained but unexperienced, trained and experienced) underwent these scenarios accompanied by measurement of biochemical, physiological, and psychological markers of stress. All participants also underwent an fMRI session during which they observed neutral and negative images from the International Affective Picture System (IAPS). Our results show that scenarios simulating physical attacks can induce a freeze-like response in men. In addition, we demonstrate that while electrodermal activity (EDA), subjective stress perception, and brain activity in fMRI predict freeze-like response in men, their effect on freeze-like response is entirely dependent on the level of training and experience of a given individual.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466879" rel="alternate" title="Biological Factors and Self-Perception of Stress Predict Human Freeze-Like Responses in the Context of Self-Defence Training and Personal Experience with Violence (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466340</id><title>Analysis of cellular and synaptic mechanisms behind spontaneous cortical activity in vitro: Insights from optimization of spiking neuronal network models (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.896573+00:00</updated><author><name>Jugoslava Aćimović</name></author><author><name>Tuomo Mäki-Marttunen</name></author><author><name>Heidi Teppola</name></author><author><name>Marja-Leena Linne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spontaneous network bursts, the intervals of intense network-wide activity interleaved with longer periods of sparse activity, are a hallmark phenomenon observed in cortical networks at postnatal developmental stages. Generation, propagation and termination of network bursts depend on a combination of synaptic, cellular and network mechanisms; however, the interplay between these mechanisms is not fully understood. We study this interplay &lt;italic&gt;in silico,&lt;/italic&gt; using a new data-driven framework for generating spiking neuronal networks fitted to the microelectrode array recordings. We recorded the network bursting activity from rat postnatal cortical networks under several pharmacological conditions. In each condition, the function of specific excitatory and inhibitory synaptic receptors was reduced in order to examine their impact on global network dynamics. The obtained data was used to develop two complementary model fitting protocols for automatic model generation. These protocols allowed us to disentangle systematically the modeled cellular and synaptic mechanisms that affect the observed network bursts. We confirmed that the change in excitatory and inhibitory synaptic transmission &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;, consistent with pharmacological conditions, can account for the changes in network bursts relative to the control data. Reproducing the exact recorded network bursts statistics required adapting both the synaptic transmission and the cellular excitability separately for each pharmacological condition. Our results bring new understanding of the complex interplay between cellular, synaptic and network mechanisms supporting the burst dynamics. While here we focused on analysis of &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; data, our approach can be applied &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; given that the appropriate experimental data is available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;New &amp;amp; Noteworthy&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We studied the role of synaptic mechanisms in shaping the neural population activity by proposing a new method to combine experimental data and data-driven computational modeling based on spiking neuronal networks. We analyze a dataset recorded from postnatal rat cortical cultures &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; under the pharmacological influence of excitatory and inhibitory synaptic receptor antagonists. Our computational model identifies neurobiological mechanisms necessary to reproduce the changes in population activity seen across pharmacological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466340" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of cellular and synaptic mechanisms behind spontaneous cortical activity in vitro: Insights from optimization of spiking neuronal network models (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466896</id><title>Influence of Response Criterion on Nociceptive Detection Thresholds and Evoked Potentials (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.898624+00:00</updated><author><name>Boudewijn van den Berg</name></author><author><name>L. Vanwinsen</name></author><author><name>G. Pezzali</name></author><author><name>Jan R. Buitenweg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pain scientists and clinicians search for objective measures of altered nociceptive processing to study and stratify chronic pain patients. Nociceptive processing can be studied by observing a combination of nociceptive detection thresholds and evoked potentials. However, it is unknown whether the nociceptive detection threshold measured using a Go-/No-Go (GN) procedure can be biased by a response criterion. In this study, we compared nociceptive detection thresholds, psychometric slopes and central evoked potentials obtained during a GN procedure with those obtained during a 2-interval forced choice (2IFC) procedure to determine 1) if the nociceptive detection threshold during a GN procedure is biased by a criterion and 2) to determine if nociceptive evoked potentials observed in response to stimuli around the detection threshold are biased by a criterion. We found that the detection threshold can be higher when assessed using a GN procedure in comparison with the 2IFC procedure. The average P2 component in the central evoked potential showed on-off behavior with respect to stimulus detection and increased proportionally with the detection probability during a GN procedure. These data suggest that nociceptive detection thresholds estimated using a GN procedure are subject to a response criterion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466896" rel="alternate" title="Influence of Response Criterion on Nociceptive Detection Thresholds and Evoked Potentials (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466525</id><title>Concerted cellular responses to type I interferon propel memory impairment associated with amyloid β plaques (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.899058+00:00</updated><author><name>Ethan R. Roy</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Chiu</name></author><author><name>Sanming Li</name></author><author><name>Nicholas E. Propson</name></author><author><name>Hui Zheng</name></author><author><name>Wei Cao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite well-documented maladaptive neuroinflammation in Alzheimer’s disease (AD), the principal signal that drives memory and cognitive impairment remains elusive. Here, we reveal robust, age-dependent cellular reactions to type I interferon (IFN), an innate immune cytokine aberrantly elicited by β amyloid plaques, and examine their role in cognition and neuropathology relevant to AD in a murine amyloidosis model. Long-term blockade of IFN receptor rescued both memory and synaptic deficits, and also resulted in reduced microgliosis, inflammation, and neuritic pathology. Interestingly, microglia-specific IFN receptor ablation attenuated the loss of post-synaptic terminals, whereas IFN signaling in neural cells contributed to pre-synaptic alteration and plaque accumulation. Intriguingly, IFN pathway activation displayed a strong inverse correlation with cognitive performance, promoting selective synapse engulfment by microglia rather than amyloid plaques. Overall, IFN signaling represents a critical module within the neuroinflammatory network of AD and prompts a concerted cellular state that is detrimental to memory and cognition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466525" rel="alternate" title="Concerted cellular responses to type I interferon propel memory impairment associated with amyloid β plaques (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466949</id><title>Time-of-day influences on skill acquisition and consolidation after physical and mental practices (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.899475+00:00</updated><author><name>Charlene TRUONG</name></author><author><name>Pauline M HILT</name></author><author><name>Fatma BOUGUILA</name></author><author><name>Marco BOVE</name></author><author><name>Florent LEBON</name></author><author><name>Charalambos PAPAXANTHIS</name></author><author><name>Celia RUFFINO</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Time-of-day influences both physical and mental performance. Its impact on motor learning is, however, not well established yet. Here, using a finger tapping-task, we investigated the time-of-day effect on skill acquisition (i.e., immediately after a physical or mental practice session) and consolidation (i.e., 24 hours later). Two groups (one physical and one mental) were trained in the morning (10 a.m.) and two others (one physical and one mental) in the afternoon (3 p.m.). We found an enhancement of motor skill following both types of practice, whatever the time of the day, with a better acquisition for the physical than the mental group. Interestingly, there was a better consolidation for both groups when the training session was scheduled in the afternoon. Overall, our results indicate that the time-of-day positively influences motor skill consolidation and thus must be considered to optimize training protocols in sport and clinical domains to potentiate motor (re)learning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466949" rel="alternate" title="Time-of-day influences on skill acquisition and consolidation after physical and mental practices (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466940</id><title>Towards a general framework for modeling large-scale biophysical neuronal networks: a full-scale computational model of the rat dentate gyrus (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.900147+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivan Georgiev Raikov</name></author><author><name>Aaron D Milstein</name></author><author><name>Prannath Moolchand</name></author><author><name>Gergely G Szabo</name></author><author><name>Calvin J Schneider</name></author><author><name>Darian H Hadjiabadi</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Pierri Chatzikalymniou</name></author><author><name>Ivan Soltesz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Large-scale computational models of the brain are necessary to accurately represent anatomical and functional variability in neuronal biophysics across brain regions and also to capture and study local and global interactions between neuronal populations on a behaviorally-relevant temporal scale. We present the methodology behind and an initial implementation of a novel open-source computational framework for construction, simulation, and analysis of models consisting of millions of neurons on high-performance computing systems, based on the NEURON and CoreNEURON simulators. This framework includes an HDF5-based data format for storing morphological, synaptic, and connectivity information of large neuronal network models, and an accompanying open source software library that provides efficient, scalable parallel storage and MPI-based data movement capabilities. We outline our approaches for constructing detailed large-scale biophysical models with topographical connectivity and input stimuli, and present simulation results obtained with a full-scale model of the dentate gyrus constructed with our framework.  The model generates sparse and spatially selective population activity that fits well with in-vivo experimental data. Moreover, our approach is fully general and can be applied to modeling other regions of the hippocampal formation in order to rapidly evaluate specific hypotheses about large-scale neural architectural features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.02.466940" rel="alternate" title="Towards a general framework for modeling large-scale biophysical neuronal networks: a full-scale computational model of the rat dentate gyrus (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466692</id><title>Caste, sex, and parasitism influence brain plasticity in a social wasp (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.901103+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristine M. Gandia</name></author><author><name>Federico Cappa</name></author><author><name>David Baracchi</name></author><author><name>Mark. E. Hauber</name></author><author><name>Laura Beani</name></author><author><name>Floria M. K. Uy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phenotypic plasticity is the capacity of a single genotype to exhibit different phenotypes, and can be an adaptive response to specific environmental and social conditions. Social insects are particularly well-suited to study plasticity, because the division of labor amongst females and the different life histories of males and females are associated with specific sensory needs. Here, we take advantage of the social wasp &lt;italic&gt;Polistes dominula&lt;/italic&gt; to explore if brain plasticity is influenced by caste and sex, and the exploitation by the parasite &lt;italic&gt;Xenos vesparum&lt;/italic&gt;. Within sexes, males had proportionally larger optic lobes, while females, regardless of caste, had larger antennal lobes, which is consistent with sensory needs of sex-specific life histories. Within castes, reproductive females had larger calyces, as predicted by their sensory needs for extensive within-colony interactions and forming winter aggregations, than workers who spend more time foraging for nest material and prey. Surprisingly, parasites had different effects on female and male hosts. Female workers were castrated and behaviorally manipulated by female or male parasites, but only showed moderate differences in relative allocation of different brain tissue compared to non-parasitized workers. In contrast, the testes and behavior of parasitized males were essentially unaffected, but they had smaller brains and greater relative volume of most sensory brain regions than non-parasitized males. Our results are consistent with caste and sex mediating brain plasticity in &lt;italic&gt;P. dominula&lt;/italic&gt; and that the parasite’s manipulation can also drive differential allocation of brain regions depending on host sex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.01.466692" rel="alternate" title="Caste, sex, and parasitism influence brain plasticity in a social wasp (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466906</id><title>Anatomically-based skeleton kinetics and pose estimation in freely-moving rodents (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.901582+00:00</updated><author><name>Arne Monsees</name></author><author><name>Kay-Michael Voit</name></author><author><name>Damian J Wallace</name></author><author><name>Juergen Sawinski</name></author><author><name>Edyta Leks</name></author><author><name>Klaus Scheffler</name></author><author><name>Jakob H Macke</name></author><author><name>Jason ND Kerr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Forming a complete picture of the relationship between neural activity and body kinetics requires quantification of skeletal joint biomechanics during behavior. However, without detailed knowledge of the underlying skeletal motion, inferring joint kinetics from surface tracking approaches is difficult, especially for animals where the relationship between surface anatomy and skeleton changes during motion. Here we developed a videography-based method enabling detailed three-dimensional kinetic quantification of an anatomically defined skeleton in untethered freely-behaving animals. This skeleton-based model has been constrained by anatomical principles and joint motion limits and provided skeletal pose estimates for a range of rodent sizes, even when limbs were occluded. Model-inferred joint kinetics for both gait and gap-crossing behaviors were verified by direct measurement of limb placement, showing that complex decision making behaviors can be accurately reconstructed at the level of skeletal kinetics using our anatomically constrained model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466906" rel="alternate" title="Anatomically-based skeleton kinetics and pose estimation in freely-moving rodents (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467146</id><title>Intact Drosophila Whole Brain Cellular Quantitation reveals Sexual Dimorphism (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.902084+00:00</updated><author><name>Wei Jiao</name></author><author><name>Gard Spreemann</name></author><author><name>Evelyne Ruchti</name></author><author><name>Soumya Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Ying Shi</name></author><author><name>R. Steven Stowers</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Hess</name></author><author><name>Brian D. McCabe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Establishing with precision the quantity and identity of the cell types of the brain is a prerequisite for a detailed compendium of gene and protein expression in the central nervous system. Currently however, strict quantitation of cell numbers has been achieved only for the nervous system of C.elegans.   Here we describe the development of a synergistic pipeline of molecular genetic, imaging, and computational technologies designed to allow high-throughput, precise quantitation with cellular resolution of reporters of gene expression in intact whole tissues with complex cellular constitutions such as the brain.  We have deployed the approach to determine with exactitude the number of functional neurons and glia in the entire intact Drosophila larval brain, revealing fewer neurons and many more glial cells than previously estimated.   Moreover, we discover an unexpected divergence between the sexes at this juvenile developmental stage, with female brains having significantly more neurons than males.  Topological analysis of our data establishes that this sexual dimorphism extends to deeper features of brain organisation.   Our methodology enables robust and accurate quantification of the number and positioning of cells within intact organs, facilitating sophisticated analysis of cellular identity, diversity, and expression characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467146" rel="alternate" title="Intact Drosophila Whole Brain Cellular Quantitation reveals Sexual Dimorphism (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467132</id><title>Synergy of color and motion vision for detecting approaching objects in Drosophila (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.903376+00:00</updated><author><name>Kit D Longden</name></author><author><name>Edward M Rogers</name></author><author><name>Aljoscha Nern</name></author><author><name>Heather Dionne</name></author><author><name>Michael B Reiser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Color and motion are used by many species to identify salient moving objects. They are processed largely independently, but color contributes to motion processing in humans, for example, enabling moving colored objects to be detected when their luminance matches the background. Here, we demonstrate an unexpected, additional contribution of color to motion vision in Drosophila. We show that behavioral ON-motion responses are more sensitive to UV than for OFF-motion, and we identify cellular pathways connecting UV-sensitive R7 photoreceptors to ON and OFF-motion-sensitive T4 and T5 cells, using neurogenetics and calcium imaging. Remarkably, the synergy of color and motion vision enhances the detection of approaching UV discs, but not green discs with the same chromatic contrast, and we show how this generalizes for visual systems with ON and OFF pathways. Our results provide a computational and circuit basis for how color enhances motion vision to favor the detection of saliently colored objects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.467132" rel="alternate" title="Synergy of color and motion vision for detecting approaching objects in Drosophila (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466767</id><title>SorCS2 dynamically interacts with TrkB and GluN2B to control neurotransmission and Huntington’s disease progression (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.903919+00:00</updated><author><name>Alena Salašová</name></author><author><name>Niels Sanderhoff Degn</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Paveliev</name></author><author><name>Niels Kjærgaard Madsen</name></author><author><name>Saray López Benito</name></author><author><name>Plinio Casarotto</name></author><author><name>Peter Lund Ovesen</name></author><author><name>Benedicte Vestergaard</name></author><author><name>Andreea Cornelia Udrea</name></author><author><name>Lilian Kisiswa</name></author><author><name>Lucie Woloszczuková</name></author><author><name>Islam Faress</name></author><author><name>Sadegh Nabavi</name></author><author><name>Eero Castrén</name></author><author><name>Juan Carlos Arévalo</name></author><author><name>Mai Marie Holm</name></author><author><name>Mads Fuglsang Kjølby</name></author><author><name>Ulrik Bølcho</name></author><author><name>Anders Nykjaer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Huntington’s disease (HD) is a fatal neurodegenerative disorder characterized by progressive motor dysfunction and loss of medium spiny neurons (MSNs) in dorsal striatum. Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) sustains functionality and integrity of MSNs, and thus reduced BDNF signaling is integral to the disease. Here we show that SorCS2 is expressed in MSNs with reduced expression in R6/1 HD model, and that SorCS2 deficiency exacerbates the disease progression in R6/1 mice. Furthermore, we find that SorCS2 binds TrkB and the NMDA receptor subunit GluN2B, which is required to control neurotransmission in corticostriatal synapses. While BDNF stimulates SorCS2-TrkB complex formation to enable TrkB signaling, it disengages SorCS2 from GluN2B, leading to enrichment of the subunit at postsynaptic densities. Consequently, long-term potentiation (LTP) is abolished in SorCS2 deficient mice, despite increased striatal TrkB and unaltered BDNF expression. In contrast, the addition of exogenous BDNF rescues the phenotype. Finally, GluN2B, but not GluN2A, currents are also severely impaired in the SorCS2 KO mice. To conclude, we uncovered that SorCS2 dynamically targets TrkB and GluN2B to orchestrate BDNF-dependent plasticity in MSNs of dorsal striatum. We propose that SorCS2 deficiency impairs MSN function thereby increasing neuronal vulnerability and accelerating the motor deficits in Huntington’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.03.466767" rel="alternate" title="SorCS2 dynamically interacts with TrkB and GluN2B to control neurotransmission and Huntington’s disease progression (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>