<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.461371+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466000</id><title>Neurons in human pre-supplementary motor area encode key computations for value-based choice (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.461761+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomas G. Aquino</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey Cockburn</name></author><author><name>Adam N. Mamelak</name></author><author><name>Ueli Rutishauser</name></author><author><name>John P. O’Doherty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adaptive behavior in real-world environments demands that choices integrate over several variables, including the novelty of the options under consideration, their expected value, and uncertainty in value estimation. We recorded neurons from the human pre-supplementary motor area (preSMA), ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) and dorsal anterior cingulate to probe how integration over decision variables occurs during decision-making. In contrast to the other areas, preSMA neurons not only represented separate pre-decision variables for each choice option, but also encoded an integrated utility signal and, subsequently, the decision itself. Conversely, post-decision related encoding of variables for the chosen option was more widely distributed and especially prominent in vmPFC. Our findings position the human preSMA as central to the implementation of value-based decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466000" rel="alternate" title="Neurons in human pre-supplementary motor area encode key computations for value-based choice (22 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466306</id><title>Vagus nerve stimulation accelerates motor learning through cholinergic modulation (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.461980+00:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Bowles</name></author><author><name>Jordan Hickman</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyu Peng</name></author><author><name>W. Ryan Williamson</name></author><author><name>Rongchen Huang</name></author><author><name>Kayden Washington</name></author><author><name>Dane Donegan</name></author><author><name>Cristin Welle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vagus nerve stimulation (VNS) is a novel therapeutic option to treat a broad and rapidly expanding set of neurologic conditions. While classically used to treat epilepsy and depression, more recently VNS has received FDA approval as a therapeutic option for stroke rehabilitation and is under preclinical and clinical investigation for other disorders. Despite benefits across a diverse range of neurological disorders, the mechanism for how VNS influences central nervous system circuitry is not well described. A deeper understanding of the influence of VNS on neural circuits and activity is needed to optimize the use of VNS therapy. To define the complex dynamics between VNS, neuronal activity, plasticity, and behavior, we performed chronic VNS in mice during the learning of a dexterous motor task, and leveraged genetic tools to perform optogenetic circuit dissection and longitudinal in vivo imaging calcium activity in cortical neurons. We find VNS has the most robust effect on motor learning when paired with successful movement outcome, while randomized stimulation impairs learning, consistent with VNS serving as a reinforcement cue. In motor cortex, VNS paired with movement outcome selectively modulates neurons that are representing outcome, but not other movement-related neurons. Finally, cholinergic signaling from basal forebrain is required both for VNS-driven improvements in motor learning and the effects on neural activity in M1. This suggests that the effect of VNS on motor learning is mediated by cholinergic signaling, and also presents a novel role for cholinergic signaling in endogenous motor learning. These data imply that VNS therapy may be mediated by augmenting reinforcement cues with precisely-timed cholinergic neuronal activity, presenting strategies for optimizing the use of VNS to treat neurologic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466306" rel="alternate" title="Vagus nerve stimulation accelerates motor learning through cholinergic modulation (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465991</id><title>FiberNeat: unsupervised streamline clustering and white matter tract filtering in latent space (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.462279+00:00</updated><author><name>Bramsh Qamar Chandio</name></author><author><name>Tamoghna Chattopadhyay</name></author><author><name>Conor Owens-Walton</name></author><author><name>Julio E. Villalon Reina</name></author><author><name>Leila Nabulsi</name></author><author><name>Sophia I. Thomopoulos</name></author><author><name>Eleftherios Garyfallidis</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Thompson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole-brain tractograms generated from diffusion MRI digitally represent the white matter structure of the brain and are composed of millions of streamlines. Such tractograms can have false positive and anatomically implausible streamlines. To obtain anatomically relevant streamlines and tracts, supervised and unsupervised methods can be used for tractogram clustering and tract extraction. Here we propose FiberNeat, an unsupervised streamline clustering and tract filtering method. FiberNeat takes an input set of streamlines that could either be unlabeled clusters or labeled tracts. Individual clusters/tracts are projected into a latent space using nonlinear dimensionality reduction techniques, such as t-SNE and UMAP, to find spurious and outlier streamlines. In addition, outlier streamline clusters are detected using DBSCAN and then removed from the data in streamline space. Quantitative comparisons with expertly delineated tracts show the promise of the approach. This approach can be deployed as a filtering step after tracts are extracted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465991" rel="alternate" title="FiberNeat: unsupervised streamline clustering and white matter tract filtering in latent space (18 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466271</id><title>Cortical adaptation to sound reverberation (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.462466+00:00</updated><author><name>Aleksandar Z Ivanov</name></author><author><name>Andrew J King</name></author><author><name>Ben Willmore</name></author><author><name>Kerry M M Walker</name></author><author><name>Nicol S Harper</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In almost every natural environment, sounds are reflected by nearby objects, producing many delayed and distorted copies of the original sound, known as reverberation. Our brains usually cope well with reverberation, allowing us to recognize sound sources regardless of their environments. In contrast, reverberation can cause severe difficulties for speech recognition algorithms and hearing-impaired people. The present study examines how the auditory system copes with reverberation. We trained a linear model to recover a rich set of natural, anechoic sounds from their simulated reverberant counterparts. The model neurons achieved this by extending the inhibitory component of their receptive filters for more reverberant spaces, and did so in a frequency-dependent manner. These predicted effects were observed in the responses of auditory cortical neurons of ferrets in the same simulated reverberant environments. Together, these results suggest that auditory cortical neurons adapt to reverberation by adjusting their filtering properties in a manner consistent with dereverberation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466271" rel="alternate" title="Cortical adaptation to sound reverberation (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.24.465610</id><title>Neural basis of learning to perceive speech through touch using an acoustic-to-vibrotactile speech sensory substitution (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.462721+00:00</updated><author><name>Patrick S. Malone</name></author><author><name>Silvio P. Eberhardt</name></author><author><name>Edward T. Auer</name></author><author><name>Richard Klein</name></author><author><name>Lynne E. Bernstein</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Riesenhuber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The goal of sensory substitution is to convey the information transduced by one sensory system through a novel sensory modality. One example is vibrotactile (VT) speech, for which acoustic speech is transformed into vibrotactile patterns. Despite an almost century-long history of studying vibrotactile speech, there has been no study of the neural bases of VT speech learning. We here trained hearing adult participants to recognize VT speech syllables. Using fMRI, we showed that both somatosensory (left post-central gyrus) and auditory (right temporal lobe) regions acquire selectivity for VT speech stimuli following training. The right planum temporale in particular was selective for both VT and auditory speech. EEG source-estimated activity revealed temporal dynamics consistent with direct, low-latency engagement of right temporal lobe following activation of the left post-central gyrus. Our results suggest that VT speech learning achieves integration with the auditory speech system by “piggybacking” onto corresponding auditory speech representations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In sensory substitution, the information conveyed by one sensory system is used to replace the function of another. Blind individuals, for example, can learn to use a visual-to-acoustic sensory substitution device to navigate the world. We tested the hypothesis that sensory substitution can more generally occur in typical individuals, by exploiting the existence of multi-sensory convergence areas in the brain. We trained hearing participants to recognize speech syllables presented as vibrotactile stimulation patterns. Using fMRI and EEG, we show that vibrotactile speech learning integrates with the auditory speech system by “piggybacking” onto corresponding auditory speech representations. These results suggest that the human brain can bootstrap new senses by leveraging one sensory system to process information normally processed by another.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.24.465610" rel="alternate" title="Neural basis of learning to perceive speech through touch using an acoustic-to-vibrotactile speech sensory substitution (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.466508</id><title>A neural substrate for Bayesian integration in human parietal cortex (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.462908+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas M. Singletary</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline Gottlieb</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Horga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Making adaptive decisions often requires inferring unobservable states based on unreliable information. Bayesian logic prescribes that individuals form probabilistic beliefs about a state by integrating the likelihood of new evidence with their prior beliefs, but human neuroimaging studies on probability representations have not typically examined this integration process. We developed an inference fMRI task in which participants estimated the posterior probability of a hidden state while we parametrically modulated the prior probability of the state, the likelihood of the supporting evidence, and a monetary penalty for estimation inaccuracy. Consistent with a neural substrate for Bayesian integration, activation in left posterior parietal cortex tracked the estimated posterior probability of the solicited state and its components of prior probability and likelihood, all independently of expected value. This activation further reflected deviations in individual reports from objective probabilities. Thus, this region may provide a neural substrate for humans' ability to approximate Bayesian inference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.30.466508" rel="alternate" title="A neural substrate for Bayesian integration in human parietal cortex (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466135</id><title>Inhibiting adult neurogenesis differentially affects spatial learning in females and males (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.463074+00:00</updated><author><name>Timothy P O’Leary</name></author><author><name>Baran Askari</name></author><author><name>Bonnie Lee</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Darby</name></author><author><name>Cypress Knudson</name></author><author><name>Alyssa M Ash</name></author><author><name>Desiree R Seib</name></author><author><name>Delane F Espinueva</name></author><author><name>Jason S Snyder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adult hippocampal neurogenesis has been implicated in the spatial processing functions of the hippocampus but ablating neurogenesis does not consistently lead to behavioral deficits in spatial tasks. Parallel studies have shown that adult-born neurons also regulate behavioral responses to stressful and aversive stimuli. We therefore hypothesized that spatial functions of adult-born neurons may be more prominent under conditions of stress, and may differ between males and females given established sex differences in stress responding. To test this we trained intact and neurogenesis-deficient rats in the spatial water maze at temperatures that vary in their degree of aversiveness. At standard temperatures (25°C) ablating neurogenesis did not alter learning and memory in either sex, consistent with prior work. However, in cold water (16°C), ablating neurogenesis had divergent sex-dependent effects: relative to intact rats, male neurogenesis-deficient rats were slower to escape and female neurogenesis-deficient rats were faster. Neurogenesis promoted temperature-related changes in search strategy in females, but it promoted search strategy stability in males. Females displayed greater recruitment of the dorsal hippocampus than males, particularly at 16°C. However, blocking neurogenesis did not alter activity-dependent immediate-early gene expression in either sex. Finally, morphological analyses of retrovirally-labelled neurons revealed greater experience-dependent plasticity in new neurons in males. Neurons had comparable morphology in untrained rats but 16°C training increased spine density, and 25°C training caused shrinkage of mossy fiber presynaptic terminals, specifically in males. Collectively, these findings indicate that neurogenesis functions in memory are prominent under conditions of stress, they provide the first evidence for sex differences in the behavioral function of newborn neurons, and they suggest possibly distinct roles for neurogenesis in cognition and mental health in males and females.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466135" rel="alternate" title="Inhibiting adult neurogenesis differentially affects spatial learning in females and males (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465922</id><title>Computational and neural mechanisms of affected beliefs (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.463320+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Müller-Pinzler</name></author><author><name>Nora Czekalla</name></author><author><name>Annalina V Mayer</name></author><author><name>Alexander Schröder</name></author><author><name>David S Stolz</name></author><author><name>Frieder Michel Paulus</name></author><author><name>Sören Krach</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The feedback people receive on their behavior shapes the process of belief formation and self-efficacy in mastering a given task. The neural and computational mechanisms of how the subjective value of these beliefs and corresponding affect bias the learning process are yet unclear. Here we investigate this question during learning of self-efficacy beliefs using fMRI, pupillometry, computational modeling and individual differences in affective experience. Biases in the formation of self-efficacy beliefs were associated with affect, pupil dilation and neural activity within the anterior insula, amygdala, VTA/SN, and mPFC. Specifically, neural and pupil responses map the valence of the prediction errors in correspondence to the experienced affect and learning bias people show during belief formation. Together with the functional connectivity dynamics of the anterior insula within this network our results hint towards neural and computational mechanisms that integrate affect in the process of belief formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465922" rel="alternate" title="Computational and neural mechanisms of affected beliefs (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.463794</id><title>Chemogenetic activation of Locus Coeruleus Noradrenergic Neurons Modulates the Default Mode Network (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.463660+00:00</updated><author><name>Esteban A. Oyarzabal</name></author><author><name>Liming Hsu</name></author><author><name>Manasmita Das</name></author><author><name>Tzu-Hao Harry Chao</name></author><author><name>Jingheng Zhou</name></author><author><name>Sheng Song</name></author><author><name>Weiting Zhang</name></author><author><name>Kathleen G. Smith</name></author><author><name>Natale R. Sciolino</name></author><author><name>Irina Y. Evsyukova</name></author><author><name>Hong Yuan</name></author><author><name>Sung-Ho Lee</name></author><author><name>Guohong Cui</name></author><author><name>Patricia Jensen</name></author><author><name>Yen-Yu Ian Shih</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The default mode network (DMN) of the brain is involved in cognition, emotion regulation, impulsivity, and balancing between internally and externally focused states. Dysregulation of DMN has been implicated in several neurological and neuropsychiatric disorders. In this study, we used functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), positron emission tomography (PET), and spectral fiber-photometry to investigate the selective neuromodulatory effect of norepinephrine (NE)-releasing noradrenergic neurons in the locus coeruleus (LC) on DMN in mice. Chemogenetic-induced LC-NE activation decreased cerebral blood volume (CBV) and glucose uptake, while increasing synchronous low frequency power within the frontal cortices of the DMN. Fiber-photometry results corroborated these findings, showing LC-NE activation induces NE release, enhances calcium-weighted neuronal spiking, and reduces CBV in the anterior cingulate cortex. These data suggest the lack of conventional stimulus-evoked coupling between neuronal activity and CBV in the frontal DMN. We also demonstrated that chemogenetic activation of LC-NE neurons strengthen functional connectivity within the frontal DMN, and this effect is causally mediated by reduced modulatory inputs from retrosplenial and hippocampal regions to the association cortices of the DMN.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.463794" rel="alternate" title="Chemogenetic activation of Locus Coeruleus Noradrenergic Neurons Modulates the Default Mode Network (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466284</id><title>Spontaneous emergence of topologically robust grid cell modules: A multiscale instability theory (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.463888+00:00</updated><author><name>Mikail Khona</name></author><author><name>Sarthak Chandra</name></author><author><name>Ila Fiete</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modular structures in the brain play a central role in compositionality and intelligence, however the general mechanisms driving module emergence have remained elusive. Studying entorhinal grid cells as paradigmatic examples of modular architecture and function, we demonstrate the spontaneous emergence of a small number of discrete spatial and functional modules from an interplay between continuously varying lateral interactions generated by smooth cortical gradients. We derive a comprehensive analytic theory of modularization, revealing that the process is highly generic with its robustness deriving from topological origins. The theory generates universal predictions for the sequence of grid period ratios, furnishing the most accurate explanation of grid cell data to date. Altogether, this work reveals novel principles by which simple bottom-up dynamical interactions lead to macroscopic modular organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466284" rel="alternate" title="Spontaneous emergence of topologically robust grid cell modules: A multiscale instability theory (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465788</id><title>Experience-induced remodeling of the hippocampal post-synaptic proteome and phosphoproteome (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.464157+00:00</updated><author><name>Seok Heo</name></author><author><name>Taewook Kang</name></author><author><name>Alexei M. Bygrave</name></author><author><name>Martin R. Larsen</name></author><author><name>Richard L. Huganir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The post synaptic density (PSD) of excitatory synapses contains a highly organized protein network with thousands of proteins and is key node in the regulation of synaptic plasticity. To gain new mechanistic insight into experience-induced changes in the PSD, we examined the global dynamics of the PSD proteome and phosphoproteome in mice following various treatments. Mice were trained using an inhibitory avoidance (IA) task and hippocampal PSD fractions were isolated for quantitative proteomic and phosphoproteomics analysis. We used a sequential enrichment strategy to explore the concurrent events of protein expression and phosphorylation in the hippocampal PSD following IA training (IA) or immediate shock (Shock). We identified more than 6,200 proteins and 3,000 phosphoproteins in the sequential strategy covering a total of 7,429 proteins. On the phosphoproteins we identified a total of 9,589 phosphosites. Strikingly, of the significantly IA-regulated proteins and phosphoproteins, a large fraction of the proteins displayed an overall decrease in phosphorylation level. Bioinformatic analysis of proteins and phosphoproteins that were regulated by IA were annotated for an involvement in regulation of glutamate receptor functionality, calcium signaling, and synaptic plasticity. We also identified synaptic kinases, phosphatases and their respective phosphosites regulated by IA training or immediate shock. Furthermore, we found that AMPA receptor surface expression was regulated by protein phosphatase, Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;/Mn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; dependent 1H (Ppm1h). Together, these results unravel the dynamic remodeling of the PSD upon IA learning or immediate shock and serve as a resource for elucidating the synaptic proteome dynamics induced by experience-dependent plasticity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proteome and phosphoproteome of mouse hippocampal PSD fractions were examined using quantitative phosphoproteomics and bioinformatics following inhibitory avoidance training or non-associative immediate shock.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Approximately 6,200 proteins and 3,000 phosphoproteins were identified and quantified in the hippocampal PSD fractions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;IA mediates widespread decreases in the abundance and phosphorylation of proteins in the hippocampal PSD fraction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kinases, phosphatases and their phosphorylation status were dynamically and significantly regulated by IA and immediate shock.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functional validation shows that the protein phosphatase Ppm1h is linked to the regulation of synaptic plasticity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;In Brief&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantitative proteomics and phosphoproteomics combined with subcellular protein fractionation and bioinformatic analysis identifies a highly dynamic regulation of synaptic protein phosphorylation at the postsynaptic density following IA training and immediate shock.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465788" rel="alternate" title="Experience-induced remodeling of the hippocampal post-synaptic proteome and phosphoproteome (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465122</id><title>Neural population dynamics underlying evidence accumulation in multiple rat brain regions (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.464343+00:00</updated><author><name>Brian DePasquale</name></author><author><name>Jonathan W Pillow</name></author><author><name>Carlos Brody</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accumulating evidence in service of sensory decision making is a core cognitive function. However, previous work has focused either on the dynamics of neural activity during decision-making or on models of evidence accumulation governing behavior. We unify these two perspectives by introducing an evidence-accumulation framework that simultaneously describes multi-neuron population spiking activity and dynamic stimulus-driven behavior during sensory decision-making. We apply our method to behavioral choices and neural activity recorded from three brain regions - the posterior parietal cortex (PPC), the frontal orienting fields (FOF), and the anterior-dorsal striatum (ADS) - while rats performed a pulse-based accumulation task. The model accurately captures the relationship between stimuli and neural activity, the coordinated activity of neural populations, and the distribution of animal choices in response to the stimulus. Model fits show strikingly distinct accumulation models expressed within each brain region, and that all differ strongly from the accumulation strategy expressed at the level of choices. In particular, the FOF exhibited a suboptimal 'primacy' strategy, where early sensory evidence was favored. Including neural data in the model led to improved prediction of the moment-by-moment value of accumulated evidence and the intended-and ultimately made-choice of the animal. Our approach offers a window into the neural representation of accumulated evidence and provides a principled framework for incorporating neural responses into accumulation models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.465122" rel="alternate" title="Neural population dynamics underlying evidence accumulation in multiple rat brain regions (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466131</id><title>Artifacts in EEG-based BCI therapies: friend or foe? (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.464512+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric James McDermott</name></author><author><name>Philipp Raggam</name></author><author><name>Sven Kirsch</name></author><author><name>Paolo Belardinelli</name></author><author><name>Ulf Ziemann</name></author><author><name>Christoph Zrenner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;EEG-based brain-computer interfaces (BCI) have promising therapeutic potential beyond traditional neurofeedback training, such as enabling personalized and optimized virtual reality (VR) neurorehabilitation paradigms where the timing and parameters of the visual experience is synchronized with specific brain-states. While BCI algorithms are often designed to focus on whichever portion of a signal is most informative, in these brain-state-synchronized applications, it is of critical importance that the resulting decoder is sensitive to physiological brain activity representative of various mental states, and not to artifacts such as those arising from naturalistic movements. In this study, we compare the relative classification accuracy with which different motor tasks can be decoded from both extracted brain activity and artifacts contained in the EEG signal. EEG data was collected from 17 chronic stroke patients while performing six different head, hand, and arm movements in a realistic VR-based neurorehabilitation paradigm. Results show that the artifact component of the EEG signal is significantly more informative than brain activity to the classifier. This finding is consistent across different feature extraction methods and classification pipelines. Whereas informative artifacts are a helpful friend in BCI-based communication applications, they can be a problematic foe in the estimation of physiological brain states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466131" rel="alternate" title="Artifacts in EEG-based BCI therapies: friend or foe? (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466146</id><title>Metacognition, cortical thickness, and tauopathy in aging (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.464743+00:00</updated><author><name>Kailin Zhuang</name></author><author><name>Xi Chen</name></author><author><name>Suzanne L. Baker</name></author><author><name>William J. Jagust</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We investigated two aspects of metacognition and their relationship with cortical thickness and Alzheimer's Disease (AD) biomarkers, amyloid and tau, in cognitively healthy older adults (N=151). The two metacognition measures were self-appraisal rating of task performance and the difference between self-appraisal rating and actual task performance (appraisal discrepancy). All participants underwent neuropsychological testing and 1.5T structural MRI. A subset (N=66) received amyloid-PET with [11C] PiB and tau-PET with [18F] Flortaucipir. We found that worse performers had lower self-appraisal ratings, but still overestimated their performance, consistent with the Dunning-Kruger effect. Self-appraisal rating and appraisal discrepancy revealed distinct relationships with cortical thickness and AD pathology. Greater appraisal discrepancy, indicating overestimation, was related to thinning of inferior-lateral temporal, fusiform, and rostral anterior cingulate cortices. Lower self-appraisal was associated with higher entorhinal and inferior temporal tau. These results suggest that overestimation could implicate structural atrophy beyond AD pathology, while lower self-appraisal could indicate early behavioral alteration due to AD pathology, supporting the notion of subjective cognitive decline prior to objective deficits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466146" rel="alternate" title="Metacognition, cortical thickness, and tauopathy in aging (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466172</id><title>Dynamic Subcortical Modulators of Human Default Mode Network Function (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.464913+00:00</updated><author><name>Ben J Harrison</name></author><author><name>Christopher G Davey</name></author><author><name>Hannah S Savage</name></author><author><name>Alec J Jamieson</name></author><author><name>Christine A Leonards</name></author><author><name>Bradford A Moffat</name></author><author><name>Rebecca K Glarin</name></author><author><name>Trevor Steward</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain's 'default mode network' (DMN) enables flexible switching between internally and externally focused cognition. Precisely how this modulation occurs is not well understood, although may involve key subcortical mechanisms, including hypothesized influences from the basal forebrain (BF) and mediodorsal thalamus (MD). Here, we used ultra-high field (7T) functional magnetic resonance imaging to examine the involvement of the BF and MD across states of task-induced DMN activity modulation. Specifically, we mapped DMN activity suppression ('deactivation') when participants transitioned between rest and externally focused task performance, as well as DMN activity engagement ('activation') when task performance was internally (i.e., self) focused. Consistent with recent rodent studies, the BF showed overall activity suppression with DMN cortical regions when comparing the rest to external task conditions. Further analyses, including dynamic causal modelling, confirmed that the BF drove changes in DMN cortical activity during these rest-to-task transitions. The MD, by comparison, was specifically engaged during internally focused cognition and demonstrated a broad excitatory influence on DMN cortical activation. These results provide the first direct evidence in humans of distinct basal forebrain and thalamic circuit influences on the control of DMN function and suggest novel mechanistic avenues for ongoing translational research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466172" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic Subcortical Modulators of Human Default Mode Network Function (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465023</id><title>Mispatterned motile cilia beating causes flow blockage in the epileptic brain (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.465272+00:00</updated><author><name>Regina J Faubel</name></author><author><name>Tim N Feinstein</name></author><author><name>Veronica Santos Canellas</name></author><author><name>Jenna Gaesser</name></author><author><name>Nancy H Beluk</name></author><author><name>Yong Wang</name></author><author><name>Maya Yankova</name></author><author><name>Stephen M King</name></author><author><name>Kalyani Bindu Karunakaran</name></author><author><name>Madhavi K Ganapathiraju</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Wenya Lo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Beating of motile cilia at the brain ventricular surface generates rapid flow in an evolutionary conserved pattern mediating the transport of cerebrospinal fluid, but its functional importance has yet to be demonstrated. Here we show disturbance of this transport may contribute to seizure susceptibility. Mice haploinsufficient for FoxJ1, transcription factor regulating motile cilia exhibited cilia-driven flow blockage and increased seizure susceptibility. Mutations in two epilepsy-associated kinases, Cdkl5 and Yes1, in mice resulted in similar cilia-driven flow blockage and increased seizure susceptibility. We showed this arises from disorganized cilia polarity associated with disruption in the highly organized basal body anchoring meshwork. Together these findings suggest mispatterning of cilia-generated flow may contribute to epilepsy and thus might account for seizures unresponsive to current seizure medications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465023" rel="alternate" title="Mispatterned motile cilia beating causes flow blockage in the epileptic brain (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466136</id><title>Differential patterns of change in brain connectivity resulting from traumatic brain injury (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.465607+00:00</updated><author><name>Johan Nakuci</name></author><author><name>Matthew McGuire</name></author><author><name>Ferdinand Schweser</name></author><author><name>David Poulsen</name></author><author><name>Sarah F. Muldoon</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traumatic brain injury (TBI) damages white matter tracts, disrupting brain network structure and communication. There exists a wide heterogeneity in the pattern of structural damage associated with injury, as well as a large heterogeneity in behavioral outcomes. However, little is known about the relationship between changes in network connectivity and clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We utilize the rat lateral fluid-percussion injury (FPI) model of severe TBI to study differences in brain connectivity in 8 animals that received the insult and 11 animals that received only a craniectomy. Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI) is performed 5 weeks after the injury and network theory is used to investigate changes in white matter connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We find that 1) global network measures are not able to distinguish between healthy and injured animals; 2) injury induced alterations predominantly exist in a subset of connections (subnetworks) distributed throughout the brain; and 3) injured animals can be divided into subgroups based on changes in network motifs – measures of local structural connectivity. Additionally, alterations in predicted functional connectivity indicate that the subgroups have different propensities to synchronize brain activity, which could relate to the heterogeneity of clinical outcomes such as the risk of developing post-traumatic epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Discussion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These results suggest that network measures can be used to quantify progressive changes in brain connectivity due to injury and differentiate among subpopulations with similar injuries but different pathological trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;White matter tracts are important for efficient communication between brain regions and their connectivity pattern underlies proper brain function. Traumatic brain injury (TBI) damages white matter tracts and changes brain connectivity, but how specific changes relate to differences in clinical/behavioral outcomes is not known. Using network theory to study injury related changes in structural connectivity, we find that local measures of network structure can identify subgroups of injured rats with different types of changes in brain structure. Our results suggest that these different patterns of change could relate to differences in clinical outcomes such as the propensity to develop epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466136" rel="alternate" title="Differential patterns of change in brain connectivity resulting from traumatic brain injury (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466154</id><title>Reversing anterior insular cortex neuronal hypoexcitability attenuates compulsive behavior in juvenile rats (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.466135+00:00</updated><author><name>Kshitij Jadhav</name></author><author><name>Aurelien Bernheim</name></author><author><name>Lea Aeschlimann</name></author><author><name>Guylene Kirschmann</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Decosterd</name></author><author><name>Alexander Hoffman</name></author><author><name>Carl R Lupica</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Boutrel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Development of self-regulatory competencies during adolescence is partially dependent on normative brain maturation. Here we report that juvenile rats as compared to adults exhibit impulsive and compulsive-like behavioral traits, the latter being associated with lower expression of mRNA levels of the immediate early gene zif268 in the anterior insula (AI). This observation suggests that deficits in AI function in juvenile rats could explain their immature pattern of interoceptive cue integration in rational decision-making and compulsive phenotype. In support of this, here we report hypoexcitability of juvenile layer-V pyramidal neurons in the AI, concomitant with reduced glutamatergic synaptic input to these cells. Chemogenetic activation of the AI attenuated the compulsive trait suggesting that delayed maturation of the AI results in suboptimal integration of sensory and cognitive information in adolescents and this contributes to inflexible behaviors in specific conditions of reward availability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466154" rel="alternate" title="Reversing anterior insular cortex neuronal hypoexcitability attenuates compulsive behavior in juvenile rats (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>