<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376144+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475719</id><title>Learning in reverse: Dopamine errors drive excitatory and inhibitory components of backward conditioning in an outcome-specific manner (74 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376256+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin M. Seitz</name></author><author><name>Ivy B. Hoang</name></author><author><name>Aaron P. Blaisdell</name></author><author><name>Melissa J. Sharpe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For over two decades, midbrain dopamine was considered synonymous with the prediction error in temporal-difference reinforcement learning. Central to this proposal is the notion that reward-predictive stimuli become endowed with the scalar value of predicted rewards. When these cues are subsequently encountered, their predictive value is compared to the value of the actual reward received allowing for the calculation of prediction errors. Phasic firing of dopamine neurons was proposed to reflect this computation, facilitating the backpropagation of value from the predicted reward to the reward-predictive stimulus, thus reducing future prediction errors. There are two critical assumptions of this proposal: 1) that dopamine errors can only facilitate learning about scalar value and not more complex features of predicted rewards, and 2) that the dopamine signal can only be involved in anticipatory learning in which cues or actions precede rewards. Recent work has challenged the first assumption, demonstrating that phasic dopamine signals across species are involved in learning about more complex features of the predicted outcomes, in a manner that transcends this value computation. Here, we tested the validity of the second assumption. Specifically, we examined whether phasic midbrain dopamine activity would be necessary for backward conditioning—when a neutral cue reliably &lt;italic&gt;follows&lt;/italic&gt; a rewarding outcome. Using a specific Pavlovian-to-Instrumental Transfer (PIT) procedure, we show rats learn both excitatory and inhibitory components of a backward association, and that this association entails knowledge of the specific identity of the reward and cue. We demonstrate that brief optogenetic inhibition of VTA&lt;sub&gt;DA&lt;/sub&gt; neurons timed to the transition between the reward and cue, reduces both of these components of backward conditioning. These findings suggest VTA&lt;sub&gt;DA&lt;/sub&gt; neurons are capable of facilitating associations between contiguously occurring events, regardless of the content of those events. We conclude that these data are in line with suggestions that the VTA&lt;sub&gt;DA&lt;/sub&gt; error acts as a universal teaching signal. This may provide insight into why dopamine function has been implicated in a myriad of psychological disorders that are characterized by very distinct reinforcement-learning deficits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="475719v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475719" rel="alternate" title="Learning in reverse: Dopamine errors drive excitatory and inhibitory components of backward conditioning in an outcome-specific manner (74 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475815</id><title>Panoramic visual statistics shape retina-wide organization of receptive fields (65 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376329+00:00</updated><author><name>Divyansh Gupta</name></author><author><name>Wiktor Młynarski</name></author><author><name>Olga Symonova</name></author><author><name>Jan Svatoň</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Joesch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Visual systems have adapted to the structure of natural stimuli. In the retina, center-surround receptive fields (RFs) of retinal ganglion cells (RGCs) appear to efficiently encode natural sensory signals&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;. Conventionally, it has been assumed that natural scenes are isotropic and homogeneous; thus, the RF properties are expected to be uniform across the visual field. However, natural scene statistics such as luminance and contrast are not uniform and vary significantly across elevation&lt;sup&gt;5,6&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, by combining theory and novel experimental approaches, we demonstrate that this inhomogeneity is exploited by RGC RFs across the entire retina to increase the coding efficiency. We formulated three predictions derived from the efficient coding theory: (i) optimal RFs should strengthen their surround from the dimmer ground to the brighter sky, (ii) RFs should simultaneously decrease their center size and (iii) RFs centered at the horizon should have a marked surround asymmetry due to a stark contrast drop-off. To test these predictions, we developed a new method to image high-resolution RFs of thousands of RGCs in individual retinas. We found that the RF properties match theoretical predictions, and consistently change their shape from dorsal to the ventral retina, with a distinct shift in the RF surround at the horizon. These effects are observed across RGC subtypes, which were thought to represent visual space homogeneously, indicating that functional retinal streams share common adaptations to visual scenes. Our work shows that RFs of mouse RGCs exploit the non-uniform, panoramic structure of natural scenes at a previously unappreciated scale, to increase coding efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475815" rel="alternate" title="Panoramic visual statistics shape retina-wide organization of receptive fields (65 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475690</id><title>Atlasing white matter and grey matter joint contributions to resting-state networks in the human brain (37 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376402+00:00</updated><author><name>Victor Nozais</name></author><author><name>Stephanie J Forkel</name></author><author><name>Laurent Petit</name></author><author><name>Michel Thiebaut de Schotten</name></author><author><name>Marc Joliot</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Over the past two decades, the study of resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging (&lt;italic&gt;f&lt;/italic&gt;MRI) has revealed the existence of multiple brain areas displaying synchronous functional blood oxygen level-dependent signals (BOLD) — resting-state networks (RSNs). The variation in functional connectivity between the different areas of a resting-state network or between multiple networks, have been extensively studied and linked to cognitive states and pathologies. However, the white matter connections supporting each network remain only partially described. In this work, we developed a data-driven method to systematically map the white and grey matter contributing to resting-state networks. Using the Human Connectome Project, we generated an atlas of 30 resting-state networks, each with two maps: white matter and grey matter. By integrating structural and functional neuroimaging data, this method builds an atlas that unlocks the joint anatomical exploration of white and grey matter to resting-state networks. The method also allows highlighting the overlap between networks, which revealed that most (89%) of the brain’s white matter is shared amongst multiple networks, with 16% shared by at least 7 resting-state networks. These overlaps, especially the existence of regions shared by numerous networks, suggest that white matter lesions in these areas might strongly impact the correlations and the communication within resting-state networks. We provide an open-source software to explore the joint contribution of white and grey matter to RSNs and facilitate the study of the impact of white matter damage on RSNs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475690" rel="alternate" title="Atlasing white matter and grey matter joint contributions to resting-state networks in the human brain (37 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475721</id><title>Sex differences in pain-related behaviors and clinical progression of disease in mouse models of visceral pain (25 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376469+00:00</updated><author><name>Adela M. Francis-Malave</name></author><author><name>Santiago Martinez Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Caren Pichardo</name></author><author><name>Torri D. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Luis G. Rivera</name></author><author><name>Lauren R. Brinster</name></author><author><name>Yarimar Carrasquillo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous studies have reported sex differences in irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) and inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) patients, including differences in visceral pain perception. Despite this, sex differences in behavioral manifestations of visceral pain and underlying pathology of the gastrointestinal tract have been largely understudied in preclinical research. In this study, we evaluated potential sex differences in spontaneous visceral nociceptive responses, referred abdominal hypersensitivity, disease progression and bowel pathology in mouse models of acute and persistent colon inflammation. Our experiments show that females exhibit more visceral nociceptive responses and referred abdominal hypersensitivity than males in the context of acute but not persistent colon inflammation. We further demonstrate that, following acute and persistent colon inflammation, visceral pain-related behavioral responses in females and males are distinct, with increases in licking of the abdomen only observed in females and increases in abdominal contractions only seen in males. During persistent colon inflammation, males exhibit worse disease progression than females, which is manifested as worse physical appearance and higher weight loss. However, no measurable sex differences were observed in persistent inflammation-induced bowel pathology, stool consistency or fecal blood. Overall, our findings demonstrate that visceral pain-related behaviors and disease progression in the context of acute and persistent colon inflammation are sex-dependent, highlighting the importance of considering sex as a biological variable in future mechanistic studies of visceral pain as well as in the development of diagnostics and therapeutic options for chronic gastrointestinal diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475721" rel="alternate" title="Sex differences in pain-related behaviors and clinical progression of disease in mouse models of visceral pain (25 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475507</id><title>Glucocorticoid Receptor-Regulated Enhancers Play a Central Role in the Gene Regulatory Networks Underlying Drug Addiction (21 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376544+00:00</updated><author><name>Sascha H. Duttke</name></author><author><name>Patricia Montilla-Perez</name></author><author><name>Max W. Chang</name></author><author><name>Hairi Li</name></author><author><name>Hao Chen</name></author><author><name>Lieselot L. G. Carrette</name></author><author><name>Giordano de Guglielmo</name></author><author><name>Olivier George</name></author><author><name>Abraham A. Palmer</name></author><author><name>Christopher Benner</name></author><author><name>Francesca Telese</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Substance abuse and addiction represent a significant public health problem that impacts multiple dimensions of society, including healthcare, the economy, and the workforce. In 2021, over 100,000 drug overdose deaths were reported in the US, with an alarming increase in fatalities related to opioids and psychostimulants. Understanding the fundamental gene regulatory mechanisms underlying addiction and related behaviors could facilitate more effective treatments. To explore how repeated drug exposure alters gene regulatory networks in the brain, we combined capped small (cs)RNA-seq, which accurately captures nascent-like initiating transcripts from total RNA, with Hi-C and single nuclei (sn)ATAC-seq. We profiled initiating transcripts in two addiction-related brain regions, the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and the nucleus accumbens (NAc), from rats that were never exposed to drugs or were subjected to prolonged abstinence after oxycodone or cocaine intravenous self-administration (IVSA). Interrogating over 100,000 active transcription start regions (TSRs) revealed that most TSRs had hallmarks of bonafide enhancers and highlighted the KLF/SP1, RFX, and AP1 transcription factors families as central to establishing brain-specific gene regulatory programs. Analysis of rats with addiction-like behaviors versus controls identified addiction-associated repression of transcription at regulatory enhancers recognized by nuclear receptor subfamily 3 group C (NR3C) factors, which include glucocorticoid receptors. Cell-type deconvolution analysis using snATAC-seq uncovered a potential role of glial cells in driving the gene regulatory programs associated with addiction-related phenotypes. These findings highlight the power of advanced transcriptomics methods to provide insight into how addiction perturbs gene regulatory programs in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475507" rel="alternate" title="Glucocorticoid Receptor-Regulated Enhancers Play a Central Role in the Gene Regulatory Networks Underlying Drug Addiction (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475331</id><title>Foveal vision predictively sensitizes to defining features of eye movement targets (19 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376631+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa M. Kroell</name></author><author><name>Martin Rolfs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the fovea’s singular importance for active human vision, the impact of large eye movements on foveal processing remains elusive. Building on findings from passive fixation tasks, we hypothesized that during the preparation of rapid eye movements (saccades), foveal processing anticipates soon-to-be fixated visual features. Using a dynamic large-field noise paradigm, we indeed demonstrate that sensitivity for defining features of a saccade target is enhanced in the pre-saccadic center of gaze. Enhancement manifested in higher Hit Rates for foveal probes with target-congruent orientation, and a sensitization to incidental, target-like orientation information in foveally presented noise. Enhancement was spatially confined to the center of gaze and its immediate vicinity. We suggest a crucial contribution of foveal processing to trans-saccadic visual continuity which has previously been overlooked: Foveal processing of saccade targets commences before the movement is executed and thereby enables a seamless transition once the center of gaze reaches the target.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475331" rel="alternate" title="Foveal vision predictively sensitizes to defining features of eye movement targets (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476230</id><title>3D-imaging reveals conserved cerebrospinal fluid drainage via meningeal lymphatic vasculature in mice and humans (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376689+00:00</updated><author><name>Laurent Jacob</name></author><author><name>Jose de Brito Neto</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Lenck</name></author><author><name>Celine Corcy</name></author><author><name>Farhat Benbelkacem</name></author><author><name>Luiz Henrique Medeiros Geraldo</name></author><author><name>Yunling Xu</name></author><author><name>Jean-Mickael Thomas</name></author><author><name>Marie-Renee El Kamouh</name></author><author><name>Marie-Claude Potier</name></author><author><name>Stephane Haik</name></author><author><name>Stephane Lehericy</name></author><author><name>Anne Eichmann</name></author><author><name>Jean-Leon Thomas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meningeal lymphatic vessels (MLVs) contribute to waste product elimination and immune surveillance in brain tissues. MLVs were identified in the dorsal and caudo-basal regions of the dura mater, where they ensure the clearance of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Whether MLVs exist in the complex anterior part of the murine and human skull, and how they connect with the glymphatic system and extracranial lymphatic vasculature remained unclear. Here, we generated three-dimensional (3D) maps of MLV drainage by light-sheet fluorescence microscopy (LSFM) imaging of mouse whole-head preparations following fluorescent OVA-A555 tracer injections into the CSF. In humans, we performed real-time magnetic resonance vessel wall imaging (MR-VWI) after systemic gadobutrol injections. We observed a conserved 3D-anatomy of MLVs in mice and humans, and we discovered an extended anterior network around the dural cavernous sinus including multiple capillary beds and exit routes through the foramina of emissary veins. MR-VWI may provide a diagnostic tool for patients with CSF drainage defects and neurological diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476230" rel="alternate" title="3D-imaging reveals conserved cerebrospinal fluid drainage via meningeal lymphatic vasculature in mice and humans (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475823</id><title>Pathological relevance of post-translationally modified alpha-synuclein (pSer87, pSer129, nTyr39) in idiopathic Parkinson’s disease and Multiple System Atrophy (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376786+00:00</updated><author><name>Berkiye Sonustun</name></author><author><name>Firat M Altay</name></author><author><name>Catherine Strand</name></author><author><name>Geshanthi Hondhamuni</name></author><author><name>Thomas T Warner</name></author><author><name>Hilal A Lashuel</name></author><author><name>Rina Bandopadhyay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aggregated alpha-synuclein (α-synuclein) is the main component of Lewy bodies (LBs), Lewy neurites (LNs), and glial cytoplasmic inclusions (GCIs), which are pathological hallmarks of idiopathic Parkinson’s disease (IPD) and multiple system atrophy (MSA), respectively. Initiating factors that culminate in forming LBs/LNs/GCIs remain elusive. Several species of α-synuclein exist, including phosphorylated and nitrated forms. It is unclear which α-synuclein post-translational modifications (PTMs) appear within aggregates throughout disease pathology. Herein we aimed to establish the predominant α–synuclein PTMs in post-mortem IPD and MSA pathology using immunohistochemistry. We examined the patterns of three α-synuclein PTMs (pS87, pS129, nY39) simultaneously in pathology-affected regions of 15 PD, 5 MSA, 6 neurologically normal controls. All antibodies recognized LBs, LNs, and GCIs, albeit to a variable extent. pS129 α-synuclein antibody was particularly immunopositive for LNs and synaptic dot-like structures followed by nY39 α-synuclein antibody. GCIs, neuronal inclusions, and small threads were positive for nY39 α-synuclein in MSA. Quantification of the LB scores revealed that pS129 α-synuclein was the dominant and earliest α-synuclein PTM followed by nY39 α-synuclein, while lower amounts of pSer87 α-synuclein appeared later in disease progression in PD. These results may have implications for novel biomarker and therapeutic developments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475823" rel="alternate" title="Pathological relevance of post-translationally modified alpha-synuclein (pSer87, pSer129, nTyr39) in idiopathic Parkinson’s disease and Multiple System Atrophy (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476162</id><title>Involvement of prelimbic cortex neurons and related circuits in the acquisition of cooperative learning by pairs of rats (14 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376859+00:00</updated><author><name>A.R. Conde-Moro</name></author><author><name>F. Rocha-Almeida</name></author><author><name>E. Gebara</name></author><author><name>J.M. Delgado-García</name></author><author><name>C. Sandi</name></author><author><name>A. Gruart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Social behaviors such as cooperation are crucial for mammals. A deeper knowledge of the neuronal mechanisms underlying cooperation can be beneficial for people suffering from pathologies with impaired social behavior. Our aim was to study the brain activity when two animals synchronize their behavior to obtain a mutual reinforcement. In a previous work, we showed that the activity of the prelimbic cortex (PrL) was enhanced during cooperation in rats, especially in the ones leading most cooperative trials (&lt;italic&gt;leader&lt;/italic&gt; rats). In this study, we investigated the specific cell type/s in the PrL contributing to cooperative behaviors. To this end, we collected rats’ brains at key moments of the learning process to analyze the levels of c-FOS expression in the main cellular groups of the PrL (glutamatergic cells containing D1 and D2 receptors and interneurons). &lt;italic&gt;Leader&lt;/italic&gt; rats showed increased c-FOS activity in cells expressing D1 receptors during cooperation. In addition, we analyzed the levels of anxiety, dominance, and locomotor behavior, finding that &lt;italic&gt;leader&lt;/italic&gt; rats are in general less anxious and less dominant than &lt;italic&gt;followers&lt;/italic&gt;. We also recorded local field potentials (LFPs) from the PrL, the nucleus accumbens septi (NAc), and the basolateral amygdala (BLA). Spectral analysis showed that delta activity in PrL and NAc increased when rats cooperated, while BLA activity in delta and theta bands decreased considerably during cooperation. The PrL and NAc also increased their connectivity in the high theta band during cooperation. Thus, the present work identifies the specific PrL cell types engaged in this behavior, as well as its connectivity with subcortical brain regions (BLA, NAc) during cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brain mechanisms underlying cooperative behaviors remain unknown. The present study identified specific neuronal types from the PrL cortex engaged in the acquisition of a cooperative task, as well as their connectivity with subcortical projection sites, such as the NAc and the BLA during cooperation. Rats leading the cooperation trials (designated &lt;italic&gt;leaders&lt;/italic&gt;) presented an increased activation of D1-containing neurons in the PrL during cooperation. The PrL and NAc electrical activity increased when rats were cooperating, while the BLA activity increased before cooperation. The PrL and NAc showed increased functional connectivity at the moment of cooperation on the platform, whereas during the individual phase the highest connectivity was found before the animals climbed individually onto the platform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476162" rel="alternate" title="Involvement of prelimbic cortex neurons and related circuits in the acquisition of cooperative learning by pairs of rats (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475329</id><title>Comprehensive preclinical evaluation of human-derived anti-poly-GA antibodies in cellular and animal models of C9ORF72 disease (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.376926+00:00</updated><author><name>Melanie Jambeau</name></author><author><name>Kevin D. Meyer</name></author><author><name>Marian Hruska-Plochan</name></author><author><name>Ricardos Tabet</name></author><author><name>Chao-Zong Lee</name></author><author><name>Ananya Ray-Soni</name></author><author><name>Corey Aguilar</name></author><author><name>Kitty Savage</name></author><author><name>Nibha Mishra</name></author><author><name>Nicole Cavegn</name></author><author><name>Petra Borter</name></author><author><name>Chun-Chia Lin</name></author><author><name>Karen Jansen-West</name></author><author><name>Jay Jiang</name></author><author><name>Fernande Freyermuth</name></author><author><name>Nan Li</name></author><author><name>Pierre De Rossi</name></author><author><name>Manuela Perez-Berlanga</name></author><author><name>Xin Jiang</name></author><author><name>Lilian M. Daughrity</name></author><author><name>Joao Pereira</name></author><author><name>Sarav Narayanan</name></author><author><name>Yuanzheng Gu</name></author><author><name>Shekhar Dhokai</name></author><author><name>Isin Dalkilic-Liddle</name></author><author><name>Zuzanna Maniecka</name></author><author><name>Julien Weber</name></author><author><name>Michael Workman</name></author><author><name>Melissa McAlonis-Downes</name></author><author><name>Eugene Berezovski</name></author><author><name>Yong-Jie Zhang</name></author><author><name>James Berry</name></author><author><name>Brian J. Wainger</name></author><author><name>Mark W. Kankel</name></author><author><name>Mia Rushe</name></author><author><name>Christoph Hock</name></author><author><name>Roger M. Nitsch</name></author><author><name>Don W. Cleveland</name></author><author><name>Leonard Petrucelli</name></author><author><name>Tania Gendron</name></author><author><name>Fabio Montrasio</name></author><author><name>Jan Grimm</name></author><author><name>Magdalini Polymenidou</name></author><author><name>Clotilde Lagier-Tourenne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hexanucleotide G4C2 repeat expansions in the C9ORF72 gene are the most common genetic cause of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and frontotemporal dementia (FTD). Dipeptide repeat proteins (DPRs) generated by translation of repeat-containing RNAs show toxic effects in vivo as well as in vitro and are key targets for therapeutic intervention. We generated human antibodies that bind DPRs with high affinity and specificity. Anti-GA antibodies engaged extra- and intracellular poly-GA and reduced aggregate formation in a poly-GA over-expressing human cell line. However, antibody treatment in human neuronal cultures synthesizing exogenous poly-GA resulted in the formation of large extracellular immune complexes and did not affect accumulation of intracellular poly-GA aggregates. Treatment with antibodies was also shown to directly alter the morphological and biochemical properties of poly-GA and to shift poly-GA/antibody complexes to more rapidly sedimenting ones. These alterations were not observed with poly-GP and have important implications for accurate measurement of poly-GA levels including the need to evaluate all centrifugation fractions and disrupt the interaction between treatment antibodies and poly-GA by denaturation. Targeting poly-GA and poly-GP in two mouse models expressing G4C2 repeats by systemic antibody delivery for up to 16 months was well-tolerated and led to measurable brain penetration of antibodies. Long term treatment with anti-GA antibodies produced improvement in an open field movement test in aged C9ORF72450 mice. However, chronic administration of anti-GA antibodies in AAV-(G4C2)149 mice was associated with increased levels of poly-GA detected by immunoassay and did not significantly reduce poly-GA aggregates or alleviate disease progression in this model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475329" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive preclinical evaluation of human-derived anti-poly-GA antibodies in cellular and animal models of C9ORF72 disease (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.473633</id><title>Hebbian activity-dependent plasticity in white matter (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377126+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Lazari</name></author><author><name>Piergiorgio Salvan</name></author><author><name>Michiel Cottaar</name></author><author><name>Daniel Papp</name></author><author><name>Matthew Rushworth</name></author><author><name>Heidi Johansen-Berg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synaptic plasticity is required for learning and follows Hebb’s Rule, the com-putational principle underpinning associative learning. In recent years, a complementary type of brain plasticity has been identified in myelinated axons, which make up the majority of brain’s white matter. Like synaptic plasticity, myelin plasticity is required for learning, but it is unclear whether it is Hebbian or whether it follows different rules. Here, we provide evidence that white matter plasticity operates following Hebb’s Rule in humans. Across two experiments, we find that co-stimulating cortical areas to induce Hebbian plasticity leads to relative increases in cortical excitability and associated increases in a myelin marker within the stimulated fiber bundle. We conclude that Hebbian plasticity extends beyond synaptic changes, and can be observed in human white matter fibers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.473633" rel="alternate" title="Hebbian activity-dependent plasticity in white matter (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475638</id><title>A striatal plasticity that supports the long-term preservation of motor function in Parkinsonian mice (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377196+00:00</updated><author><name>Joe C. Brague</name></author><author><name>Rebecca P. Seal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motor deficits of Parkinson’s disease (PD) such as rigidity, bradykinesia and akinesia result from a progressive loss of nigrostriatal dopamine neurons. No therapies exist that slow their degeneration and the most effective treatments for the motor symptoms: L-dopa -the precursor to dopamine, and deep brain stimulation can produce dyskinesias and are highly invasive, respectively. Hence, alternative strategies targeted to slow the progression or delay the onset of motor symptoms are still highly sought. Here we report the identification of a long-term striatal plasticity mechanism that delays for several months, the onset of motor deficits in a mouse PD model. Specifically, we show that a one-week transient daily elevation of midbrain dopamine neuron activity during depletion preserves the connectivity of direct but not indirect pathway projection neurons. The findings are consistent with the balance theory of striatal output pathways and suggest a novel approach for treating the motor symptoms of PD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475638" rel="alternate" title="A striatal plasticity that supports the long-term preservation of motor function in Parkinsonian mice (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475844</id><title>Influence of data sampling methods on the representation of neural spiking activity in vivo (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377251+00:00</updated><author><name>Meike E. van der Heijden</name></author><author><name>Amanda M. Brown</name></author><author><name>Roy V. Sillitoe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;In vivo&lt;/italic&gt; single-unit recordings distinguish the basal spiking properties of neurons in different experimental settings and disease states. Here, we examined over 300 spike trains recorded from Purkinje cells and cerebellar nuclei neurons to test whether data sampling approaches influence the extraction of rich descriptors of firing properties. Our analyses included neurons recorded in awake and anesthetized control mice, as well as disease models of ataxia, dystonia, and tremor. We find that recording duration circumscribes overall representations of firing rate and pattern. Notably, shorter recording durations skew estimates for global firing rate variability towards lower values. We also find that only some populations of neurons in the same mouse are more similar to each other than to neurons recorded in different mice. These data reveal that recording duration and approach are primary considerations when interpreting task-independent single-neuron firing properties. If not accounted for, group differences may be concealed or exaggerated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475844" rel="alternate" title="Influence of data sampling methods on the representation of neural spiking activity in vivo (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475895</id><title>Brain responses in aggression-prone individuals: A systematic review and meta-analysis of functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies of anger- and aggression-eliciting tasks (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377310+00:00</updated><author><name>Maja Nikolic</name></author><author><name>Patrizia Pezzoli</name></author><author><name>Natalia Jaworska</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Seto</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While reactive aggression (in response to a perceived threat or provocation) is part of humans’ adaptive behavioral repertoire, it can violate social and legal norms. Understanding brain function in individuals with high levels of reactive aggression as they process anger- and aggression-eliciting stimuli is critical for refining interventions. Three neurobiological models of reactive aggression–the limbic hyperactivity, prefrontal hypoactivity, and dysregulated limbic-prefrontal connectivity models–have been proposed. However, these models are based on neuroimaging studies involving mainly healthy individuals, leaving it unclear which model best describes brain function in aggression-prone individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conducted a systematic literature search (PubMed and Psycinfo) and Multilevel Kernel Density meta-analysis (MKDA) of nine functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies of brain responses to tasks putatively eliciting anger and aggression in aggression-prone individuals alone, and relative to healthy controls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aggression-prone individuals exhibited greater activity during reactive aggression relative to baseline in the superior temporal gyrus and in regions comprising the cognitive control and default mode networks (right posterior cingulate cortex, precentral gyrus, precuneus, right inferior frontal gyrus). Compared to healthy controls, aggression-prone individuals exhibited increased activity in limbic regions (left hippocampus, left amygdala, left parahippocampal gyrus) and temporal regions (superior, middle, inferior temporal gyrus), and reduced activity in occipital regions (left occipital cortex, left calcarine cortex).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;These findings lend support to the limbic hyperactivity model and further indicate altered temporal and occipital activity in anger- and aggression-eliciting situations that involve face and speech processing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475895" rel="alternate" title="Brain responses in aggression-prone individuals: A systematic review and meta-analysis of functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies of anger- and aggression-eliciting tasks (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475985</id><title>Role of Yap1 in adult neural stem cell activation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377371+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenqiang Fan</name></author><author><name>Jerónimo Jurado-Arjona</name></author><author><name>Gregorio Alanis-Lobato</name></author><author><name>Sophie Péron</name></author><author><name>Christian Berger</name></author><author><name>Miguel A. Andrade-Navarro</name></author><author><name>Sven Falk</name></author><author><name>Benedikt Berninger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Most adult hippocampal neural stem cells (NSCs) remain quiescent with only a minor portion undergoing active proliferation and neurogenesis. The molecular mechanisms that trigger eventually the transition from quiescence to activation are still poorly understood. Here, we found the activity of the transcriptional activator Yap1 to be enriched in active NSCs. Genetic deletion of Yap1 led to a significant reduction in the relative proportion of active NSCs supporting a physiological role of Yap1 in regulating the transition from quiescence to activation. Overexpression of wild type Yap1 in adult NSCs did not induce NSC activation suggesting tight upstream control mechanisms, but overexpression of a gain-of-function mutant (Yap1-5SA) elicited cell cycle entry in NSCs and hilar astrocytes. Consistent with a role of Yap1 in NSC activation, single cell RNA sequencing revealed the partial induction of an activated NSC gene expression program. Yet, Yap1-5SA expression also induced Taz and other key components of the Yap/Taz regulon previously identified in glioblastoma stem cell-like cells. Consequently, dysregulated Yap1 activity led to repression of hippocampal neurogenesis, promoting aberrant differentiation instead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.475985" rel="alternate" title="Role of Yap1 in adult neural stem cell activation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476128</id><title>Harmonized-Multinational qEEG Norms (HarMNqEEG) (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377446+00:00</updated><author><name>Min Li</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><author><name>Carlos Lopez-Naranjo</name></author><author><name>Aini Ismafairus Abd Hamid</name></author><author><name>Alan C. Evans</name></author><author><name>Alexander N. Savostyanov</name></author><author><name>Ana Calzada-Reyes</name></author><author><name>Ariosky Areces-Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Arno Villringer</name></author><author><name>Carlos A. Tobon-Quintero</name></author><author><name>Daysi Garcia-Agustin</name></author><author><name>Deirel Paz-Linares</name></author><author><name>Dezhong Yao</name></author><author><name>Li Dong</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Aubert-Vazquez</name></author><author><name>Faruque Reza</name></author><author><name>Hazim Omar</name></author><author><name>Jafri Malin Abdullah</name></author><author><name>Janina R. Galler</name></author><author><name>John F. Ochoa-Gomez</name></author><author><name>Leslie S. Prichep</name></author><author><name>Lidice Galan-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Lilia Morales-Chacon</name></author><author><name>Mitchell J. Valdes-Sosa</name></author><author><name>Marius Tröndle</name></author><author><name>Mohd Faizal Bin Mohd Zulkifly</name></author><author><name>Muhammad Riddha Bin Abdul Rahman</name></author><author><name>Natalya S. Milakhina</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Langer</name></author><author><name>Pavel Rudych</name></author><author><name>Shiang Hu</name></author><author><name>Thomas Koenig</name></author><author><name>Trinidad A. Virues-Alba</name></author><author><name>Xu Lei</name></author><author><name>Maria L. Bringas-Vega</name></author><author><name>Jorge F. Bosch-Bayard</name></author><author><name>Pedro Antonio Valdes-Sosa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This paper extends our frequency domain quantitative electroencephalography (qEEG) methods pursuing higher sensitivity to detect Brain Developmental Disorders. Prior qEEG work lacked integration of cross-spectral information omitting important functional connectivity descriptors. Lack of geographical diversity precluded accounting for site-specific variance, increasing qEEG nuisance variance. We ameliorate these weaknesses. i) Create lifespan Hermitian Riemannian multinational qEEG norms for cross-spectral tensors. These norms result from the HarMNqEEG project fostered by the Global Brain Consortium. We calculate the norms with data from 9 countries, 12 devices, and 14 studies, including 1564 subjects. Instead of raw data, only anonymized metadata and EEG cross-spectral tensors were shared. After visual and automatic quality control developmental equations for the mean and standard deviation of qEEG traditional and Hermitian Riemannian descriptive parameters were calculated using additive mixed-effects models. We demonstrate qEEG “batch effects” and provide methods to calculate harmonized z-scores. ii) We also show that the multinational harmonized Hermitian Riemannian norms produce z-scores with increased diagnostic accuracy to predict brain dysfunction at school-age produced by malnutrition only in the first year of life. We provide data and software for constructing norms. iii) We offer open code and data to calculate different individual z-scores from the HarMNqEEG dataset. These results contribute to developing bias-free, low-cost neuroimaging technologies applicable in various health settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We create lifespan Hermitian Riemannian qEEG norms for cross-spectral tensors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The norms are based on 9 countries, 12 devices, and 14 studies, with 1564 subjects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate qEEG “batch effects”, providing harmonization methods to remove them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multinational harmonized z-scores increase diagnostic accuracy of brain dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data and software are available for norm and individual z-scores calculation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476128" rel="alternate" title="Harmonized-Multinational qEEG Norms (HarMNqEEG) (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475717</id><title>Astrogliosis mapping in individual brains using multidimensional MRI (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377622+00:00</updated><author><name>Dan Benjamini</name></author><author><name>David S Priemer</name></author><author><name>Daniel P Perl</name></author><author><name>David L Brody</name></author><author><name>Peter J Basser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are currently no noninvasive imaging methods available for astrogliosis mapping in the central nervous system despite its essential role in the response to injury, disease, and infection. We have developed a machine learning-based multidimensional MRI framework that provides a signature of astrogliosis, distinguishing it from normative brain at the individual level. We investigated &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; cortical tissue specimen derived from subjects who sustained blast induced injuries, which resulted in scar-border forming astrogliosis without being accompanied by other types of neuropathology. By performing a combined postmortem radiology and histopathology correlation study we found that astrogliosis induces microstructural changes that are robustly detected using our framework, resulting in MRI neuropathology maps that are significantly and strongly correlated with co-registered histological images of increased glial fibrillary a cidic protein deposition. The demonstrated high spatial sensitivity in detecting reactive astrocytes at the individual level has great potential to significantly impact neuroimaging studies in diseases, injury, repair, and aging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475717" rel="alternate" title="Astrogliosis mapping in individual brains using multidimensional MRI (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475910</id><title>HIV and FIV glycoproteins increase cellular tau pathology via cGMP-dependent kinase II activation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377687+00:00</updated><author><name>Matheus F. Sathler</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Doolittle</name></author><author><name>James A. Cockrell</name></author><author><name>India R. Nadalin</name></author><author><name>Franz Hofmann</name></author><author><name>Sue VandeWoude</name></author><author><name>Seonil Kim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As the development of combination antiretroviral therapy (cART) against human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) drastically improves the lifespan of individuals with HIV, many are now entering the prime age when Alzheimer’s disease (AD)-like symptoms begin to manifest. Hyperphosphorylated tau, a known AD pathological characteristic, has been prematurely increased in the brains of HIV-infected patients as early as in their 30s and is increased with age. This thus suggests that HIV infection may lead to accelerated AD phenotypes. However, whether HIV infection causes AD to develop more quickly in the brain is not yet fully determined. Interestingly, we have previously revealed that viral glycoproteins, HIV gp120 and feline immunodeficiency virus (FIV) gp95, induce neuronal hyperexcitation via cGMP-dependent kinase II (cGKII) activation in cultured hippocampal neurons. Here, we use cultured mouse cortical neurons to demonstrate that HIV gp120 and FIV gp95 are sufficient to increase cellular tau pathology, including intracellular tau hyperphosphorylation and tau release to the extracellular space. We further reveal that viral glycoprotein-induced cellular tau pathology requires cGKII activation. Together, HIV infection likely accelerates AD-related tau pathology via cGKII activation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475910" rel="alternate" title="HIV and FIV glycoproteins increase cellular tau pathology via cGMP-dependent kinase II activation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476338</id><title>White Matter Brain Structure Predicts Language Performance and Learning Success (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377758+00:00</updated><author><name>Stella M. Sánchez</name></author><author><name>Helmut Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Guillermo Gallardo</name></author><author><name>Alfred Anwander</name></author><author><name>Jens Brauer</name></author><author><name>Angela D. Friederici</name></author><author><name>Thomas R. Knösche</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Individual differences in the ability to deal with language have long been discussed. The neural basis of these, however, is yet unknown. Here we investigated the relationship between long-range white matter connectivity of the brain, as revealed by diffusion tractography, and the ability to process syntactically complex sentences in the participants’ native language as well as the improvement thereof by multi-day training. We identified specific network motifs that indeed related white matter tractography to individual language processing performance. First, for two such motifs, one in the left and one in the right hemisphere, their individual prevalence significantly predicted the individual language performance suggesting a predisposition for the individual ability to process syntactically complex sentences, which manifests itself in the white matter brain structure. Both motifs comprise a number of cortical regions, but seem to be dominated by areas known for the involvement in working memory rather than the classical language network itself. Second, we identified another left hemispheric network motif, whose change of prevalence over the training period significantly correlated with the individual change in performance, thus reflecting training induced white matter plasticity. This motif comprises diverse cortical areas including regions known for their involvement in language processing, working memory and motor functions. The present findings suggest that individual differences in language processing and learning can be explained, in part, by individual differences in the brain’s white matter structure. Brain structure may be a crucial factor to be considered when discussing variations in human cognitive performance, more generally.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476338" rel="alternate" title="White Matter Brain Structure Predicts Language Performance and Learning Success (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475853</id><title>Cd59 and inflammation orchestrate Schwann cell development (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377829+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashtyn T. Wiltbank</name></author><author><name>Emma R. Steinson</name></author><author><name>Stacey J. Criswell</name></author><author><name>Melanie Piller</name></author><author><name>Sarah Kucenas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Efficient neurotransmission is essential for organism survival and is enhanced by myelination. However, the genes that regulate myelin and myelinating glial cell development have not been fully characterized. Data from our lab and others demonstrates that &lt;italic&gt;cd59&lt;/italic&gt;, which encodes for a small GPI-anchored glycoprotein, is highly expressed in developing zebrafish, rodent, and human oligodendrocytes (OLs) and Schwann cells (SCs), and that patients with CD59 dysfunction develop neurological dysfunction during early childhood. Yet, the function of CD59 in the developing nervous system is currently undefined. In this study, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;cd59&lt;/italic&gt; is expressed in a subset of developing SCs. Using &lt;italic&gt;cd59&lt;/italic&gt; mutant zebrafish, we show that developing SCs proliferate excessively, which leads to reduced myelin volume, altered myelin ultrastructure, and perturbed node of Ranvier assembly. Finally, we demonstrate that complement activity is elevated in &lt;italic&gt;cd59&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and that inhibiting inflammation restores SC proliferation, myelin volume, and nodes of Ranvier to wildtype levels. Together, this work identifies Cd59 and developmental inflammation as key players in myelinating glial cell development, highlighting the collaboration between glia and the innate immune system to ensure normal neural development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475853" rel="alternate" title="Cd59 and inflammation orchestrate Schwann cell development (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476145</id><title>Increased insula activity precedes the formation of subjective Gestalt (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377894+00:00</updated><author><name>Marilena Wilding</name></author><author><name>Christof Koerner</name></author><author><name>Anja Ischebeck</name></author><author><name>Natalia Zaretskaya</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The constructive nature of human perception sometimes leads us to perceiving rather complex impressions from simple sensory input. Bistable stimuli give us a rare opportunity to study the neural mechanisms behind this process. Such stimuli can be visually interpreted as simple or as more complex on the basis of the same sensory input. Previous studies demonstrated increased activity in the superior parietal cortex when participants perceived an illusory Gestalt impression compared to a simpler interpretation of individual elements. Here we tested whether activity related to the illusory Gestalt can be detected not only during, but also prior to it, by examining the slow fluctuations of resting-state-fMRI activity before the stimulus onset. We presented 31 participants with a bistable motion stimulus, which can be perceived either as four moving dot pairs (local) or two moving illusory squares (global). This allowed us to isolate the specific neural mechanisms that accompany the experience of an illusion under matched sensory input. fMRI was used to measure brain activity in a sparse event-related design. We observed stronger IPS and putamen responses to the stimulus when participants perceived the global interpretation compared to local, confirming the previously reported role of these areas in perceptual grouping. Most importantly, we also observed that the global stimulus interpretation was preceded by an increased activity of the bilateral dorsal insula, which is known to process saliency and gate information for conscious access. Our data suggest an important role of the dorsal insula in shaping an internally generated illusory Gestalt percept.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476145" rel="alternate" title="Increased insula activity precedes the formation of subjective Gestalt (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475630</id><title>Enhancement of central norepinephrinergic neurotransmission contributes to inhibition of seizure-induced respiratory arrest by targeting the beta-1 adrenergic receptor (β1-AR) locating in the cardiomyocytes in the DBA/1 mouse SUDEP model (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.377955+00:00</updated><author><name>XiTing Lian</name></author><author><name>Qian Yu</name></author><author><name>HaiXiang Ma</name></author><author><name>LeYuan Gu</name></author><author><name>Qing Xu</name></author><author><name>HongHai Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sudden unexpected death of epilepsy (SUDEP) is the key cause of of death in patients with epilepsy. Due to the complicated pathogenesis of SUDEP, however, the exact mechanism of SUDEP remains elusive. Currently, although it is recognized that the seizure-induced respiratory arrest (S-IRA) may be a main cause for SUDEP, other factors resulting in SUDEP can not be excluded e.g arrhythmias. Our previous findings indicated that the incidence of seizure-induced respiratory arrest S-IRA and SUDEP evoked by acoustic stimulation or pentetrazol (PTZ) injection was significantly reduced by atomoxetine, a norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (NRI), suggesting that noradrenergic neurotransmission modulates S-IRA and SUDEP. Given that norepinephrine acts on the central and peripheral target to modulate respiratory and circulation function by targeting adrenergic receptor α and beta (a-AR and β-AR) and the arrhythmias can be contributed to SUDEP. Meanwhile, to further test whether cardiac factors are implicated in S-IRA and SUDEP, we choose esmolol hydrochloride, a selective antagonist of beta-1 adrenergic receptor (β1-AR) to test it in our models. Our findings demonstrated that the lower incidence of S-IRA and SUDEP evoked by acoustic stimulation or PTZ in DBA/1 mice by administration with atomoxetine was significantly reversed by intraperitoneal (IP) of esmolol hydrochloride. Importantly, the data of electrocardiogram (ECG) showed that the cardiac arrhythmia evoked by acoustic stimulation including the ventricular tachycardia, ventricular premature beat and atrioventricular block and administration of atomoxetine significantly reduced theses arrhythmias and the incidence of S-IRA and SUDEP in our models. Thus, the dysfunction of respiratory and circulation may be implicated in the pathogenesis of S-IRA and SUDEP hand in hand and enhancing central norepinephrinergic neurotransmission contributes to inhibition of seizure-induced respiratory arrest by targeting β1-AR locating in the cardiomyocytes. Our findings will show a new light on decoding the pathogenesis of SUDEP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475630" rel="alternate" title="Enhancement of central norepinephrinergic neurotransmission contributes to inhibition of seizure-induced respiratory arrest by targeting the beta-1 adrenergic receptor (β1-AR) locating in the cardiomyocytes in the DBA/1 mouse SUDEP model (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475737</id><title>Corrective feedback control of competing neural network with entire connections (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378022+00:00</updated><author><name>Uramogi Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Continuous persist activity of the competitive network is related to many functions, such as working memory, oculomotor integrator and decision making. Many competition models with mutual inhibition structures achieve activity maintenance via positive feedback, which requires meticulous fine tuning of the network parameters strictly. Negative derivative feedback, according to recent research, might represent a novel mechanism for sustaining neural activity that is more resistant to multiple neural perturbations than positive feedback. Many classic models with only mutual inhibition structure are not capable of providing negative derivative feedback because double-inhibition acts as a positive feedback loop, and lack of negative feedback loop that is indispensable for negative derivative feedback. Here in the proposal, we aim to derive a new competition network with negative derivative feedback. The network is made up of two symmetric pairs of EI populations that the four population are completely connected. We conclude that the negative derivative occurs in two circumstances, in which one the activity of the two sides is synchronous but push-pull-like in the other, as well as the switch of two conditions in mathematical analysis and numerical simulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475737" rel="alternate" title="Corrective feedback control of competing neural network with entire connections (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476185</id><title>Forebrain glucocorticoid receptor overexpression alters behavioral encoding of hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells in mice (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378071+00:00</updated><author><name>Joanna L Spencer-Segal</name></author><author><name>Swapnil Gavade</name></author><author><name>Qiang Wei</name></author><author><name>Colin Johnston</name></author><author><name>Savannah Kounelis</name></author><author><name>Klaudia Laborc</name></author><author><name>Huda Akil</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stress hormone signaling via the glucocorticoid receptor (GR) modulates vulnerability to stress-related disorders, but whether GR influences how the brain encodes contextual experience is unknown. Mice with lifelong GR overexpression in forebrain glutamatergic neurons (GRov) show increased sensitivity to environmental stimuli. This phenotype is developmentally programmed and associated with profound changes in hippocampal gene expression. We hypothesized that GR overexpression influences hippocampal encoding of experiences. To test our hypothesis, we performed in vivo microendoscopic calcium imaging of 1359 dorsal CA1 pyramidal cells in freely behaving male and female WT and GRov mice during exploration of a novel open field. We compared calcium amplitude and event rate as well as sensitivity to center location and mobility between genotypes. GRov neurons exhibited higher average calcium activity than WT neurons in the novel open field. While most neurons showed sensitivity to center location and/or mobility, GRov neurons were more likely to be sensitive to center location and less likely to be sensitive to mobility, as compared to WT neurons. More than one-third of behavior-selective GRov neurons were uniquely sensitive to location without mobility sensitivity; these uniquely center-sensitive neurons were rare in WT. We conclude that dorsal CA1 pyramidal cells in GRov mice show increased activity in a novel environment and preferentially encode emotionally salient behavior. This heightened sensitivity to a novel environment and preferential encoding of emotionally salient elements of experience could underlie differential stress vulnerability in humans with increased glucocorticoid sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476185" rel="alternate" title="Forebrain glucocorticoid receptor overexpression alters behavioral encoding of hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells in mice (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475705</id><title>Single-nucleus RNA-seq of normal-appearing brain regions in relapsing-remitting vs. secondary progressive multiple sclerosis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378142+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasuyuki Kihara</name></author><author><name>Yunjiao Zhu</name></author><author><name>Deepa Jonnalagadda</name></author><author><name>William Romanow</name></author><author><name>Carter Palmer</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Siddoway</name></author><author><name>Richard Rivera</name></author><author><name>Ranjan Dutta</name></author><author><name>Bruce D. Trapp</name></author><author><name>Jerold Chun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an immune-mediated demyelinating disease that alters central nervous system (CNS) functions. Relapsing-remitting MS (RRMS) is the most common form, which can transform into secondary-progressive MS (SPMS) that is associated with progressive neurodegeneration. Single-nucleus RNA sequencing (snRNA-seq) of MS lesions identified disease-related transcriptomic alterations; however, their relationship to non-lesioned MS brain regions has not been reported and which could identify prodromal or other disease susceptibility signatures. Here, snRNA-seq was used to generate high-quality RRMS vs. SPMS datasets of 33,197 nuclei from 8 normal-appearing MS brains, which revealed divergent cell type-specific changes. Notably, SPMS brains downregulated astrocytic sphingosine kinases (&lt;italic&gt;SPHK1/2&lt;/italic&gt;) – the enzymes required to phosphorylate and activate the MS drug, fingolimod. This reduction was modeled with astrocyte-specific &lt;italic&gt;Sphk1/2&lt;/italic&gt; null mice in which fingolimod lost activity, supporting functionality of observed transcriptomic changes. These data provide an initial resource for studies of single cells from non-lesioned RRMS and SPMS brains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475705" rel="alternate" title="Single-nucleus RNA-seq of normal-appearing brain regions in relapsing-remitting vs. secondary progressive multiple sclerosis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476037</id><title>Impaired functional connectivity of the hippocampus in murine models of NMDA-receptor antibody associated pathology (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378265+00:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Kuchling</name></author><author><name>Betty Jurek</name></author><author><name>Mariya Kents</name></author><author><name>Jakob Kreye</name></author><author><name>Christian Geis</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Wickel</name></author><author><name>Susanne Mueller</name></author><author><name>Stefan Paul Koch</name></author><author><name>Philipp Boehm-Sturm</name></author><author><name>Harald Prüss</name></author><author><name>Carsten Finke</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;While decreased hippocampal connectivity and disruption of functional networks are established MRI features in human anti-N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDAR) encephalitis, the underlying pathophysiology for brain network alterations remains poorly understood. Application of patient-derived monoclonal antibodies against the NR1 subunit of the NMDAR allows for the investigation of potential functional connectivity alterations in experimental murine NMDAR antibody disease models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To explore functional connectivity changes in NR1 antibody mouse models using resting-state functional MRI (rs-fMRI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adult C57BL/6J mice (n=10) were intrathecally injected with a recombinant human NR1 antibody over 14 days and then studied using rs-fMRI at 7 Tesla. In addition, a newly established mouse model with &lt;italic&gt;in utero&lt;/italic&gt; exposure to a human recombinant NR1 antibody characterized by a neurodevelopmental disorder (NR1-offspring) was investigated with rs-fMRI at the age of 8 weeks (n=15) and 10 months (n=14). Mice exposed to isotype-matched control antibodies served as controls. Independent component analysis (ICA) and dual regression analysis were performed to compare functional connectivity between NMDAR antibody mouse models and control mice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adult NR1-antibody injected mice showed significantly impaired functional connectivity within the dentate gyrus of the left hippocampus in comparison to controls, resembling impaired hippocampal functional connectivity patterns observed in human patients with NMDAR encephalitis. Similarly, analyses showed significantly reduced functional connectivity in the dentate gyrus in NR1-offspring compared after 8 weeks, and impaired connectivity in the dentate gyrus and CA3 hippocampal subregion in NR1-offspring at the age of 10 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functional connectivity changes within the hippocampus resulting from both direct application and &lt;italic&gt;in utero&lt;/italic&gt; exposure to NMDAR antibodies can be modeled in experimental murine systems. With this translational approach, we successfully reproduced functional MRI alterations previously observed in human NMDAR encephalitis patients. Future experimental studies will identify the detailed mechanisms that cause functional network alterations and may eventually allow for non-invasive monitoring of disease activity and therapeutic effects in autoimmune encephalitis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476037" rel="alternate" title="Impaired functional connectivity of the hippocampus in murine models of NMDA-receptor antibody associated pathology (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476381</id><title>Mitochondrial and redox modifications in early stages of Huntington disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378352+00:00</updated><author><name>Carla Lopes</name></author><author><name>Ildete Luisa Ferreira</name></author><author><name>Carina Maranga</name></author><author><name>Margarida Beatriz</name></author><author><name>Sandra Mota</name></author><author><name>Jose Sereno</name></author><author><name>Joao Castelhano</name></author><author><name>Antero Abrunhosa</name></author><author><name>Francisco Oliveira</name></author><author><name>Maura De Rosa</name></author><author><name>Michael R. Hayden</name></author><author><name>Mario Laco</name></author><author><name>Cristina Januario</name></author><author><name>Miguel Castelo Branco</name></author><author><name>Ana Cristina Rego</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Defects in mitochondrial function and mitochondrial-related redox deregulation have been attributed to Huntington disease (HD), a genetic neurodegenerative disorder largely affecting the striatum. However, whether these changes occur in early stages of the disease and can be detected in vivo is still unclear. Thus, in the present study, we analyzed changes in mitochondrial function and overreduced states associated with production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) at early stages and along disease progression in vivo in the brain by positron emission tomography (PET) and in skin fibroblasts of premanifest/early and manifest HD patients, and in YAC128 transgenic mouse brain (striatum and cortex) at early-symptomatic (3 month-old, mo) and symptomatic (6 to 12 mo) stages. In vivo human and mouse brain PET imaging was assessed using [64Cu]-ATSM; analysis of oxygen consumption rates was assessed by Seahorse analysis, hydrogen peroxide levels were determined using fluorescent probes and mitochondrial morphology by transmission electron microscopy in human skin fibroblasts and mouse striatal and cortical isolated mitochondria. Premanifest and prodromal HD carriers exhibited enhanced whole-brain (with exception of caudate) [64Cu]-ATSM labelling, correlating with CAG repeat number, concomitantly with enhanced basal and maximal respiration, proton (H+) leak and increased hydrogen peroxide levels, the later progressing to advanced HD stage, in human fibroblasts. Mitochondria from fibroblasts of premanifest HD carriers also showed reduced roundness, while higher number of mitochondrial DNA copies correlated with maximal respiratory capacity. In vivo animal PET analysis showed increased accumulation of [64Cu]-ATSM in YAC128 mouse striatum. Pre/early-symptomatic YAC128 mouse striatal, but not cortical, isolated mitochondria exhibited a rise in basal and maximal mitochondrial respiration and in ATP production along with increased complex II and III activities, enhanced mitochondrial hydrogen peroxide and roundness, as revealed by brain ultrastructure analysis, further presenting defects in Ca2+ handling, supporting increased striatal susceptibility in the YAC128 mouse model. Data demonstrate both human and mouse mitochondrial overactivity and altered morphology at early HD stages, facilitating redox unbalance, the latter extending over late disease stages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476381" rel="alternate" title="Mitochondrial and redox modifications in early stages of Huntington disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475854</id><title>Acetazolamide modulates intracranial pressure directly by its action on the cerebrospinal fluid secretion apparatus (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378453+00:00</updated><author><name>Dagne Barbuskaite</name></author><author><name>Eva K. Oernbo</name></author><author><name>Jonathan H. Wardman</name></author><author><name>Trine L. Toft-Bertelsen</name></author><author><name>Eller Conti</name></author><author><name>Søren N. Andreassen</name></author><author><name>Niklas J. Gerkau</name></author><author><name>Christine R. Rose</name></author><author><name>Nanna MacAulay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Elevated intracranial pressure (ICP) is observed in many neurological pathologies, e.g. hydrocephalus and stroke. This condition is routinely relieved with neurosurgical approaches, since effective and targeted pharmacological tools are still lacking. The carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, acetazolamide (AZE), may be employed to treat elevated ICP. However, its effectiveness is questioned, its location of action unresolved, and its tolerability low. Here, we employed &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; approaches to reveal the efficacy and mode of action of AZE in the rat brain. The drug effectively reduced the ICP, irrespective of the mode of drug administration and level of anaesthesia. The effect occurred via a direct action on the choroid plexus and an associated decrease in cerebrospinal fluid secretion, and not indirectly via the systemic action of AZE on renal and vascular processes. Upon a single administration, the reduced ICP endured for approximately 10 h post-AZE delivery with no long-term changes of brain water content or choroidal transporter expression. However, a persistent reduction of ICP was secured with repeated AZE administrations throughout the day. Future specific targeting of choroidal carbonic anhydrases may limit the systemic side effects, and therefore enhance the treatment tolerability and effectiveness in select patient groups experiencing elevated ICP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475854" rel="alternate" title="Acetazolamide modulates intracranial pressure directly by its action on the cerebrospinal fluid secretion apparatus (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475723</id><title>Impaired OTUD7A-dependent Ankyrin regulation mediates neuronal dysfunction in mouse and human models of the 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378532+00:00</updated><author><name>Brianna K. Unda</name></author><author><name>Leon Chalil</name></author><author><name>Sehyoun Yoon</name></author><author><name>Savannah Kilpatrick</name></author><author><name>Sansi Xing</name></author><author><name>Nadeem Murtaza</name></author><author><name>Anran Cheng</name></author><author><name>Alexandria Afonso</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth McCready</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Ronen</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Howe</name></author><author><name>Aurélie Caye-Eude</name></author><author><name>Alain Verloes</name></author><author><name>Brad W. Doble</name></author><author><name>Laurence Faivre</name></author><author><name>Antonio Vitobello</name></author><author><name>Stephen W Scherer</name></author><author><name>Yu Lu</name></author><author><name>Peter Penzes</name></author><author><name>Karun K. Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Copy number variations (CNV) are associated with psychiatric and neurodevelopmental disorders (NDDs), and most, including the recurrent 15q13.3 microdeletion disorder, have unknown disease mechanisms. We used a heterozygous 15q13.3 microdeletion mouse model and patient iPSC-derived neurons to reveal developmental defects in neuronal maturation and network activity. To identify the underlying molecular dysfunction, we developed a neuron-specific proximity-labeling proteomics (BioID2) pipeline, combined with patient mutations, to target the 15q13.3 CNV genetic driver &lt;italic&gt;OTUD7A&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;OTUD7A&lt;/italic&gt; is an emerging independent NDD risk gene with no known function in the brain, but has putative deubiquitinase (DUB) function. The OTUD7A protein-protein interaction (PPI) network revealed interactions with synaptic, axonal, and cytoskeletal proteins and was enriched for known ASD and epilepsy risk genes. The interactions between OTUD7A and the NDD risk genes Ankyrin-G (&lt;italic&gt;Ank3&lt;/italic&gt;) and Ankyrin-B (&lt;italic&gt;Ank2&lt;/italic&gt;) were disrupted by an epilepsy-associated &lt;italic&gt;OTUD7A&lt;/italic&gt; L233F variant. Further investigation of Ankyrin-G in mouse and human 15q13.3 microdeletion and OTUD7A&lt;italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;L233F/L233F&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; models revealed protein instability, increased polyubiquitination, and decreased levels in the axon initial segment (AIS), while structured illumination microscopy identified reduced Ankyrin-G nanodomains in dendritic spines. Functional analysis of human 15q13.3 microdeletion and OTUD7A&lt;italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;L233F/L233F&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; models revealed shared and distinct impairments to axonal growth and intrinsic excitability. Importantly, restoring OTUD7A or Ankyrin-G expression in 15q13.3 microdeletion neurons led to a reversal of abnormalities. These data reveal a critical OTUD7A-Ankyrin pathway in neuronal development, which is impaired in the 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome, leading to neuronal dysfunction. Further, our study highlights the utility of targeting CNV genes using cell-type specific proteomics to identify shared and unexplored disease mechanisms across NDDs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475723" rel="alternate" title="Impaired OTUD7A-dependent Ankyrin regulation mediates neuronal dysfunction in mouse and human models of the 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475656</id><title>Microstructural Impairments in a Topologically Distinct Prefrontal-Habenular Connection in Cocaine Addiction (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378648+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah G. King</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Olivier Gaudreault</name></author><author><name>Pias Malaker</name></author><author><name>Joo-won Kim</name></author><author><name>Nelly Alia-Klein</name></author><author><name>Junqian Xu</name></author><author><name>Rita Z. Goldstein</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drug addiction is characterized by neuroadaptations in mesocorticolimbic networks regulating reward and inhibitory control. The habenula (Hb) is central to adaptive reward and aversion-driven behaviors, serving as a hub connecting emotion/cognitive processing regions including the prefrontal cortex (PFC). However, its role in human drug addiction has not been fully explored. Using diffusion tractography, we detailed PFC structural connectivity with three regions, namely the Hb, ventral tegmental area (VTA), and anterior thalamus (AT), and quantified the tract-specific microstructural integrity using diffusion tensor imaging within the anterior limb of the internal capsule (ALIC) in healthy and cocaine-addicted individuals. White matter microstructure in cocaine-addicted individuals was uniquely impaired in PFC-Hb projections in the ALIC, distinguishable from adjacent PFC-VTA and PFC-AT projections, with more pronounced abnormalities in short-term abstinence. These findings extend preclinical evidence of PFC-Hb circuit impairments in addiction and contextualize the plausible existence of a similar PFC-Hb connection in the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475656" rel="alternate" title="Microstructural Impairments in a Topologically Distinct Prefrontal-Habenular Connection in Cocaine Addiction (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475604</id><title>Local interactions between steady-state visually evoked potentials at nearby flickering frequencies (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378719+00:00</updated><author><name>Kumari Liza</name></author><author><name>Supratim Ray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Steady-state visually evoked potentials (SSVEP) are widely used to index top-down cognitive processing in human electroencephalogram (EEG) studies. Typically, two stimuli flickering at different temporal frequencies (TFs) are presented, each producing a distinct response in the EEG at its flicker frequency. However, how SSVEP responses in EEG are modulated in the presence of a competing flickering stimulus just due to sensory interactions is not well understood. We have previously shown in local field potentials (LFP) recorded from awake monkeys that when two overlapping full screen gratings are counter-phased at different TFs, there is an asymmetric SSVEP response suppression, with greater suppression from lower TFs, which further depends on the relative orientations of the gratings (stronger suppression and asymmetry for parallel compared to orthogonal gratings). Here, we first confirmed these effects in both male and female human EEG recordings. Then, we mapped the response suppression of one stimulus (target) by a competing stimulus (mask) over a much wider range than the previous study. Surprisingly, we found that the suppression was not stronger at low frequencies in general, but systematically varied depending on the target TF, indicating local interactions between the two competing stimuli. These results were confirmed in both human EEG and monkey LFP and electrocorticogram (ECoG) data. Our results show that sensory interactions between multiple SSVEPs are more complex than shown previously and are influenced by both local and global factors, underscoring the need to cautiously interpret the results of studies involving SSVEP paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475604" rel="alternate" title="Local interactions between steady-state visually evoked potentials at nearby flickering frequencies (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475608</id><title>Short periods of bipolar anodal TDCS induce no instantaneous dose-dependent increase in cerebral blood flow in the targeted human motor cortex (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378774+00:00</updated><author><name>Marie Louise Liu</name></author><author><name>Anke Ninija Karabanov</name></author><author><name>Marjolein Piek</name></author><author><name>Esben Thade Petersen</name></author><author><name>Axel Thielscher</name></author><author><name>Hartwig Roman Siebner</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anodal transcranial direct current stimulation (aTDCS) of primary motor hand area (M1-HAND) can enhance corticomotor excitability. Yet, it is still unknown which current intensity produces the strongest effect on regional neural activity. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) combined with pseudo-continuous Arterial Spin Labeling (pc-ASL MRI) can map regional cortical blood flow (rCBF) and may thus be useful to probe the relationship between current intensity and neural response at the individual level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we employed pc-ASL MRI to map acute rCBF changes during short-duration aTDCS of left M1-HAND. Using the rCBF response as a proxy for regional neuronal activity, we investigated if short-duration aTDCS produces an instantaneous dose-dependent rCBF increase in the targeted M1-HAND that may be useful for individual dosing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nine healthy right-handed participants received 30 seconds of aTDCS at 0.5, 1.0, 1.5, and 2.0 mA with the anode placed over left M1-HAND and cathode over the right supraorbital region. Concurrent pc-ASL MRI at 3 T probed TDCS-related rCBF changes in the targeted M1-HAND. Movement-induced rCBF changes were also assessed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apart from a subtle increase in rCBF at 0.5 mA, short-duration aTDCS did not modulate rCBF in the M1-HAND relative to no-stimulation periods. None of the participants showed a dose-dependent increase in rCBF during aTDCS, even after accounting for individual differences in TDCS-induced electrical field strength. In contrast, finger movements led to robust activation of left M1-HAND before and after aTDCS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short-duration bipolar aTDCS does not produce instantaneous dose-dependent rCBF increases in the targeted M1-HAND at conventional intensity ranges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the regional hemodynamic response profile to short-duration aTDCS may not be suited to inform individual dosing of TDCS intensity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arterial spin labeling (ASL) MRI probed regional cerebral blood flow (rCBF) during anodal TDCS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short-duration anodal TDCS was applied to left motor hand area (M1-HAND) at 0.5, 1.0, 1.5 and 2.0 mA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anodal TDCS produced no instantaneous dose-dependent rCBF increase in left M1-HAND.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apart from a subtle increase at 0.5 mA, rCBF was not modified in M1-HAND during anodal TDCS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475608" rel="alternate" title="Short periods of bipolar anodal TDCS induce no instantaneous dose-dependent increase in cerebral blood flow in the targeted human motor cortex (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475450</id><title>FTY720 requires vitamin B12-TCN2-CD320 signaling in astrocytes to reduce disease in an animal model of multiple sclerosis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378841+00:00</updated><author><name>Deepa Jonnalagadda</name></author><author><name>Yasuyuki Kihara</name></author><author><name>Aran Groves</name></author><author><name>Manisha Ray</name></author><author><name>Arjun Saha</name></author><author><name>Hyeon-Cheol Lee-Okada</name></author><author><name>Tomomi Furihata</name></author><author><name>Takehiko Yokomizo</name></author><author><name>Edward V. Quadros</name></author><author><name>Richard Rivera</name></author><author><name>Jerold Chun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;FTY720 (fingolimod) is a sphingosine 1-phosphate (S1P) receptor modulator and sphingosine analogue approved for multiple sclerosis (MS) therapy, which can functionally antagonize the S1P receptor, S1P&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;. Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; (B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;) deficiency produces neurological manifestations resembling MS. Here, we report a new mechanism where FTY720 suppresses neuroinflammation by regulating B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; metabolic pathways. Nuclear RNA-seq of c-Fos-activated astrocytes (called &lt;italic&gt;ieAstrocytes&lt;/italic&gt;) from experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) spinal cords identified up-regulation of CD320, a transcobalamin 2 (TCN2)-B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; receptor, by S1P&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; inhibition. CD320 was reduced in MS plaques. Deficiency of CD320 or dietary B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; worsened EAE and eliminated FTY720’s efficacy, while concomitantly down-regulating type I interferon signaling. TCN2 functioned as a chaperone for FTY720 and sphingosine, which induced astrocytic CD320 internalization. An accompanying paper identified a requirement for astrocyte sphingosine kinases in FTY720 efficacy and its altered expression in MS brains, molecularly linking MS and B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; deficiency that can be accessed by sphingolipid/fingolimod metabolic pathways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475450" rel="alternate" title="FTY720 requires vitamin B12-TCN2-CD320 signaling in astrocytes to reduce disease in an animal model of multiple sclerosis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.473972</id><title>Accurate sex classification from neural responses to sexual stimuli (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.378927+00:00</updated><author><name>Vesa Putkinen</name></author><author><name>Sanaz Nazari-Farsani</name></author><author><name>Tomi Karjalainen</name></author><author><name>Severi Santavirta</name></author><author><name>Matthew Hudson</name></author><author><name>Kerttu Seppälä</name></author><author><name>Lihua Sun</name></author><author><name>Henry K. Karlsson</name></author><author><name>Jussi Hirvonen</name></author><author><name>Lauri Nummenmaa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sex differences in brain activity evoked by sexual stimuli remain elusive despite robust evidence for stronger enjoyment of and interest towards sexual stimuli in men than in women. To test whether visual sexual stimuli evoke different brain activity patterns in men and women, we measured haemodynamic brain activity induced by visual sexual stimuli in two experiments in 91 subjects (46 males). In one experiment, the subjects viewed sexual and non-sexual film clips and dynamic annotations for nudity in the clips was used to predict their hemodynamic activity. In the second experiment, the subjects viewed sexual and non-sexual pictures in an event-related design. Males showed stronger activation than females in the visual and prefrontal cortices and dorsal attention network in both experiments. Furthermore, using multivariate pattern classification we could accurately predict the sex of the subject on the basis of the brain activity elicited by the sexual stimuli. The classification generalized across the experiments indicating that the sex differences were consistent. Eye tracking data obtained from an independent sample of subjects (N = 110) showed that men looked longer than women at the chest area of the nude female actors in the film clips. These results indicate that visual sexual stimuli evoke discernible brain activity patterns in men and women which may reflect stronger attentional engagement with sexual stimuli in men than women.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.473972" rel="alternate" title="Accurate sex classification from neural responses to sexual stimuli (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476378</id><title>Activation of the dorsal septum increases alcohol consumption in male C57BL/6J mice. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.379008+00:00</updated><author><name>Harold L Haun</name></author><author><name>Shannon L D'Ambrosio</name></author><author><name>Thomas L Kash</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Binge drinking is a common pattern of excessive alcohol consumption associated with Alcohol Use Disorder (AUD) and unraveling the neurocircuitry that promotes this type of drinking is critical to the development of novel therapeutic interventions. The septal region was once a focal point of alcohol research yet has seen limited study over the last decade in relation to binge drinking. Numerous studies point to involvement of the dorsal septum (dSep) in excessive drinking and withdrawal, but few studies have manipulated this region in the context of binge drinking behavior. The present experiments were primarily designed to determine the effect of chemogenetic manipulation of the dSep on binge-like alcohol drinking in male and female C57BL/6J mice. Mice received bilateral infusion of AAVs harboring hM4Di, hM3Dq, or mCherry into the dSep and subjects were challenged with systemic administration of clozapine-N-oxide (CNO; 3 mg/kg) or vehicle (saline; 0.9%) in the context of binge-like alcohol consumption, locomotor activity, and sucrose drinking. CNO-mediated activation (hM3Dq) of the dSep resulted in a significant increase in binge-like alcohol consumption, locomotor activity, and sucrose intake in male mice. DSep activation promoted sucrose drinking in female mice, but alcohol intake and locomotor activity were unaffected. Conversely, silencing (hM4Di) of the dSep modestly decreased locomotor activity in males and did not influence alcohol or sucrose intake in either sex. Lastly, CNO was without effect in mCherry-expressing control groups. These data support a role for the dSep in promoting excessive, binge-like drinking behavior in a sex-dependent fashion and suggests a broad role for the region in the modulation of locomotor activity as well as general appetitive behavior such as sucrose drinking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476378" rel="alternate" title="Activation of the dorsal septum increases alcohol consumption in male C57BL/6J mice. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>