<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.673325+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474489</id><title>High density single-unit human cortical recordings using the Neuropixels probe (50 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.673693+00:00</updated><author><name>Jason E Chung</name></author><author><name>Kristin K Sellers</name></author><author><name>Matthew K Leonard</name></author><author><name>Laura Gwilliams</name></author><author><name>Duo Xu</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Dougherty</name></author><author><name>Viktor Kharazia</name></author><author><name>Marleen Welkenhuysen</name></author><author><name>Barundeb Dutta</name></author><author><name>Edward F Chang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A fundamental unit of neural computation is the action potential. While significant advances have been made in the ability to sample action potentials of large numbers of individual neurons in animal models, translation of these methodologies to humans has been lacking due to clinical time constraints, electrical noise in the operating room, and reliability of the methodology. Here we present a reliable method for intraoperative recording of dozens of neurons in humans using the Neuropixels probe, yielding up to ~100 simultaneously-recorded single-units (n=596 across 11 recordings in 8 participants). Most single-units were active within 1 minute of reaching target depth, compatible with clinical time constraints. Cell pairs active close in time were spatially closer in most recordings, demonstrating the power to resolve complex cortical dynamics. Altogether, this approach provides access to population single-unit activity across the depth of human neocortex at scales previously only accessible in animal models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474489" rel="alternate" title="High density single-unit human cortical recordings using the Neuropixels probe (50 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474304</id><title>Techniques for visualizing fibroblast-vessel interactions in the developing and adult CNS (40 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.674123+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah E Jones</name></author><author><name>Kelsey A Abrams</name></author><author><name>Julie A Siegenthaler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fibroblasts are found associated with blood vessels in various locations across the CNS: in the meninges, the choroid plexus, and in the parenchyma within perivascular spaces. CNS fibroblasts have been characterized using transcriptional profiling and a Col1a1-GFP mouse line used to identify CNS fibroblasts in vivo. However, current methods for visualizing CNS fibroblasts are lacking and, in particular, prevent adequate assessment of fibroblast-vessel interactions. Here, we describe methods for whole mount visualization of meningeal and choroid plexus fibroblasts, and optical tissue clearing methods for visualization of parenchymal vessel-associated fibroblasts. Importantly, these techniques can be combined with immunohistochemistry methods for labeling different cell types in the meninges and blood vasculature as well as EdU-based cell proliferation assays. These methods are ideal for visualization of vessel-fibroblast interactions in these CNS structures and provide significant improvement over traditional sectioning and staining methods. We expect these methods will advance studies of CNS fibroblast development and functions in homeostasis, injury, and disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474304" rel="alternate" title="Techniques for visualizing fibroblast-vessel interactions in the developing and adult CNS (40 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474605</id><title>Roles for Mitochondrial Complex I subunits in regulating synaptic transmission and growth (31 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.674328+00:00</updated><author><name>Bhagaban Mallik</name></author><author><name>C. Andrew Frank</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To identify conserved components of synapse function that are also associated with human diseases, we conducted a genetic screen. We used the Drosophila melanogaster neuromuscular junction (NMJ) as a model. We employed RNA interference (RNAi) on selected targets and assayed synapse function by electrophysiology. We focused our screen on genetic factors known to be conserved from human neurological or muscle functions (321 total RNAi lines screened). Knockdown of a particular Mitochondrial Complex I (MCI) subunit gene (ND-20L) lowered levels of NMJ neurotransmission. Due to the severity of the phenotype, we studied MCI function further. Knockdown of core MCI subunits concurrently in neurons and muscle led to impaired neurotransmission. Further, pharmacology targeting MCI phenocopied the impaired neurotransmission phenotype. Finally, MCI subunit knockdowns led to profound cytological defects, including reduced NMJ growth and altered NMJ morphology. Mitochondria are essential for cellular bioenergetics and produce ATP through oxidative phosphorylation. Five multi-protein complexes achieve this task, and MCI is the largest. Impaired Mitochondrial Complex I subunits in humans are associated with disorders such as Parkinsons disease, Leigh syndrome, and cardiomyopathy. Together, our data present an analysis of Complex I in the context of synapse function and plasticity. We speculate that in the context of human MCI dysfunction, similar neuronal and synaptic defects could contribute to pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474605" rel="alternate" title="Roles for Mitochondrial Complex I subunits in regulating synaptic transmission and growth (31 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474246</id><title>Species-specific mitochondria dynamics and metabolism regulate the timing of neuronal development (27 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.674500+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryohei Iwata</name></author><author><name>Pierre Casimir</name></author><author><name>Emir Erkol</name></author><author><name>Leïla Boubakar</name></author><author><name>Mélanie Planque</name></author><author><name>Martyna Ditkowska</name></author><author><name>Katlijn Vints</name></author><author><name>Suresh Poovathingal</name></author><author><name>Vaiva Gaspariunaite</name></author><author><name>Matthew Bird</name></author><author><name>Nikky Corthout</name></author><author><name>Pieter Vermeersch</name></author><author><name>Kristofer Davie</name></author><author><name>Natalia V. Gounko</name></author><author><name>Stein Aerts</name></author><author><name>Bart Ghesquière</name></author><author><name>Sarah-Maria Fendt</name></author><author><name>Pierre Vanderhaeghen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The evolution of species involves changes in the timeline of key developmental programs. Among these, neuronal development is considerably prolonged in the human cerebral cortex compared with other mammals, leading to brain neoteny. Here we explore whether mitochondria influence the species-specific properties of cortical neuron maturation. By comparing human and mouse cortical neuronal maturation at high temporal and cell resolution, we found a slower pattern of mitochondria development in human cortical neurons compared with the mouse, together with lower mitochondria metabolic activity, particularly oxidative phosphorylation. Stimulation of mitochondria metabolism in human neurons resulted in accelerated maturation, leading to excitable and complex cells weeks ahead of time. Our data identify mitochondria as important regulators of the pace of neuronal development underlying human-specific features of brain evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474246" rel="alternate" title="Species-specific mitochondria dynamics and metabolism regulate the timing of neuronal development (27 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474366</id><title>The mitochondrial calcium uniporter regulates mitochondrial mass and dendritic localization in distinct hippocampal circuits (19 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.674885+00:00</updated><author><name>Katy E Pannoni</name></author><author><name>Daniela Gil</name></author><author><name>Logan Campbell</name></author><author><name>Shannon Farris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CA2 is an understudied subregion of the hippocampus that is critical for social memory. Previous studies identified multiple components of the mitochondrial calcium uniporter (MCU) complex as selectively enriched in CA2, however the functional significance of this enrichment remains unclear. The MCU complex regulates calcium entry into mitochondria, which in turn regulates mitochondrial transport and localization to active synapses. We found that MCU is strikingly enriched in CA2 distal apical dendrites, precisely where CA2 neurons receive entorhinal cortical input carrying social information. Further, MCU-enriched mitochondria in CA2 distal dendrites are larger compared to mitochondria in CA2 proximal apical dendrites and neighboring CA1 apical dendrites. Genetic knockdown of MCU in CA2 resulted in smaller mitochondria in CA2 distal dendrites, indicating that MCU expression plays a role in regulating mitochondrial mass in CA2. MCU overexpression in neighboring CA1 led to larger mitochondria preferentially in proximal dendrites compared to distal dendrites and GFP controls. Our findings demonstrate that mitochondria are molecularly and structurally diverse across hippocampal cell types and circuits, and that MCU expression cell-autonomously regulates mitochondrial mass, but layer-specific dendritic localization depends on cell type. Our data support the idea that CA2 mitochondria are functionally distinct from CA1 mitochondria, which may confer unique synaptic and circuit properties underlying CA2 function in social memory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474366" rel="alternate" title="The mitochondrial calcium uniporter regulates mitochondrial mass and dendritic localization in distinct hippocampal circuits (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474477</id><title>Optogenetic inhibition of the dorsal hippocampus CA3 region during early-stage cocaine-memory reconsolidation disrupts subsequent context-induced cocaine seeking in rats (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.675068+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuyi Qi</name></author><author><name>Shi Min Tan</name></author><author><name>Rong Wang</name></author><author><name>Jessica A. Higginbotham</name></author><author><name>Jobe L. Ritchie</name></author><author><name>Christopher K. Ibarra</name></author><author><name>Amy A. Arguello</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Christian</name></author><author><name>Rita A. Fuchs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The dorsal hippocampus (DH) is key to the long-term maintenance of cocaine memories following retrieval-induced memory destabilization; even though, it is not the site of protein synthesis-dependent memory reconsolidation. Here, we took advantage of the temporal and spatial specificity of an optogenetic manipulation to examine the role of the cornu ammonis 3 subregion of the DH (dCA3) in early-stage cocaine-memory reconsolidation. Male Sprague-Dawley rats expressing eNpHR3.0 in the DH were trained to self-administer cocaine in a distinct context and underwent extinction training in a different context. Rats then received a 15-min memory-reactivation session, to destabilize cocaine memories and trigger reconsolidation, or remained in their home cages (no-reactivation controls). Optogenetic inhibition of the dCA3 for 1 h immediately, but not 1 h, after memory reactivation resulted in cocaine-memory impairment as indicated by reduction in drug-seeking behavior selectively in the cocaine-paired context 3 d later, at test, relative to responding in no-inhibition, no-reactivation, and no-eNpHR3.0 controls. Cocaine-memory impairment was associated with reduced c-Fos expression, an index of neuronal activation, in the dCA3 stratum lucidum (SL) and stratum pyramidale (SP) at test. Based on these observations and extant literature, we postulate that recurrent circuits in the SP are activated during early-stage memory reconsolidation to maintain labile cocaine memories prior to protein synthesis-dependent restabilization in another brain region, such as the basolateral amygdala. Furthermore, SL and SP interneurons may enhance memory reconsolidation by limiting synaptic noise in the SP and also contribute to recall as elements of the updated cocaine engram or retrieval links.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474477" rel="alternate" title="Optogenetic inhibition of the dorsal hippocampus CA3 region during early-stage cocaine-memory reconsolidation disrupts subsequent context-induced cocaine seeking in rats (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474262</id><title>Uncovering a neural circuit controlling adult quiescent neural stem cell activation in the subventricular zone (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.675345+00:00</updated><author><name>Moawiah Naffaa</name></author><author><name>Rehan Khan</name></author><author><name>Chay T Kuo</name></author><author><name>Henry H Yin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The maintenance and differentiation of the adult neural stem cells (NSCs) in the subventricular zone (SVZ) are controlled by cell-intrinsic molecular pathways that interact with extrinsic signaling cues. How neurogenesis in the SVZ is regulated by neural circuit activity remains poorly understood. Here we identified a novel neural circuit that regulates the state of lateral ventricular wall (LV) NSCs. Our results demonstrate that direct glutamatergic inputs from the frontal cortex, as well as local inhibitory interneurons, control the activity of subependymal cholinergic neurons. In vivo optogenetic and chemogenetic stimulation of defined neuronal populations within this circuit were sufficient to control LV NSC proliferation and SVZ neurogenesis. Moreover, acetylcholine (ACh), which activates M1 muscarinic ACh receptors, triggers the activation of quiescent NSCs. These findings shed light on neural activity-dependent regulation of postnatal and adult LV NSCs activation and SVZ neurogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474262" rel="alternate" title="Uncovering a neural circuit controlling adult quiescent neural stem cell activation in the subventricular zone (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474557</id><title>Properties and proximity proteomics of synaptopodin provide insight into the molecular organization of the spine apparatus of dendritic spines (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.675529+00:00</updated><author><name>Hanieh Falahati</name></author><author><name>Yumei Wu</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Feuerer</name></author><author><name>Pietro De Camilli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spine apparatus is a specialization of the neuronal ER in dendritic spines consisting of stacks of interconnected cisterns separated by a dense matrix. Synaptopodin, a specific actin binding protein of the spine apparatus, is essential for its formation, but the underlying mechanisms remain unknown. We show that synaptopodin, when expressed in fibroblasts, forms actin-rich structures with connections to the ER, and that an ER-tethered synaptopodin assembles into liquid condensates. We also identified protein neighbors of synaptopodin in spines by in vivo proximity biotinylation. We validated a small subset of such proteins and showed that they co-assemble with synaptopodin in living cells.  One of them is Pdlim7, an actin binding protein not previously identified in spines, and we show its precise colocalization with synaptopodin. We suggest that the matrix of the spine apparatus has the property of a liquid protein condensate generated by a multiplicity of low affinity interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474557" rel="alternate" title="Properties and proximity proteomics of synaptopodin provide insight into the molecular organization of the spine apparatus of dendritic spines (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474558</id><title>BDNF-induced BDNF release mediates presynaptic LTP and is regulated by cannabinoids (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.675780+00:00</updated><author><name>Coralie Berthoux</name></author><author><name>Kaoutsar Nasrallah</name></author><author><name>Pablo E Castillo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) and its effector, Tropomyosin receptor kinase B (TrkB), are implicated in activity-dependent synaptic plasticity, the precise underlying mechanisms remain unclear. In the dentate gyrus, a hippocampal input region that expresses uniquely high levels of BDNF, repetitive activation of mossy cells (MCs) induces a presynaptic, BDNF/TrkB-dependent form of LTP at MC to granule cell (GC) synapses. Here, we report that activity-induced BDNF release from MC axons in mice elicits postsynaptic BDNF release in a TrkB- and calcium-dependent manner, and that BDNF-induced BDNF release is essential for LTP induction. Suppression of BDNF release by tonic and phasic activity of presynaptic type-1 cannabinoid receptors dampened LTP, revealing an unprecedented role of these receptors in controlling neuropeptide release. Lastly, BDNF-mediated MC-GC LTP can be elicited in vivo. Thus, BDNF-induced BDNF release emerges as a mechanism for activity-dependent LTP that may contribute to dentate gyrus-dependent learning, epilepsy, and neuropsychiatric disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474558" rel="alternate" title="BDNF-induced BDNF release mediates presynaptic LTP and is regulated by cannabinoids (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.26.473589</id><title>Biological Aging of CNS-Resident Cells Alters the Clinical Course and Immunopathology of Autoimmune Demyelinating Disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.675978+00:00</updated><author><name>Jeffrey R. Atkinson</name></author><author><name>Andrew D. Jerome</name></author><author><name>Andrew R. Sas</name></author><author><name>Ashley Munie</name></author><author><name>W. David Arnold</name></author><author><name>Benjamin M. Segal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological aging is the strongest factor associated with the clinical phenotype of multiple sclerosis (MS). Relapsing remitting MS (RRMS) typically presents in the third or fourth decade, while the mean age of presentation of progressive MS (pMS) is 45 years old. Here we show that experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE), induced by the adoptive transfer of encephalitogenic CD4+ Th17 cells, is more severe, and less like to remit, in middle-aged compared with young adult mice. Donor T cells and neutrophils are more abundant, while B cells are relatively sparse, in central nervous system (CNS) infiltrates of the older mice. Experiments with reciprocal bone marrow chimeras demonstrate that radio-resistant, non-hematopoietic cells play a dominant role in shaping age-related features of the neuroinflammatory response, as well as the clinical course, during EAE. Reminiscent of pMS, EAE in middle-aged adoptive transfer recipients is characterized by widespread microglial activation. Microglia from older mice express a distinctive transcriptomic profile, suggestive of enhanced chemokine synthesis and antigen presentation. Collectively, our findings suggest that drugs that suppress microglial activation, and acquisition or expression of aging-associated properties, may be beneficial in the treatment of progressive forms of inflammatory demyelinating disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.26.473589" rel="alternate" title="Biological Aging of CNS-Resident Cells Alters the Clinical Course and Immunopathology of Autoimmune Demyelinating Disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474302</id><title>Perceptual uncertainty alternates top-down and bottom-up fronto-temporal network signaling during response inhibition (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.676175+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaho Tsumura</name></author><author><name>Reiko Shintaki</name></author><author><name>Masaki Takeda</name></author><author><name>Junichi Chikazoe</name></author><author><name>Kiyoshi Nakahara</name></author><author><name>Koji Jimura</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Response inhibition is a primary executive control function that allows the withholding of inappropriate responses, and requires appropriate perception of the external environment to achieve a behavioral goal. It remains unclear, however, how response inhibition is achieved when goal-relevant information involves perceptual uncertainty. Twenty-six human participants of both sexes performed a go/no-go task where visually presented random-dot motion stimuli involved perceptual uncertainties. The right inferior frontal cortex (rIFC) was involved in response inhibition, and the middle temporal (MT) region showed greater activity when dot motions involved less uncertainty. A neocortical temporal region in the superior temporal sulcus (STS) specifically showed greater activity during response inhibition in more perceptually certain trials. In this STS region, activity was greater when response inhibition was successful than when it failed. Directional effective connectivity analysis revealed that in more coherent trials, the MT and STS regions showed enhanced connectivity to the rIFC, whereas in less coherent trials, the signal direction was reversed. These results suggest that a reversible fronto-temporal functional network guides response inhibition under perceptual uncertainty, and in this network, perceptual information in the MT is converted to control information in the rIFC via STS, enabling achievement of response inhibition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.27.474302" rel="alternate" title="Perceptual uncertainty alternates top-down and bottom-up fronto-temporal network signaling during response inhibition (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474505</id><title>Information encoded in volumes and areas of dendritic spines is nearly maximal across mammalian brains (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.676464+00:00</updated><author><name>Jan Karbowski</name></author><author><name>Paulina Urban</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long-term information associated with neuronal memory resides in dendritic spines. However, spines can have a limited size due to metabolic and neuroanatomical constraints, which should effectively limit the amount of encoded information in excitatory synapses. This study investigates how much information can be stored in the sizes of dendritic spines, and whether is it optimal in any sense? It is shown here, using empirical data for several mammalian brains across different regions and physiological conditions, that dendritic spines nearly maximize entropy contained in their volumes and surface areas for a given mean size. This result is essentially independent of the type of a fitting distribution to size data, as both short- and heavy-tailed distributions yield similar nearly 100 % information efficiency in the majority of cases, although heavy-tailed distributions slightly better fit the data. On average, the highest information is contained in spine volume, and the lowest in spine length or spine head diameter. Depending on a species and brain region, a typical spine can encode between 6.1 and 10.8 bits of information in its volume, and 3.1-8.1 bits in its surface area. Our results suggest a universality of entropy maximization in spine volumes and areas, which can be a new principle of memory storing in synapses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474505" rel="alternate" title="Information encoded in volumes and areas of dendritic spines is nearly maximal across mammalian brains (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474511</id><title>A systematic characterization of intrinsically formed microglia-like cells during retinal organoid differentiation. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.676665+00:00</updated><author><name>Katarina Bartalska</name></author><author><name>Verena Hübschmann</name></author><author><name>Medina Korkut-Demirbaş</name></author><author><name>Ryan John Abat Cubero</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Venturino</name></author><author><name>Karl Rössler</name></author><author><name>Thomas Czech</name></author><author><name>Sandra Siegert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain organoids differentiated from human induced pluripotent stem cells provide a unique opportunity to investigate the development, organization and connectivity of neurons in a complex cellular environment. However, organoids usually lack microglia, brain-resident immune cells which are both present in the early human embryonic brain and participate in neuronal circuit development. Here, we find that microglia innately develop in unguided retinal organoid differentiation between week 3 and 4 in 2.5D culture and appear later in floating, non-pigmented, 3D-cystic compartments. We enriched for cystic structures using a low-dosed BMP4 application and performed mass spectrometry, thus defining the protein composition of microglia-containing compartments. We found that cystic compartments expressed both mesenchymal and epithelial markers with microglia enriched in the mesenchymal region. Interestingly, microglia-like cells started to express the border-associated macrophage marker CD163. The preferential localization of human microglia to a mesenchymal compartment provides insight into the behavior and migration of microglia. The model will ultimately allow detailed study of these enigmatic cells and how they enter and distribute within the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474511" rel="alternate" title="A systematic characterization of intrinsically formed microglia-like cells during retinal organoid differentiation. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474596</id><title>Oxytocin modulates social brain network correlations in resting and task state (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.676916+00:00</updated><author><name>Qingyuan Wu</name></author><author><name>Qi Huang</name></author><author><name>Chao Liu</name></author><author><name>Haiyan Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Oxytocin (OT) is a neuropeptide that modulates social behaviors and the social brain. The effects of OT on the social brain can be tracked by assessing the neural activity in the resting and task states, providing a system-level framework for characterizing state-based functional relationships of its distinct effect. Here, we contribute to this framework by examining how OT modulates social brain network correlations during the resting and task states using fMRI. Firstly, we investigated network activation, followed by analyzing the relationship between networks and individual differences measured by the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule and the Big-Five scales. Subsequently, we evaluated functional connectivity in both states. Finally, the relationship between networks across the states was represented by the predictive power of networks in the resting state for task-evoked activity. The difference in predicted accuracy between subjects displayed individual variations in this relationship. Our results showed decreased  dorsal default mode network (DDMN) for OT group in the resting state. Additionally, only in the OT group, the activity of the DDMN in the resting state had the largest predictive power for task-evoked activation of the precuneus network (PN). The results also demonstrated OT reduced individual variation of PN, specifically, the difference of accuracy between predicting a subject's own and others' PN task activation. These findings suggest a distributed but modulatory effect of OT on the association between resting brain networks and task-dependent brain networks, showing increased DDMN to PN connectivity after OT administration, which may support OT-induced distributed processing during task performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.30.474596" rel="alternate" title="Oxytocin modulates social brain network correlations in resting and task state (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474396</id><title>Differential regulation of prelimbic and thalamic transmission to the basolateral amygdala by acetylcholine receptors (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.677156+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah C. Tryon</name></author><author><name>Joshua X. Bratsch-Prince</name></author><author><name>James W. Warren</name></author><author><name>Grace C. Jones</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. McDonald</name></author><author><name>David D. Mott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The amygdalar anterior basolateral nucleus (BLa) plays a vital role in emotional behaviors. This region receives dense cholinergic projections from basal forebrain which are critical in regulating neuronal activity and synaptic transmission. Cholinergic signaling in BLa is thought to occur through both a slow mode of volume transmission as well as a rapid, phasic mode. However, the relative effect of each mode of signaling in BLa is not understood. Here, we used electrophysiology and optogenetics in mouse brain slices to compare regulation of afferent input from cortex and thalamus to the BLa by these two modes of transmission. Phasic ACh release evoked by single pulse stimulation of cholinergic terminals had a biphasic effect on glutamatergic transmission at cortical input, producing rapid nicotinic receptor-mediated facilitation followed by slower muscarinic receptor (mAChR)-mediated depression. In contrast, tonic elevation of ACh through application of the cholinesterase inhibitor physostigmine suppressed glutamatergic transmission at cortical inputs through mAChRs only. This suppression was not observed at thalamic inputs to BLa. In agreement with this pathway-specificity, the mAChR agonist, muscarine more potently suppressed transmission at inputs from prelimbic cortex (PL) than thalamus. Muscarinic inhibition at PL input was dependent on presynaptic M4 mAChRs, while at thalamic input it depended upon M3 mAChR-mediated stimulation of retrograde endocannabinoid signaling. Muscarinic inhibition at both pathways was frequency-dependent, allowing only high frequency activity to pass. These findings demonstrate complex cholinergic regulation of afferent input to BLa that depends upon the mode of ACh release and is both pathway specific and frequency dependent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474396" rel="alternate" title="Differential regulation of prelimbic and thalamic transmission to the basolateral amygdala by acetylcholine receptors (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>