<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.051996+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.465477</id><title>kTMP: A New Non-invasive Magnetic Induction Method to Modulate Cortical Excitability (84 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.052370+00:00</updated><author><name>Ludovica Labruna</name></author><author><name>Christina Merrick</name></author><author><name>Ben Inglis</name></author><author><name>Richard Ivry</name></author><author><name>Daniel Sheltraw</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report a novel subthreshold non-invasive brain stimulation approach that we refer to as kilohertz transcranial magnetic perturbation, or kTMP. kTMP is a magnetic induction method that delivers kHz-frequency cortical E-fields and, through amplitude modulation of the kHz carrier frequency, may mimic E-fields at physiological frequencies. To evaluate the efficacy of kTMP, we used suprathreshold TMS to elicit motor-evoked potentials (MEP) in a peripheral muscle, comparing the amplitude of the MEPs before and after kTMP stimulation. In Experiment 1, we used non-modulated kTMP with an E-field amplitude of 2 V/m over motor cortex. Ten minutes of kTMP stimulation resulted in an increase in cortical excitability in a frequency-specific manner. We replicated this effect in Experiment 2 and found that amplitude-modulation at 20 Hz produced an additional boost in cortical excitability. The only percept associated with kTMP is a faint auditory tone, making kTMP ideal for double-blind experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.465477" rel="alternate" title="kTMP: A New Non-invasive Magnetic Induction Method to Modulate Cortical Excitability (84 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469009</id><title>Not so fast: Limited validity of deep convolutional neural networks as in silico models for human naturalistic face processing (39 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.052571+00:00</updated><author><name>Guo Jiahui</name></author><author><name>Ma Feilong</name></author><author><name>Matteo Visconti di Oleggio Castello</name></author><author><name>Samuel A Nastase</name></author><author><name>James V Haxby</name></author><author><name>Maria Ida Gobbini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deep convolutional neural networks (DCNNs) trained for face identification can rival and even exceed human-level performance. The relationships between internal representations learned by DCNNs and those of the primate face processing system are not well understood, especially in naturalistic settings. We developed the largest naturalistic dynamic face stimulus set in human neuroimaging research (700+ naturalistic video clips of unfamiliar faces) and used representational similarity analysis to investigate how well the representations learned by high-performing DCNNs match human brain representations across the entire distributed face processing system. DCNN representational geometries were strikingly consistent across diverse architectures and captured meaningful variance among faces. Similarly, representational geometries throughout the human face network were highly consistent across subjects. Nonetheless, correlations between DCNN and neural representations were very weak overall—DCNNs captured 3% of variance in the neural representational geometries at best. Intermediate DCNN layers better matched visual and face-selective cortices than the final fully-connected layers. Behavioral ratings of face similarity were highly correlated with intermediate layers of DCNNs, but also failed to capture representational geometry in the human brain. Our results suggest that the correspondence between intermediate DCNN layers and neural representations of naturalistic human face processing is weak at best, and diverges even further in the later fully-connected layers. This poor correspondence can be attributed, at least in part, to the dynamic and cognitive information that plays an essential role in human face processing but is not modeled by DCNNs. These mismatches indicate that current DCNNs have limited validity as &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; models of dynamic, naturalistic face processing in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469009" rel="alternate" title="Not so fast: Limited validity of deep convolutional neural networks as in silico models for human naturalistic face processing (39 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468535</id><title>Rapid reconstruction of neural circuits using tissue expansion and lattice light sheet microscopy (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.052738+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua L. Lillvis</name></author><author><name>Hideo Otsuna</name></author><author><name>Xiaoyu Ding</name></author><author><name>Igor Pisarev</name></author><author><name>Takashi Kawase</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Colonell</name></author><author><name>Konrad Rokicki</name></author><author><name>Cristian Goina</name></author><author><name>Ruixuan Gao</name></author><author><name>Amy Hu</name></author><author><name>Kaiyu Wang</name></author><author><name>John Bogovic</name></author><author><name>Daniel E. Milkie</name></author><author><name>Linus Meienberg</name></author><author><name>Edward S. Boyden</name></author><author><name>Stephan Saalfeld</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Tillberg</name></author><author><name>Barry J. Dickson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Electron microscopy (EM) allows for the reconstruction of dense neuronal connectomes but suffers from low throughput, limiting its application to small numbers of reference specimens. We developed a protocol and analysis pipeline using tissue expansion and lattice light-sheet microscopy (ExLLSM) to rapidly reconstruct selected circuits across many samples with single synapse resolution and molecular contrast. We validate this approach in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt;, demonstrating that it yields synaptic counts similar to those obtained by EM, can be used to compare counts across sex and experience, and to correlate structural connectivity with functional connectivity. This approach fills a critical methodological gap in studying variability in the structure and function of neural circuits across individuals within and between species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468535" rel="alternate" title="Rapid reconstruction of neural circuits using tissue expansion and lattice light sheet microscopy (35 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.467545</id><title>Slow fluctuations in ongoing brain activity decrease in amplitude with ageing yet their impact on task-related evoked responses is dissociable from behaviour (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053018+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria J. Ribeiro</name></author><author><name>Miguel Castelo-Branco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In humans, ageing is characterized by decreased brain signal variability and increased behavioural variability. To understand how reduced brain variability segregates with increased behavioural variability, we investigated the association between reaction time variability, evoked brain responses and ongoing brain signal dynamics, in young (N = 36) and older adults (N = 39). We studied the electroencephalogram (EEG) and pupil size fluctuations to characterize the cortical and arousal responses elicited by a cued go/no-go task. Evoked responses were strongly modulated by slow (&amp;lt; 2 Hz) fluctuations of the ongoing signals, which presented reduced power in the older participants. Although variability of the evoked responses was lower in the older participants, once we adjusted for the effect of the ongoing signal fluctuations, evoked responses were equally variable in both groups. Moreover, the modulation of the evoked responses caused by the ongoing signal fluctuations had no impact on reaction time, thereby explaining why although ongoing brain signal variability is decreased in older individuals, behavioural variability is not. Finally, we showed that adjusting for the effect of the ongoing signal was critical to unmask the link between neural responses and behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.467545" rel="alternate" title="Slow fluctuations in ongoing brain activity decrease in amplitude with ageing yet their impact on task-related evoked responses is dissociable from behaviour (27 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468735</id><title>Modulation of Cutaneous Responses in the Cuneate Nucleus of Macaques During Active Movement (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053155+00:00</updated><author><name>Qinpu He</name></author><author><name>Christopher S. Versteeg</name></author><author><name>Aneesha K. Suresh</name></author><author><name>Lee E. Miller</name></author><author><name>Sliman J. Bensmaia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To achieve stable and precise movement execution, the sensorimotor system integrates exafferent sensory signals originating from interactions with the external world and reafferent signals caused by our own movements. This barrage of sensory information is regulated such that behaviorally relevant signals are boosted at the expense of irrelevant ones. For example, sensitivity to touch is reduced during movement – when cutaneous signals caused by skin stretch are expected and uninteresting – a phenomenon reflected in a decreased cutaneous responsiveness in thalamus and cortex. Some evidence suggests that movement gating of touch may originate from the cuneate nucleus (CN), the first recipient of signals from tactile nerve fibers along the dorsal columns medial lemniscal pathway. To test this possibility, we intermittently delivered mechanical pulses to the receptive fields (RFs) of identified cutaneous CN neurons as monkeys performed a reach-to-grasp task. As predicted, we found that the cutaneous responses of individual CN neurons were reduced during movement. However, this movement gating of cutaneous signals was observed for CN neurons with RFs on the arm but not those with RFs on the hand. We conclude that sensory gating occurs in the first processing stage along the somatosensory neuraxis and sculpts incoming signals according to their task relevance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468735" rel="alternate" title="Modulation of Cutaneous Responses in the Cuneate Nucleus of Macaques During Active Movement (26 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469032</id><title>Anatomical connectivity along the anterior-posterior axis of the human hippocampus: new insights using quantitative fibre-tracking. (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053299+00:00</updated><author><name>Marshall Axel Dalton</name></author><author><name>Arkiev D'Souza</name></author><author><name>Jinglei Lv</name></author><author><name>Fernando Calamante</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hippocampus supports multiple cognitive functions including episodic memory. Recent work has highlighted functional differences along the anterior-posterior axis of the human hippocampus but the neuroanatomical underpinnings of these differences remain unclear. We leveraged track-density imaging to systematically examine anatomical connectivity between the cortical mantle and the anterior-posterior axis of the in-vivo human hippocampus. We first identified the most highly connected cortical areas and detailed the degree to which they preferentially connect along the anterior-posterior axis of the hippocampus. Then, using a tractography pipeline specifically tailored to measure the location and density of streamline endpoints within the hippocampus, we characterised where, within the hippocampus, these cortical areas preferentially connect. Our results were striking in showing that different parts of the hippocampus preferentially connect with distinct cortical areas. Furthermore, we provide evidence that both gradients and circumscribed areas of dense extrinsic anatomical connectivity exist within the human hippocampus. These findings inform conceptual debates in the field by unveiling how specific regions along the anterior-posterior axis of the hippocampus are associated with different cortical inputs/outputs. Overall, our results represent a major advance in our ability to map the anatomical connectivity of the human hippocampus in-vivo and inform our understanding of the neural architecture of hippocampal dependent memory systems in the human brain. This detailed characterization of how specific portions of the hippocampus anatomically connect with cortical brain regions may promote a better understanding of its role in cognition and we emphasize the importance of considering the hippocampus as a heterogeneous structure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469032" rel="alternate" title="Anatomical connectivity along the anterior-posterior axis of the human hippocampus: new insights using quantitative fibre-tracking. (25 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468615</id><title>Using OPM-MEG in contrasting magnetic environments (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053435+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan M. Hill</name></author><author><name>Jasen Devasagayam</name></author><author><name>Niall Holmes</name></author><author><name>Elena Boto</name></author><author><name>Vishal Shah</name></author><author><name>James Osborne</name></author><author><name>Kristina Safar</name></author><author><name>Frank Worcester</name></author><author><name>Christopher Mariani</name></author><author><name>Eliot Dawson</name></author><author><name>David Woolger</name></author><author><name>Richard Bowtell</name></author><author><name>Margot J. Taylor</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Brookes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Magnetoencephalography (MEG) has been revolutionised in recent years by optically pumped magnetometers (OPMs). “OPM-MEG” offers higher sensitivity, better spatial resolution and lower cost than conventional instrumentation based on superconducting quantum interference devices (SQUIDS). Moreover, OPMs offer the possibility of motion robustness and lifespan compliance, dramatically expanding the range of MEG applications. However, OPM-MEG remains nascent technology; it places stringent requirements on magnetic shielding, and whilst a number of viable systems exist, most are custom made and there have been no cross-site investigations showing the reliability of data. In this paper, we undertake the first cross-site OPM-MEG comparison, using near identical commercial systems scanning the same participant. The two sites are deliberately contrasting, with different magnetic environments: a “green field” campus university site with an OPM-optimised shielded room (low interference) and a city centre hospital site with a “standard” (non-optimised) MSR (high interference). We show that despite a 25-fold difference in background field, and a 30-fold difference in low frequency interference, using dynamic field control and software-based suppression of interference we can generate comparable noise floors at both sites. In human data recorded during a visuo-motor task and a face processing paradigm, we were able to generate similar data, with source localisation showing that brain regions could be pinpointed with just ~10 mm spatial discrepancy and temporal correlations of &amp;gt; 80%. Overall, our study demonstrates that “plug- and-play” OPM-MEG systems exist and can be sited even in challenging magnetic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468615" rel="alternate" title="Using OPM-MEG in contrasting magnetic environments (20 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468866</id><title>Brain state and cortical layer-specific mechanisms underlying perception at threshold (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053633+00:00</updated><author><name>Mitchell P. Morton</name></author><author><name>Sachira Denagamage</name></author><author><name>Isabel J. Blume</name></author><author><name>John H. Reynolds</name></author><author><name>Monika P. Jadi</name></author><author><name>Anirvan S. Nandy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identical stimuli can be perceived or go unnoticed across successive presentations, producing divergent behavioral readouts despite similarities in sensory input. We hypothesized that fluctuations in neurophysiological states in the sensory neocortex, which could alter cortical processing at the level of neural subpopulations, underlies this perceptual variability. We analyzed cortical layer-specific electrophysiological activity in visual area V4 during a cued attention task. We find that hit trials are characterized by a larger pupil diameter and lower incidence of microsaccades, indicative of a behavioral state with increased arousal and perceptual stability. Target stimuli presented at perceptual threshold evoke elevated multi-unit activity in V4 neurons in hit trials compared to miss trials, across all cortical layers. Putative excitatory and inhibitory neurons are strongly positively modulated in the input (IV) and deep (V &amp;amp; VI) layers of the cortex during hit trials. Excitatory neurons in the superficial cortical layers exhibit lower variability in hit trials. Deep layer neurons are less phase-locked to low frequency rhythms in hits. Hits are also characterized by greater interlaminar coherence between the superficial and deep layers in the pre-stimulus period, and a complementary pattern between the input layer and both the superficial and deep layers in the stimulus-evoked period. Taken together, these results indicate that a state of elevated levels of arousal and perceptual stability allow enhanced processing of sensory stimuli, which contributes to hits at perceptual threshold.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468866" rel="alternate" title="Brain state and cortical layer-specific mechanisms underlying perception at threshold (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469047</id><title>Awake ripples enhance emotional memory encoding in the human brain (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053780+00:00</updated><author><name>Haoxin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Ivan Skelin</name></author><author><name>Shiting Ma</name></author><author><name>Michelle Paff</name></author><author><name>Michael A Yassa</name></author><author><name>Robert T Knight</name></author><author><name>Jack J Lin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intracranial recordings from the human amygdala and the hippocampus during an emotional memory encoding and discrimination task reveal increased awake sharp-wave/ripples (aSWR) after encoding of emotional compared to neutral stimuli. Further, post-encoding aSWR-locked memory reinstatement in the amygdala and the hippocampus was predictive of later memory discrimination. These findings provide electrophysiological evidence that post-encoding aSWRs enhance memory for emotional events.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469047" rel="alternate" title="Awake ripples enhance emotional memory encoding in the human brain (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468657</id><title>Learning a new class of multisensory associations: High-density electrophysiological mapping of the temporal course of audio-visual object processing (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.053932+00:00</updated><author><name>Tiziana Vercillo</name></author><author><name>Edward G. Freedman</name></author><author><name>Joshua B. Ewen</name></author><author><name>Sophie Molholm</name></author><author><name>John J. Foxe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multisensory objects that are frequently encountered in the natural environment lead to strong associations across a distributed sensory cortical network, with the end result experience of a unitary percept. Remarkably little is known, however, about the cortical processes sub-serving multisensory object formation and recognition. To advance our understanding in this important domain, the present study investigated the brain processes involved in learning and identification of novel visual-auditory objects. Specifically, we introduce and test a rudimentary three-stage model of multisensory object-formation and processing. Thirty adults were remotely trained for a week to recognize a novel class of multisensory objects (3D shapes paired to complex sounds), and high-density event related potentials (ERPs) were recorded to the corresponding unisensory (shapes or sounds only) and multisensory (shapes and sounds) stimuli, before and after intensive training. We identified three major stages of multisensory processing: 1) an early, multisensory, automatic effect (&amp;lt;100 ms) in occipital areas, related to the detection of simultaneous audiovisual signals and not related to multisensory learning 2) an intermediate object-processing stage (100-200 ms) in occipital and parietal areas, sensitive to the learned multisensory associations and 3) a late multisensory processing stage (&amp;gt;250 ms) that appears to be involved in both object recognition and possibly memory consolidation. Results from this study provide support for multiple stages of multisensory object learning and recognition that are subserved by an extended network of cortical areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468657" rel="alternate" title="Learning a new class of multisensory associations: High-density electrophysiological mapping of the temporal course of audio-visual object processing (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468749</id><title>Affinity Scores: An Individual-centric Fingerprinting Framework for Neuropsychiatric Disorders (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054071+00:00</updated><author><name>Cassandra M J Wannan</name></author><author><name>Christos Pantelis</name></author><author><name>Antonia Merritt</name></author><author><name>Bruce Tonge</name></author><author><name>Warda T Syeda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Population-centric frameworks of biomarker identification for psychiatric disorders focus primarily on comparing averages between groups and assume that diagnostic groups are (1) mutually-exclusive, and (2) homogeneous. There is a paucity of individual-centric approaches capable of identifying individual-specific fingerprints across multiple domains. To address this, we propose a novel framework, combining a range of biopsychosocial markers, including brain structure, cognition, and clinical markers, into higher-level fingerprints, capable of capturing intra-illness heterogeneity and inter-illness overlap. Methods: A multivariate framework was implemented to identify individualised patterns of brain structure, cognition and clinical markers based on affinity to other participants in the database. First, individual-level affinity scores defined a neighbourhood for each participant across each measure based on variable-specific hop sizes. Next, diagnostic verification and classification algorithms were implemented based on multivariate affinity score profiles. To perform affinity-based classification, data were divided into training and test samples, and 5-fold nested cross-validation was performed on the training data. Affinity-based classification was compared to weighted K-nearest neighbours (KNN) classification. K-means clustering was used to create clusters based on multivariate affinity score profiles. The framework was applied to the Australian Schizophrenia Research Bank (ASRB) dataset. Results: Individualised affinity scores provided a fingerprint of brain structure, cognition, and clinical markers, which described the affinity of an individual to the representative groups in the dataset Diagnostic verification capability was moderate to high depending on the choice of multivariate affinity metric. Affinity score-based classification achieved a high degree of accuracy in the training, nested cross-validation and prediction steps, and outperformed KNN classification in the training and test datasets. Conclusion: Affinity scores demonstrate utility in two keys ways: (1) Early and accurate diagnosis of neuropsychiatric disorders, whereby an individual can be grouped within a diagnostic category/ies that best matches their fingerprint, and (2) identification of biopsychosocial factors that most strongly characterise individuals/disorders, and which may be most amenable to intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468749" rel="alternate" title="Affinity Scores: An Individual-centric Fingerprinting Framework for Neuropsychiatric Disorders (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469401</id><title>The Contributions of Eye Gaze Fixations and Target-Lure Similarity to Behavioral and fMRI Indices of Pattern Separation and Pattern Completion (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054209+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel K Bjornn</name></author><author><name>Julie Van</name></author><author><name>Brock Kirwan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pattern separation and pattern completion are generally studied in humans using mnemonic discrimination tasks such as the Mnemonic Similarity Task (MST) where participants identify similar lures and repeated items from a series of images. Failures to correctly discriminate lures are thought to reflect a failure of pattern separation and a propensity toward pattern completion. Recent research has challenged this perspective, suggesting that poor encoding rather than pattern completion accounts for the occurrence of false alarm responses to similar lures. In two experiments, participants completed a continuous recognition task version of the MST while eye movement (Experiment 1 and 2) and fMRI data (Experiment 2) were collected. While we replicated the result that fixation counts at study predicted accuracy on lure trials, we found that target-lure similarity was a much stronger predictor of accuracy on lure trials across both experiments. Lastly, we found that fMRI activation changes in the hippocampus were significantly correlated with the number of fixations at study for correct but not incorrect mnemonic discrimination judgments when controlling for target-lure similarity. Our findings indicate that while eye movements during encoding predict subsequent hippocampal activation changes, mnemonic discrimination performance is better described by pattern separation and pattern completion processes that are influenced by target-lure similarity than simply poor encoding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.20.469401" rel="alternate" title="The Contributions of Eye Gaze Fixations and Target-Lure Similarity to Behavioral and fMRI Indices of Pattern Separation and Pattern Completion (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469104</id><title>Effortless integration of probabilistic visual input (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054337+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrey Chetverikov</name></author><author><name>Árni Kristjánsson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prominent theories of perception suggest that the brain builds probabilistic models of the world, assessing the statistics of the visual input to inform this construction. However, the evidence for this idea is often based on simple impoverished stimuli, and the results have often been discarded as an illusion reflecting simple "summary statistics" of visual inputs. Here we show that the visual system represents probabilistic distributions of complex heterogeneous stimuli. Importantly, we show how these statistical representations are integrated with representations of other features and bound to locations, and can therefore serve as building blocks for object and scene processing. We uncover the organization of these representations at different spatial scales by showing how expectations for incoming features are biased by neighboring locations. We also show that there is not only a bias, but also a skew in the representations, arguing against accounts positing that probabilistic representations are discarded in favor of simplified summary statistics (e.g., mean and variance). In sum, our results reveal detailed probabilistic encoding of stimulus distributions, representations that are bound with other features and to particular locations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469104" rel="alternate" title="Effortless integration of probabilistic visual input (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469307</id><title>Constructing threat probability, fear behaviour, and aversive prediction error in the brainstem. (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054457+00:00</updated><author><name>Jasmin Strickland</name></author><author><name>Michael McDannald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When faced with potential threat we must estimate its probability, respond advantageously, and leverage experience to update future estimates. Threat estimates are the proposed domain of the forebrain, while behaviour is elicited by the brainstem. Yet, the brainstem is also a source of prediction error, a learning signal to acquire and update threat estimates. Neuropixels probes allowed us to record single-unit activity across a 21-region brainstem axis during probabilistic fear discrimination. Against a backdrop of widespread threat probability and behaviour signaling, a dorsally-based brainstem network rapidly signaled threat probability. Remapping of neuronal function following shock outcome gave rise to brainstem networks signaling prediction error on multiple timescales. The results reveal construction of threat probability, behaviour, and prediction error along a single brainstem axis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.469307" rel="alternate" title="Constructing threat probability, fear behaviour, and aversive prediction error in the brainstem. (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469134</id><title>Distinct neurocognitive bases for social trait judgments of faces in autism spectrum disorder (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054575+00:00</updated><author><name>Hongbo Yu</name></author><author><name>Runnan Cao</name></author><author><name>Chujun Lin</name></author><author><name>Shuo Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is characterized by difficulties in social processes, interactions, and communication. Yet, the neurocognitive bases underlying these difficulties are unclear. Here, we triangulated the trans-diagnostic approach to personality, social trait judgments of faces, and neurophysiology to investigate (1) the relative position of autistic traits in a comprehensive social-affective personality space and (2) the distinct associations between the social-affective personality dimensions and social trait judgment from faces in individuals with ASD and neurotypical individuals. We collected personality and facial judgment data from a large sample of online participants (N = 89 self-identified ASD; N = 308 neurotypical controls). Factor analysis with 33 sub-scales of 10 social-affective personality questionnaires identified a 4-dimensional personality space. This analysis revealed that ASD and control participants did not differ significantly along the personality dimensions of empathy and prosociality, antisociality, or social agreeableness. However, the associations between these dimensions and judgments of facial trustworthiness and warmth differed across groups. Neurophysiological data also indicated that ASD and control participants might rely on distinct neuronal representations for judging trustworthiness and warmth from faces. These results suggest that the atypical association between social-affective personality and social trait judgment from faces may contribute to the social and affective difficulties associated with ASD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469134" rel="alternate" title="Distinct neurocognitive bases for social trait judgments of faces in autism spectrum disorder (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469119</id><title>An insight into new glycotherapeutic in glial inflammation: Understanding the role of glycosylation from acute to chronic phase of inflammation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054713+00:00</updated><author><name>Vaibhav Patil</name></author><author><name>Raghvendra Bohara</name></author><author><name>Carla Winter</name></author><author><name>Michelle Kilcoyne</name></author><author><name>Siobhan McMahon</name></author><author><name>Abhay Pandit</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glycosylation plays a critical role during inflammation and glial scar formation upon spinal cord injury (SCI) disease progression. Astrocytes and microglia are involved in this cascade to modulate the inflammation and tissue remodelling from acute to chronic phases. Therefore, understating the glycan changes in these glial cells is paramount. Herein a lectin microarray was undertaken using a cytokine-driven inflammatory MGC model, revealing considerable differential glycosylation from the acute to the chronic phase in a cytokine-combination generated inflamed MGC model. It was found that several N- and O-linked glycans associated with glia during SCI were differentially regulated. Pearson's correlation hierarchical clustering showed that groups were separated into several clusters, illustrating the heterogenicity among the control, cytokine combination, and LPS treated groups and the day on which treatment was given. Control and LPS treatments were observed to be in dense clusters. This was further confirmed with lectin immunostaining in which GalNAc, GlcNAc, mannose, fucose and sialic acid-binding residues were detected in astrocytes and microglia. However, this modification (upregulation of sialic acid expression) was inhibited by the sialyltransferase inhibitor which indeed modulates the mitochondrial functions. The present study is the first functional investigation of glycosylation modulation in a MGC (MGC) model which elucidates the role of the glycome in neuroinflammation and identified potential therapeutic targets for future glycol- therapeutics in neuroinflammation&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469119" rel="alternate" title="An insight into new glycotherapeutic in glial inflammation: Understanding the role of glycosylation from acute to chronic phase of inflammation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468950</id><title>Differential replay for reward and punishment paths predicts approach and avoidance (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054840+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica McFadyen</name></author><author><name>Yunzhe Liu</name></author><author><name>Raymond J Dolan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Planning is thought to involve neural replay, where states relevant to a task goal are rapidly reactivated in sequence. It remains unclear if, during planning, replay of a path relates to an actual prospective choice. Here, using magnetoencephalography (MEG), we studied participants while they planned to either approach or avoid an uncertain environment that contained paths leading to reward and to punishment. We show significant planning-related forward sequential replay with state-to-state transitions in the range of 20 to 90 ms. Replay of rewarding paths was boosted prior to a decision to avoid, and attenuated prior to a decision to approach. Crucially, a trial-by-trial bias in replaying punishing paths predicted an irrational choice to approach when a prospective environment was more risky, an effect that was particularly marked in more anxious participants. The findings reveal a coupling between the content of forwards replay and rational choice behaviour, such that replay prioritises an online representation of potential reward.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.468950" rel="alternate" title="Differential replay for reward and punishment paths predicts approach and avoidance (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468122</id><title>The output of interneurons in the primary visual cortex is best reflected by pre-synaptic activity, not somatic activity (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.054951+00:00</updated><author><name>Rozan Vroman</name></author><author><name>Lawrie S McKay</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in 2-photon calcium-imaging in awake mice have made it possible to study the effect of different behavioural states on cortical circuitry. Many studies assume that somatic activity can be used as a measure for neuronal output. We set out to test the validity of this assumption by comparing somatic activity with the pre-synaptic activity of VIP (Vasoactive intestinal peptide)- and SST (Somatostatin)-positive interneurons in layer 2/3 of the primary visual cortex (V1). We used mice expressing genetically encoded calcium indicators in VIP/SST-interneurons across the whole cell (VIP/SST:GCaMP6f) or confined to pre-synapses (VIP/SST:SyGCaMP5). Mice were exposed to a full-field visual stimulation protocol consisting of 60-second-long presentations of moving Gabor gratings (0.04 cpd, 2 Hz) alternated by 30 seconds of grey screen. During imaging, mice were placed on an air-suspended Styrofoam ball, allowing them to run voluntarily. We compared neural activity during three 4-second time-windows: Before visual stimulation (−4 to 0 sec), during the initial onset (1 to 5 sec) and at the end of the stimulation (56 to 60 sec.). These were further compared while the mice were stationary and while they were voluntarily locomoting. Unlike VIP-somas, VIP-pre-synapses showed strong suppressive responses to the visual stimulus. Furthermore, VIP-somas were positively correlated with locomotion, whereas in VIP-synapses we observed a split between positive and negative correlations. In addition, a similar but weaker distinction was found between SST-somas and pre-synapses. The excitatory effect of locomotion in VIP-somas increased over the course of the visual stimulus but this property was only shared with the positively correlated VIP-pre-synapses. The remaining negatively correlated pre-synapses showed no relation to the overall activity of the Soma. Our results suggest that when making statements about the involvement of interneurons in V1 layer 2/3 circuitry it is crucial to measure from synaptic terminals as well as from somas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.468122" rel="alternate" title="The output of interneurons in the primary visual cortex is best reflected by pre-synaptic activity, not somatic activity (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468309</id><title>Repressing PTBP1 is incapable to convert reactive astrocytes to dopaminergic neurons in a mouse model of Parkinson’s disease (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.055472+00:00</updated><author><name>Weizhao Chen</name></author><author><name>Qiongping Zheng</name></author><author><name>Qiaoying Huang</name></author><author><name>Shanshan Ma</name></author><author><name>Mingtao Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lineage reprograming of resident glia cells to induced dopaminergic neurons (iDAns) holds attractive prospect for cell-replacement therapy of Parkinson’s disease (PD). Recently, whether repressing polypyrimidine tract binding protein 1 (PTBP1) could truly achieve efficient astrocyte-to-iDAn conversion in substantia nigra and striatum aroused widespread controversy. Although reporter positive iDAns were observed by two groups after delivering adeno-associated virus (AAV) expressing a reporter with shRNA or Crispr-CasRx to repress astroglial PTBP1, the possibility of AAV leaking into endogenous DAns could not be excluded without using a reliable lineage tracing method. By adopting stringent lineage tracing strategy, two other studies showed that neither knockdown nor genetic deletion of quiescent astroglial PTBP1 fails to obtain iDAns under physiological condition. However, the role of reactive astrocyte might be underestimated since upon brain injury, reactive astrocyte could acquire certain stem cell hallmarks which may facilitate the lineage conversion process. Therefore, whether reactive astrocytes could be genuinely converted to DAns after PTBP1 repression in a PD model needs further validation. In this study, we used &lt;italic&gt;Aldh1l1-CreER&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;T2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;-mediated specific astrocyte-lineage tracing method to investigate whether reactive astrocytes could be converted to DAns in the 6-OHDA PD model. However, we found that no astrocyte-originated DAn was generated after effective knockdown of astroglial PTBP1 either in the substantia nigra or in the striatum, while AAV “leakage” to nearby neurons was observed. Our results further confirmed that repressing PTBP1 is unable to convert astrocytes to DAns no matter in physiological or PD-related pathological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphic abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="468309v2_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;AAV-sh&lt;italic&gt;Ptbp1&lt;/italic&gt; rapidly and efficiently induces viral-reporter-labeled DAns in mouse brain under physiological condition&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viral-reporter-positive DAns are not originated from PTBP1 repressed and lineage traced reactive astrocytes in a mouse PD model&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468309" rel="alternate" title="Repressing PTBP1 is incapable to convert reactive astrocytes to dopaminergic neurons in a mouse model of Parkinson’s disease (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468679</id><title>Essential functions of MLL1 and MLL2 in retinal development and cone cell maintenance (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.055634+00:00</updated><author><name>Chi Sun</name></author><author><name>Xiaodong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Philip A. Ruzycki</name></author><author><name>Shiming Chen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MLL1 (KMT2A) and MLL2 (KMT2B) are homologous members of the mixed-lineage leukemia (MLL) family of histone methyltransferases involved in epigenomic transcriptional regulation. Their sequence variants have been associated with neurological and psychological disorders, but little is known about their roles and mechanism of action in CNS development. Using mouse retina as a model, we previously reported MLL1’s role in retinal neurogenesis and horizontal cell maintenance. Here we determine roles of MLL2 and MLL1/MLL2 together in retinal development using conditional knockout (CKO) mice. Deleting &lt;italic&gt;Mll2&lt;/italic&gt; from Chx10&lt;italic&gt;+&lt;/italic&gt; retinal progenitors resulted in a similar phenotype as &lt;italic&gt;Mll1 CKO&lt;/italic&gt;, but removal of both alleles produced much more severe deficits than each single &lt;italic&gt;CKO&lt;/italic&gt;: 1-month &lt;italic&gt;double CKO&lt;/italic&gt; mutants displayed null light responses in electroretinogram; thin retinal layers, including shorter photoreceptor outer segments with impaired phototransduction gene expression; and reduced numbers of M-cones, horizontal and amacrine neurons, followed by fast retinal degeneration. Despite moderately reduced progenitor cell proliferation at P0, the neurogenic capacity was largely maintained in &lt;italic&gt;double CKO&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. However, upregulated apoptosis and reactive gliosis were detected during postnatal retinal development. Finally, the removal of both MLLs in fated rods produced a normal phenotype, but the CKO in M-cones impaired M-cone function and survival, indicating both cell non-autonomous and autonomous mechanisms. Altogether, our results suggest that MLL1/MLL2 play redundant roles in maintaining specific retinal neurons after cell fate specification and are essential for establishing functional neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468679" rel="alternate" title="Essential functions of MLL1 and MLL2 in retinal development and cone cell maintenance (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469035</id><title>The influence of somatosensory and auditory evoked potentials on concurrent transcranial-magnetic stimulation electroencephalography recordings (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.055760+00:00</updated><author><name>Nahian S Chowdhury</name></author><author><name>Nigel C Rogasch</name></author><author><name>Alan Chiang</name></author><author><name>Samantha K Millard</name></author><author><name>Patrick Skippen</name></author><author><name>Wei-Ju Chang</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna Bilska</name></author><author><name>Emily Si</name></author><author><name>David A Seminowicz</name></author><author><name>Siobhan M Schabrun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) evoked potentials (TEPs) can be used to index cortical excitability. However, it remains unclear to what extent TEPs reflect somatosensory and auditory-evoked potentials which arise from the scalp sensation and click of the TMS coil, as opposed to transcranial stimulation of cortical circuits. Objectives: The present study had two aims; a) to determine the extent to which sensory potentials contaminate TEPs using a spatially matched sham condition, and b) to determine whether sensory potentials reflect auditory or somatosensory potentials alone, or a combination of the two. Methods: Twenty healthy participants received active or sham stimulation, with the latter consisting of the click of a sham coil combined with scalp electrical stimulation. Earplugs/headphones were used to suppress the TMS click noise. Two additional control conditions i) electrical stimulation alone and ii) auditory stimulation alone were included in a subset of 13 participants. Results: Signals from active and sham stimulation were correlated in spatial and temporal domains, especially &amp;gt;70ms post-stimulation. Relative to auditory or electrical stimulation alone, combined (sham) stimulation resulted in a) larger evoked responses b) stronger correlations with active stimulation and c) a signal that could not be explained by the linear sum of electrical and auditory stimulation alone. Conclusions: Sensory potentials can confound data interpretations of TEPs at timepoints &amp;gt;70ms post-TMS, while earlier timepoints appear reflective of cortical excitability. Furthermore, contamination of TEPs cannot be explained by auditory or somatosensory potentials alone, but instead reflects a non-linear interaction between both sources. Future studies may benefit from controlling for sensory contamination using sham conditions that are spatially matched to active TMS, and which consist of combined auditory and somatosensory stimulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469035" rel="alternate" title="The influence of somatosensory and auditory evoked potentials on concurrent transcranial-magnetic stimulation electroencephalography recordings (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469381</id><title>Stress deceleration theory: chronic adolescent stress exposure results in decelerated neurobehavioral maturation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.055918+00:00</updated><author><name>Kshitij Jadhav</name></author><author><name>Alexander Hoffman</name></author><author><name>Morgane Burgisser</name></author><author><name>Clara Rosetti</name></author><author><name>Lea Aeschlimann</name></author><author><name>Carl R Lupica</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Boutrel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Normative development in adolescence indicates that the prefrontal cortex is still under development thereby unable to exert efficient top-down inhibitory control on subcortical regions such as the basolateral amygdala and the nucleus accumbens. This imbalance in the developmental trajectory between cortical and subcortical regions is implicated in expression of the prototypical impulsive, compulsive, reward seeking and risk-taking adolescent behavior. Here we demonstrate that a chronic mild unpredictable stress procedure during adolescence in male Wistar rats arrests the normal behavioral maturation such that they continue to express adolescent-like impulsive, hyperactive, and compulsive behaviors into late adulthood. This arrest in behavioral maturation is associated with the hypoexcitability of prelimbic cortex (PLC) pyramidal neurons and reduced PLC-mediated synaptic glutamatergic control of BLA and nucleus accumbens core (NAcC) neurons that lasts late into adulthood. At the same time stress exposure in adolescence results in the hyperexcitability of the BLA pyramidal neurons sending stronger glutamatergic projections to the NAcC. Chemogenetic reversal of the PLC hypoexcitability decreased compulsivity and improved the expression of goal-directed behavior in rats exposed to stress during adolescence, suggesting a causal role for PLC hypoexcitability in this stress-induced arrested behavioral development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469381" rel="alternate" title="Stress deceleration theory: chronic adolescent stress exposure results in decelerated neurobehavioral maturation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469021</id><title>Hidden temporal structure of the ongoing task impacts detection strategy and is reflected in pupillary dynamics (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056216+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer Lawlor</name></author><author><name>Agnes Zagala</name></author><author><name>Sara Jamali</name></author><author><name>Yves Boubenec</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Estimating temporal regularities in incoming sensory inputs supports optimal decisions in noisy environments. In particular, inferred temporal structure can ease the detection of likely target events. Here we postulated that timely urgency signals can adapt subjects' decision-making to the ongoing task temporal structure, possibly through neuromodulatory tone. To test this hypothesis, we used an auditory change detection task in which targets followed a block-based temporal contingency, unbeknownst to participants. False alarm occurrences were driven by the distribution of target timings, indicating that participants adapted their behavior to the ongoing temporal structure. Task-evoked pupillary responses were larger for blocks with earliest target timings, and correlated with individual subjects' behavioral adaptation. Individual pupil responses matched an urgency signal extracted from a decision model fitted to behavior. This work demonstrates that internal temporal expectation can be tracked through pupillary dynamics, suggesting a role of neuromodulatory systems in context-dependent modulation of decision variable dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.469021" rel="alternate" title="Hidden temporal structure of the ongoing task impacts detection strategy and is reflected in pupillary dynamics (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468806</id><title>Trajectory of rich club properties in structural brain networks (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056349+00:00</updated><author><name>Levin Riedel</name></author><author><name>Martijn P van den Heuvel</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Markett</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many organizational principles of structural brain networks are established before birth and undergo considerable developmental changes afterwards. These include the topologically central hub regions and a densely connected rich club. While several studies have mapped developmental trajectories of brain connectivity and brain network organization across childhood and adolescence, comparatively little is known about subsequent development over the course of the lifespan. Here, we present a cross-sectional analysis of structural brain network development in N = 8,066 participants aged 5 to 80 years. Across all brain regions, structural connectivity strength followed an ′inverted-U′-shaped trajectory with vertex in the early 30s. Connectivity strength of hub regions showed a similar trajectory and the identity of hub regions remained stable across all age groups. While connectivity strength declined with advancing age, the organization of hub regions into a rich club did not only remain intact but became more pronounced, presumingly through a selected sparing of relevant connections from age-related connectivity loss. The stability of rich club organization in the face of overall age-related decline is consistent with a ′first come, last served′ model of neurodevelopment, where the first principles to develop are the last to decline with age. Rich club organization has been shown to be highly beneficial for communicability and higher cognition. A resilient rich club might thus be protective of a functional loss in late adulthood and represent a neural reserve to sustain cognitive functioning in the aging brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468806" rel="alternate" title="Trajectory of rich club properties in structural brain networks (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469102</id><title>Single nucleus RNA-seq in the hippocampus of a Down syndrome mouse model reveals new key players in memory (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056468+00:00</updated><author><name>Cesar Sierra</name></author><author><name>Ilario De Toma</name></author><author><name>Mara Dierssen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Down syndrome (DS) is the most common genetic cause of intellectual disability. Even though great advances in the last decades have allowed better delineation of its pathogenetic mechanisms, its cellular and molecular bases are still poorly understood. To evaluate the consequences of chromosome aneuploidy on the hippocampus, we analyzed single-nucleus transcriptional profiles of the DS mouse model Ts65Dn. Our data revealed abnormal cell composition specifically of the Ts65Dn dentate gyrus and of specific subtypes of interneurons, without major changes in CA1 or CA3. We found that trisomy results in a highly cell-type specific global alteration of the transcriptome and detected previously undefined differentially expressed genes in specific neuronal populations. We identified the long-non-coding gene Snhg11 to be specifically downregulated in the trisomic dentate gyrus and provide evidence for its involvement in hippocampal-dependent cognitive phenotypes, possibly contributed by impaired adult neurogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469102" rel="alternate" title="Single nucleus RNA-seq in the hippocampus of a Down syndrome mouse model reveals new key players in memory (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468788</id><title>The sleep EEG envelope: a novel, neuronal firing-based human biomarker (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056585+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter Przemyslaw Ujma</name></author><author><name>Martin Dresler</name></author><author><name>Peter Simor</name></author><author><name>Daniel Fabo</name></author><author><name>Istvan Ulbert</name></author><author><name>Lorand Eross</name></author><author><name>Robert Bodizs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep EEG reflects instantaneous voltage differences relative to a reference, while its spectrum reflects the degree to which it is comprised of oscillations at various frequencies. In contrast, the envelope of the sleep EEG reflects the instantaneous amplitude of oscillations at specific frequencies, and its spectrum reflects the rhythmicity of the occurrence of these oscillations. The ordinary sleep EEG and its spectrum have been extensively studied and its individual stability and relationship to various demographic characteristics, psychological traits and pathologies is well known. In contrast, the envelope spectrum has not been extensively studied before. In two studies, we explored the generating mechanisms and utility of studying the envelope of the sleep EEG. First, we used human invasive data from cortex-penetrating microelectrodes and subdural grids to demonstrate that the sleep EEG envelope spectrum reflects local neuronal firing. Second, we used a large database of healthy volunteers to demonstrate that the scalp EEG envelope spectrum is highly stable within individuals, especially in NREM sleep, and that it is affected by age and sex. Multivariate models based on a learning algorithm could predict both age (r=0.6) and sex (r=0.5) with considerable accuracy from the EEG envelope spectrum. With age, oscillations characteristically shifted from a 4-5 second rhythm to higher rhythms. The envelope spectrum was not associated with general cognitive ability (IQ). Our results demonstrate that the sleep envelope spectrum is a promising, neuronal firing-based biomarker of various demographic and disease-related phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468788" rel="alternate" title="The sleep EEG envelope: a novel, neuronal firing-based human biomarker (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468841</id><title>Stimulus-induced narrow-band gamma oscillations in humans can be recorded using open-hardware low-cost EEG amplifier (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056722+00:00</updated><author><name>Srividya Pattisapu</name></author><author><name>Supratim Ray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stimulus-induced narrow-band gamma oscillations (30-70 Hz) in human electro - encephalograph (EEG) have been linked to attentional and memory mechanisms and are abnormal in mental health conditions such as autism, schizophrenia and Alzheimer's Disease. This suggests that gamma oscillations could be valuable both as a research tool and an inexpensive, non-invasive biomarker for disease evaluation. However, since the absolute power in EEG decreases rapidly with increasing frequency following a "1/f" power law, and the gamma band includes line noise frequency, these oscillations are highly susceptible to instrument noise. Previous studies that recorded stimulus-induced gamma oscillations used expensive research-grade EEG amplifiers to address this issue. While low-cost EEG amplifiers have become popular in Brain Computer Interface applications that mainly rely on low-frequency oscillations (&amp;lt;30 Hz) or steady-state-visually-evoked-potentials, whether they can also be used to measure stimulus-induced gamma oscillations is unknown. We recorded EEG signals using a low-cost, open-source amplifier (OpenBCI) and a traditional, research-grade amplifier (Brain Products GmbH) in male (N = 6) and female (N = 5) subjects (22-29 years) while they viewed full-screen static gratings that are known to induce gamma oscillations. OpenBCI recordings showed gamma response in almost all the subjects who showed a gamma response in Brain Products recordings, and the spectral and temporal profiles of these responses in alpha (8-13 Hz) and gamma bands were highly correlated between OpenBCI and Brain Products recordings. These results suggest that low-cost amplifiers can potentially be used in stimulus induced gamma response detection, making its research, and application in medicine more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468841" rel="alternate" title="Stimulus-induced narrow-band gamma oscillations in humans can be recorded using open-hardware low-cost EEG amplifier (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469448</id><title>Motor plans under uncertainty reflect a trade-off between maximizing reward and success (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056833+00:00</updated><author><name>Aaron L Wong</name></author><author><name>Audrey L Green</name></author><author><name>Mitchell W Isaacs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When faced with multiple potential movement options, individuals either reach directly to one of the options, or initiate a reach intermediate between the options. It remains unclear why people generate these two types of behaviors. Using the go-before-you-know task (commonly used to study behavior under choice uncertainty), we examined two key questions. First, do these two types of responses reflect distinct movement strategies, or are they simply examples of a more general response to choice uncertainty? If the former, the relative desirability (i.e., weighing the likelihood of successfully hitting the target versus the attainable reward) of the two target options might be computed differently for direct versus intermediate reaches. We showed that indeed, when exogenous reward and success likelihood (i.e., endogenous reward) differ between the two options, direct reaches were more strongly biased by likelihood whereas intermediate movements were more strongly biased by reward. Second, what drives individual differences in how people respond under uncertainty? We found that risk/reward-seeking individuals generated a larger proportion of intermediate reaches and were more sensitive to trial-to-trial changes in reward, suggesting these movements reflect a strategy to maximize reward. In contrast, risk-adverse individuals tended to generate more direct reaches in an attempt to maximize success. Together, these findings suggest that when faced with choice uncertainty, individuals adopt movement strategies consistent with their risk/reward-seeking tendency, preferentially biasing behavior toward exogenous rewards or endogenous success and consequently modulating the relative desirability of the available options.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469448" rel="alternate" title="Motor plans under uncertainty reflect a trade-off between maximizing reward and success (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469446</id><title>Transient inhibition to light explains stronger V1 responses to dark stimuli (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.056946+00:00</updated><author><name>David St-Amand</name></author><author><name>Curtis L Baker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurons in the primary visual cortex (V1) receive excitation and inhibition from two different pathways processing lightness (ON) and darkness (OFF). V1 neurons overall respond more strongly to dark than light stimuli (Yeh, Xing and Shapley, 2010; Kremkow et al., 2014), consistent with a preponderance of darker regions in natural images (Ratliff et al., 2010), as well as human psychophysics (Buchner &amp;amp; Baumgartner, 2007). However, it has been unclear whether this "dark-dominance" is due to more excitation from the OFF pathway (Jin et al., 2008) or more inhibition from the ON pathway (Taylor et al., 2018). To understand the mechanisms behind dark-dominance, we record electrophysiological responses of individual simple-type V1 neurons to natural image stimuli and then train biologically inspired convolutional neural networks to predict the neuronal responses. Analyzing a sample of 74 neurons (in anesthetized, paralyzed cats) has revealed their responses to be more driven by dark than light stimuli, consistent with previous investigations (Yeh et al., 2010; Kremkow et al., 2013). We show this asymmetry to be predominantly due to slower inhibition to dark stimuli rather than by stronger excitation from the thalamocortical OFF pathway. Consistent with dark-dominant neurons having faster responses than light-dominant neurons (Komban et al., 2014), we find dark-dominance to solely occur in the early latencies of neuronal responses. Neurons that are strongly dark-dominated also tend to be less orientation selective. This novel approach gives us new insight into the dark-dominance phenomenon and provides an avenue to address new questions about excitatory and inhibitory integration in cortical neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469446" rel="alternate" title="Transient inhibition to light explains stronger V1 responses to dark stimuli (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>