<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.260990+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472950</id><title>Assembly of recombinant tau into filaments identical to those of Alzheimer's disease and chronic traumatic encephalopathy (130 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.261353+00:00</updated><author><name>Sofia Lövestam</name></author><author><name>Fujiet Adrian Koh</name></author><author><name>Bart van Knippenberg</name></author><author><name>Abhay Kotecha</name></author><author><name>Alexey G Murzin</name></author><author><name>Michel Goedert</name></author><author><name>Sjors Scheres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abundant filamentous inclusions of tau are characteristic of more than 20 neurodegenerative diseases that are collectively termed tauopathies. Electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM) structures of tau amyloid filaments from human brain revealed that different tau folds characterise many different diseases. A lack of laboratory-based model systems to generate these structures has hampered efforts to uncover the molecular mechanisms that underlie tauopathies. Here, we report in vitro assembly conditions with recombinant tau that replicate the structures of filaments from both Alzheimer's disease (AD) and chronic traumatic encephalopathy (CTE), as determined by cryo-EM. Our results suggest that post-translational modifications of tau modulate filament assembly, and that previously observed additional densities in AD and CTE filaments may arise from the presence of inorganic salts, like phosphates and sodium chloride. In vitro assembly of tau into disease-relevant filaments will facilitate studies to determine their roles in different diseases, as well as the development of compounds that specifically bind to these structures or prevent their formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472950" rel="alternate" title="Assembly of recombinant tau into filaments identical to those of Alzheimer's disease and chronic traumatic encephalopathy (130 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472392</id><title>Characterizing the Behavioral and Neuroendocrine Features of Susceptibility and Resilience to Social Stress (52 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.261547+00:00</updated><author><name>Dalia Murra</name></author><author><name>Kathryn L. Hilde</name></author><author><name>Anne Fitzpatrick</name></author><author><name>Pamela M. Maras</name></author><author><name>Stanley J. Watson</name></author><author><name>Huda Akil</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Evaluating and coping with stressful social events as they unfold is a critical strategy in overcoming them without long-lasting detrimental effects. Individuals display a wide range of responses to stress, which can manifest in a variety of outcomes for the brain as well as subsequent behavior. Chronic Social Defeat Stress (CSDS) in mice has been widely used to model individual variation following a social stressor. Following a course of repeated intermittent psychological and physical stress, mice diverge into separate populations of social reactivity: resilient (socially interactive) and susceptible (socially avoidant) animals. A rich body of work reveals distinct neurobiological and behavioral consequences of this experience that map onto the resilient and susceptible groups. However, the range of factors that emerge over the course of defeat have not been fully described. Therefore, in the current study, we focused on characterizing behavioral, physiological, and neuroendocrine profiles of mice in three separate phases: before, during, and following CSDS. We found that following CSDS, traditional read-outs of anxiety-like and depression-like behaviors do not map on to the resilient and susceptible groups. By contrast, behavioral coping strategies used during the initial social stress encounter better predict which mice will eventually become resilient or susceptible. In particular, mice that will emerge as susceptible display greater escape behavior on Day 1 of social defeat than those that will emerge as resilient, indicating early differences in coping mechanisms used between the two groups. We further show that the social avoidance phenotype in susceptible mice is specific to the aggressor strain and does not generalize to conspecifics or other strains, indicating that there may be features of threat discrimination that are specific to the susceptible mice. Our findings suggest that there are costs and benefits to both the resilient and susceptible outcomes, reflected in their ability to cope and adapt to the social stressor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472392" rel="alternate" title="Characterizing the Behavioral and Neuroendocrine Features of Susceptibility and Resilience to Social Stress (52 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472691</id><title>A reusable benchmark of brain-age prediction from M/EEG resting-state signals (50 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.261687+00:00</updated><author><name>Denis A Engemann</name></author><author><name>Apolline Mellot</name></author><author><name>Richard Hoechenberger</name></author><author><name>Hubert Banville</name></author><author><name>David Sabbagh</name></author><author><name>Lukas Gemein</name></author><author><name>Tonio Ball</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Gramfort</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Population-level modeling can define quantitative measures of individual aging by applying machine learning to large volumes of brain images. These measures of brain age, obtained from the general population, helped characterize disease severity in neurological populations, improving estimates of diagnosis or prognosis. Magnetoencephalography (MEG) and Electroencephalography (EEG) have the potential to further generalize this approach towards prevention and public health by enabling assessments of brain health at large scales in socioeconomically diverse environments. However, more research is needed to define methods that can handle the complexity and diversity of M/EEG signals across diverse real-world contexts. To catalyse this effort, here we propose reusable benchmarks of competing machine learning approaches for brain age modeling. We benchmarked popular classical machine learning pipelines and deep learning architectures previously used for pathology decoding or brain age estimation in 4 international M/EEG cohorts from diverse countries and cultural contexts, including recordings from more than 2500 participants. Our benchmarks were built on top of the M/EEG adaptations of the BIDS standard, providing tools that can be applied with minimal modification on any M/EEG dataset provided in the BIDS format. Our results suggest that, regardless of whether classical machine learning or deep learning was used, the highest performance was reached by pipelines and architectures involving spatially aware representations of the M/EEG signals, leading to R^2 scores between 0.60-0.71. Hand-crafted features paired with random forest regression provided robust benchmarks even in situations in which other approaches failed. Taken together, this set of benchmarks, accompanied by open-source software and high-level Python scripts, can serve as a starting point and quantitative reference for future efforts at developing M/EEG-based measures of brain aging. The generality of the approach renders this benchmark reusable for other related objectives such as modeling specific cognitive variables or clinical endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472691" rel="alternate" title="A reusable benchmark of brain-age prediction from M/EEG resting-state signals (50 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472009</id><title>A somatosensory computation that unifies limbs and tools (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.261873+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke E. Miller</name></author><author><name>Cécile Fabio</name></author><author><name>Frédérique de Vignemont</name></author><author><name>Alice Roy</name></author><author><name>W. Pieter Medendorp</name></author><author><name>Alessandro Farnè</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is often claimed that tools are embodied by the user, but whether the brain actually repurposes its body-based computations to perform similar tasks with tools is not known. A fundamental body-based computation used by the somatosensory system is &lt;italic&gt;trilateration&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, the location of touch on a limb is computed by integrating estimates of the distance between sensory input and its boundaries (e.g., elbow and wrist of the forearm). As evidence of this computational mechanism, tactile localization on a limb is most precise near its boundaries and lowest in the middle. If the brain repurposes trilateration to localize touch on a tool, we should observe this computational signature in behavior. In a large sample of participants, we indeed found that localizing touch on a tool produced the signature of trilateration, with highest precision close to the base and tip of the tool. A computational model of trilateration provided a good fit to the observed localization behavior. Importantly, model selection demonstrated that trilateration better explained each participant’s behavior than an alternative model of localization. These results have important implications for how trilateration may be implemented by somatosensory neural populations. In sum, the present study suggests that tools are indeed embodied at a computational level, repurposing a fundamental spatial computation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472009" rel="alternate" title="A somatosensory computation that unifies limbs and tools (34 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472746</id><title>Astrocytes in the dorsal vagal complex are not activated by systemic glucoprivation and their chemogenetic activation does not elicit homeostatic glucoregulatory responses in mice (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.262008+00:00</updated><author><name>Alastair J MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Katherine R Pye</name></author><author><name>Craig Beall</name></author><author><name>Kate LJ Ellacott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The dorsal vagal complex (DVC) is a brainstem site regulating diverse aspects of physiology including food intake and blood glucose homeostasis. Astrocytes are purported to play an active role in regulating DVC function and, by extension, physiological parameters. Previous work has demonstrated that DVC astrocytes directly sense hormones that regulate food intake and blood glucose and are critical for their effect. In addition, DVC astrocytes in ex vivo slices respond to low tissue glucose. The response of neurons, including catecholaminergic neurons, to low glucose is conditional on intact astrocyte signalling in slice preparations suggesting astrocytes are possibly the primary sensors of glucose deprivation (glucoprivation). Based on these findings we hypothesised that if DVC astrocytes act as glucoprivation sensors in vivo they would both show a response to systemic glucoprivation and drive physiological responses to restore blood glucose. We found that 2 hours of systemic glucoprivation induced neither FOS nor glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP)-immunoreactivity in DVC astrocytes, specifically those in the nucleus of the solitary tract (NTS). Furthermore, we found that while chemogenetic activation of DVC astrocytes suppressed food intake by reducing both meal size and meal number, this manipulation also suppressed food intake under conditions of glucoprivation. Chemogenetic activation of DVC astrocytes did not increase basal blood glucose nor protect against insulin-induced hypoglycaemia. In male mice chemogenetic DVC astrocyte activation did not alter glucose tolerance, in female mice the initial glucose excursion was reduced, suggesting enhanced glucose absorption. Taken together this suggests that as a whole-population DVC astrocytes do not function as glucoprivation sensors in vivo in mice. Instead, we propose that DVC astrocytes play an indispensable, homeostatic role to maintain the function of glucoregulatory neuronal circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472746" rel="alternate" title="Astrocytes in the dorsal vagal complex are not activated by systemic glucoprivation and their chemogenetic activation does not elicit homeostatic glucoregulatory responses in mice (31 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472377</id><title>An intrinsic endothelial dysfunction causes cerebral small vessel disease (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.262130+00:00</updated><author><name>Sophie Quick</name></author><author><name>Tessa V. Procter</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Moss</name></author><author><name>Angus Lawson</name></author><author><name>Serena Baker</name></author><author><name>Marc Walton</name></author><author><name>Mehreen Mohammad</name></author><author><name>Will Mungall</name></author><author><name>Ami Onishi</name></author><author><name>Zuzanna Tobola</name></author><author><name>Michael Stringer</name></author><author><name>Maurits A. Jansen</name></author><author><name>Antoine Vallatos</name></author><author><name>Ylenia Giarratano</name></author><author><name>Miguel O. Bernabeu</name></author><author><name>Joanna M. Wardlaw</name></author><author><name>Anna C. Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Small Vessel Disease (SVD) is the leading cause of vascular dementia, causes a quarter of strokes, and worsens stroke outcomes(1, 2). The disease is characterised by cerebral small vessel and white matter pathology, but the underlying mechanisms are poorly understood. Classically, the microvascular and tissue damage has been considered secondary to extrinsic factors, such as hypertension, consisting of microvessel stiffening, impaired vasoreactivity and blood-brain barrier dysfunction identified in human sporadic SVDs. However, increasing evidence points to an underlying vulnerability to SVD-related brain damage, not just extrinsic factors. Here, in a novel normotensive transgenic rat model where the phospholipase flippase &lt;italic&gt;Atp11b&lt;/italic&gt; is deleted, we show pathological, imaging and behavioural changes typical of those in human sporadic SVD, but that occur without hypertension. These changes are due to an intrinsic endothelial cell dysfunction, identified in vessels of the brain white matter and the retina, with pathological evidence of vasoreactivity and blood-brain barrier deficits, which precipitate a secondary maturation block in oligodendroglia and myelin disruption around the small vessels. This highlights that an intrinsic endothelial dysfunction may underlie vulnerability to human sporadic SVD, providing alternative therapeutic targets to prevent a major cause of stroke and dementia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472377" rel="alternate" title="An intrinsic endothelial dysfunction causes cerebral small vessel disease (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472475</id><title>Non-rapid eye movement sleep and wake neurophysiology in schizophrenia (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.262324+00:00</updated><author><name>Nataliia Kozhemiako</name></author><author><name>Jun Wang</name></author><author><name>Chenguang Jiang</name></author><author><name>Lei A Wang</name></author><author><name>Guan-chen Gai</name></author><author><name>Kai Zou</name></author><author><name>Zhe Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiao-man Yu</name></author><author><name>Lin Zhou</name></author><author><name>Shen Li</name></author><author><name>Zhenglin Guo</name></author><author><name>Robert G Law</name></author><author><name>James Coleman</name></author><author><name>Dimitrios Mylonas</name></author><author><name>Lu Shen</name></author><author><name>Guoqiang Wang</name></author><author><name>Shuping Tan</name></author><author><name>Shengying Qin</name></author><author><name>Hailiang Huang</name></author><author><name>Michael Murphy</name></author><author><name>Robert Stickgold</name></author><author><name>Dara S Manoach</name></author><author><name>Zhenhe Zhou</name></author><author><name>Wei Zhu</name></author><author><name>Mei-Hua Hall</name></author><author><name>Shaun M Purcell</name></author><author><name>Jen Pan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the potential of objective neurophysiological markers to index thalamocortical function in patients with severe psychiatric illnesses, we comprehensively characterized key NREM sleep parameters across multiple domains, their interdependencies, and their relationship to waking event-related potentials and symptom severity. In 130 schizophrenia (SCZ) patients and controls, we confirmed a marked reduction in sleep spindle density in SCZ and extended these findings to show that only slow spindles predicted symptom severity, and that fast and slow spindle properties were largely uncorrelated. We also describe a novel measure of slow oscillation and spindle interaction that was attenuated in SCZ. The main sleep findings were replicated in a demographically distinct sample, and a joint model, based on multiple NREM components, predicted disease status in the replication cohort. Although also altered in patients, auditory event-related potentials elicited during wake were unrelated to NREM metrics. Consistent with a growing literature implicating thalamocortical dysfunction in SCZ, our characterization identifies independent NREM and wake EEG biomarkers that may index distinct aspects of SCZ pathophysiology and point to multiple neural mechanisms underlying disease heterogeneity. This study lays the groundwork for evaluating these neurophysiological markers, individually or in combination, to guide efforts at treatment and prevention as well as identifying individuals most likely to benefit from specific interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472475" rel="alternate" title="Non-rapid eye movement sleep and wake neurophysiology in schizophrenia (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472555</id><title>Innate heuristics and fast learning support escape route selection in mice (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.262677+00:00</updated><author><name>Federico Claudi</name></author><author><name>Dario Campagner</name></author><author><name>Tiago Branco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When faced with imminent danger, animals must rapidly take defensive actions to reach safety. Mice can react to innately threatening stimuli in less than 250 milliseconds [1] and, in simple environments, use spatial memory to quickly escape to shelter [2,3]. Natural habitats, however, often offer multiple routes to safety which animals must rapidly identify and choose from to maximize the chances of survival [4]. This is challenging because while rodents can learn to navigate complex mazes to obtain rewards [5,6], learning the value of different routes through trial-and-error during escape from threat would likely be deadly. Here we have investigated how mice learn to choose between different escape routes to shelter. By using environments with paths to shelter of varying length and geometry we find that mice prefer options that minimize both path distance and path angle relative to the shelter. This choice strategy is already present during the first threat encounter and after only ~10 minutes of exploration in a novel environment, indicating that route selection does not require experience of escaping. Instead, an innate heuristic is used to assign threat survival value to alternative paths after rapidly learning the spatial environment. This route selection process is flexible and allows quick adaptation to arenas with dynamic geometries. Computational modelling of different classes of reinforcement learning agents shows that the observed behavior can be replicated by model-based agents acting in an environment where the shelter location is rewarding during exploration. These results show that mice combine fast spatial learning with innate heuristics to choose escape routes with the highest survival value. They further suggest that integrating priors acquired through evolution with knowledge learned from experience supports adaptation to changing environments while minimizing the need for trial-and-error when the errors are very costly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472555" rel="alternate" title="Innate heuristics and fast learning support escape route selection in mice (17 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472367</id><title>A neuron, microglia, and astrocyte triple coculture model to study Alzheimer disease (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.262807+00:00</updated><author><name>Celia Luchena</name></author><author><name>Jone Zuazo-Ibarra</name></author><author><name>Jorge Valero</name></author><author><name>Carlos Matute</name></author><author><name>Elena Alberdi</name></author><author><name>Estibaliz Capetillo-Zarate</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glial cells are essential to understand Alzheimer’s disease (AD) progression, given their role in neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration. There is a need for reliable and easy to manipulate models that allow studying the mechanisms behind neuron and glia communication. Currently available models such as cocultures require complex methodologies and/or might not be affordable for all laboratories. With this in mind, we aimed to establish a straightforward &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; setting with neurons and glial cells to study AD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We generated a triple co-culture with neurons, microglia and astrocytes. Immunofluorescence, western blot and ELISA techniques were used to characterize the effects of oligomeric Aβ (oAβ) in this model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We found that, in the triple co-culture, microglia increased the expression of anti-inflammatory markers Arginase I and TGF-β1, and reduced pro-inflammatory iNOS and IL-1β, compared with microglia alone. Astrocytes reduced expression of pro-inflammatory A1 markers AMIGO2 and C3, and displayed a ramified morphology resembling physiological conditions. Lastly, neurons increased post-synaptic markers, and developed more and longer branches than in individual primary cultures. Addition of oAβ in the triple coculture reduced synaptic markers and increased microglial activation, which are hallmarks of AD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, we developed a reliable model, where cells better resemble physiological conditions: microglia are less inflammatory, astrocytes are less reactive and neurons display a more mature morphology than in individual primary cultures. Moreover, we were able to recapitulate Aβ-induced synaptic loss and inflammation. This model emerges as a powerful tool to study neurodegeneration and inflammation in the context of AD and other neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Table of content image&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472367v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Main points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our model, microglia and astrocytes are less reactive, and neurons have a more mature morphology than in primary cultures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;oAβ reduced synaptic markers and increased microglial activation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This triple co-culture is a reliable tool to study neurodegeneration and gliosis &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472367" rel="alternate" title="A neuron, microglia, and astrocyte triple coculture model to study Alzheimer disease (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472559</id><title>Prefrontal top-down projections control context-dependent strategy selection (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263013+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivier Gschwend</name></author><author><name>Tao Yang</name></author><author><name>Daniëlle van de Lisdonk</name></author><author><name>Xian Zhang</name></author><author><name>Radhashree Sharma</name></author><author><name>Bo Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rules governing behavior often vary with behavioral contexts. As a consequence, an action rewarded in one context may be discouraged in another. Animals and humans are capable of switching between behavioral strategies under different contexts and acting adaptively according to the variable rules, a flexibility that is thought to be mediated by the prefrontal cortex (PFC)&lt;sup&gt;1–4&lt;/sup&gt;. However, how the PFC orchestrates context-dependent switch of strategies remains unclear. Here we show that pathway-specific projection neurons in the medial PFC (mPFC) differentially contribute to context-instructed strategy selection. In a decision-making task in which mice have been trained to flexibly switch between a previously established rule and a newly learned rule in a context-dependent manner, the activity of mPFC neurons projecting to the dorsomedial striatum encodes the contexts, and further represents decision strategies conforming to the old and new rules. Moreover, the activity of these neuron is required for context-instructed strategy selection. In contrast, the activity of mPFC neurons projecting to the ventral midline thalamus does not discriminate between the contexts, and represents the old rule even if mice have adopted the new one; furthermore, these neurons act to prevent the strategy switch under the new rule. Our results suggest that the mPFC→striatum pathway promotes flexible strategy selection guided by contexts, whereas the mPFC→thalamus pathway favors fixed strategy selection by preserving old rules. Balanced activity between the two pathways may be critical for adaptive behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472559" rel="alternate" title="Prefrontal top-down projections control context-dependent strategy selection (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472810</id><title>Interferon-ɣ Exposure of Human iPSC-derived Neurons Alters Major Histocompatibility Complex I and Synapsin I Protein Expression (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263150+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam Pavelinek</name></author><author><name>Rugile Matuleviciute</name></author><author><name>Laura Sichlinger</name></author><author><name>Lucia Dutan Polit</name></author><author><name>Nikos Armeniakos</name></author><author><name>Anthony C Vernon</name></author><author><name>Deepak P Srivastava</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human epidemiological data links maternal immune activation during gestation with increased risk for neurodevelopmental disorders including schizophrenia. Animal models of maternal immune activation (MIA) provide causal evidence for this association and strongly suggest that inflammatory cytokines act is a critical link between maternal infection and aberrant offspring brain and behavior development. This includes evidence for reduced synapse formation, consistent with post-mortem and in vivo evidence of reduced synaptic density in schizophrenia. However, to what extent specific cytokines are necessary and sufficient for these effects remains unclear. Using a human cellular model, we recently demonstrated that acute exposure to interferon-ɣ (IFNɣ) recapitulates molecular and cellular phenotypes associated with neurodevelopmental disorders. Here, we extend this work to test whether IFNɣ affects synapse formation in an induced neuron model that generates forebrain glutamatergic neurons. Using immunocytochemistry and quantitative PCR, we demonstrate that acute IFNɣ exposure results in significantly increased MHCI expression at the mRNA and protein level. Furthermore, acute IFNɣ exposure decreases synapsin I protein in neurons but does not affect synaptic gene mRNA levels. Interestingly, complement component 4A (C4A) mRNA is also significantly increased following acute IFNɣ exposure. This study builds on our previous work by showing that IFNɣ-mediated disruption of relevant synaptic proteins can occur at early stages of synapse formation, potentially contributing to neurodevelopmental disorder phenotypes such as schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472810" rel="alternate" title="Interferon-ɣ Exposure of Human iPSC-derived Neurons Alters Major Histocompatibility Complex I and Synapsin I Protein Expression (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473118</id><title>Population coding and oscillatory subspace synchronization integrate context into actions (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263322+00:00</updated><author><name>Jan Weber</name></author><author><name>Anne-Kristin Solbakk</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Blenkmann</name></author><author><name>Anais Llorens</name></author><author><name>Ingrid Funderud</name></author><author><name>Sabine Leske</name></author><author><name>Pal Gunnar Larsson</name></author><author><name>Jugoslav Ivanovic</name></author><author><name>Robert Thomas Knight</name></author><author><name>Tor Endestad</name></author><author><name>Randolph Helfrich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Contextual cues and prior evidence guide human goal-directed behavior. To date, the neurophysiological mechanisms that implement contextual priors to guide subsequent actions remain unclear. Here we demonstrate that increasing behavioral uncertainty introduces a shift from an oscillatory to a continuous processing mode in human prefrontal cortex. At the population level, we found that oscillatory and continuous dynamics reflect dissociable signatures that support distinct aspects of encoding, transmission and execution of context-dependent action plans. We show that prefrontal population activity encodes predictive context and action plans in serially unfolding orthogonal subspaces, while prefrontal-motor theta oscillations synchronize action-encoding population subspaces to mediate the hand-off of action plans. Collectively, our results reveal how two key features of large-scale population activity, namely continuous population trajectories and oscillatory synchrony, operate in concert to guide context-dependent human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473118" rel="alternate" title="Population coding and oscillatory subspace synchronization integrate context into actions (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472322</id><title>Spatially distributed computation in cortical circuits (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263514+00:00</updated><author><name>Sergei Gepshtein</name></author><author><name>Ambarish Pawar</name></author><author><name>Sunwoo Kwon</name></author><author><name>Sergey Savel’ev</name></author><author><name>Thomas D. Albright</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The traditional view of neural computation in the cerebral cortex holds that sensory neurons are specialized, i.e., selective for certain dimensions of sensory stimuli. This view was challenged by evidence of contextual interactions between stimulus dimensions in which a neuron’s response to one dimension strongly depends on other dimensions. Here we use methods of mathematical modeling, psychophysics, and electrophysiology to address shortcomings of the traditional view. Using a model of a generic cortical circuit, we begin with the simple demonstration that cortical responses are always distributed among neurons, forming characteristic waveforms, which we call neural waves. When stimulated by patterned stimuli, circuit responses arise by interference of neural waves. Resulting patterns of interference depend on interaction between stimulus dimensions. Comparison of these modeled responses with responses of biological vision makes it clear that the framework of neural wave interference provides a useful alternative to the standard concept of neural computation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investigating interference of neural waves helps to overcome limitations of the traditional view of cortical computation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472322" rel="alternate" title="Spatially distributed computation in cortical circuits (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472509</id><title>Milking it for all it’s worth: The effects of environmental enrichment on maternal nurturance, lactation quality, and offspring social behavior (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263660+00:00</updated><author><name>Holly DeRosa</name></author><author><name>Hieu Tran</name></author><author><name>Amanda C. Kentner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While alterations in the neonatal environment can have dramatic effects on offspring outcomes, the mechanisms that drive this phenomenon remain unclear. Breastfeeding confers robust benefits to offspring development, including those related to growth, immunity, and neurophysiology. Similarly, improving environmental complexity (i.e., environmental enrichment; EE) contributes developmental advantages to both humans and laboratory animal models. However, the impact of environmental context on maternal care and milk quality has not been thoroughly evaluated, nor are the biological underpinnings of EE on offspring development understood. Here, Sprague-Dawley rats were housed and bred in either EE or standard-housed (SD) conditions. Although EE dams gave birth to a larger number of pups, litters were standardized and cross-fostered across groups on postnatal day (P)1. Maternal milk samples were then collected on P1 (transitional milk phase) and P10 (mature milk phase) for analysis. While EE dams spent less time nursing, postnatal enrichment exposure was associated with heavier offspring bodyweights. Moreover, milk from EE dams had increased triglyceride levels compared to SD dams. Milk from EE mothers also contained a greater microbiome diversity and a significantly higher abundance of bacterial families related to bodyweight and energy metabolism. In addition to changes in lactational quality, we observed sex- and time-dependent effects of EE on offspring social behavior. Specifically, prenatal EE exposure was associated with greater sociability in females, while postnatal EE was associated with greater sociability in male offspring. Together, these results underscore the multidimensional impact of the combined neonatal and maternal environments on offspring development. These data also identify potential deficiencies in the quality of the “gold standard” laboratory housing condition and its impact on the welfare and design of translationally relevant animal models in biomedical research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472509" rel="alternate" title="Milking it for all it’s worth: The effects of environmental enrichment on maternal nurturance, lactation quality, and offspring social behavior (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472983</id><title>Low Frequency Oscillations drive EEG's complexity changes during wakefulness and sleep (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263776+00:00</updated><author><name>Joaquin Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Diego M. Mateos</name></author><author><name>Matias Cavelli</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Mondino</name></author><author><name>Claudia Pascovich</name></author><author><name>Pablo Torterolo</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Rubido</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recently, the sleep-wake states have been analysed using novel complexity measures, complementing the classical analysis of EEGs by frequency bands. This new approach consistently shows a decrease in EEG's complexity during slow-wave sleep, yet it is unclear how cortical oscillations shape these complexity variations. In this work, we analyse how the frequency content of brain signals affects the complexity estimates in freely moving rats. We find that the low-frequency spectrum - including the Delta, Theta, and Sigma frequency bands - drives the complexity changes during the sleep-wake states. This happens because low-frequency oscillations emerge from neuronal population patterns, as we show by recovering the complexity variations during the sleep-wake cycle from micro, meso, and macroscopic recordings. Moreover, we find that the lower frequencies reveal synchronisation patterns across the neocortex, such as a sensory-motor decoupling that happens during REM sleep. Overall, our works shows that EEG's low frequencies are critical in shaping the sleep-wake states' complexity across cortical scales.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472983" rel="alternate" title="Low Frequency Oscillations drive EEG's complexity changes during wakefulness and sleep (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472688</id><title>Mice identify subgoal locations through an action-driven mapping process (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.263912+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip Shamash</name></author><author><name>Tiago Branco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mammals instinctively explore and form mental maps of their spatial environments. Models of cognitive mapping in neuroscience mostly depict map-learning as a process of random or biased diffusion. In practice, however, animals explore spaces using structured, purposeful, sensory-guided actions. Here we test the hypothesis that executing specific exploratory actions is a key strategy for building a cognitive map. Previous work has shown that in arenas with obstacles and a shelter, mice spontaneously learn efficient multi-step escape routes by memorizing allocentric subgoal locations. We thus used threat-evoked escape to probe the relationship between ethological exploratory behavior and allocentric spatial memory. Using closed-loop neural manipulations to interrupt running movements during exploration, we found that blocking runs targeting an obstacle edge abolished subgoal learning. In contrast, blocking other movements while sparing edge-directed runs had no effect on memorizing subgoals. Finally, spatial analyses suggest that the decision to use a subgoal during escape takes into account the mouse's starting position relative to the layout of the environment. We conclude that mice use an action-driven learning process to identify subgoals and that these subgoals are then integrated into a map-based planning process. We suggest a conceptual framework for spatial learning that is compatible with the successor representation from reinforcement learning and sensorimotor enactivism from cognitive science.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472688" rel="alternate" title="Mice identify subgoal locations through an action-driven mapping process (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472468</id><title>A library for fMRI real-time processing systems in python (RTPSpy) with comprehensive online noise reduction, fast and accurate anatomical image processing, and online processing simulation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264040+00:00</updated><author><name>Masaya Misaki</name></author><author><name>Jerzy Bodurka</name></author><author><name>Martin P Paulus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We introduce a python library for real-time fMRI (rtfMRI) data processing systems, Real-Time Processing System in python (RTPSpy), to provide building blocks for a custom rtfMRI application with extensive and advanced functionalities. RTPSpy is a library package including 1) a fast, comprehensive, and flexible online fMRI denoising pipeline comparable to offline processing, 2) utilities for fast and accurate anatomical image processing to define a target region on-site, 3) a simulation system of online fMRI processing to optimize a pipeline and target signal calculation, 4) interface to an external application for feedback presentation, and 5) a boilerplate graphical user interface (GUI) integrating operations with RTPSpy library. Since online fMRI data processing cannot be equivalent to offline, we discussed the limitations of online analysis and their solutions in the RTPSpy implementation. We developed a fast and accurate anatomical image processing script with fast tissue segmentation (FastSeg), image alignment, and spatial normalization, utilizing the FastSurfer, AFNI, and ANTs. We confirmed that the FastSeg output was comparable with FreeSurfer, and could complete all the anatomical image processing in a few minutes. Thanks to its highly modular architecture, RTPSpy can easily be used for a simulation analysis to optimize a processing pipeline and target signal calculation. We present a sample script for building a real-time processing pipeline and running a simulation using RTPSpy. The library also offers a simple signal exchange mechanism with an external application. An external application can receive a real-time neurofeedback signal from RTPSpy in a background thread with a few lines of script. While the main components of the RTPSpy are the library modules, we also provide a GUI class for easy access to the RTPSpy functions. The boilerplate GUI application provided with the package allows users to develop a customized rtfMRI application with minimum scripting labor. Finally, we discussed the limitations of the package regarding environment-specific implementations. We believe that RTPSpy is an attractive option for developing rtfMRI applications highly optimized for individual purposes. The package is available from GitHub (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mamisaki/RTPSpy"&gt;https://github.com/mamisaki/RTPSpy&lt;/ext-link&gt;) with GPL3 license.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472468" rel="alternate" title="A library for fMRI real-time processing systems in python (RTPSpy) with comprehensive online noise reduction, fast and accurate anatomical image processing, and online processing simulation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472997</id><title>Dopamine and GPCR-mediated modulation of DN1 clock neurons gates the circadian timing of sleep (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264171+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthias Schlichting</name></author><author><name>Shlesha Richhariya</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Herndon</name></author><author><name>Dingbang Ma</name></author><author><name>Jason Xin</name></author><author><name>William Lenh</name></author><author><name>Katharine Abruzzi</name></author><author><name>Michael Rosbash</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The metronome-like circadian regulation of sleep timing must still adapt to an uncertain environment. Recent studies in Drosophila indicate that neuromodulation not only plays a key role in clock neuron synchronization but also affects interactions between the clock network and brain sleep centers. We show here that the targets of neuromodulators, G-Protein Coupled Receptors (GPCRs), are highly enriched in the fly brain circadian clock network. Single cell sequencing indicates that they are not only differentially expressed but also define clock neuron identity. We generated a comprehensive guide library to mutagenize individual GPCRs in specific neurons and verified the strategy with a targeted sequencing approach. Combined with a behavioral screen, the mutagenesis strategy revealed a novel role of dopamine in sleep regulation by identifying two dopamine receptors and a clock neuron subpopulation that gate the timing of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472997" rel="alternate" title="Dopamine and GPCR-mediated modulation of DN1 clock neurons gates the circadian timing of sleep (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472958</id><title>Real-time imaging of Arc/Arg3.1 transcription ex vivo reveals input-specific immediate early gene dynamics (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264311+00:00</updated><author><name>Pablo J Lituma</name></author><author><name>Robert H Singer</name></author><author><name>Sulagna Das</name></author><author><name>Pablo E Castillo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability of neurons to process and store salient environmental features underlies information processing in the brain. Long-term information storage requires synaptic plasticity and regulation of gene expression. While distinct patterns of activity have been linked to synaptic plasticity, their impact on immediate early gene (IEG) expression remains poorly understood. The activity regulated cytoskeleton associated (Arc) gene has received wide attention as an IEG implicated in synaptic plasticity and memory. Yet, to date, the transcriptional dynamics of Arc in response to compartment and input-specific activity is unclear. By developing a knock-in mouse to fluorescently tag Arc alleles, we studied real-time transcription dynamics after stimulation of dentate granule cells (GCs) in acute hippocampal slices. To our surprise, we found that Arc transcription displayed distinct temporal kinetics depending on the activation of excitatory inputs that convey functionally distinct information, i.e. medial and lateral perforant paths (MPP and LPP, respectively). Moreover, the transcriptional dynamics of Arc after synaptic stimulation was similar to direct activation of GCs, although the contribution of ionotropic glutamate receptors, L-type voltage gated calcium channel, and the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) differed. Specifically, we observed an ER-mediated synapse-to-nucleus signal that supported elevations in nuclear calcium, and rapid induction of Arc transcription following MPP stimulation. However, activation of LPP inputs displayed lower nuclear calcium rise, which could underlie the delayed transcriptional onset of Arc. Our findings highlight how input-specific activity distinctly impacts transcriptional dynamics of an IEG linked to learning and memory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472958" rel="alternate" title="Real-time imaging of Arc/Arg3.1 transcription ex vivo reveals input-specific immediate early gene dynamics (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472107</id><title>Attenuated transcriptional response to pro-inflammatory cytokines in schizophrenia hiPSC-derived neural progenitor cells (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264429+00:00</updated><author><name>Anjali Bhat</name></author><author><name>Haritz Irizar</name></author><author><name>Pooja Raval</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo RR Duarte</name></author><author><name>Lucia Dutan Polit</name></author><author><name>Timothy Powell</name></author><author><name>P.J. Michael Deans</name></author><author><name>Carol Shum</name></author><author><name>Roland Nagy</name></author><author><name>Grainne McAlonan</name></author><author><name>Conrad O Iyegbe</name></author><author><name>Jack Price</name></author><author><name>Elvira Bramon</name></author><author><name>Sagnik Bhattacharyya</name></author><author><name>Anthony C Vernon</name></author><author><name>Deepak P Srivastava</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Maternal immune activation (MIA) during prenatal development is an environmental risk factor for psychiatric disorders including schizophrenia (SZ). This link is particularly well established in the case of schizophrenia. Converging lines of evidence from human and animal model studies have suggested that elevated cytokine levels in the maternal and fetal compartments are an important indication of the mechanisms driving this association. However, there is variability in susceptibility to the psychiatric risk conferred by MIA, likely influenced by genetic factors. How MIA interacts with a genetic profile susceptible to SZ is challenging to test in animal models. To address this gap, we examined whether differential gene expression responses occur in forebrain-lineage neural progenitor cells (NPCs) derived from human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC) generated from three individuals with a diagnosis of schizophrenia and three healthy controls. Following acute (24 hour) treatment with either interferon-gamma (IFNγ; 25 ng/μl) or interleukin (IL)-1β (10 ng/μl), we identified, by RNA sequencing, 3380 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in the IFNγ-treated control lines (compared to untreated controls), and 1980 DEGs in IFNγ-treated SZ lines (compared to untreated SZ lines). Of these, 359 genes responded differently to IFNγ treatment in SZ relative to control lines, which were enriched for genes differentially expressed in adult SZ cases and in pathways related to the regulation of antigen processing, neuronal post-synaptic density, and the presynapse. There were no differentially expressed genes in the IL-1β-treatment conditions after Benjamini-Hochberg correction. Gene set enrichment analysis however showed that IL-1β impacts immune function and neuronal differentiation. Collectively, our data suggest that a) SZ NPCs show an attenuated transcriptional response to IFNγ treatment compared to control NPCs; b) IL-1β may be less relevant to NPC cultures than IFNγ and c) the genes differentially regulated in schizophrenia lines are primarily mitochondrial, loss-of-function, pre- and post-synaptic genes. Our findings particularly highlight early synaptic development as a key target for future research into the mechanisms of association between maternal immune activation and schizophrenia risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472107" rel="alternate" title="Attenuated transcriptional response to pro-inflammatory cytokines in schizophrenia hiPSC-derived neural progenitor cells (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472647</id><title>Attention enhances category representations across the brain with strengthened residual correlations to ventral temporal cortex (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264614+00:00</updated><author><name>Arielle S Keller</name></author><author><name>Akshay V Jagadeesh</name></author><author><name>Lior Bugatus</name></author><author><name>Leanne M Williams</name></author><author><name>Kalanit Grill-Spector</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How does attention enhance neural representations of goal-relevant stimuli while suppressing representations of ignored stimuli across regions of the brain? While prior studies have shown that attention enhances visual responses, we lack a cohesive understanding of how selective attention modulates visual representations across the brain. Here, we used functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) while participants performed a selective attention task on superimposed stimuli from multiple categories and used a data-driven approach to test how attention affects both decodability of category information and residual correlations (after regressing out stimulus-driven variance) with category-selective regions of ventral temporal cortex (VTC). Our data reveal three main findings. First, when two objects are simultaneously viewed, the category of the attended object can be decoded more readily than the category of the ignored object, with the greatest attentional enhancements observed in occipital and temporal lobes. Second, after accounting for the response to the stimulus, the correlation in the residual brain activity between a cortical region and a category-selective region of VTC was elevated when that region's preferred category was attended vs. ignored, and more so in the right occipital, parietal, and frontal cortices. Third, we found that the stronger the residual correlations between a given region of cortex and VTC, the better visual category information could be decoded from that region. These findings suggest that heightened residual correlations by selective attention may reflect the sharing of information between sensory regions and higher-order cortical regions to provide attentional enhancement of goal-relevant information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472647" rel="alternate" title="Attention enhances category representations across the brain with strengthened residual correlations to ventral temporal cortex (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472435</id><title>Spike initiation properties in the axon support high-fidelity signal transmission (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264775+00:00</updated><author><name>Mohammad Amin Kamaleddin</name></author><author><name>Nooshin Abdollahi</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Ratté</name></author><author><name>Steven A Prescott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The axon initial segment (AIS) converts graded depolarization into all-or-none spikes that are transmitted by the axon to downstream neurons. Analog-to-digital transduction and digital signal transmission call for distinct spike initiation properties (filters) and those filters should, therefore, differ between the AIS and distal axon. Here we show that unlike the AIS, which spikes repetitively during sustained depolarization, the axon spikes transiently and only if depolarization reaches threshold before K&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1 channels activate. Rate of depolarization is critical. This was shown by optogenetically evoking spikes in the distal axon of CA1 pyramidal neurons using different photostimulus waveforms and pharmacological conditions while recording antidromically propagated spikes at the soma, thus circumventing the prohibitive difficulty of patching intact axons. Computational modeling shows that K&lt;sub&gt;V&lt;/sub&gt;1 channels in the axon implement a high-pass filter that is matched to the axial current waveform associated with spike propagation, thus maximizing the signal-to-noise ratio to ensure high-fidelity transmission of spike-based signals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472435" rel="alternate" title="Spike initiation properties in the axon support high-fidelity signal transmission (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472078</id><title>LKB1 Is Physiologically Required for Sleep from Drosophila to the Mouse (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.264894+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziyi Liu</name></author><author><name>Lifen Jiang</name></author><author><name>Chaoyi Li</name></author><author><name>Chengang Li</name></author><author><name>Jingqun Yang</name></author><author><name>Dan Wang</name></author><author><name>Renbo Mao</name></author><author><name>Yi Rao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;LKB1 is known as a master kinase for 14 kinases related to the adenosine monophosphate (AMP)-activated protein kinase (AMPK). Two of them (SIK3 and AMPKα) have previously been implicated in sleep regulation. We generated loss-of-function (LOF) mutants for Lkb1 in both Drosophila and mice. Sleep was reduced in Lkb1-mutant flies and in flies with neuronal deletion of Lkb1. Sleep was reduced in mice after virally mediated reduction of Lkb1 in the brain. Electroencephalography (EEG) analysis showed that non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep and sleep need were both reduced in Lkb1-mutant mice. These results indicate that LKB1 plays a physiological role in sleep regulation conserved from flies to mice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472078" rel="alternate" title="LKB1 Is Physiologically Required for Sleep from Drosophila to the Mouse (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472761</id><title>The neural cell adhesion molecule NrCAM regulates development of hypothalamic tanycytes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265034+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Moore</name></author><author><name>Kavitha Chinnaiya</name></author><author><name>Dong Won Kim</name></author><author><name>Sarah Brown</name></author><author><name>Iain Stewart</name></author><author><name>Sarah Robins</name></author><author><name>Georgina Dowsett</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Muir</name></author><author><name>Marco Travaglio</name></author><author><name>Jo E Lewis</name></author><author><name>Fran Ebling</name></author><author><name>Seth Blackshaw</name></author><author><name>Andrew Furley</name></author><author><name>Marysia Placzek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hypothalamic tanycytes are neural stem and progenitor cells, but little is known of how they are regulated. Here we provide evidence that the cell adhesion molecule, NrCAM, regulates tanycytes in the adult niche. NrCAM is strongly expressed in adult mouse tanycytes. Immunohistochemical and in situ hybridization analysis revealed that NrCAM loss of function leads to both a reduced number of tanycytes and reduced expression of tanycyte-specific cell markers, along with a small reduction in tyrosine hydroxylase-positive arcuate neurons.  Similar analyses of NrCAM mutants at E16 identify few changes in gene expression or cell composition, indicating that NrCAM regulates tanycytes, rather than early embryonic hypothalamic development. Neurosphere and organotypic assays support the idea that NrCAM governs cellular homeostasis. Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-Seq) shows that tanycyte-specific genes, including a number that are implicated in thyroid hormone metabolism, show reduced expression in the mutant mouse. However, the mild tanycyte depletion and loss of markers observed in NrCAM-deficient mice were associated with only a subtle metabolic phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472761" rel="alternate" title="The neural cell adhesion molecule NrCAM regulates development of hypothalamic tanycytes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472760</id><title>Simple contextual cueing prevents retroactive interference in short-term perceptual training of orientation detection tasks (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265209+00:00</updated><author><name>Hui Huang</name></author><author><name>Yangming Zhang</name></author><author><name>Sheng Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perceptual training of multiple tasks suffers from interference between the trained tasks. Here, we conducted four psychophysical experiments with separate groups of participants to investigate the possibility of preventing the interference in short-term perceptual training. We trained the participants to detect two orientations of Gabor stimuli in two adjacent days at the same retinal location and examined the interference of training effects between the two orientations. The results showed significant retroactive interference from the second orientation to the first orientation (Experiments 1 and 2). Introducing a 6-hour interval between the pre-test and training of the second orientation did not eliminate the interference effect, excluding the interpretation of disrupted reconsolidation as the pre-test of the second orientation may reactivate and destabilize the representation of the first orientation (Experiment 3). Finally, the training of the two orientations was accompanied by fixations in two colors, each served as a contextual cue for one orientation. The results showed that the retroactive interference was not evident after introducing these passively perceived contextual cues (Experiment 4). Our findings suggest that the retroactive interference effect in short-term perceptual training of orientation detection tasks was likely the result of higher-level factors such as shared contextual cues embedded in the tasks. The effect of multiple perceptual training could be facilitated by associating the trained tasks with different contextual cues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472760" rel="alternate" title="Simple contextual cueing prevents retroactive interference in short-term perceptual training of orientation detection tasks (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472113</id><title>Tissue Optimisation Strategies for High Quality Ex Vivo Diffusion Imaging (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265343+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel L. C. Barrett</name></author><author><name>Diana Cash</name></author><author><name>Camilla Simmons</name></author><author><name>Eugene Kim</name></author><author><name>Tobias C. Wood</name></author><author><name>Richard Stones</name></author><author><name>Anthony C. Vernon</name></author><author><name>Marco Catani</name></author><author><name>Flavio Dell’Acqua</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; diffusion imaging can be used to study healthy and pathological tissue microstructure in the rodent brain with microscopic resolution, providing a link between &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; MRI and &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; microscopy techniques. A major challenge for the successful acquisition of &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; diffusion imaging data however are changes in the relaxivity and diffusivity of brain tissue following perfusion fixation. In this study we address this question by examining the combined effects of tissue preparation factors that influence image quality, including tissue rehydration time, fixative concentration and contrast agent concentration. We present an optimisation strategy combining these factors to manipulate the T1 and T2 of fixed tissue and maximise signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) efficiency. Applying this strategy in the rat brain resulted in a doubling of SNR and an increase in SNR per unit time by 135% in grey matter and 88% in white matter. This enabled the acquisition of excellent quality high-resolution (78 µm isotropic voxel size) diffusion data in less than 4 days, with a &lt;italic&gt;b&lt;/italic&gt;-value of 4000 s/mm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, 30 diffusion directions and a field of view of 40 × 13 × 18 mm, using a 9.4 Tesla scanner with a standard 39 mm volume coil and a 660 mT/m 114 mm gradient insert. It was also possible to achieve comparable data quality for a standard resolution (150 µm) diffusion dataset in 2&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; hours. In conclusion, the optimisation strategy presented here may be used to improve signal quality, increase spatial resolution and/or allow faster acquisitions in preclinical &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; diffusion MRI experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472113" rel="alternate" title="Tissue Optimisation Strategies for High Quality Ex Vivo Diffusion Imaging (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472498</id><title>Arousal elevation drives the development of oscillatory vocal output (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265509+00:00</updated><author><name>Yisi S. Zhang</name></author><author><name>John L. Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Asif A. Ghazanfar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adult behaviors, such as vocal production, often exhibit temporal regularity. In contrast, their immature forms are more irregular. We ask whether the coupling of motor behaviors with arousal changes give rise to temporal regularity and drive the transition from variable to regular motor output over the course of development. We used marmoset monkey vocal production to explore this putative influence of arousal on the nonlinear changes in their developing vocal output patterns. Based on a detailed analysis of vocal and arousal dynamics in marmosets, we put forth a general model incorporating arousal and auditory-feedback loops for spontaneous vocal production. Using this model, we show that a stable oscillation can emerge as the baseline arousal increases, predicting the transition from stochastic to periodic oscillations occurring in marmoset vocal development. We further provide a solution for how this model can explain vocal development as the joint consequence of energetic growth and social feedback. Together, our model offers a plausible mechanism for the development of arousal-mediated adaptive behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472498" rel="alternate" title="Arousal elevation drives the development of oscillatory vocal output (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472840</id><title>Chronic Seizures Worsen Cognitive Function with Loss of Presenilin 2 Function in a Sex-Related Manner (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265623+00:00</updated><author><name>Kevin M Knox</name></author><author><name>Megan Beckman</name></author><author><name>Carole L Smith</name></author><author><name>Suman Jayadev</name></author><author><name>Melissa Barker-Haliski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Patients with early-onset Alzheimer's disease (EOAD) are at elevated risk for seizures, including patients with variants in presenilin 2 (PSEN2). Like patients with epilepsy, untreated seizures may also worsen cognitive function in AD. We therefore sought to define the impact of loss of normal PSEN2 function and chronic seizures on cognitive function in the aged brain. Male and female PSEN2 KO and age- and sex-matched wild-type (WT) mice were sham or corneal kindled beginning at 6-months-old. Kindled and sham-kindled mice were then challenged up to 6 weeks later in a battery of cognitive tests: non-habituated open field (OF), T-maze spontaneous alternation (TM), and Barnes maze (BM), followed by immunohistochemistry for markers of neuroinflammation and neuroplasticity. PSEN2 KO mice required significantly more stimulations to kindle (males: p&amp;lt;0.02; females: p&amp;lt;0.02). Chronic seizures more significantly worsened anxiety-like behaviors of female PSEN2 KO mice as measured by percentage of total time exploring the center of an OF. TM performance was significantly worsened in kindled female (p=0.024), but not male, PSEN2 KO mice. Male BM performance was generally worsened by seizures (p=0.038), but not by genotype. Conversely, kindled PSEN2 KO females made the most BM errors (p=0.007). Chronic seizures also significantly altered expression of hippocampal neuroinflammation and neuroplasticity markers in a sex-specific manner. This study demonstrates that hippocampus-dependent cognitive function may be only worsened by uncontrolled chronic seizures in female, but not male, PSEN2 KO mice. Our work aligns with clinical evidence of sex-specific worsening of AD burden and supports sex-specific anticonvulsant interventions in AD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472840" rel="alternate" title="Chronic Seizures Worsen Cognitive Function with Loss of Presenilin 2 Function in a Sex-Related Manner (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.453704</id><title>Identifying Uncertainty States during Wayfinding in Indoor Environments: An EEG Classification Study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265799+00:00</updated><author><name>Bingzhao Zhu</name></author><author><name>Jesus G Cruz-Garza</name></author><author><name>Mahsa Shoaran</name></author><author><name>Saleh Kalantari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The researchers used a machine-learning classification approach to better understand neurological features  associated with periods of wayfinding uncertainty. The participants (n=30) were asked to complete wayfinding tasks of varying difficulty in a virtual reality (VR) hospital environment. Time segments when participants experienced navigational uncertainty were first identified using a combination of objective measurements (frequency of inputs into the VR controller) and behavioral annotations from two independent observers. Uncertainty time-segments during navigation were ranked on a scale from 1 (low) to 5 (high). The machine-learning model, a random forest classifier implemented using scikit-learn in Python, was used to evaluate common spatial patterns of EEG spectral power across the theta, alpha, and beta bands associated with the researcher-identified uncertainty states. The overall predictive power of the resulting model was 0.70 in terms of the area under the Receiver Operating Characteristics curve (ROC-AUC). These findings indicate that EEG data can potentially be used as a metric for identifying navigational uncertainty states, which may provide greater rigor and efficiency in studies of human responses to architectural design variables and wayfinding cues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.453704" rel="alternate" title="Identifying Uncertainty States during Wayfinding in Indoor Environments: An EEG Classification Study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472768</id><title>Metabolic alterations in a Drosophila model of Parkinson's disease based on DJ-1 deficiency (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.265921+00:00</updated><author><name>Cristina Solana-Manrique</name></author><author><name>Francisco Jose Sanz</name></author><author><name>Isabel Torregrosa</name></author><author><name>Martina Palomino-Schatzlein</name></author><author><name>Carolina Hernandez-Oliver</name></author><author><name>Antonio Pineda</name></author><author><name>Nuria Paricio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parkinson's disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder whose physiopathology is still unclear. Besides, it is urgent to discover new biomarkers and therapeutic targets to facilitate its diagnosis and treatment. Previous studies performed in PD models and samples from PD patients already demonstrated that metabolic alterations were associated with this disease. In this context, the aim of this study is to give a better understanding of metabolic disturbances underlying PD pathogenesis. To achieve this goal, we used a &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; PD model based on inactivation of the &lt;italic&gt;DJ-1β&lt;/italic&gt; gene (ortholog of human &lt;italic&gt;DJ-1&lt;/italic&gt;). Metabolomic analyses were performed in 1-day-old and 15-day-old &lt;italic&gt;DJ-1β&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and control flies using &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, combined with expression and enzymatic activity assays of proteins implicated in altered pathways. Our results showed that PD model flies exhibit protein metabolism alterations, a shift from tricarboxylic acid cycle to glycolytic pathway to obtain ATP, together with an increase in the expression of some urea cycle enzymes. Thus, these metabolic changes could be contributing to PD pathogenesis and might constitute possible therapeutic targets and/or biomarkers for this disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472768" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic alterations in a Drosophila model of Parkinson's disease based on DJ-1 deficiency (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472887</id><title>Nanoscale patterning of in vitro neuronal circuits (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.266093+00:00</updated><author><name>Jose C. Mateus</name></author><author><name>Sean Weaver</name></author><author><name>Dirk van Swaay</name></author><author><name>Aline Renz</name></author><author><name>Julian Hengsteler</name></author><author><name>Paulo Aguiar</name></author><author><name>János Vörös</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Methods for patterning neurons &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; have gradually improved and are used to investigate questions difficult to address &lt;italic&gt;in&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Though these techniques guide axons between groups of neurons, multiscale control of neuronal connectivity, from circuits to synapses, is yet to be achieved &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;. As studying neuronal circuits with synaptic resolution &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; poses significant challenges, an &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; alternative could serve as a testbed for &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; experiments or as a platform for validating biophysical and computational models. In this work we use a combination of electron beam and photolithography to create polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) structures with features ranging from 150 nanometers to a few millimeters. Leveraging the difference between average axon and dendritic spine diameters, we restrict axon growth while allowing spines to pass through nanochannels to guide synapse formation between small groups of neurons (i.e.  nodes). We show this technique can be used to generate large numbers of isolated feed-forward circuits where connections between nodes are restricted to regions connected by nanochannels. Using a genetically encoded calcium indicator in combination with fluorescently tagged post synaptic protein, PSD-95, we demonstrate functional synapses can form in this region. Although more work needs to be done to control connectivity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, we believe this is a significant step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472887" rel="alternate" title="Nanoscale patterning of in vitro neuronal circuits (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472594</id><title>Neural Readout of a Latency Code in the Active Electrosensory System (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.266231+00:00</updated><author><name>Krista Perks</name></author><author><name>Nathaniel B Sawtell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The latency of spikes relative to a stimulus conveys sensory information across modalities. However, in most cases it remains unclear whether and how such latency codes are utilized by postsynaptic neurons. In the active electrosensory system of mormyrid fish, a latency code for stimulus amplitude in electroreceptor afferent nerve fibers (EAs) is hypothesized to be read out by a central reference provided by motor corollary discharge (CD). Here we demonstrate that CD enhances sensory responses in postsynaptic granular cells of the electrosensory lobe, but is not required for reading out EA input. Instead, diverse latency and spike count tuning across the EA population gives rise to graded information about stimulus amplitude that can be read out by standard integration of converging excitatory synaptic inputs. Inhibitory control over the temporal window of integration renders two granular cell subclasses differentially sensitive to information derived from relative spike latency versus spike count.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472594" rel="alternate" title="Neural Readout of a Latency Code in the Active Electrosensory System (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472826</id><title>Neural signature of everyday function in older adults at-risk of cognitive impairment (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.266340+00:00</updated><author><name>Pierfilippo De Sanctis</name></author><author><name>Johanna Wagner</name></author><author><name>Sophie Molholm</name></author><author><name>John J. Foxe</name></author><author><name>Helena Blumen</name></author><author><name>Douwe Horsthuis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Assessment of everyday activities are central to the diagnosis of pre-dementia and dementia. Yet, little is known about the brain substrates and processes that contribute to everyday functional impairment, particularly during early stages of cognitive decline. We investigated everyday function using a complex gait task in normal older adults stratified by risk of cognitive impairment. We applied a novel EEG approach, which combines electroencephalographic with 3D-body tracking technology to measure brain-gait dynamics with millisecond precision while participants are in motion. Twenty-six participants (mean age = 74.9 years) with cognitive and everyday functional profiles within the normal range for their age and sex were ranked for risk of cognitive impairment. We used the Montreal Cognitive Assessment battery, a global index of cognition with a range from 0 to 30, to classify individuals as being at higher (22-26) and lower risk (27+). Individuals walking on a treadmill were exposed to visual perturbation designed to destabilize gait. Assuming that brain changes precede behavioral decline, we predicted that older adults increase step width to gain stability, yet the underlying neural signatures would be different for lower versus higher risk individuals. When pooling across risk groups, we found that step width increased and fronto-parietal activation shifted from transient, during swing phases, to sustained across the gait cycle during visually perturbed input. As predicted, step width increased in both groups but underlying neural signatures were different. Fronto-medial theta (3-7Hz) power of gait-related brain oscillations were increased in higher risk individuals during both perturbed and unperturbed inputs. On the other hand, left central gyri beta (13-28Hz) power was decreased in lower risk individuals, specifically during visually perturbed input. Finally, relating MoCA scores to spectral power pooled across fronto-parietal regions, we found associations between increased theta power and worse MoCA scores and between decreased beta power and better MoCA scores. Able-bodied older adults at-risk of cognitive impairment are characterized by unique neural signatures of mobility. Stronger reliance on frontomedial theta activation in at-risk individuals may reflect higher-order compensatory responses for deterioration of basic sensorimotor processes. Region and spectral-specific signatures of mobility may provide brain targets for early intervention against everyday functional decline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472826" rel="alternate" title="Neural signature of everyday function in older adults at-risk of cognitive impairment (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>