<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.928392+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457079</id><title>Humans and mice fluctuate between external and internal modes of sensory processing (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.928737+00:00</updated><author><name>Veith Andreas Weilnhammer</name></author><author><name>Heiner Stuke</name></author><author><name>Anna-Lena Eckert</name></author><author><name>Kai Standvoss</name></author><author><name>Philipp Sterzer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perception cycles through periods of enhanced and reduced sensitivity to external information. Here, we asked whether such infra-slow oscillations arise as a noise-related epiphenomenon of limited processing capacity or, alternatively, represent a structured mechanism of perceptual inference. Using two large-scale datasets, we found that humans and mice waver between alternating intervals of externally- and internally-oriented modes of sensory analysis. During external mode, perception was more sensitive to external sensory information, whereas internal mode was characterized by enhanced biases toward perceptual history. Computational modeling indicated that dynamic changes in mode are governed by two interlinked factors: (i), the integration of subsequent stimuli over time and, (ii), infra-slow anti-phase oscillations in the perceptual impact of external sensory information versus internal predictions that are provided by perceptual history. Between-mode fluctuations may benefit perception by enabling the generation of stable representations of the environment despite an ongoing stream of noisy sensory inputs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457079" rel="alternate" title="Humans and mice fluctuate between external and internal modes of sensory processing (40 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456545</id><title>Learning predictive cognitive maps with spiking neurons during behaviour and replays (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.928943+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacopo Bono</name></author><author><name>Sara Zannone</name></author><author><name>Victor Pedrosa</name></author><author><name>Claudia Clopath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We describe a framework where a biologically plausible spiking neural network mimicking hippocampal layers learns a cognitive map known as the successor representation. We show analytically how, on the algorithmic level, the learning follows the TD(&lt;italic&gt;λ&lt;/italic&gt;) algorithm, which emerges from the underlying spike-timing dependent plasticity rule. We then analyze the implications of this framework, uncovering how behavioural activity and experience replays can play complementary roles when learning the representation of the environment, how we can learn relations over behavioural timescales with synaptic plasticity acting on the range of milliseconds, and how the learned representation can be flexibly encoded by allowing state-dependent delay discounting through neuromodulation and altered firing rates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456545" rel="alternate" title="Learning predictive cognitive maps with spiking neurons during behaviour and replays (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456935</id><title>Characterising the Photoplethysmography Pulse Waveform for Use in Human Neuroscience: The Hybrid Excess and Decay (HED) Model (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.929108+00:00</updated><author><name>Simon Williamson</name></author><author><name>Lucie Daniel-Watanabe</name></author><author><name>Johanna Finnemann</name></author><author><name>Craig Powell</name></author><author><name>Adam Teed</name></author><author><name>Micah Allen</name></author><author><name>Martin Paulus</name></author><author><name>Sahib S. Khalsa</name></author><author><name>Paul C. Fletcher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography (PPG) offers a widely-used, convenient and non-invasive approach to monitoring basic indices of cardiovascular function such as heart rate and blood oxygenation. However, while the pulse waveform, generated by PPG comprises features that are shaped by physiological and psychological factors, it is frequently overlooked in analyses of such data. We suggest that studies could be enriched by exploiting the possibilities afforded by a systematic analysis of PPG waveforms. To do this we initially require a robust and automated means of characterising it, thereby allowing us to examine variations across individuals and between different physiological and psychological contexts. We present a psychophysiologically-relevant model, the Hybrid Excess and Decay (HED) Model, which characterises pulse wave morphology in terms of three underlying pressure waves and a decay function. We show that these parameters capture PPG data with a high degree of precision and, moreover, are sensitive to specific, physiologically-relevant changes within individuals. We present the theoretical and practical basis for the model and demonstrate its performance when applied to a pharmacological dataset of 105 participants receiving intravenous administrations of the sympathomimetic drug isoproterenol (Isoprenaline). We conclude by discussing the possible value in using the HED model to complement standard measures of PPG outputs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456935" rel="alternate" title="Characterising the Photoplethysmography Pulse Waveform for Use in Human Neuroscience: The Hybrid Excess and Decay (HED) Model (28 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456813</id><title>Prefrontal cortex neural compensation during an operant devaluation task (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.929575+00:00</updated><author><name>Hayley Fisher</name></author><author><name>Hongyu Lin</name></author><author><name>Jensen May</name></author><author><name>Caitlin McLean</name></author><author><name>Charles L. Pickens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deficits in goal-directed action are reported in multiple neuropsychiatric conditions, including schizophrenia. However, dysfunction is not always apparent in early stages of schizophrenia, possibly due to neural compensation. We designed a novel devaluation task in which goal-directed action could be guided by stimulus-outcome (S-O) [presumably orbitofrontal cortex (OFC)-mediated] or response-outcome (R-O) associations [presumably prelimbic cortex (PL)-mediated]. We previously found suggestive evidence that OFC and PL could compensate for each other in this task, and we more directly assessed this potential compensation here. In Experiment 1, rats received OFC, PL, combined OFC+PL, or sham lesions and then completed our devaluation task. The OFC+PL lesion group exhibited impaired devaluation. In Experiment 2, rats received cholera-toxin-b (CTb) into OFC and either neurotoxic or sham PL lesions. Rats were then sacrificed on the last training day to double-label for Arc and CTb. We found increased Arc+CTb in mediodorsal thalamus (MD) and increased Arc+ neurons in OFC when PL was lesioned, suggesting that PL lesions lead to a compensatory increased activation of the MD→OFC circuit. Our results suggest that our devaluation task can model neural compensation between OFC and PL and this compensation may be regulated by MD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To detect compensatory responses, behavioral models that use different strategies must be developed to determine if the strategies shift when a brain area or circuit is incapacitated. Neural compensation is commonly observed in human research but only a few models of neural compensation exist, and few identify compensation within the prefrontal cortex. This research is among the first to show neural compensation between prefrontal cortex regions and implicate a thalamocortical circuit in modulating this compensation. Not only will this model provide a way to behaviorally identify subtle neurological shifts, it can also elucidate basic neurological mechanisms that mediate how circuits interact with each other and how dysfunction in one circuit can affect connectivity in other brain areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456813" rel="alternate" title="Prefrontal cortex neural compensation during an operant devaluation task (23 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456345</id><title>Brain transcriptomic profiling reveals common alterations across neurodegenerative and psychiatric disorders (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.929888+00:00</updated><author><name>Iman Sadeghi</name></author><author><name>Juand Domingo Gispert</name></author><author><name>Emilio Palumbo</name></author><author><name>Manuel Munoz-Aguirre</name></author><author><name>Valentin Wucher</name></author><author><name>Valeria D'Argenio</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Santpere</name></author><author><name>Arcadi Navarro</name></author><author><name>Roderic Guigo</name></author><author><name>Natalia Vilor-Tejedor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric disorders (ND-NPs) are multifactorial, polygenic and complex behavioral phenotypes caused by brain abnormalities. Large-scale collaborative efforts have tried to identify the genetic architecture of these conditions. However, specific and shared underlying molecular pathobiology of brain illnesses is not clear. Here, we examine transcriptome-wide characterization of eight conditions, using a total of 2633 post-mortem brain samples from patients with Alzheimer's disease (AD), Parkinson's disease (PD), Progressive Supranuclear Palsy (PSP), Pathological Aging (PA), Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD), Schizophrenia (Scz), Major Depressive Disorder (MDD), and Bipolar Disorder (BP)–in comparison with 2,078 brain samples from matched control subjects. Similar transcriptome alterations were observed between NDs and NPs with the top correlations obtained between Scz-BP, ASD-PD, AD-PD, and Scz-ASD. Region-specific comparisons also revealed shared transcriptome alterations in frontal and temporal lobes across NPs and NDs. Co-expression network analysis identified coordinated dysregulations of cell-type-specific modules across NDs and NPs. This study provides a transcriptomic framework to understand the molecular alterations of NPs and NDs through their shared- and specific gene expression in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456345" rel="alternate" title="Brain transcriptomic profiling reveals common alterations across neurodegenerative and psychiatric disorders (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.457007</id><title>Methods for recording and imaging spreading depolarizations and seizure-like events in mouse hippocampal slices (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.930094+00:00</updated><author><name>Yi-Ling Lu</name></author><author><name>Helen E. Scharfman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spreading depolarization (SD) is a sudden and synchronized depolarization of principal cells followed by depression of activity, which slowly propagates across brain regions like cortex or hippocampus. SD is considered to be mechanistically relevant to migraine, epilepsy, and traumatic brain injury. Interestingly, research into SD typically uses SD triggered immediately after a focal stimulus. Here we optimize an in vitro experimental model allowing us to record SD without focal stimulation. This method uses electrophysiological recordings and intrinsic optical imaging in slices. The method is also relatively easy and inexpensive. Acute hippocampal slices from mice or rats were prepared and used for extracellular and whole-cell recordings. Recordings were made in a submerged-style chamber with flow of artificial cerebrospinal fluid (aCSF) above and below the slices. Flow was fast (&amp;gt; 5ml/min), and temperature was 32°C. As soon as slices were placed in the chamber, aCSF containing 0 mM Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and 5 mM K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; (0 Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;/5 K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; aCSF) was used. Two major types of activity were observed: SD and seizure-like events (SLEs). Both occurred after many minutes of recording. Although both mouse and rat slices showed SLEs, only mouse slices developed SD and did so in the first hour of 0 Mg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;/5 K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; aCSF exposure. Intrinsic optical imaging showed that most SDs initiated in CA3 and could propagate into CA1 and dentate gyrus. In dentate gyrus, SD propagated in two separate waves: (1) into the hilus and (2) into granule cell and molecular layers simultaneously. This in vitro model can be used to better understand the mechanisms and relationship between SD and SLEs. It could also be useful in preclinical drug screening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.457007" rel="alternate" title="Methods for recording and imaging spreading depolarizations and seizure-like events in mouse hippocampal slices (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457247</id><title>Beyond dimension reduction: Stable electric fields emerge from and allow representational drift (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.930244+00:00</updated><author><name>Dimitris Pinotsis</name></author><author><name>Earl K Miller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is known that the exact neurons maintaining a given memory (the neural ensemble) change from trial to trial. This raises the question of how the brain achieves stability in the face of this representational drift.  Here, we demonstrate that this stability emerges at the level of the electric fields that arise from neural activity.  The electric fields, in turn, can act as 'guard rails' that funnel higher dimensional variable neural activity along stable lower dimensional routes. We show that electric fields carry information about working memory content.   We obtained the latent space associated with each memory. We then confirmed the stability of the electric field by mapping the latent space to different cortical patches (that comprise a neural ensemble) and reconstructing information flow between patches.   Stable electric fields can allow latent states to be transferred between brain areas, in accord with modern engram theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457247" rel="alternate" title="Beyond dimension reduction: Stable electric fields emerge from and allow representational drift (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457086</id><title>Dysfunction of grey matter NG2 glial cells affects neuronal plasticity and behavior (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.930430+00:00</updated><author><name>Aline Timmermann</name></author><author><name>Ronald Jabs</name></author><author><name>Anne Boehlen</name></author><author><name>Catia Domingos</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Skubal</name></author><author><name>Wenhui Huang</name></author><author><name>Frank Kirchhoff</name></author><author><name>Christian Henneberger</name></author><author><name>Andras Bilkei-Gorzo</name></author><author><name>Gerald Seifert</name></author><author><name>Christian Werner Steinhauser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;NG2 glia represent a distinct type of macroglial cells in the CNS and are unique among glia because they receive synaptic input from neurons. They are abundantly present in white and grey matter. While the majority of white matter NG2 glia differentiates into oligodendrocytes, the physiological impact of grey matter NG2 glia and their synaptic input are ill defined yet. Here we asked whether dysfunctional NG2 glia affect neuronal signaling and behavior. We generated mice with inducible deletion of the K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; channel Kir4.1 in NG2 glia and performed comparative electrophysiological, immunohistochemical, molecular and behavioral analyses. Focussing on the hippocampus, we found that loss of the Kir4.1 potentiated synaptic depolarizations of NG2 glia and enhanced the expression of myelin basic protein. Notably, while mice with targeted deletion of the K&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; channel in NG2 glia showed impaired long term potentiation at CA3-CA1 synapses, they demonstrated improved spatial memory as revealed by testing new object location recognition. Our data demonstrate that proper NG2 glia function is critical for normal brain function and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457086" rel="alternate" title="Dysfunction of grey matter NG2 glial cells affects neuronal plasticity and behavior (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456579</id><title>Cyclin-G-associated kinase GAK/Aux orchestrates glial autophagy via Atg9 phosphorylation in Parkinson’s disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.930673+00:00</updated><author><name>Shiping Zhang</name></author><author><name>Linfang Wang</name></author><author><name>Shuanglong Yi</name></author><author><name>Shuhua Li</name></author><author><name>Honglei Wang</name></author><author><name>Li Song</name></author><author><name>Jiayao Ou</name></author><author><name>Min Zhang</name></author><author><name>Mengxiao Wang</name></author><author><name>Yuchen Zheng</name></author><author><name>Ruiqi Wang</name></author><author><name>Kai Yang</name></author><author><name>Tong Liu</name></author><author><name>Wei Yan</name></author><author><name>Chang Liu</name></author><author><name>Margaret S. Ho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glia serve as double-edged swords to modulate neuropathology in Parkinson’s disease (PD), but how they react opposingly to be beneficial or detrimental under pathological conditions, like promote or eliminate α-Synuclein inclusions, remain elusive. Here we present evidence that the PD risk factor Cyclin G-associated kinase (GAK)/dAuxilin (Aux) is a new component in glial autophagy. Lack of GAK/Aux promotes autophagic induction, disrupts lysosome acidification, and blocks glial clearance of substrates. Aux regulates Atg9 trafficking to autophagosomes and lysosomes for autophagosome biogenesis and autolysosome maturation, respectively, via Atg9 phosphorylation at newly identified residues T62 and T69. GAK/Aux-mediated glial autophagy is required for α-Syn degradation and contributes to a broad spectrum of parkinsonian symptoms in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; and mice. Our findings indicate that glial autophagy is a critical component in PD progression and identify a new autophagy factor functioning in a tissue-specific manner; targeting glial autophagy is potentially a therapeutic solution for PD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456579" rel="alternate" title="Cyclin-G-associated kinase GAK/Aux orchestrates glial autophagy via Atg9 phosphorylation in Parkinson’s disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456505</id><title>The cytokine receptor Fn14 regulates neuronal transcription during development and brain function in the adult (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.930912+00:00</updated><author><name>Austin Ferro</name></author><author><name>Uma Vrudhula</name></author><author><name>Yohan S.S. Auguste</name></author><author><name>Lucas Cheadle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytokine signaling between microglia and neurons is required for synapse elimination during brain development, but the mechanisms by which neurons respond to microglia-derived cytokines remain to be fully defined. Here, we demonstrate that microglia are necessary for sensory experience-dependent synapse elimination in the dorsal lateral geniculate nucleus (dLGN) of the mouse, a process previously shown to be mediated by the microglia-derived cytokine TWEAK and its neuronal receptor Fn14. Single-nucleus RNA-sequencing in mice lacking Fn14 or TWEAK at the height of experience-dependent refinement revealed that TWEAK-Fn14 signaling coordinates robust programs of gene expression in excitatory thalamocortical neurons of the dLGN. Gene targets of TWEAK and Fn14 are enriched for regulators of synapse and chromatin remodeling, suggesting that TWEAK-Fn14 signaling coordinates neuronal transcription to promote circuit refinement and epigenomic maturation in response to experience. We further find that Fn14 expression is not restricted to the dLGN but extends to other brain regions as well, both during development and in the adult. Consistent with the expression of Fn14 outside of the visual system, Fn14 knockout mice show significant impairments in multiple tests of memory task proficiency. At baseline, loss of Fn14 does not affect macroscopic neural activity measured by electroencephalogram recordings &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. However, mice lacking Fn14 displayed worse seizure outcomes and were less likely to survive when seizures were pharmacologically induced. Thus, TWEAK-Fn14 signaling coordinates neuronal transcription during development and contributes to cognitive function in the adult. Taken together, these data reveal that molecular pathways associated with inflammation in the periphery can coordinate with sensory experience to shape neuronal transcription and connectivity across the lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microglia regulate sensory-dependent refinement at the retinogeniculate synapse&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;TWEAK-Fn14 signaling induces the expression of neuronal genes involved in synaptic and chromatin remodeling&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fn14 signaling is dispensable for learning but required for memory in multiple tasks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss of Fn14 exacerbates seizure susceptibility and the severity of seizure outcomes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456505" rel="alternate" title="The cytokine receptor Fn14 regulates neuronal transcription during development and brain function in the adult (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>