<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.254541+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457251</id><title>Modeling movie-evoked human brain activity using motion-energy and space-time vision transformer features (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.254897+00:00</updated><author><name>Shinji Nishimoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, the process of building a model for predicting human brain activity under video viewing conditions was described as a part of an entry into the Algonauts Project 2021 Challenge. The model was designed to predict brain activity measured using functional MRI (fMRI) by weighted linear summations of the spatiotemporal visual features that appear in the video stimuli (video features). Two types of video features were used: (1) motion-energy features designed based on neurophysiological findings, and (2) features derived from a space-time vision transformer (TimeSformer). To utilize the features of various video domains, the features of the TimeSformer models pre-trained using several different movie sets were combined. Through these model building and validation processes, results showed that there is a certain correspondence between the hierarchical representation of the TimeSformer model and the hierarchical representation of the visual system in the brain. The motion-energy features are effective in predicting brain activity in the early visual areas, while TimeSformer-derived features are effective in higher-order visual areas, and a hybrid model that uses motion energy and TimeSformer features is effective for predicting whole brain activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.22.457251" rel="alternate" title="Modeling movie-evoked human brain activity using motion-energy and space-time vision transformer features (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457491</id><title>TREM2 regulates purinergic receptor-mediated calcium signaling and motility in human iPSC-derived microglia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.255130+00:00</updated><author><name>Amit Jairaman</name></author><author><name>Amanda McQuade</name></author><author><name>You Jung Kang</name></author><author><name>Alberto Granzotto</name></author><author><name>Jean Paul Chadarevian</name></author><author><name>Sunil Gandhi</name></author><author><name>Ian Parker</name></author><author><name>Ian Smith</name></author><author><name>Shivashankar Othy</name></author><author><name>Hansang Cho</name></author><author><name>Mathew Blurton-Jones</name></author><author><name>Michael Cahalan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The membrane protein TREM2 (Triggering Receptor Expressed on Myeloid cells 2) regulates key microglial functions including phagocytosis and chemotaxis. Loss-of-function variants of TREM2 are associated with increased risk of Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Because abnormalities in Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling have been observed in several AD models, we investigated TREM2 regulation of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling via genetic deletion in human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived microglia (iPSC- microglia). We found that iPSC-microglia lacking TREM2 (TREM2 KO) show exaggerated Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signals in response to purinergic agonists such as ADP that shape microglial injury responses. This ADP hypersensitivity, driven by increased expression of P2Y12 and P2Y13 receptors, results in sustained Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; influx and alters cell motility and process extension in TREM2 KO microglia. In a “Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; clamp” assay using iPSC-microglia expressing the genetically encoded Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; probe, Salsa6f, we found that cytosolic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; tunes motility to a greater extent in TREM2 KO microglia. Despite showing greater overall displacement, TREM2 KO microglia exhibit reduced directional chemotaxis along ADP gradients. Accordingly, the chemotactic defect in TREM2 KO microglia was rescued by reducing cytosolic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; using a P2Y12 receptor antagonist. Our results show that loss of TREM2 confers a defect in microglial Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; response to purinergic signals, suggesting a window of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; signaling for optimal microglial motility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457491" rel="alternate" title="TREM2 regulates purinergic receptor-mediated calcium signaling and motility in human iPSC-derived microglia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>