<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.844333+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.463730</id><title>Dual polarity voltage imaging reveals subthreshold dynamics and concurrent spiking patterns of multiple neuron-types (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.844857+00:00</updated><author><name>Madhuvanthi Kannan</name></author><author><name>Ganesh Vasan</name></author><author><name>Simon Haziza</name></author><author><name>Cheng Huang</name></author><author><name>Radek Chrapkiewicz</name></author><author><name>Junjie Luo</name></author><author><name>Jessica A Cardin</name></author><author><name>Mark J Schnitzer</name></author><author><name>Vincent A Pieribone</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetically encoded fluorescent voltage indicators are ideally suited to reveal the millisecond-scale interactions among and between distinct, targeted cell populations. However, current indicator families lack the requisite sensitivity for in vivo multipopulation imaging. We describe high-performance green and red sensors, Ace-mNeon2 and VARNAM2, and their reverse response-polarity variants, pAce and pAceR. Our indicators enable 0.4-1 kHz voltage recordings from &amp;gt;50 neurons per field-of-view in awake mice and ~30-min continuous imaging in flies. Using dual-polarity multiplexed imaging, we uncovered behavioral state-dependent interactions between distinct neocortical subclasses, as well as contributions to hippocampal field potentials from non-overlapping projection neuronal ensembles. By combining three mutually compatible indicators, we demonstrate concurrent triple-population voltage imaging. Our approach will empower investigations of the dynamic interplay between neuronal subclasses at single-spike resolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.463730" rel="alternate" title="Dual polarity voltage imaging reveals subthreshold dynamics and concurrent spiking patterns of multiple neuron-types (29 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.464400</id><title>Intratumoral and extratumoral synapses are required for glioblastoma progression in Drosophila (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.845379+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Losada-Perez</name></author><author><name>Mamen Hernandez Garcia-Moreno</name></author><author><name>Sergio Casas-Tinto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glioblastoma (GB) is the most aggressive, lethal and frequent primary brain tumor. It originates from glial cells and is characterized by rapid expansion through infiltration. GB cells interact with the microenvironment and healthy surrounding tissues, mostly neurons and vessels. GB cells project tumor microtubes (TMs) that contact with neurons and exchange signaling molecules related to Wingless/WNT, JNK, Insulin or Neuroligin-3 pathways. This cell to cell communication promotes GB expansion and neurodegeneration. Moreover, healthy neurons form glutamatergic functional synapses with GB cells which facilitate GB expansion and premature death in mouse GB xerograph models. Targeting signaling and synaptic components of GB progression may become a suitable strategy against glioblastoma. In a Drosophila GB model, we have determined the post-synaptic nature of GB cells with respect to neurons, and the contribution of post-synaptic genes expressed in GB cells to tumor progression. In addition, we document the presence of intratumoral synapses between GB cells, and the functional contribution of pre-synaptic genes to GB calcium dependent activity and expansion. Finally, we explore the relevance of synaptic genes in GB cells to the lifespan reduction caused by GB advance. Our results indicate that both presynaptic and postsynaptic proteins play a role in GB progression and lethality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.464400" rel="alternate" title="Intratumoral and extratumoral synapses are required for glioblastoma progression in Drosophila (16 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464098</id><title>The Hair Cell Analysis Toolbox: A machine learning-based whole cochlea analysis pipeline (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.845615+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher J. Buswinka</name></author><author><name>David B. Rosenberg</name></author><author><name>Artur A. Indzhykulian</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Auditory hair cells, the whole length of the cochlea, are routinely visualized using light microscopy techniques. It is common, therefore, for one to collect more data than is practical to analyze manually. There are currently no widely accepted tools for unsupervised, unbiased, and comprehensive analysis of cells in an entire cochlea. This represents a stark gap between image-based data and other tests of cochlear function. To close this gap, we present a machine learning-based hair cell analysis toolbox, for the analysis of whole cochleae, imaged with confocal microscopy. The software presented here allows the automation of common image analysis tasks such as counting hair cells, determining their best frequency, as well as quantifying single cell immunofluorescence intensities along the entire cochlear coil. We hope these automated tools will remove a considerable barrier in cochlear image analysis, allowing for more informative and less selective data analysis practices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464098" rel="alternate" title="The Hair Cell Analysis Toolbox: A machine learning-based whole cochlea analysis pipeline (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.15.464515</id><title>Spatial signatures of anesthesia-induced burst-suppression differ between primates and rodents (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.845810+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikoloz Sirmpilatze</name></author><author><name>Judith Mylius</name></author><author><name>Michael Ortiz-Rios</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Baudewig</name></author><author><name>Jaakko Paasonen</name></author><author><name>Daniel Golkowski</name></author><author><name>Andreas Ranft</name></author><author><name>Rüdiger Ilg</name></author><author><name>Olli Gröhn</name></author><author><name>Susann Boretius</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During deep anesthesia, the electroencephalographic (EEG) signal of the brain alternates between bursts of activity and periods of relative silence (suppressions). The origin of burst-suppression and its distribution across the brain remain matters of debate. In this work, we used functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to map the brain areas involved in anesthesia-induced burst-suppression across four mammalian species: humans, long-tailed macaques, common marmosets, and rats. At first, we determined the fMRI signatures of burst-suppression in human EEG-fMRI data. Applying this method to animal fMRI datasets, we found distinct burst-suppression signatures in all species. The burst-suppression maps revealed a marked inter-species difference: in rats the entire neocortex engaged in burst-suppression, while in primates most sensory areas were excluded—predominantly the primary visual cortex. We anticipate that the identified species-specific fMRI signatures and whole-brain maps will guide future targeted studies investigating the cellular and molecular mechanisms of burst-suppression in unconscious states.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.15.464515" rel="alternate" title="Spatial signatures of anesthesia-induced burst-suppression differ between primates and rodents (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.464590</id><title>TRPV1-lineage somatosensory fibers communicate with taste neurons in the mouse parabrachial nucleus (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.846028+00:00</updated><author><name>Jinrong Li</name></author><author><name>Md Sams Sazzad Ali</name></author><author><name>Christian H Lemon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trigeminal neurons supply somatosensation to craniofacial tissues. In mouse brain, ascending projections from medullary trigeminal neurons arrive at taste neurons in the autonomic parabrachial nucleus, suggesting taste neurons participate in somatosensory processing. However, the genetic cell types that support this convergence were undefined. Using Cre-directed optogenetics and in vivo neurophysiology in anesthetized mice of both sexes, here we studied whether TRPV1-lineage nociceptive and thermosensory fibers are primary neurons that drive trigeminal circuits reaching parabrachial taste cells. We monitored spiking activity in individual parabrachial neurons during photoexcitation of the terminals of TRPV1-lineage fibers that arrived at the dorsal spinal trigeminal nucleus pars caudalis, which relays orofacial somatosensory messages to the parabrachial area. Parabrachial neural responses to oral delivery of taste, chemesthetic, and thermal stimuli were also recorded. We found that optical excitation of TRPV1-lineage fibers frequently stimulated traditionally defined taste neurons in lateral parabrachial nuclei. The tuning of neurons across diverse tastes associated with their sensitivity to excitation of TRPV1-lineage fibers, which only sparingly engaged neurons oriented to preferred tastes like sucrose. Moreover, neurons that responded to photostimulation of TRPV1-lineage afferents showed strong responses to temperature including noxious heat, which predominantly excited parabrachial bitter taste cells. Multivariate analyses revealed the parabrachial confluence of TRPV1-lineage signals with taste captured sensory valence information shared across aversive gustatory, nociceptive, and thermal stimuli. Our results reveal that trigeminal fibers with defined roles in thermosensation and pain communicate with parabrachial taste neurons. This multisensory convergence supports dependencies between gustatory and somatosensory hedonic representations in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.464590" rel="alternate" title="TRPV1-lineage somatosensory fibers communicate with taste neurons in the mouse parabrachial nucleus (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>