<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.483244+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471435</id><title>Visual imagery vividness declines across the lifespan (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.483705+00:00</updated><author><name>Erzsébet Gulyás</name></author><author><name>Sára Sütöri</name></author><author><name>Andrea Lovas</name></author><author><name>Gergő Ziman</name></author><author><name>Ferenc Gombos</name></author><author><name>Ilona Kovács</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The capacity to elicit vivid visual mental images varies within an extensive range across individuals between hyper- and aphantasia. It is not clear, however, whether imagery vividness is constant across the lifespan or changes during development and later in life. Without enforcing the constraints of strict experimental procedures and representativity across the entire population, our purpose was to take a first look at the self-reported level of imagery vividness and determine the relative proportion of aphantasic/hyperphantasic participants in different age-groups. Relying on the frequently used Vividness of Visual Mental Imagery questionnaire, we collected data on a random sample of 2252 participants between the ages of 12 to 60 years. We found a novel developmental pattern describing a declining ability to elicit vivid visual mental images in the group averages of different age-groups from adolescence to middle age. This effect involves both a decreasing proportion of individuals with very vivid imagery and an increasing proportion of individuals with weak imagery as maturation (assessed by boneage estimations in adolescents) and aging progresses. This finding may help to shed light on yet unknown developmental mechanisms of our internal, stimulus-independent processes, and might also help to determine genetic, maturational, and age-dependent factors in the extreme cases of hyper- and aphantasia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471435" rel="alternate" title="Visual imagery vividness declines across the lifespan (45 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471432</id><title>Graded Variation In Cortical T1w/T2w Myelination During Adolescence (44 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.483962+00:00</updated><author><name>Graham L. Baum</name></author><author><name>John C. Flournoy</name></author><author><name>Matthew F. Glasser</name></author><author><name>Michael P. Harms</name></author><author><name>Patrick Mair</name></author><author><name>Ashley Sanders</name></author><author><name>Deanna M. Barch</name></author><author><name>Randy L. Buckner</name></author><author><name>Susan Bookheimer</name></author><author><name>Mirella Dapretto</name></author><author><name>Stephen Smith</name></author><author><name>Kathleen M. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Essa Yacoub</name></author><author><name>David C. Van Essen</name></author><author><name>Leah H. Somerville</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Myelination influences brain connectivity during sensitive periods of development by enhancing neural signaling speed and regulating synapse formation to reduce plasticity. However, &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; studies characterizing the maturational timing of cortical myelination during human development remain scant. Here, we take advantage of recent advances in high-resolution cortical T1w/T2w myelin mapping methods, including principled correction of B1+ transmit field effects, using data from the Human Connectome Project in Development (&lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt;=628, ages 8-21) to characterize the maturational timing of myelination from childhood through early adulthood throughout the cerebral neocortex. We apply Bayesian spline models and functional latent clustering analysis to demonstrate graded variation in the rate of cortical T1w/T2w myelin growth in neocortical areas that is strongly correlated with the sensorimotor-association (S-A) axis of cortical organization reported by others. In sensorimotor areas T1w/T2w myelin starts at high levels at early ages, increases at a fast pace, and decelerates at later ages (18-21). In intermediate multimodal areas along the S-A axis, T1w/T2w myelin tends to start at intermediate levels and increase linearly at an intermediate pace. In transmodal/paralimbic association areas high along the S-A axis, T1w/T2w myelin tends to start at low levels and increase linearly at the slowest pace. These data provide evidence for graded variation along the S-A axis in the rate of cortical myelination during adolescence, which could reflect ongoing plasticity underlying the development of complex information processing and psychological functioning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Myelin is a lipid membrane that is essential to healthy brain function. Myelin wraps axons to increase neural signaling speed, enabling complex neuronal functioning underlying learning and cognition. Here we characterize the developmental timing of myelination across the cerebral cortex during adolescence using recent advances in non-invasive myelin mapping. Our results provide new evidence demonstrating graded variation across the cortex in the timing of myelination during adolescence, with rapid myelination in lower-order sensory areas and gradual myelination in higher-order association areas. This spatial pattern of microstructural brain development closely parallels the sensorimotor-to-association axis of cortical organization and plasticity during ontogeny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471432" rel="alternate" title="Graded Variation In Cortical T1w/T2w Myelination During Adolescence (44 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471939</id><title>Preserved representations and decodability of diverse cognitive functions across the cortex, cerebellum, and subcortex (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484166+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomoya Nakai</name></author><author><name>Shinji Nishimoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Which part of the brain contributes to our complex cognitive processes? Studies have revealed contributions of the cerebellum and subcortex to higher-order cognitive functions; however it is unclear whether such functional representations are preserved across the cortex, cerebellum, and subcortex. In this study, we used functional magnetic resonance imaging data with 103 cognitive tasks and constructed three voxel-wise encoding and decoding models independently using cortical, cerebellar, and subcortical voxels. Representational similarity analysis revealed that the structure of task representations is preserved across the three brain parts. Principal component analysis visualized distinct organizations of abstract cognitive functions in each part of the cerebellum and subcortex. More than 90% of the cognitive tasks were decodable from the cerebellum and subcortical activities, even for the novel tasks not included in model training. Furthermore, we discovered that the cerebellum and subcortex have sufficient information to reconstruct activity in the cerebral cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471939" rel="alternate" title="Preserved representations and decodability of diverse cognitive functions across the cortex, cerebellum, and subcortex (38 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471897</id><title>Comparing Brain Asymmetries Independently of Brain Size (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484284+00:00</updated><author><name>Camille Michele WILLIAMS</name></author><author><name>Hugo Peyre</name></author><author><name>Roberto Toro</name></author><author><name>Franck Ramus</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Studies examining cerebral asymmetries typically divide the L-R Measure (e.g., Left-Right Volume) by the L+R Measure to obtain an Asymmetry Index (AI). However, contrary to widespread belief, such a division fails to render the AI independent from the L+R Measure and/or from total brain size. As a result, variations in brain size may bias correlation estimates with the AI or group differences in AI. We investigated how to analyze brain asymmetries in to distinguish global from regional effects, and report unbiased group differences in cerebral asymmetries. We analyzed the extent to which the L+R Measure, Total Cerebral Measure (TCM, e.g., Total Brain Volume), and L-R TCM predict regional asymmetries. As a case study, we assessed the consequences of omitting each of these predictors on the magnitude and significance of sex differences in asymmetries. We found that the L+R Measure, the TCM, and the L-R TCM predicted the AI of more than 89% of regions and that their relationships were generally linear. Removing any of these predictors changed the significance of sex differences in 33% of regions and the magnitude of sex differences across 13-42% of regions. Although we generally report similar sex and age effects on cerebral asymmetries to those of previous large-scale studies, properly adjusting for regional and global brain size revealed additional sex and age effects on brain asymmetry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471897" rel="alternate" title="Comparing Brain Asymmetries Independently of Brain Size (18 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471484</id><title>BDNF-dependent modulation of axonal transport is selectively impaired in ALS (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484411+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew P. Tosolini</name></author><author><name>James N. Sleigh</name></author><author><name>Sunaina Surana</name></author><author><name>Elena R. Rhymes</name></author><author><name>Stephen D. Cahalan</name></author><author><name>Giampietro Schiavo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Axonal transport ensures long-range delivery of essential cargoes between proximal and distal compartments of neurons, and is needed for neuronal development, function, and survival. Deficits in axonal transport have been detected at pre-symptomatic stages in mouse models of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), suggesting that impairments are fundamental for disease pathogenesis. However, the precise mechanisms responsible for the transport deficits and whether they preferentially affect α-motor neuron (MN) subtypes remain unresolved. Here, we report that stimulation of wild-type neurons with brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) enhances trafficking of signalling endosomes specifically in fast MNs (FMNs). In early symptomatic SOD1&lt;sup&gt;G93A&lt;/sup&gt; mice, FMNs display selective impairment of axonal transport and develop an insensitivity to BDNF stimulation, with pathology upregulating classical non-pro-survival receptors in muscles and sciatic nerves. Altogether, these data indicate that cell- and non-cell autonomous BDNF signalling is impaired in vulnerable SOD1&lt;sup&gt;G93A&lt;/sup&gt; MNs, thus identifying a new key deficit in ALS amenable for future therapeutic interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471484" rel="alternate" title="BDNF-dependent modulation of axonal transport is selectively impaired in ALS (18 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472000</id><title>Pharmacologic analysis of non-synonymous coding 5-HT2A SNPs reveals alterations psychedelic drug potencies and efficacies (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484548+00:00</updated><author><name>Gavin P. Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Manish K. Jain</name></author><author><name>Samuel T. Slocum</name></author><author><name>Bryan L. Roth</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Serotonin (5-Hydroxytryptamine; 5-HT) 2A receptor (5-HT&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R) signaling is essential for the actions of classical psychedelic drugs. In this study, we examined whether random sequence variations in the gene (single nucleotide polymorphisms, SNPs) encoding the 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R affect the signaling of four commonly used psychedelic drugs. We examined the &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; pharmacology of seven non-synonymous SNPs, which give rise to S12N, T25N, D48N, I197V, A230T, A447V, and H452Y variant 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt; serotonin receptors. We found that these non-synonymous SNPs exert statistically significant, although modest, effects on the efficacy and potency of four therapeutically relevant hallucinogens. Significantly, the &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; pharmacological effects of the SNPs drug actions at 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;2A&lt;/sub&gt;R are drug specific.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Table of Contents/Abstract Graphic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472000v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472000" rel="alternate" title="Pharmacologic analysis of non-synonymous coding 5-HT2A SNPs reveals alterations psychedelic drug potencies and efficacies (14 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471649</id><title>Rewarded extinction increases amygdalar connectivity and stabilizes long-term memory traces in the vmPFC (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484672+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicole E. Keller</name></author><author><name>Augustin C. Hennings</name></author><author><name>Emily K. Leiker</name></author><author><name>Jarrod A. Lewis-Peacock</name></author><author><name>Joseph E. Dunsmoor</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neurobiological evidence in rodents indicates that threat extinction incorporates reward neurocircuitry. Consequently, incorporating reward associations with an extinction memory may be an effective strategy to persistently attenuate threat responses. Moreover, while there is considerable research on the short-term effects of extinction strategies in humans, the long-term effects of extinction are rarely considered. In a within-subjects fMRI study, we compared counterconditioning (a form of rewarded-extinction) to standard extinction, at recent (24 hours) and remote (~1 month) retrieval tests. Relative to standard extinction, counterconditioning diminished 24-hour relapse of arousal and threat expectancy, and reduced activity in brain regions associated with the appraisal and expression of threat (e.g., thalamus, insula, periaqueductal gray). The retrieval of reward-associated extinction memory was accompanied by functional connectivity between the amygdala and the ventral striatum, whereas the retrieval of standard-extinction memories was associated with connectivity between the amygdala and ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC). One-month later, the retrieval of both standard- and rewarded-extinction was associated with amygdala-vmPFC connectivity. However, only rewarded extinction created a stable memory trace in the vmPFC, identified through overlapping multivariate patterns of fMRI activity from extinction to 24-hour and 1-month retrieval. These findings provide new evidence that reward may generate a more stable and enduring memory trace of attenuated threat in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471649" rel="alternate" title="Rewarded extinction increases amygdalar connectivity and stabilizes long-term memory traces in the vmPFC (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471883</id><title>Shared mechanisms of auditory and non-auditory vocal learning in the songbird brain (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484799+00:00</updated><author><name>James McGregor</name></author><author><name>Abigail Grassler</name></author><author><name>Paul I. Jaffe</name></author><author><name>Amanda Louise Jacob</name></author><author><name>Michael Brainard</name></author><author><name>Samuel J Sober</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Songbirds and humans share the ability to adaptively modify their vocalizations based on sensory feedback. Prior studies have focused primarily on the role that auditory feedback plays in shaping vocal output throughout life. In contrast, it is unclear whether and how non-auditory information drives vocal plasticity. Here, we first used a reinforcement learning paradigm to establish that non-auditory feedback can drive vocal learning in adult songbirds. We then assessed the role of a songbird basal ganglia-thalamocortical pathway critical to auditory vocal learning in this novel form of vocal plasticity. We found that both this circuit and its dopaminergic inputs are necessary for non-auditory vocal learning, demonstrating that this pathway is not specialized exclusively for auditory-driven vocal learning. The ability of this circuit to use both auditory and non-auditory information to guide vocal learning may reflect a general principle for the neural systems that support vocal plasticity across species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471883" rel="alternate" title="Shared mechanisms of auditory and non-auditory vocal learning in the songbird brain (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471139</id><title>Vestibular Agnosia is linked to abnormal functional brain networks (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.484933+00:00</updated><author><name>Zaeem Hadi</name></author><author><name>Yuscah Pondeca</name></author><author><name>Elena Calzolari</name></author><author><name>Mariya Chepisheva</name></author><author><name>Rebecca M Smith</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Mahmud</name></author><author><name>Heiko Rust</name></author><author><name>David J Sharp</name></author><author><name>Barry M Seemungal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Activation of the peripheral vestibular apparatus simultaneously elicits a reflex vestibular nystagmus and the vestibular perception of self-motion (vestibular-motion perception) or vertigo. In a newly characterised condition called Vestibular Agnosia found in conditions with disrupted brain network connectivity, e.g. traumatic brain injury (TBI) or neurodegeneration (Parkinson’s Disease), the link between vestibular reflex and perception is uncoupled, such that, peripheral vestibular activation elicits a vestibular ocular reflex nystagmus but without vertigo. Using structural brain imaging in acute traumatic brain injury, we recently linked vestibular agnosia to postural imbalance via disrupted right temporal white-matter circuits (inferior longitudinal fasciculus), however no white-matter tracts were specifically linked to vestibular agnosia. Given the relative difficulty in localizing the neuroanatomical correlates of vestibular-motion perception, and compatible with current theories of human consciousness (viz. the Global Neuronal Workspace Theory), we postulate that vestibular-motion perception (vertigo) is mediated by the coordinated interplay between fronto-parietal circuits linked to whole-brain broadcasting of the vestibular signal of self-motion. We thus used resting state functional MRI (rsfMRI) to map functional brain networks and hence test our postulate of an anterior-posterior cortical network mediating vestibular agnosia. Whole-brain rsfMRI was acquired from 39 prospectively recruited acute TBI patients (and 37 matched controls) with preserved peripheral and reflex vestibular function, along with self-motion perceptual thresholds during passive yaw rotations in the dark, and posturography. Following quality control of the brain imaging, 25 TBI patients’ images were analyzed. We classified 11 TBI patients with vestibular agnosia and 14 without vestibular agnosia based on laboratory testing of self-motion perception. Using independent component analysis, we found altered functional connectivity within posterior (right superior longitudinal fasciculus) and anterior networks (left rostral prefrontal cortex) in vestibular agnosia. Regions of interest analyses showed both inter-hemispheric and intra-hemispheric (left anterior-posterior) network disruption in vestibular agnosia. Assessing the brain regions linked via right inferior longitudinal fasciculus, a tract linked to vestibular agnosia in unbalanced patients (but now controlled for postural imbalance), seed-based analyses showed altered connectivity between higher order visual cortices involved in motion perception and mid-temporal regions. In conclusion, vestibular agnosia in our patient group is mediated by multiple brain network dysfunction, involving primarily left frontal and bilateral posterior networks. Understanding the brain mechanisms of vestibular agnosia provide both an insight into the physiological mechanisms of vestibular perception as well as an opportunity to diagnose and monitor vestibular cognitive deficits in brain disease such as TBI and neurodegeneration linked to imbalance and spatial disorientation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471139" rel="alternate" title="Vestibular Agnosia is linked to abnormal functional brain networks (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471196</id><title>Sleep Dependent Changes of Lactate Concentration in Human Brain (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485081+00:00</updated><author><name>Selda Yildiz</name></author><author><name>Miranda M. Lim</name></author><author><name>Manoj K. Sammi</name></author><author><name>Katherine Powers</name></author><author><name>Charles F. Murchison</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Iliff</name></author><author><name>William D. Rooney</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lactate is an important cellular metabolite that is present at high concentrations in the brain, both within cells and in the extracellular space between cells. Small animal studies demonstrated high extracellular concentrations of lactate during wakefulness with reductions during sleep and/or anesthesia with a recent study suggesting the glymphatic activity as the mechanism for the reduction of lactate concentrations. We have recently developed a rigorous non-invasive imaging approach combining simultaneous magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) and polysomnography (PSG) measurements, and here, we present the first &lt;italic&gt;in-vivo&lt;/italic&gt; evaluation of brain lactate levels during sleep-wake cycles in young healthy humans. First, we collected single voxel proton MRS (1H-MRS) data at the posterior cingulate with high temporal resolution (every 7.5 sec), and simultaneously recorded PSG data while temporally registering with &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H-MRS time-series. Second, we evaluated PSG data in 30 s epochs, and classified into four stages Wake (W), Non-REM sleep stage 1 (N1), Non-REM sleep stage 2 (N2), and Non-REM sleep stage 3 (N3). Third, we determined lactate signal intensity from each 7.5-s spectrum, normalized to corresponding water signal, and averaged over 30-s for each PSG epoch. In examinations of nine healthy participants (four females, five males; mean age 24.2 (±2; SD) years; age range: 21-27 years) undergoing up to 3-hour simultaneous MRS/PSG recordings, we observed a group mean reduction of [4.9 ± 4.9] % in N1, [10.4 ± 5.2] % in N2, and [24.0 ± 5.8] % in N3 when compared to W. Our finding is consistent with more than 70 years of invasive lactate measurements from small animal studies. In addition, reduced brain lactate was accompanied by a significant reduction the apparent diffusion coefficient of brain lactate. Taken together, these findings are consistent with the loss of lactate from the extracellular space during sleep while suggesting lactate metabolism is altered and/or lactate clearance via glymphatic exchange is increased during sleep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study describes a non-invasive magnetic resonance spectroscopy/polysomnography technique that allows rigorous measurement of brain metabolite levels together with simultaneous characterization of brain arousal state as either wakeful or one of the several sleep states. The results provide the first &lt;italic&gt;in-vivo&lt;/italic&gt; demonstration of reductions in brain lactate concentration and diffusivity during sleep versus wakefulness in young healthy human brain. These findings are consistent with invasive small-animal studies showing the loss of extracellular lactate during sleep, and support the notion of altered lactate metabolism and/or increased glymphatic activity in sleeping human brain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471196" rel="alternate" title="Sleep Dependent Changes of Lactate Concentration in Human Brain (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471210</id><title>Effects of stimulus pulse rate on somatosensory adaptation in the human cortex (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485217+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher L Hughes</name></author><author><name>Sharlene N Flesher</name></author><author><name>Robert A Gaunt</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intracortical microstimulation (ICMS) of the somatosensory cortex can restore sensation to people with neurological diseases. However, many aspects of ICMS are poorly understood, including the effect of continuous stimulation on percept intensity over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we evaluate how tactile percepts, evoked by ICMS in the somatosensory cortex of a human participant adapt over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We delivered continuous and intermittent ICMS to the somatosensory cortex and assessed the reported intensity of tactile percepts over time in a human participant. Experiments were conducted across approximately one year and linear mixed effects models were used to assess significance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuous stimulation at high frequencies led to rapid decreases in intensity, while low frequency stimulation maintained percept intensity for longer periods. Burst-modulated stimulation extended the time before the intensity began to decrease, but all protocols ultimately resulted in complete sensation loss within one minute. Intermittent stimulation paradigms with several seconds between stimulus trains also led to decreases in intensity on many electrodes, but never resulted in extinction of sensation after over three minutes of stimulation. Additionally, longer breaks between each pulse train resulted in some recovery of the stimulus-evoked percepts. For several electrodes, intermittent stimulation had almost no effect on the perceived intensity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intermittent ICMS paradigms were more effective at maintaining percepts, and given that transient activity in the somatosensory cortex dominates the response to object contact, this stimulation method may mimic natural cortical activity and improve the perception of stimulation over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471210" rel="alternate" title="Effects of stimulus pulse rate on somatosensory adaptation in the human cortex (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471232</id><title>Met/HGFR triggers detrimental reactive microglia in TBI (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485331+00:00</updated><author><name>Rida Rehman</name></author><author><name>Michael Miller</name></author><author><name>Sruthi Sankari Krishnamurthy</name></author><author><name>Jacob Kjell</name></author><author><name>Lobna Elsayed</name></author><author><name>Florian olde Heuvel</name></author><author><name>Alison Conquest</name></author><author><name>Akila Chandrasekar</name></author><author><name>Albert Ludolph</name></author><author><name>Tobias Boeckers</name></author><author><name>Medhanie A Mulaw</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Goetz</name></author><author><name>Maria Cristina Morganti-Kossmann</name></author><author><name>Aya Takeoka</name></author><author><name>Francesco Roselli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The complexity of the signaling events, cellular responses unfolding in neuronal, glial and immune cells upon Traumatic brain injury (TBI) constitutes an obstacle in elucidating pathophysiological links and targets for intervention. We used array phosphoproteomics in a murine mild blunt TBI to reconstruct the temporal dynamics of tyrosine-kinase signaling in TBI and then to scrutinize the large-scale effects of the perturbation of cMet/HGFR, VEGFR1 and Btk signaling by small molecules. cMet/HGFR emerged as a selective modifier of the early microglial response, and cMet/HGFR blockade prevented the induction of microglial inflammatory mediators, of reactive microglia morphology and of TBI-associated responses in neurons, vessels and brain extracellular matrix. Acute or prolonged cMet/HGFR inhibition ameliorated neuronal survival and motor recovery. Early elevation of HGF itself in the CSF of TBI patients suggest that this mechanism has translational value in human subjects. Our findings identify cMet/HGFR as a modulator of early neuroinflammation in TBI with translational potential and indicate several RTK families as possible additional targets for TBI treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controlling neuroinflammation in neurotrauma is an important but unachieved goal. This study exploits a moderate TBI model and array-based proteomics to identify cMet as a new inducer of reactive microglia. A small-molecule inhibitor of cMet contains microglial reactivity, reduces neuronal and vascular alterations, limits behavioural disturbances and accelerates recovery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Met is activated in microglia upon TBI and drives microglial reactivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Met inhibitor reduces motor dysfunction upon TBI and promotes recovery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blockade of MET prevents the appearance of a reactive microglia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cMET inhibitor reduces the sub-acute neuronal loss after TBI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471232" rel="alternate" title="Met/HGFR triggers detrimental reactive microglia in TBI (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.470276</id><title>Finger stability in precision grips (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485517+00:00</updated><author><name>Neelima Sharma</name></author><author><name>Madhusudhan Venkadesan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stable precision grips using the fingertips are a cornerstone of human hand dexterity. Occasionally, however, our fingers become unstable and snap into a hyper-extended posture. This is because multi-link mechanisms, like our fingers, can buckle under tip forces. Suppressing this instability is crucial for hand dexterity, but how the neuromuscular system does so is unknown. Here we show that finger stability is due to the stiffness from muscle contraction and likely not feedback control. We recorded maximal force application with the index finger and found that most buckling events lasted less than 50ms, too fast for sensorimotor feedback to act. However, a biomechanical model of the finger predicted that muscle-induced stiffness is also insufficient for stability at maximal force unless we add springs to stiffen the joints. We tested this prediction in 39 volunteers. Upon adding stiffness, maximal force increased by 34±3%, and muscle electromyography readings were 21±3% higher for the finger flexors (mean±standard error). Hence, people refrain from applying truly maximal force unless an external stabilizing stiffness allows their muscles to apply higher force without losing stability. Muscle recordings and mathematical modeling show that the splint offloads the demand for muscle co-contraction and this reduced co-contraction with the splint underlies the increase in force. But more stiffness is not always better. Stiff fingers would interfere the ability to passively adapt to complex object geometries and precisely regulate force. Thus, our results show how hand function arises from neurally tuned muscle stiffness that balances finger stability with compliance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.470276" rel="alternate" title="Finger stability in precision grips (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.471894</id><title>An epitope specific patient-derived LGI1-autoantibody enhances neuronal excitability by modulating the Kv1.1 channel. (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485629+00:00</updated><author><name>Johanna Extrémet</name></author><author><name>Oussama El Far</name></author><author><name>Sarosh R Irani</name></author><author><name>Dominique Debanne</name></author><author><name>Michael Russier</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Leucine-rich Glioma Inactivated protein 1 (LGI1) is expressed in the central nervous and genetic loss of function is associated with epileptic disorders. Also, patients with LGI1-directed autoantibodies have frequent focal seizures as a key feature of their disease. LGI1 is composed of a Leucine Rich Repeat (LRR) and an Epitempin (EPTP) domain. These domains are reported to interact with different aspects of the transsynaptic complex formed by LGI1 at excitatory synapses, including presynaptic Kv1 potassium channels. Patient-derived monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) are ideal reagents to study whether domain-specific LGI1-autoantibodies induce epileptiform activities in neurons, and their downstream mechanisms. To address this question, we measured the intrinsic excitability of CA3 pyramidal neurons in organotypic cultures from rat hippocampus treated with either a LRR- or an EPTP- reactive patient-derived mAb. The antibodies induced changes in neuronal intrinsic excitability which led us to measure their effects on Kv1-type potassium currents. We found an increase of intrinsic excitability correlated with a reduction of the sensitivity to a selective Kv1.1-channel blocker in neurons treated with the LRR mAb compared to the control, but not in neurons treated with the EPTP mAb. Our findings suggest LRR mAbs are able to modulate neuronal excitability that could account for epileptiform activities observed in patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.471894" rel="alternate" title="An epitope specific patient-derived LGI1-autoantibody enhances neuronal excitability by modulating the Kv1.1 channel. (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471336</id><title>A tool for the in vivo gating of gene expression in neurons using the co-occurrence of neural activity and light (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485757+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam T. Vogel</name></author><author><name>Shelley J. Russek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advancements in genetically based technologies have begun to allow us to better understand the relationships between underlying neural activity and the patterns of measurable behavior that can be reproducibly studied in the laboratory. As this field develops, there are key limitations to the currently available technologies hindering their full potential to deliver meaningful datasets. The limitations which are most critical to advancement of these technologies in behavioral neuroscience are: the temporal resolution at which physiological events can be windowed, the divergent molecular pathways in signal transduction that introduce ambiguity into the output of activity sensors, and the impractical size of the genetic material that requires 3-4 separate AAV vectors to deliver a fully functional system into a cell. To address these limitations and help bring the potential of these types of technologies into better realization, we have engineered a nucleus localized light-sensitive Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-dependent gene expression system based on AsLOV&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and the downstream responsive element antagonist modulator (DREAM). The design and engineering of each component was performed in such a way to: 1) preserve behaviorally relevant temporal dynamics, 2) preserve signal fidelity appropriate for studying experience-driven neural activity patterns and their relationship to specific animal responses, and 3) have full delivery of the genetic material via a single AAV vector. The system was tested in vitro and subsequently &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; with neural activity induced by Channelrhodopsin and could be used in the future with behaviorally-driven neural activity. To our knowledge this is the first optogenetic tool for the practical use of linking activity-dependent gene activation in response to direct nuclear calcium transduction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471336" rel="alternate" title="A tool for the in vivo gating of gene expression in neurons using the co-occurrence of neural activity and light (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.471989</id><title>miR-124 regulates Notch and NeuroD1 to mediate transition states of neuronal development (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.485868+00:00</updated><author><name>Kalin Diane Konrad</name></author><author><name>Jia L. Song</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MicroRNAs (miRNAs) regulate gene expression by destabilizing target mRNA and/or inhibiting translation in animal cells. The ability to mechanistically dissect the function of miR-124 during specification, differentiation, and maturation of neurons during development within a single system has not been accomplished. Using the sea urchin (Strongylocentrotus purpuratus) embryo, we take advantage of the manipulability of the embryo and its well-documented gene regulatory networks (GRNs). We incorporated NeuroD1 as part of the sea urchin neuronal GRN and determined that miR-124 inhibition resulted in decreased gut contractions, swimming velocity, and neuronal development. We further integrated post-transcriptional regulation of miR-124 into the neuronal GRN. Inhibition of miR-124 resulted in increased number of cells expressing transcription factors associated with progenitor neurons and a concurrent decrease of mature and functional neurons. Results revealed that miR-124 regulates undefined factors early in neurogenesis during neuronal specification and differentiation in the early blastula and gastrula stages. In the late gastrula and larval stages, miR-124 regulates Notch and NeuroD1. Specifically, miR-124 regulates the transition between neuronal differentiation and maturation, by directly suppressing NeuroD1. Removal of miR-124	″s suppression of NeuroD1 results in increased mature neurons with decreased Synaptagmin B-positive mature, functional neurons. By removing both miR-124 suppression of NeuroD1 and Notch, we were able to phenocopy miR-124 inhibitor induced defects. Overall, we have improved the neuronal GRN and identified miR-124 to play a prolific role in regulating various transitions of neuronal development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.471989" rel="alternate" title="miR-124 regulates Notch and NeuroD1 to mediate transition states of neuronal development (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471653</id><title>Analysis of visual processing capabilities and neural coding strategies of a detailed model for laminar cortical microcircuits in mouse V1 (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.486264+00:00</updated><author><name>Guozhang Chen</name></author><author><name>Franz Scherr</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Maass</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The neocortex is a network of rather stereotypical cortical microcircuits that share an exquisite genetically encoded architecture: Neurons of a fairly large number of different types are distributed over several layers (laminae), with specific probabilities of synaptic connections that depend on the neuron types involved and their spatial locations. Most available knowledge about this structure has been compiled into a detailed model [Billeh et al., 2020] for a generic cortical microcircuit in the primary visual cortex, consisting of 51,978 neurons of 111 different types. We add a noise model to the network that is based on experimental data, and analyze the results of network computations that can be extracted by projection neurons on layer 5. We show that the resulting model acquires through alignment of its synaptic weights via gradient descent training the capability to carry out a number of demanding visual processing tasks. Furthermore, this weight-alignment induces specific neural coding features in the microcircuit model that match those found in the living brain: High dimensional neural codes with an arguably close to optimal power-law decay of explained variance of PCA components, specific relations between signal- and noise-coding dimensions, and network dynamics in a critical regime. Hence these important features of neural coding and dynamics of cortical microcircuits in the brain are likely to emerge from aspects of their genetically encoded architecture that are captured by this data-based model in combination with learning processes. In addition, the model throws new light on the relation between visual processing capabilities and details of neural coding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471653" rel="alternate" title="Analysis of visual processing capabilities and neural coding strategies of a detailed model for laminar cortical microcircuits in mouse V1 (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471796</id><title>Drosophila gustatory projections are segregated by taste modality and connectivity (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.486410+00:00</updated><author><name>Stefanie Engert</name></author><author><name>Gabriella R. Sterne</name></author><author><name>David T. Harris</name></author><author><name>Kristin Scott</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gustatory sensory neurons detect caloric and harmful compounds in potential food and convey this information to the brain to inform feeding decisions. To examine the signals that gustatory neurons transmit and receive, we reconstructed gustatory axons and their synaptic sites in the adult &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt; brain, utilizing a whole-brain electron microscopy volume. We reconstructed 87 gustatory projections from the proboscis labellum in the right hemisphere and 57 in the left, representing the majority of labellar gustatory axons. Morphology- and connectivity-based clustering revealed six distinct clusters, likely representing neurons recognizing different taste modalities. Gustatory neurons contain a nearly equal number of interspersed pre-and post-synaptic sites, with extensive synaptic connectivity among gustatory axons. The vast majority of synaptic connections are between morphologically similar neurons, although connections also exist between distinct neuronal subpopulations. This study resolves the anatomy of labellar gustatory projections, reveals that gustatory projections are likely segregated based on taste modality, and uncovers synaptic connections that may alter the transmission of gustatory signals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471796" rel="alternate" title="Drosophila gustatory projections are segregated by taste modality and connectivity (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471521</id><title>Distributed Feedforward and Feedback Processing across Perisylvian Cortex Supports Human Speech (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.486553+00:00</updated><author><name>Ran Wang</name></author><author><name>Xupeng Chen</name></author><author><name>Amirhossein Khalilian-Gourtani</name></author><author><name>Leyao Yu</name></author><author><name>Patricia Dugan</name></author><author><name>Daniel Friedman</name></author><author><name>Werner Doyle</name></author><author><name>Orrin Devinsky</name></author><author><name>Yao Wang</name></author><author><name>Adeen Flinker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Speech production is a complex human function requiring continuous feedforward commands together with reafferent feedback processing. These processes are carried out by distinct frontal and posterior cortical networks, but the degree and timing of their recruitment and dynamics remain unknown. We present a novel deep learning architecture that translates neural signals recorded directly from cortex to an interpretable representational space that can reconstruct speech. We leverage state-of-the-art learnt decoding networks to disentangle feedforward vs. feedback processing. Unlike prevailing models, we find a mixed cortical architecture in which frontal and temporal networks each process both feedforward and feedback information in tandem. We elucidate the timing of feedforward and feedback related processing by quantifying the derived receptive fields. Our approach provides evidence for a surprisingly mixed cortical architecture of speech circuitry together with decoding advances that have important implications for neural prosthetics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471521" rel="alternate" title="Distributed Feedforward and Feedback Processing across Perisylvian Cortex Supports Human Speech (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471391</id><title>Molecular Mechanisms of Neurotransmitter Release Control Distinct Features of Sensory Coding Reliability (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.486749+00:00</updated><author><name>Eyal Rozenfeld</name></author><author><name>Nadine Ehmann</name></author><author><name>Julia E. Manoim</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Kittel</name></author><author><name>Moshe Parnas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A key requirement for the repeated identification of a stimulus is a reliable neural representation each time it is encountered. Neural coding is often considered to rely on two major coding schemes: the firing rate of action potentials, known as rate coding, and the precise timing of action potentials, known as temporal coding. Synaptic transmission is the major mechanism of information transfer between neurons. While theoretical studies have examined the effects of neurotransmitter release probability on neural code reliability, it has not yet been addressed how different components of the release machinery affect coding of physiological stimuli &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Here, we use the first synapse of the &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila&lt;/italic&gt; olfactory system to show that the reliability of the neural code is sensitive to perturbations of specific presynaptic proteins controlling distinct stages of neurotransmitter release. Notably, the presynaptic manipulations decreased coding reliability of postsynaptic neurons only at high odor intensity. We further show that while the reduced temporal code reliability arises from monosynaptic effects, the reduced rate code reliability arises from circuit effects, which include the recruitment of inhibitory local neurons. Finally, we find that reducing neural coding reliability decreases behavioral reliability of olfactory stimulus classification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471391" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Mechanisms of Neurotransmitter Release Control Distinct Features of Sensory Coding Reliability (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471089</id><title>Human neural networks with sparse TDP-43 pathology reveal NPTX2 misregulation in ALS/FTLD (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.486967+00:00</updated><author><name>Marian Hruska-Plochan</name></author><author><name>Katharina M. Betz</name></author><author><name>Silvia Ronchi</name></author><author><name>Vera I. Wiersma</name></author><author><name>Zuzanna Maniecka</name></author><author><name>Eva-Maria Hock</name></author><author><name>Florent Laferriere</name></author><author><name>Sonu Sahadevan</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Hoop</name></author><author><name>Igor Delvendahl</name></author><author><name>Martina Panatta</name></author><author><name>Alexander van der Bourg</name></author><author><name>Dasa Bohaciakova</name></author><author><name>Karl Frontzek</name></author><author><name>Adriano Aguzzi</name></author><author><name>Tammaryn Lashley</name></author><author><name>Mark D. Robinson</name></author><author><name>Theofanis Karayannis</name></author><author><name>Martin Mueller</name></author><author><name>Andreas Hierlemann</name></author><author><name>Magdalini Polymenidou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human cellular models of neurodegeneration require reproducibility and longevity, which is necessary for simulating these age-dependent diseases. Such systems are particularly needed for TDP-43 proteinopathies&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;, which involve human-specific mechanisms&lt;sup&gt;3–6&lt;/sup&gt; that cannot be directly studied in animal models. To explore the emergence and consequences of TDP-43 pathologies, we generated iPSC-derived, colony morphology neural stem cells (iCoMoNSCs) via manual selection of neural precursors&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;. Single-cell transcriptomics (scRNA-seq) and comparison to independent NSCs&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;, showed that iCoMoNSCs are uniquely homogenous and self-renewing. Differentiated iCoMoNSCs formed a self-organized multicellular system consisting of synaptically connected and electrophysiologically active neurons, which matured into long-lived functional networks. Neuronal and glial maturation in iCoMoNSC-derived cultures was similar to that of cortical organoids&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;. Overexpression of wild-type TDP-43 in a minority of iCoMoNSC-derived neurons led to progressive fragmentation and aggregation, resulting in loss of function and neurotoxicity. scRNA-seq revealed a novel set of misregulated RNA targets coinciding in both TDP-43 overexpressing neurons and patient brains exhibiting loss of nuclear TDP-43. The strongest misregulated target encoded for the synaptic protein NPTX2, which was consistently misaccumulated in ALS and FTLD patient neurons with TDP-43 pathology. Our work directly links TDP-43 misregulation and NPTX2 accumulation, thereby highlighting a new pathway of neurotoxicity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471089" rel="alternate" title="Human neural networks with sparse TDP-43 pathology reveal NPTX2 misregulation in ALS/FTLD (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471856</id><title>Multi-taskLearning and Ensemble Approach to Predict Cognitive Scores for Patients with Alzheimer's Disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.487426+00:00</updated><author><name>Daren Ma</name></author><author><name>Christabelle Pabalan</name></author><author><name> Akanksha</name></author><author><name>Yannet Interian</name></author><author><name>Ashish Raj</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this research was to explore the efficacy of integrating 1) using multi-task learning, 2) neuroimaging data and common risk factors to predict the ADAS-cog 11 score in Alzheimer's patients. We studied the magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans of 798 participants ranging between 0 and 96 months from the initial diagnosis. This enabled us to exploit the benefits of the U-Net architecture, a structure historically known to perform well on medical imaging tasks using limited data with heavy image augmentations. The multi-task model simultaneously performed segmentation of white matter, gray matter, and cerebrospinal fluid on the MRI input and regression to predict the ADAS-cog 11 score. There is a body of literature highlighting the independent relationships between gray and white matter volumes and dementia severity; the trajectory was to explore if the multi-task model structure for these interrelated tasks would boost performance for each individual task. The final model integrates the deep learning results with a Gradient Boosting model trained on demographic data. A considerable performance improvement from the initial multi-task U-Net on the ADAS-cog 11 prediction task was achieved across our experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471856" rel="alternate" title="Multi-taskLearning and Ensemble Approach to Predict Cognitive Scores for Patients with Alzheimer's Disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471862</id><title>Escape Steering by Cholecystokinin Peptidergic Signaling (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.487564+00:00</updated><author><name>Lili Chen</name></author><author><name>Yuting Liu</name></author><author><name>Pan Su</name></author><author><name>Wesley Hung</name></author><author><name>Haiwen Li</name></author><author><name>Ya Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhongpu Yue</name></author><author><name>Minghai Ge</name></author><author><name>Zhengxing Wu</name></author><author><name>Yan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Peng Fei</name></author><author><name>Li-Ming Chen</name></author><author><name>Louis Tao</name></author><author><name>Heng Mao</name></author><author><name>Mei Zhen</name></author><author><name>Shangbang Gao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Escape is an evolutionarily conserved and essential avoidance response. Considered to be innate, most studies on escape responses focused on hard-wired circuits. We report here that peptidergic signaling is an integral and necessary component of the &lt;italic&gt;Caenorhabditis elegans&lt;/italic&gt; escape circuit. Combining genetic screening, electrophysiology and calcium imaging, we reveal that a neuropeptide NLP-18 and its cholecystokinin receptor CKR-1 enable the escape circuit to execute a full omega (Ω) turn, the last motor step where the animal robustly steers away from its original trajectory. We demonstrate &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; that CKR-1 is a Gα&lt;sub&gt;q&lt;/sub&gt; protein coupled receptor for NLP-18. &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;, NLP-18 is mainly secreted by the gustatory sensory neuron (ASI) to activate CKR-1 in the head motor neuron (SMD) and the turn-initiating interneuron (AIB). Removal of NLP-18, removal of CKR-1, or specific knockdown of CKR-1 in SMD or AIB neurons lead to shallower turns hence less robust escape steering. Consistently, elevation of head motor neuron (SMD)’s Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; transients during escape steering is attenuated upon the removal of NLP-18 or CKR-1. &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt;, synthetic NLP-18 directly evokes CKR-1-dependent currents in oocytes and CKR-1-dependent Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; transients in SMD. Thus, cholecystokinin signaling modulates an escape circuit to generate robust escape steering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471862" rel="alternate" title="Escape Steering by Cholecystokinin Peptidergic Signaling (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471434</id><title>Neuronal population activity dynamics reveal a low-dimensional signature of operant learning (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.487825+00:00</updated><author><name>Renan M. Costa</name></author><author><name>Douglas A. Baxter</name></author><author><name>John H. Byrne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Learning engages a high-dimensional neuronal population space spanning multiple brain regions. We identified a low-dimensional signature associated with operant conditioning, a ubiquitous form of learning in which animals learn from the consequences of behavior. Using single-neuron resolution voltage imaging, we identified two low-dimensional motor modules in the neuronal population underlying &lt;italic&gt;Aplysia&lt;/italic&gt; feeding. Our findings point to a temporal shift in module recruitment as the primary signature of operant learning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471434" rel="alternate" title="Neuronal population activity dynamics reveal a low-dimensional signature of operant learning (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471371</id><title>Task-dependent switching of feedback controllers (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.488218+00:00</updated><author><name>Justinas Česonis</name></author><author><name>David W. Franklin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The separation of distinct motor memories by contextual cues is a well known and well studied phenomenon of feedforward human motor control. However, there is no clear evidence of such context-induced separation in feedback control. Here we test both experimentally and computationally if context-dependent switching of feedback controllers is possible in the human motor system. Specifically, we probe visuomotor feedback responses of our human participants in two different tasks – stop and hit – and under two different schedules. The first, blocked schedule, is used to measure the behaviour of stop and hit controllers in isolation, showing that it can only be described by two independent controllers with two different sets of control gains. The second, mixed schedule, is then used to compare how such behaviour evolves when participants regularly switch from one task to the other. Our results support our hypothesis that there is contextual switching of feedback controllers, further extending the accumulating evidence of shared features between feedforward and feedback control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471371" rel="alternate" title="Task-dependent switching of feedback controllers (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471362</id><title>Response plasticity of Drosophila olfactory sensory neurons (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.489003+00:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Halty-deLeon</name></author><author><name>Venkatesh Pal Mahadevan</name></author><author><name>Bill S. Hansson</name></author><author><name>Dieter Wicher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In insect olfaction, sensitization refers to the amplification of a weak olfactory signal when the stimulus is repeated within a specific time window. In the vinegar fly, &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;, his occurs already at the periphery, at the level of olfactory sensory neurons (OSNs) located in the antenna. In our study, we investigate whether sensitization is a widespread property in a set of seven types of OSNs, as well as the mechanisms involved. First, we characterize and compare differences in spontaneous activity, response velocity and response dynamics among the selected OSN types. These express different receptors with distinct tuning properties and behavioral relevance. Second, we show that sensitization is not a general property. Among our selected OSNs types, it occurs in those responding to more general food odors, while OSNs involved in very specific detection of highly specific ecological cues like pheromones and warning signals show no sensitization. Moreover, we show that mitochondria play an active role in sensitization by contributing to the increase in intracellular Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; upon weak receptor activation. Thus, by using a combination of single sensillum recordings (SSR), calcium imaging and pharmacology, we widen the understanding of how the olfactory signal is processed at the periphery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="471362v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471362" rel="alternate" title="Response plasticity of Drosophila olfactory sensory neurons (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472035</id><title>The intrinsic spatiotemporal organization of the human brain - A multi-dimensional functional network atlas (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.489389+00:00</updated><author><name>Jian Li</name></author><author><name>Yijun Liu</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Wisnowski</name></author><author><name>Richard M. Leahy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human brain is a complex, integrative and segregative network that exhibits dynamic fluctuations in activity across space and time. A canonical set of large-scale networks has been historically identified from resting-state fMRI (rs-fMRI), including the default mode, visual, somatomotor, salience, attention, and executive control. However, the methods used in identification of these networks have relied on assumptions that may inadvertently constrain their properties and consequently our understanding of the human connectome. Here we define a brain "network" as a functional component that jointly describes its spatial distribution and temporal dynamics, where neither domain suffers from unrealistic constraints. Using our recently developed BrainSync algorithm and the Nadam-Accelerated SCAlable and Robust (NASCAR) tensor decomposition, we identified twenty-three brain networks using rs-fMRI data from a large group of healthy subjects acquired by the Human Connectome Project. These networks are spatially overlapped, temporally correlated, and highly reproducible across two independent groups and sessions. We show that these networks can be clustered into six distinct functional categories and naturally form a representative functional network atlas for a healthy population. Using this atlas, we demonstrate that individuals with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder display disproportionate brain activity increases, relative to neurotypical subjects, in visual, auditory, and somatomotor networks concurrent with decreases in the default mode and higher-order cognitive networks. Thus, this work not only yields a highly reproducible set of spatiotemporally overlapped functional brain networks, but also provides convergent evidence that individual differences in these networks can be used to explain individual differences in neurocognitive functioning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.472035" rel="alternate" title="The intrinsic spatiotemporal organization of the human brain - A multi-dimensional functional network atlas (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471486</id><title>Leaders are made: Learning acquisition of consistent leader-follower relationships depends on implicit haptic interactions. (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.495935+00:00</updated><author><name>Asuka Takai</name></author><author><name>Qiushi Fu</name></author><author><name>Yuzuru Doibata</name></author><author><name>Giuseppe Lisi</name></author><author><name>Toshiki Tsuchiya</name></author><author><name>Keivan Mojtahedi</name></author><author><name>Toshinori Yoshioka</name></author><author><name>Mitsuo Kawato</name></author><author><name>Jun Morimoto</name></author><author><name>Marco Santello</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Are leaders made or born? Leader-follower roles have been well characterized in social science, but they remain somewhat obscure in sensory-motor coordination. Furthermore, it is unknown how and why leader-follower relationships are acquired, including innate versus acquired controversies. We developed a novel asymmetrical coordination task in which two participants (dyad) need to collaborate in transporting a simulated beam while maintaining its horizontal attitude. This experimental paradigm was implemented by twin robotic manipulanda, simulated beam dynamics, haptic interactions, and a projection screen. Clear leader-follower relationships were learned despite participants not being informed that they were interacting with each other, but only when strong haptic feedback was introduced. For the first time, we demonstrate the emergence of consistent leader-follower relationships in sensory-motor coordination, and further show that haptic interaction is essential for dyadic co-adaptation. These results provide insights into neural mechanisms responsible for the formation of leader-follower relationships in our society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471486" rel="alternate" title="Leaders are made: Learning acquisition of consistent leader-follower relationships depends on implicit haptic interactions. (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471843</id><title>Boosting serotonin increases information gathering by reducing subjective cognitive costs (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.496411+00:00</updated><author><name>Jochen Michely</name></author><author><name>Ingrid M. Martin</name></author><author><name>Raymond J. Dolan</name></author><author><name>Tobias U. Hauser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Serotonin is implicated in the valuation of aversive costs, such as delay or physical effort. However, its role in governing sensitivity to cognitive effort, for example deliberation costs during information gathering, is unclear. We show that week-long treatment with a serotonergic antidepressant enhances a willingness to gather information when trying to maximize reward. Using computational modelling, we show this arises from a diminished sensitivity to subjective deliberation costs during the sampling process. This result is consistent with the notion that serotonin alleviates sensitivity to aversive costs in a domain-general fashion, with implications for its potential contribution to a positive impact on motivational deficits in psychiatric disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471843" rel="alternate" title="Boosting serotonin increases information gathering by reducing subjective cognitive costs (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471955</id><title>Systematic analysis of C. elegans embryo behavior reveals a stereotyped developmental progression and a rhythmic pattern of behavioral quiescence (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.496560+00:00</updated><author><name>Evan L Ardiel</name></author><author><name>Andrew Lauziere</name></author><author><name>Stephen Xu</name></author><author><name>Brandon J Harvey</name></author><author><name>Ryan Christensen</name></author><author><name>Stephen Nurrish</name></author><author><name>Joshua M Kaplan</name></author><author><name>Hari Shroff</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Systematic analysis of rich behavioral recordings is being used to uncover how circuits encode complex behaviors. Here we apply the approach to embryos. What are the first embryonic behaviors and how do they evolve as early neurodevelopment ensues? To address these questions, we present a systematic description of behavioral maturation for Caenorhabditis elegans embryos. Posture libraries were derived from a genetically encoded motion capture suit imaged with light-sheet microscopy and annotated using custom semi-automated tracking software (Multiple Hypothesis Hypergraph Tracking; MHHT). Analysis of cell trajectories, postures, and behavioral motifs revealed a stereotyped developmental progression. Early movement is dominated by flipping between dorsal and ventral coiling, which gradually slows into a period of reduced motility. Late-stage embryos exhibit sinusoidal waves of dorsoventral bends, prolonged bouts of directed motion, and a rhythmic pattern of pausing, which we designate slow wave twitch (SWT). Synaptic transmission is required for late-stage motion but not for early flipping or the intervening inactive phase. A high-throughput behavioral assay and calcium imaging revealed that SWT is elicited by the rhythmic activity of a quiescence-promoting neuron (RIS). Similar periodic quiescent states are seen prenatally in divergent animals and may play an important role in promoting normal developmental outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471955" rel="alternate" title="Systematic analysis of C. elegans embryo behavior reveals a stereotyped developmental progression and a rhythmic pattern of behavioral quiescence (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471184</id><title>Transparent and Conformal Microcoil Arrays for Spatially Selective Neuronal Activation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.496761+00:00</updated><author><name>Vineeth Raghuram</name></author><author><name>Aditya D. Datye</name></author><author><name>Shelley I. Fried</name></author><author><name>Brian P. Timko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Magnetic stimulation represents a compelling modality for achieving neuronal activation with high spatial resolution and low toxicity. Stimulation coils can be designed to achieve localized, spatially asymmetric fields that target neurons of a particular orientation. Furthermore, these devices may be encapsulated within biopolymers thereby avoiding direct metal/tissue interfaces that could induce chronic inflammation and glial scarring. Herein, we report a multiplexed microcoil array for localized activation of cortical neurons and retinal ganglion cells. We designed a computational model that related the activation function to the geometry and arrangement of coils, and selected a geometry with a region of activation &amp;lt;50 μm wide. We then fabricated SU8/Cu/SU8 tri-layer devices which were flexible, transparent and conformal and featured four individually-addressable microcoil stimulation elements. Interfaced with ex vivo cortex or retina slices from GCaMP6-transfected mice, we observed that individual neurons located within 40 μm of the element tip could be activated repeatedly and in a dose (power) dependent fashion. Taken together, these results highlight the potential of magnetic stimulation devices for brain-machine interfaces and could open new routes toward bioelectronic therapies including prosthetic vision devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471184" rel="alternate" title="Transparent and Conformal Microcoil Arrays for Spatially Selective Neuronal Activation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471183</id><title>Disrupted controlling mechanism of salience network on default-mode network and central-executive network in schizophrenia (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.496922+00:00</updated><author><name>Ganesh B. Chand</name></author><author><name>Deepa S. Thakuri</name></author><author><name>Bhavin Soni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging studies suggest that the human brain consists of intrinsically organized large-scale neural networks. Among those networks, the interplay among default-mode network (DMN), salience network (SN), and central-executive network (CEN)has been widely employed to understand the functional interaction patterns in health and diseases. This triple network model suggests that SN causally controls DMN and CEN in healthy individuals. This interaction is often referred to as the dynamic controlling mechanism of SN. However, such interactions are not well understood in individuals with schizophrenia. In this study, we leveraged resting state functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) data of schizophrenia (n = 67) and healthy controls (n = 81) to evaluate the functional interactions among DMN, SN, and CEN using dynamical causal modeling. In healthy controls, our analyses replicated previous findings that SN regulates DMN and CEN activities (Mann-Whitney U test; p &amp;lt; 10&lt;sup&gt;−8&lt;/sup&gt;). In schizophrenia, however, our analyses revealed the disrupted SN-based controlling mechanism on DMN and CEN (Mann-Whitney U test; p &amp;lt; 10&lt;sup&gt;−16&lt;/sup&gt;). These results indicate that the disrupted controlling mechanism of SN on two other neural networks may be a candidate neuroimaging phenotype in schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471183" rel="alternate" title="Disrupted controlling mechanism of salience network on default-mode network and central-executive network in schizophrenia (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471376</id><title>Short latency stretch reflexes depend on the balance of activity in agonist and antagonist muscles during ballistic elbow movements (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.497048+00:00</updated><author><name>Zoe Villamar</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ludvig</name></author><author><name>Eric J Perreault</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The spinal stretch reflex is a fundamental building block of motor function, modulating sensitivity across tasks to augment volitional control. Stretch reflex sensitivity can vary continuously during movement and changes between movement and posture. While there have been many demonstrations of reflex modulation and investigations into the underlying mechanisms, there have been few attempts to provide simple, quantitative descriptions of the relationship between the volitional control and stretch reflex sensitivity throughout tasks that require the coordinated activity of several muscles. Here we develop such a description and use it to test the hypothesis that the modulation of stretch reflex sensitivity during movement can be explained by the balance of activity within the relevant agonist and antagonist muscles better than by the activity only in the muscle homonymous with the elicited reflex. We applied continuous pseudo-random perturbations of elbow angle as subjects completed approximately 500 movements in elbow flexion and extension. Measurements were averaged across the repeated movements to obtain continuous estimates of stretch reflex amplitude and background muscle activity. We also ran a control experiment on a subset of subjects performing postural tasks at muscle activity levels matched to those measured in the movement task. For both experiments, we assessed the relationship between background activity in the agonist and antagonist muscles controlling elbow movement and the stretch reflexes elicited in them. We found that modulation in the stretch reflexes during movement can be described by modulation of the background activity in the agonist and antagonist muscles, and that models incorporating agonists and antagonists are significantly better than those considering only the homonymous muscle. Increases in agonist muscle activity enhanced stretch reflex sensitivity whereas increases in antagonist activity suppressed reflex activity. Surprisingly, the magnitude of these effects was similar, suggesting a balance of control between agonists and antagonist that is very different than the dominance of sensitivity to agonist activity during postural tasks. This greater relative sensitivity to antagonist background activity during movement is due to a large decrease in sensitivity to homonymous muscle activity during movement rather than substantial changes in the influence of antagonist muscle activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471376" rel="alternate" title="Short latency stretch reflexes depend on the balance of activity in agonist and antagonist muscles during ballistic elbow movements (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472063</id><title>Topologically controlled circuits of human iPSC-derived neurons for electrophysiology recordings (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.497168+00:00</updated><author><name>Sophie Girardin</name></author><author><name>Blandine Clément</name></author><author><name>Stephan J. Ihle</name></author><author><name>Sean Weaver</name></author><author><name>Jana B. Petr</name></author><author><name>José C. Mateus</name></author><author><name>Jens Duru</name></author><author><name>Csaba Forró</name></author><author><name>Tobias Ruff</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Fruh</name></author><author><name>Matthias Müller</name></author><author><name>János Vörös</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bottom-up neuroscience, which consists of building and studying controlled networks of neurons in vitro, is a promising method to investigate information processing at the neuronal level. However, in vitro studies tend to use cells of animal origin rather than human neurons, leading to conclusions that might not be generalizable to humans and limiting the possibilities for relevant studies on neurological disorders. Here we present a method to build arrays of topologically controlled circuits of human induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC)-derived neurons. The circuits consist of 4 to 50 neurons with mostly unidirectional connections, confined by microfabricated polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) membranes. Such circuits were characterized using optical imaging and microelectrode arrays (MEAs). Electrophysiology recordings were performed on circuits of human iPSC-derived neurons for at least 4.5 months. We believe that the capacity to build small and controlled circuits of human iPSC-derived neurons holds great promise to better understand the fundamental principles of information processing and storing in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472063" rel="alternate" title="Topologically controlled circuits of human iPSC-derived neurons for electrophysiology recordings (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471331</id><title>Interoceptive sensitivity modulates heart rate and insula activity when listening to music (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.497347+00:00</updated><author><name>Toru Maekawa</name></author><author><name>Takafumi Sasaoka</name></author><author><name>Toshio Inui</name></author><author><name>Shigeto Yamawaki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interoception plays an important role in emotion processing, but the relationship between the physiological responses associated with emotional experience and interoception is unclear. In this study, we measured interoceptive sensitivity using the heartbeat discrimination task and investigated the effects of individual differences in interoceptive sensitivity on changes in heart rate and insula activity in response to music-induced emotions. We found that the heart rate increased when listening to the music pieces rated as emotionally high-touching in the high interoceptive sensitivity group only. Compared to the emotionally low-touching music, listening to the emotionally high-touching music was associated with higher insula activity. Furthermore, relative to individuals with low interoceptive sensitivity, the region of interest analysis of the insula subregions for individuals with high interoceptive sensitivity revealed significant activity in the bilateral dorsal granular insula, the right ventral dysgranular insula, and the right granular and dorsal dysgranular insula while listening to the high-touching music pieces. Our results suggest that individuals with high interoceptive sensitivity use their physical condition to assess their emotional level when listening to music. Furthermore, the insula activity may reflect the use of interoception to estimate emotions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471331" rel="alternate" title="Interoceptive sensitivity modulates heart rate and insula activity when listening to music (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471306</id><title>Endogenous Syngap1 Alpha Splice Forms Promote Cognitive Function and Seizure Protection (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.497473+00:00</updated><author><name>Murat Kilinc</name></author><author><name>Vineet Arora</name></author><author><name>Thomas K. Creson</name></author><author><name>Camilo Rojas</name></author><author><name>Aliza A. Le</name></author><author><name>Julie Lauterborn</name></author><author><name>Brent Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Hartel</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Graham</name></author><author><name>Adrian Reich</name></author><author><name>Gemma Gou</name></author><author><name>Yoichi Araki</name></author><author><name>Àlex Bayés</name></author><author><name>Marcelo P. Coba</name></author><author><name>Gary Lynch</name></author><author><name>Courtney A. Miller</name></author><author><name>Gavin Rumbaugh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Loss-of-function variants in &lt;italic&gt;SYNAGP1&lt;/italic&gt; cause a developmental encephalopathy defined by cognitive impairment, autistic features, and epilepsy. &lt;italic&gt;SYNGAP1&lt;/italic&gt; splicing leads to expression of distinct functional protein isoforms. Splicing imparts multiple cellular functions of SynGAP proteins through coding of distinct C-terminal motifs. However, it remains unknown how these different splice sequences function &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; to regulate neuronal function and behavior. Reduced expression of SynGAP-α1/2 C-terminal splice variants in mice caused severe phenotypes, including reduced survival, impaired learning, and reduced seizure latency. In contrast, upregulation of α1/2 expression improved learning and increased seizure latency. Mice expressing α1-specific mutations, which disrupted SynGAP cellular functions without altering protein expression, promoted seizure, disrupted synapse plasticity, and impaired learning. These findings demonstrate that endogenous SynGAP isoforms with α1/2 spliced sequences promote cognitive function and impart seizure protection. Regulation of SynGAP-α expression or function may be a viable therapeutic strategy to broadly improve cognitive function and mitigate seizure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471306" rel="alternate" title="Endogenous Syngap1 Alpha Splice Forms Promote Cognitive Function and Seizure Protection (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>