<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.091024+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462148</id><title>Adeno-associated virus (AAV) reduces cortical dendritic complexity in a TLR9-dependent manner (83 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.106630+00:00</updated><author><name>Christos M. Suriano</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Verpeut</name></author><author><name>Neerav Kumar</name></author><author><name>Jie Ma</name></author><author><name>Caroline Jung</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Boulanger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recombinant adeno-associated viruses (AAVs) allow rapid and efficient gene delivery in the nervous system. AAVs are widely used in research and are the basis of multiple FDA-approved gene therapies. Here, we find that the immune response to AAV’s genome reduces dendritic complexity in mammalian cortex. Dendritic loss associated with AAV-mediated gene delivery occurs at experimentally-relevant titers, cannot be explained by responses to transgene expression or surgery, and is not restricted to a particular capsid serotype, encoded transgene, promoter, or production facility. AAV-associated dendritic loss is accompanied by a decrease in the frequency and amplitude of miniature excitatory postsynaptic currents (mEPSCs) and upregulation of immune molecules that can limit dendritic complexity and synaptic transmission. Blocking detection of unmethylated CpG-rich DNA via Toll-like receptor 9 (TLR9) protects dendritic complexity, suggesting that immunodetection of a core feature of the AAV genome triggers dendritic loss. These results reveal previously unsuspected impacts of AAV on neuronal structure and function and identify TLR9 inhibitors as important tools to improve the safety and efficacy of AAV-mediated gene delivery in the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462148" rel="alternate" title="Adeno-associated virus (AAV) reduces cortical dendritic complexity in a TLR9-dependent manner (83 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462068</id><title>Here’s the twist: How the brain updates naturalistic event memories as our understanding of the past changes (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.107290+00:00</updated><author><name>Asieh Zadbood</name></author><author><name>Samuel A. Nastase</name></author><author><name>Janice Chen</name></author><author><name>Kenneth A. Norman</name></author><author><name>Uri Hasson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain actively reshapes past memories in light of new incoming information. In the current study, we ask how the brain supports this updatinge process during the encoding and recall of naturalistic stimuli. One group of participants watched a movie (“The Sixth Sense”) with a cinematic “twist” at the end that dramatically changed the interpretation of previous events. Next, participants were asked to verbally recall the movie events, taking into account the new “twist” information. Most participants updated their recall to incorporate the twist. Two additional groups recalled the movie without having to update their memories during recall: one group never saw the twist; another group was exposed to the twist prior to the beginning of the movie, and thus the twist information was incorporated both during encoding and recall. We found that providing participants with information about the twist beforehand altered neural response patterns during movie-viewing in the default mode network (DMN). Moreover, presenting participants with the twist at the end of the movie changed the neural representation of the previously-encoded information during recall in a subset of DMN regions. Further evidence for this transformation was obtained by comparing the neural activation patterns during encoding and recall and correlating them with behavioral signatures of memory updating. Our results demonstrate that neural representations of past events encoded in the DMN are dynamically integrated with new information that reshapes our memory in natural contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462068" rel="alternate" title="Here’s the twist: How the brain updates naturalistic event memories as our understanding of the past changes (12 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462379</id><title>Modeling spatial, developmental, physiological, and topological constraints on human brain connectivity (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.107704+00:00</updated><author><name>S. Oldham</name></author><author><name>B. D. Fulcher</name></author><author><name>K. Aquino</name></author><author><name>A. Arnatkevičiūtė</name></author><author><name>C. Paquola</name></author><author><name>R. Shishegar</name></author><author><name>A. Fornito</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The complex connectivity of nervous systems is thought to have been shaped by competitive selection pressures to minimize wiring costs and support adaptive function. Accordingly, recent modeling work indicates that stochastic processes, shaped by putative trade-offs between the cost and value of each connection, can successfully reproduce many topological properties of macroscale human connectomes measured with diffusion magnetic resonance imaging. Here, we derive a new formalism with the aim to more accurately capture the competing pressures of wiring cost minimization and topological complexity. We further show that model performance can be improved by accounting for developmental changes in brain geometry and associated wiring costs, and by using inter-regional transcriptional or microstructural similarity rather than topological wiring-rules. However, all models struggled to capture topologies spatial embedding. Our findings highlight an important role for genetics in shaping macroscale brain connectivity and indicate that stochastic models offer an incomplete account of connectome organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462379" rel="alternate" title="Modeling spatial, developmental, physiological, and topological constraints on human brain connectivity (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462517</id><title>Hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells do not receive monosynaptic input from thalamic nucleus reuniens (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.108277+00:00</updated><author><name>Lilya Andrianova</name></author><author><name>Erica S Brady</name></author><author><name>Gabriella Margetts-Smith</name></author><author><name>Shivali Kohli</name></author><author><name>Chris J McBain</name></author><author><name>Michael T Craig</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Thalamic nucleus reuniens (NRe) is located on the midline and acts as a hub to mediate interactions between hippocampal, entorhinal and prefrontal areas although these connections are poorly defined at the cellular and synaptic level. Using electrophysiology and monosynaptic circuit-tracing, we found that pyramidal cells in CA1 receive no direct input from NRe. This contrasts starkly with prefrontal cortex, subiculum and entorhinal cortex, and indicates that NRe inputs to CA1 primarily drive local inhibition and not excitation they do in the other regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462517" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells do not receive monosynaptic input from thalamic nucleus reuniens (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.459010</id><title>A whole-brain monosynaptic input connectome to neuron classes in mouse visual cortex (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.108771+00:00</updated><author><name>Shenqin Yao</name></author><author><name>Quanxin Wang</name></author><author><name>Karla E. Hirokawa</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Ouellette</name></author><author><name>Ruweida Ahmed</name></author><author><name>Jasmin Bomben</name></author><author><name>Krissy Brouner</name></author><author><name>Linzy Casal</name></author><author><name>Shiella Caldejon</name></author><author><name>Andy Cho</name></author><author><name>Nadezhda I. Dotson</name></author><author><name>Tanya L. Daigle</name></author><author><name>Tom Egdorf</name></author><author><name>Rachel Enstrom</name></author><author><name>Amanda Gary</name></author><author><name>Emily Gelfand</name></author><author><name>Melissa Gorham</name></author><author><name>Fiona Griffin</name></author><author><name>Hong Gu</name></author><author><name>Nicole Hancock</name></author><author><name>Robert Howard</name></author><author><name>Leonard Kuan</name></author><author><name>Sophie Lambert</name></author><author><name>Eric Kenji Lee</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Luviano</name></author><author><name>Kyla Mace</name></author><author><name>Michelle Maxwell</name></author><author><name>Marty T. Mortrud</name></author><author><name>Maitham Naeemi</name></author><author><name>Chelsea Nayan</name></author><author><name>Nhan-Kiet Ngo</name></author><author><name>Thuyanh Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Kat North</name></author><author><name>Shea Ransford</name></author><author><name>Augustin Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Sam Seid</name></author><author><name>Jackie Swapp</name></author><author><name>Michael J Taormina</name></author><author><name>Wayne Wakeman</name></author><author><name>Thomas Zhou</name></author><author><name>Philip R. Nicovich</name></author><author><name>Ali Williford</name></author><author><name>Lydia Potekhina</name></author><author><name>Medea McGraw</name></author><author><name>Lydia Ng</name></author><author><name>Peter A. Groblewski</name></author><author><name>Bosiljka Tasic</name></author><author><name>Stefan Mihalas</name></author><author><name>Julie A Harris</name></author><author><name>Ali Cetin</name></author><author><name>Hongkui Zeng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identification of the structural connections between neurons is a prerequisite to understanding brain function. We developed a pipeline to systematically map brain-wide monosynaptic inputs to specific neuronal populations using Cre-driver mouse lines and the recombinant rabies tracing system. We first improved the rabies virus tracing strategy to accurately identify starter cells and to efficiently quantify presynaptic inputs. We then mapped brain-wide presynaptic inputs to different excitatory and inhibitory neuron subclasses in the primary visual cortex and seven higher visual areas. Our results reveal quantitative target-, layer- and cell-class-specific differences in the retrograde connectomes, despite similar global input patterns to different neuronal populations in the same anatomical area. The retrograde connectivity we define is consistent with the presence of the ventral and dorsal visual information processing streams and reveals further subnetworks within the dorsal stream. The hierarchical organization of the entire visual cortex can be derived from intracortical feedforward and feedback pathways mediated by upper- and lower-layer input neurons, respectively. This study expands our knowledge of the brain-wide inputs regulating visual areas and demonstrates that our improved rabies virus tracing strategy can be used to scale up the effort in dissecting connectivity of genetically defined cell populations in the whole mouse brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.459010" rel="alternate" title="A whole-brain monosynaptic input connectome to neuron classes in mouse visual cortex (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462081</id><title>Performance-optimized neural networks as an explanatory framework for decision confidence (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.111764+00:00</updated><author><name>Taylor W. Webb</name></author><author><name>Kiyofumi Miyoshi</name></author><author><name>Tsz Yan So</name></author><author><name>Sivananda Rajananda</name></author><author><name>Hakwan Lau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Previous work has sought to understand decision confidence as a prediction of the probability that a decision will be correct, leading to debate over whether these predictions are optimal, and whether they rely on the same decision variable as decisions themselves. This work has generally relied on idealized, low-dimensional modeling frameworks, such as signal detection theory or Bayesian inference, leaving open the question of how decision confidence operates in the domain of high-dimensional, naturalistic stimuli. To address this, we developed a deep neural network model optimized to assess decision confidence directly given high-dimensional inputs such as images. The model naturally accounts for a number of puzzling dissociations between decisions and confidence, suggests a principled explanation of these dissociations in terms of optimization for the statistics of sensory inputs, and makes the surprising prediction that, despite these dissociations, decisions and confidence depend on a common decision variable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462081" rel="alternate" title="Performance-optimized neural networks as an explanatory framework for decision confidence (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462203</id><title>Numb reduces Tau levels and prevents neurodegeneration in mouse models of tauopathy in an isoform-specific manner (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.112220+00:00</updated><author><name>Marine Lacomme</name></author><author><name>Sarah C. Hales</name></author><author><name>Katarina Stevanovic</name></author><author><name>Christine Jolicoeur</name></author><author><name>Therence Bois</name></author><author><name>Jenny Cai</name></author><author><name>Melissa Desrosiers</name></author><author><name>Deniz Dalkara</name></author><author><name>Michel Cayouette</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accumulation of the microtubule-associated protein Tau is linked to neuronal cell death in tauopathies, but how exactly intraneuronal Tau levels are regulated in health and disease remains unclear. Here we identify the trafficking adaptor protein Numb as an essential regulator of Tau homeostasis. Conditional inactivation of Numb in retinal ganglion cells (RGCs) increases monomeric and oligomeric Tau levels, leading to axonal blebbing followed by neuronal cell loss in aged mice. Moreover, in a mouse model of tauopathy, inactivation of Numb in RGCs and spinal motoneurons accelerates neurodegeneration, and leads to precocious hindlimb paralysis. Conversely, overexpression of the long isoform of Numb (Numb-72), but not other isoforms, decreases intracellular Tau levels by promoting the extracellular release of monomeric Tau, and AAV-mediated delivery of Numb-72 in RGCs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; prevents neurodegeneration in two different mouse models of tauopathy. Taken together, these results uncover Numb as a modulator of intracellular Tau levels and identify Numb-72 as a novel therapeutic factor for tauopathies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462203" rel="alternate" title="Numb reduces Tau levels and prevents neurodegeneration in mouse models of tauopathy in an isoform-specific manner (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462468</id><title>Distance estimation from monocular cues in an ethological visuomotor task (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.112683+00:00</updated><author><name>Philip R. L. Parker</name></author><author><name>Elliott T. T. Abe</name></author><author><name>Natalie T. Beatie</name></author><author><name>Emmalyn S. P. Leonard</name></author><author><name>Dylan M. Martins</name></author><author><name>Shelby L. Sharp</name></author><author><name>David G. Wyrick</name></author><author><name>Luca Mazzucato</name></author><author><name>Cristopher M. Niell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In natural contexts, sensory processing and motor output are closely coupled, which is reflected in the fact that many brain areas contain both sensory and movement signals. However, standard reductionist paradigms decouple sensory decisions from their natural motor consequences, and head-fixation prevents the natural sensory consequences of self-motion. In particular, movement through the environment provides a number of depth cues beyond stereo vision that are poorly understood. To study the integration of visual processing and motor output in a naturalistic task, we investigated distance estimation in freely moving mice. We found that mice use vision to accurately jump across a variable gap, thus directly coupling a visual computation to its corresponding ethological motor output. Monocular eyelid suture did not affect performance, thus mice can use cues that do not depend on binocular disparity and stereo vision. Under monocular conditions, mice performed more vertical head movements, consistent with the use of motion parallax cues, and optogenetic suppression of primary visual cortex impaired task performance. Together, these results show that mice can use monocular cues, relying on visual cortex, to accurately judge distance. Furthermore, this behavioral paradigm provides a foundation for studying how neural circuits convert sensory information into ethological motor output.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462468" rel="alternate" title="Distance estimation from monocular cues in an ethological visuomotor task (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462361</id><title>Higher-order olfactory neurons in the lateral horn supports odor valence and odor identity coding in Drosophila (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.113579+00:00</updated><author><name>Sudeshna Das Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Hetan Chang</name></author><author><name>Bill S. Hansson</name></author><author><name>Silke Sachse</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding neuronal representations of odor-evoked activities and their progressive transformation from the sensory level to higher brain centers features one of the major aims in olfactory neuroscience. Here, we investigated how odor information is transformed and represented in higher-order neurons of the lateral horn, one of the higher olfactory centers implicated in determining innate behavior, using &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. We focused on a subset of third-order glutamatergic lateral horn neurons (LHNs) and characterized their odor coding properties in relation to their presynaptic partner neurons, the projection neurons (PNs) by two-photon functional imaging. We found that odors evoke reproducible, stereotypic and odor-specific response patterns in LHNs. Notably, odor-evoked responses in these neurons are valence-specific in a way that their response amplitude is positively correlated with innate odor preferences. We postulate that this valence-specific activity is the result of integrating inputs from multiple olfactory channels through second-order neurons. GRASP and micro-lesioning experiments provide evidence that glutamatergic LHNs obtain their major excitatory input from uniglomerular PNs, while they receive an odor-specific inhibition through inhibitory multiglomerular PNs. In summary, our study indicates that odor representations in glutamatergic LHNs encode hedonic valence and odor identity and primarily retain the odor coding properties of second-order neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462361" rel="alternate" title="Higher-order olfactory neurons in the lateral horn supports odor valence and odor identity coding in Drosophila (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462120</id><title>Real-time decoding of 5 finger movements from 2 EMG channels for mixed reality human-computer interaction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.113894+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric J. McDermott</name></author><author><name>Thimm Zwiener</name></author><author><name>Ulf Ziemann</name></author><author><name>Christoph Zrenner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The search for optimized forms of human-computer interaction (HCI) has intensified alongside the growing potential for the combination of biosignals with virtual reality (VR) and augmented reality (AR) to enable the next generation of personal computing. At the core, this requires decoding the user’s biosignals into digital commands. Electromyography (EMG) is a biosensor of particular interest due to the ease of data collection, the relatively high signal-to-noise-ratio, its non-invasiveness, and the ability to interpret the signal as being generated by (intentional) muscle activity. Here, we investigate the potential of using data taken from a simple 2-channel EMG setup to differentiate 5 distinct movements. In particular, EMG was recorded from two bipolar sensors over small hand muscles (&lt;italic&gt;extensor digitorum&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;flexor digitorum profundus&lt;/italic&gt;) while a subject performed 50 trials of dorsal extension and return for each of the five digits. The maximum and the mean values across the trial were determined for each channel and used as features. A k-nearest neighbors (kNN) classification was performed and overall 5-class classification accuracy reached 94% when using the full trial’s time window, while simulated real-time classification reached 90.4% accuracy when using the constructed kNN model (k=3) with a 280ms sliding window. Additionally, unsupervised learning was performed and a homogeneity of 85% was achieved. This study demonstrates that reliable decoding of different natural movements is possible with fewer than one channel per class, even without taking into account temporal features of the signal. The technical feasibility of this approach in a real-time setting was validated by sending real-time EMG data to a custom Unity3D VR application through a Lab Streaming Layer to control a user interface. Further use-cases of gamification and rehabilitation were also examined alongside the integration of eye-tracking and gesture recognition for a sensor fusion approach to HCI and user intent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462120" rel="alternate" title="Real-time decoding of 5 finger movements from 2 EMG channels for mixed reality human-computer interaction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462143</id><title>Hippocampal-prefrontal theta coupling develops as mice become proficient in associative odorant discrimination learning (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.114186+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Ramirez-Gordillo</name></author><author><name>Andrew A. Parra</name></author><author><name>K. Ulrich Bayer</name></author><author><name>Diego Restrepo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Learning and memory requires coordinated activity between different regions of the brain. Here we studied the interaction between medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC) and hippocampal dorsal CA1 during associative odorant discrimination learning in the mouse. We found that as the animal learns to discriminate odorants in a go-no go task the coupling of high frequency neural oscillations to the phase of theta oscillations (phase-amplitude coupling or PAC) changes in a manner that results in divergence between rewarded and unrewarded odorant-elicited changes in the theta-phase referenced power (tPRP) for beta and gamma oscillations. In addition, in the proficient animal there was a decrease in the coordinated oscillatory activity between CA1 and mPFC in the presence of the unrewarded odorant. Furthermore, the changes in PAC resulted in a marked increase in the accuracy for decoding odorant identity from tPRP when the animal became proficient. Finally, we studied the role of Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase II α (CaMKIIα), a protein involved in learning and memory, in oscillatory neural processing in this task. We find that the accuracy for decoding the odorant identity from tPRP decreases in CaMKIIα knockout mice and that this accuracy correlates with behavioral performance. These results implicate a role for PAC and CaMKIIα in olfactory go-no go associative learning in the hippocampal-prefrontal circuit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462143" rel="alternate" title="Hippocampal-prefrontal theta coupling develops as mice become proficient in associative odorant discrimination learning (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462800</id><title>Molecular structure and conformation of stereocilia tip-links elucidated by cryo-electron tomography (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.114471+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes Elferich</name></author><author><name>Sarah Clark</name></author><author><name>Jingpeng Ge</name></author><author><name>April Goehring</name></author><author><name>Aya Matsui</name></author><author><name>Eric Gouaux</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanosensory transduction (MT), the conversion of mechanical stimuli into electrical signals, underpins hearing and balance and is carried out within hair cells in the inner ear. Hair cells harbor actin-filled stereocilia, arranged in rows of descending heights, where the tips of stereocilia are connected to their taller neighbors by a filament composed of protocadherin 15 (PCDH15) and cadherin 23 (CDH23), deemed the ‘tip-link’. Tension exerted on the tip-link opens an ion channel at the tip of the shorter stereocilia, thus converting mechanical force into an electrical signal. While biochemical and structural studies have provided insights into the molecular composition and structure of isolated portions of the tip-link, the architecture, location and conformational states of intact tip-links, on stereocilia, remains unknown. Here we report &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; cryo-electron microscopy imaging of the tip-link in mouse stereocilia. We observe individual PCDH15 molecules at the tip and shaft of stereocilia and determine their stoichiometry, conformational heterogeneity, and their complexes with CDH23. The PCDH15/CDH23 complexes occur in clusters, frequently with more than one copy of PCDH15 at the tip of stereocilia, suggesting that tip-links might consist of more than one copy of the PCDH15/CDH23 heterotetramer and by extension, might include multiple MT complexes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.01.462800" rel="alternate" title="Molecular structure and conformation of stereocilia tip-links elucidated by cryo-electron tomography (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462177</id><title>Towards real-world neuroscience using mobile EEG and augmented reality (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.114784+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra Krugliak</name></author><author><name>Alex Clarke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Our visual environment impacts multiple aspects of cognition including perception, attention and memory, yet most studies traditionally remove or control the external environment. As a result, we have a limited understanding of neurocognitive processes beyond the controlled lab environment. Here, we aim to study neural processes in real-world environments, while also maintaining a degree of control over perception. To achieve this, we combined mobile EEG (mEEG) and augmented reality (AR), which allows us to place virtual objects into the real world. We validated this AR and mEEG approach using a well-characterised cognitive response - the face inversion effect. Participants viewed upright and inverted faces in three EEG tasks (1) a lab-based computer task, (2) walking through an indoor environment while seeing face photographs, and (3) walking through an indoor environment while seeing virtual faces. We find greater low frequency EEG activity for inverted compared to upright faces in all experimental tasks, demonstrating that cognitively relevant signals can be extracted from mEEG and AR paradigms. This was established in both an epoch-based analysis aligned to face events, and a GLM-based approach that incorporates continuous EEG signals and face perception states. Together, this research helps pave the way to exploring neurocognitive processes in real-world environments while maintaining experimental control using AR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462177" rel="alternate" title="Towards real-world neuroscience using mobile EEG and augmented reality (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462232</id><title>Evaluating the reliability, validity, and utility of overlapping networks: Implications for cognitive control (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.115050+00:00</updated><author><name>Savannah L. Cookson</name></author><author><name>Mark D’Esposito</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain regions can be consistently clustered together into a small number of large-scale networks based on the correlation of their activity across time. However, the methods typically used to assign regions to these networks typically force non- or minimal overlap between the networks, losing information about how particular regions may connect to multiple networks. However, new methods are emerging that allow networks to overlap. Here, we examined the reliability and validity of one such assignment method, the mixed membership algorithm, and the utility of overlapping assignment for identifying potential gaps in existing network models of behavior. Analyses were conducted on resting state data from a large set of participants. First, we split the data into two halves and generated group-level overlapping networks for each subgroup. We then used a bootstrapped Dice similarity analysis to demonstrate that the binarized network topographies showed good agreement between subgroups. Next, we generated nonoverlapping networks in the combined data using a typical k-means clustering method. Using the same Dice Similarity analysis, we compared these nonoverlapping networks both with previously published nonoverlapping networks (Yeo et al, 2011) and with overlapping networks likewise generated for the combined data. The nonoverlapping networks generally recapitulated known networks in the literature, and the overlapping networks captured large portions of one to three nonoverlapping network topographies. Following this, we used a relative entropy analysis to assess the uniformity of each region’s distribution of connections across the overlapping networks. While many regions were indeed assigned to one network, more were assigned to multiple networks. Furthermore, regions assigned to multiple networks did not necessarily show stronger connection to one network over the others. Finally, we assessed the network membership of regions of the fronto-parietal and cingulo-opercular networks of the Dual-Networks model of cognitive control. In combination, the regions were members of all of the overlapping networks, and the majority were assigned to multiple networks. Together, these results indicate that overlapping assignment produces consistent and biologically plausible network topographies, and that a complete network model of cognitive control, or indeed any network model of behavior needs to be updated to account for multiple-network membership and the complex interactions that occur between the relevant networks as a function of their overlapping nature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462232" rel="alternate" title="Evaluating the reliability, validity, and utility of overlapping networks: Implications for cognitive control (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462410</id><title>Moderate prenatal alcohol exposure modifies sex-specific CRFR1 activity in the central amygdala and anxiety-like behavior in adolescent offspring (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.115344+00:00</updated><author><name>Siara Kate Rouzer</name></author><author><name>Marvin R. Diaz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Anxiety disorders are highly prevalent among individuals with a history of prenatal alcohol exposure (PAE), and adolescent rodents demonstrate anxiety-like behavior following moderate PAE on Gestational Day (G) 12. A likely systemic target of PAE is the stress peptide corticotrophin-releasing factor (CRF), as activation of CRF receptor 1 (CRFR1) in the medial nucleus of the central amygdala (CeM) is known to increase anxiety-like behavior in adults. To determine if CRF-CRFR1 interactions underly PAE-induced anxiety, functional changes in CRF system activity were investigated in adolescent male and female Sprague Dawley rats following G12 PAE. Compared to air-exposed controls, PAE increased basal spontaneous (s) inhibitory post-synaptic current (IPSC) frequency in the CeM of males, but not females. Furthermore, PAE blunted CRFR1-regulated miniature (m) IPSCs in a sex- and dose-specific manner, and only PAE males demonstrated tonic CRFR1 activity in the CeM. It was further determined that G12 PAE decreased CRFR1 mRNA in the CeM of males while increasing regional expression in females. Finally, infusion of a CRFR1 agonist into the CeM of adolescents produced a blunted expression of CRFR1-induced anxiety-like behavior exclusively in PAE males, mirroring the blunted physiology demonstrated by PAE males. Cumulatively, these data suggest that CRFR1 function within the CeM is age- and sex-specific, and PAE not only increases the expression of anxiety-like behavior, but may reduce the efficacy of treatment for PAE-induced anxiety through CRFR1-associated mechanisms. Therefore, future research will be necessary to develop targeted treatment of anxiety disorders in individuals with a history of PAE.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462410" rel="alternate" title="Moderate prenatal alcohol exposure modifies sex-specific CRFR1 activity in the central amygdala and anxiety-like behavior in adolescent offspring (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>