<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.899587+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455969</id><title>Sulfonylureas target the neurovascular response to decrease Alzheimer’s pathology (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.899922+00:00</updated><author><name>Shannon L. Macauley</name></author><author><name>Molly S. Stanley</name></author><author><name>Emily E. Caesar</name></author><author><name>William R. Moritz</name></author><author><name>Annie R. Bice</name></author><author><name>Nildris Cruz-Diaz</name></author><author><name>Caitlin M. Carroll</name></author><author><name>Stephen M. Day</name></author><author><name>John Grizzanti</name></author><author><name>Thomas E. Mahan</name></author><author><name>James A. Snipes</name></author><author><name>Timothy E. Orr</name></author><author><name>Joseph P. Culver</name></author><author><name>Maria S. Remedi</name></author><author><name>Colin G. Nichols</name></author><author><name>Celeste M. Karch</name></author><author><name>Laura A. Cox</name></author><author><name>Debra I. Diz</name></author><author><name>Adam Q. Bauer</name></author><author><name>David M. Holtzman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hyperexcitability is a defining feature of Alzheimer’s disease (AD), where aberrant neuronal activity is both a cause and consequence of AD. Therefore, identifying novel targets that modulate cellular excitability is an important strategy for treating AD. ATP-sensitive potassium (K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt;) channels are metabolic sensors that modulate cellular excitability. Sulfonylureas are K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channel antagonists traditionally used to combat hyperglycemia in diabetic patients by inhibiting pancreatic K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channels, thereby stimulating insulin release. However, K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channels are not limited to the pancreas and systemic modulation of K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channels has pleotropic physiological effects, including profound effects on vascular function. Here, we demonstrate that human AD patients have higher cortical expression of vascular K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channels, important modulators of vasoreactivity. We demonstrate that peripheral treatment with the sulfonylurea and K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channel inhibitor, glyburide, reduced the aggregation and activity-dependent production of amyloid-beta (Aβ), a hallmark of AD, in mice. Since glyburide does not readily cross the blood brain barrier, our data suggests that glyburide targets vascular K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channel activity to reduce arterial stiffness, improve vasoreactivity, and normalize pericyte-endothelial cell morphology, offering a novel therapeutic target for AD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Targeting vascular K&lt;sub&gt;ATP&lt;/sub&gt; channel activity for the treatment of Alzheimer’s disease pathology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="455969v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455969" rel="alternate" title="Sulfonylureas target the neurovascular response to decrease Alzheimer’s pathology (21 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455600</id><title>Hierarchical control of visually-guided movements in a 3D-printed robot arm (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.900204+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam Matić</name></author><author><name>Pavle Valerjev</name></author><author><name>Alex Gomez-Marin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The control architecture guiding simple movements such as reaching toward a visual target remains an open problem. The nervous system needs to integrate different sensory modalities and coordinate multiple degrees of freedom in the human arm to achieve that goal. The challenge increases due to noise and transport delays in neural signals, nonlinear and fatigable muscles as actuators, and unpredictable environmental disturbances. Here we examined the capabilities of a previously proposed hierarchical feedback control model (Powers 1999, 2008), so far only tested &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt;. We built a robot arm system with four degrees of freedom, including a visual system for locating the planar position of the hand, joint angle proprioception, and pressure sensing in one point of contact. We subjected the robot to various human-inspired reaching and tracking tasks and found features of biological movement, such as isochrony and bell-shaped velocity profiles in straight-line movements, and the speed-curvature power law in curved movements. These behavioral properties emerge without trajectory planning or explicit optimization algorithms. We then applied static structural perturbations to the robot: we blocked the wrist joint, tilted the writing surface, extended the hand with a tool, and rotated the visual system. For all of them, we found that the arm &lt;italic&gt;in machina&lt;/italic&gt; adapts its behavior without being reprogrammed. In sum, while limited in speed and precision (by the nature of the do-it-yourself inexpensive components we used to build the robot from scratch), when faced with the noise, delays, nonlinearities, and unpredictable disturbances of the real world, the embodied control architecture shown here balances biological realism with design simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455600" rel="alternate" title="Hierarchical control of visually-guided movements in a 3D-printed robot arm (13 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456005</id><title>Androgen synthesis inhibition but not gonadectomy reduces persistence during strategy set-shifting and reversal learning in male rats (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.900355+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan J. Tomm</name></author><author><name>Désirée R. Seib</name></author><author><name>George V. Kachkovski</name></author><author><name>Helen R. Schweitzer</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Tobiansky</name></author><author><name>Stan B. Floresco</name></author><author><name>Kiran K. Soma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Androgens regulate behavioural flexibility, which is essential to adapt to a changing environment and depends on the medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC). Testosterone (T) administration decreases behavioural flexibility. It is well known that T is produced in the gonads, but T is also produced in the mesocorticolimbic system, which modulates behavioural flexibility. It is unclear how T produced in the brain versus the gonads influences behavioural flexibility. Here, we assess the effects of the androgen synthesis inhibitor abiraterone acetate (ABI) and long-term gonadectomy (GDX) on behavioural flexibility in two paradigms. In Experiment 1, ABI independent of GDX reduced the number of trials to criterion and perseverative errors in a strategy set-shifting task. Similarly, in Experiment 2, ABI but not GDX reduced perseverative errors in a reversal learning task. In subjects from Experiment 1, we also examined tyrosine hydroxylase immunoreactivity (TH-ir), and ABI but not GDX increased TH-ir in the mPFC. Our findings suggest that neurally-produced androgens modulate behavioural flexibility via modification of dopamine signalling in the mesocorticolimbic system. These results suggest novel roles for neurosteroids and possible side effects of ABI treatment for prostate cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456005" rel="alternate" title="Androgen synthesis inhibition but not gonadectomy reduces persistence during strategy set-shifting and reversal learning in male rats (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455977</id><title>Medial temporal and prefrontal cortices encode structural task representations at different levels of abstraction (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.900524+00:00</updated><author><name>Sam C. Berens</name></author><author><name>Chris M. Bird</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Memory generalisations may be underpinned by either encoding- or retrieval-based mechanisms. We used a transitive inference task to investigate whether these generalisation mechanisms are influenced by progressive vs randomly interleaved training, and overnight consolidation. On consecutive days, participants learnt pairwise discriminations from two transitive hierarchies before being tested during fMRI. Inference performance was consistently better following progressive training, and for pairs further apart in the transitive hierarchy. BOLD pattern similarity correlated with hierarchical distances in the medial temporal lobe (MTL) and medial prefrontal cortex (MPFC). These results are consistent with the use of representations that directly encode structural relationships between different task features. Furthermore, BOLD patterns in MPFC were similar across the two independent hierarchies. We conclude that humans preferentially employ encoding-based mechanisms to store map-like relational codes that can be used for memory generalisation. While both MTL and MPFC support these representations, the MPFC encodes more abstract relational information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455977" rel="alternate" title="Medial temporal and prefrontal cortices encode structural task representations at different levels of abstraction (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455963</id><title>RNA sequencing on muscle biopsy from a 5-week bedrest study reveals the effect of exercise and potential interactions with dorsal root ganglion neurons (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.900661+00:00</updated><author><name>Amelia J. McFarland</name></author><author><name>Pradipta R. Ray</name></author><author><name>Salman Bhai</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Levine</name></author><author><name>Theodore J. Price</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lack of physical activity is a predictor of poor health outcomes that can be prevented or reversed by exercise. Sedentary lifestyle, chronic disease or microgravity can cause muscle deconditioning that then has an impact on other physiological systems. An example is the nervous system, which is adversely affected by decreased physical activity resulting in increased incidence of neurological problems such as chronic pain. We sought to better understand how this might occur by conducting RNA sequencing experiments on muscle biopsies from human volunteers in a 5-week bed-rest study with an exercise intervention arm. We also used a computational method for examining ligand-receptor interactions between muscle and human dorsal root ganglion (DRG) neurons, the latter of which play a key role in nociception and are generators of signals responsible for chronic pain. We identified 1352 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in bed rest subjects without an exercise intervention but only 132 DEGs in subjects with the intervention. Thirty-six genes were shared between the exercise and no intervention groups. Among 591 upregulated muscle genes in the no intervention arm, 26 of these were ligands that have receptors that are expressed by human DRG neurons. We detected a specific splice variant of one of these ligands, placental growth factor (PGF), in deconditioned muscle that binds to neuropilin 1, a receptor that is highly expressed in DRG neurons and known to promote neuropathic pain. We conclude that exercise intervention protects muscle from deconditioning transcriptomic changes, and prevents changes in expression of ligands that might sensitize DRG neurons that promote pain. Our work creates a set of actionable hypotheses to better understand how deconditioned muscle may influence the function of sensory neurons that innervate the entire body.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455963" rel="alternate" title="RNA sequencing on muscle biopsy from a 5-week bedrest study reveals the effect of exercise and potential interactions with dorsal root ganglion neurons (11 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456124</id><title>Gut bacteria regulate the pathogenesis of Huntington's disease in Drosophila (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.900813+00:00</updated><author><name>Anjalika Chongtham</name></author><author><name>Jung Hyun Yoo</name></author><author><name>Theodore M Chin</name></author><author><name>Ngozi D Akingbesote</name></author><author><name>Ainul Huda</name></author><author><name>Ali Khoshnan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Changes in the composition of gut microbiota are implicated in the pathogenesis of several neurodegenerative disorders. Here, we investigated whether gut bacteria affect the hallmarks of Huntington's disease (HD) in transgenic Drosophila melanogaster (fruit fly) models expressing human full-length or N-terminal fragments of mutant huntingtin (HTT) protein, here referred to as HD flies. We find that elimination of commensal gut bacteria by antibiotics reduces the aggregation of amyloidogenic N-terminal fragments of HTT and delays the development of motor defects. Conversely, colonization of HD flies with Escherichia coli (E. coli), a known pathobiont of human gut, accelerates HTT aggregation, aggravates immobility and shortens life span. Similar to antibiotics, treatment of HD flies with compounds such as luteolin, a flavone, or crocin a beta-carotenoid, ameliorates disease phenotypes and promotes survival. Crocin prevents colonization of E. coli in the HD flies gut and alters the levels of commensal bacteria, which may be linked to its protective effects. The opposing effects of E. coli and crocin on HTT aggregation, motor defects and survival in transgenic Drosophila support the involvement of gut-brain networks in the pathogenesis of HD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456124" rel="alternate" title="Gut bacteria regulate the pathogenesis of Huntington's disease in Drosophila (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455859</id><title>Invalidity of light sensor data in field studies and a proposal of an algorithmic approach for detection and filtering of non-wear time (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.900970+00:00</updated><author><name>Larissa C. Hunt</name></author><author><name>Josef Fritz</name></author><author><name>Michael Herf</name></author><author><name>Lorna Herf</name></author><author><name>Celine Vetter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Wearable light sensors are increasingly used in intervention and population-based studies investigating the consequences of environmental light exposure on human physiology. An important step in such analyses is the reliable detection of non-wear time. We observed in light data that days with less wear-time also have lower variability in the light signal, and we sought to test if the standard deviation of the change between subsequent samples can detect this condition. In this study, we propose and validate an easy-to-implement algorithm designed to discriminate between days with a non-wear time &amp;gt;4h (“invalid days”) vs. ≤4h (“valid days”) and investigate to which extent values of commonly used physiologically meaningful light variables differ between invalid days, valid days, and algorithm-selected non-wear days. We used 83 days of light data from a field study with high participant compliance, complemented by 47 days of light data where free-living individuals were instructed not to wear the sensor for varying amounts of time. Light data were recorded every two minutes using the pendant-worn &lt;italic&gt;f.luxomete&lt;/italic&gt;r light sensor; validity was derived from daily logs where participants recorded all non-wear time. The algorithm-derived score discriminated well between valid and invalid days (area under the curve (AUC): 0.77, 95% CI: 0.67-0.87). The best cut-off value (&lt;italic&gt;i.e.&lt;/italic&gt;, highest Youden index) correctly recognized valid days with a probability of 87% (“sensitivity”), and invalid days with a probability of 63% (“specificity”). Values of various light variables derived from algorithm-selected days only (median: 264.3 (Q1: 153.6, Q3: 420.0) for 24h light intensity (in lux); 496.0 (404.0, 582.0) for time spent above 50-lux) gave values close to those derived from self-reported valid days only. However, these values did not significantly differ when derived across all days compared to self-reported valid days. Our results suggest that our proposed algorithm discriminates well between valid and invalid days. However, in high compliance cohorts, distortions in aggregated light measures of individual-level environmental light recordings across days appear to be small, making the application of our algorithm optional, but not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455859" rel="alternate" title="Invalidity of light sensor data in field studies and a proposal of an algorithmic approach for detection and filtering of non-wear time (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456294</id><title>The diazepam binding inhibitor’s modulation of the GABA-A receptor is subunit-dependent (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.901120+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer S Borchardt</name></author><author><name>Lucas M Blecker</name></author><author><name>Kenneth A Satyshur</name></author><author><name>Cynthia Czajkowski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;First synthesized in the 1950s, benzodiazepines are widely prescribed drugs that exert their anxiolytic, sedative and anticonvulsant actions by binding to GABA-A receptors, the main inhibitory ligand-gated ion channel in the brain. Scientists have long theorized that there exists an endogenous benzodiazepine, or endozepine, in the brain. While there is indirect evidence suggesting a peptide, the diazepam binding inhibitor, is capable of modulating the GABA-A receptor, direct evidence of the modulatory effects of the diazepam binding inhibitor is limited.
Here we take a reductionist approach to understand how purified diazepam binding inhibitor interacts with and affects GABA-A receptor activity. We used two-electrode voltage clamp electrophysiology to study how the effects of diazepam binding inhibitor vary with GABA-A receptor subunit composition, and found that GABA-evoked currents from α3-containing GABA-A receptors are weakly inhibited by the diazepam binding inhibitor, while currents from α5-containing receptors are positively modulated. We also used &lt;italic&gt;in  silico&lt;/italic&gt;     protein-protein docking to visualize potential diazepam binding inhibitor/GABA-A receptor interactions that revealed diazepam binding inhibitor bound at the benzodiazepine α/γ binding site interface, which provides a structural framework for understanding diazepam binding inhibitor effects on GABA-A receptors. Our results provide novel insights into mechanisms underlying how the diazepam binding inhibitor modulates GABA-mediated inhibition in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456294" rel="alternate" title="The diazepam binding inhibitor’s modulation of the GABA-A receptor is subunit-dependent (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456110</id><title>Enhanced negative response to stress following morphine administration increases wanting of social reward (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.901265+00:00</updated><author><name>Claudia Massaccesi</name></author><author><name>Matthaeus Willeit</name></author><author><name>Boris B. Quednow</name></author><author><name>Urs M. Nater</name></author><author><name>Claus Lamm</name></author><author><name>Daniel Mueller</name></author><author><name>Giorgia Silani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Animal research suggests a central role of the mu-opioid receptor (MOR) system in mediating contact seeking and the stress-buffering function of social touch. However, the human neurochemistry of social motivation in aversive situations is still poorly understood. In a randomized, double-blind, between-subject design, healthy female volunteers (N = 80) received either 10 mg of the mu-opioid agonist morphine sulfate or a placebo. Following psychosocial stress induction, participants engaged in a social reward task, in which the motivation (subjective ratings of wanting and physical effort) to obtain skin-to-skin social touch and the hedonic reactions (subjective ratings of liking and facial electromyography) elicited by it were assessed. Morphine administration prevented the increase of salivary cortisol, usually observed in response to acute stress exposure. The dampened physiological reaction to the psychosocial stress was associated with increased negative mood and subsequent higher subjective wanting of the most pleasurable touch. Furthermore, participants administered with morphine displayed greater activity of the corrugator muscle during reward anticipation, possibly tracking enhanced attention toward the social stimuli. Overall, the results provide novel evidence on the effect of exogenous opioids administration on the reactions to psychosocial stress and point to a state-dependent regulation of social motivation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456110" rel="alternate" title="Enhanced negative response to stress following morphine administration increases wanting of social reward (7 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456160</id><title>Mixed selectivity in the cerebellar Purkinje-cell response during visuomotor association learning (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.901425+00:00</updated><author><name>Naveen Sendhilnathan</name></author><author><name>Anna E. Ipata</name></author><author><name>Michael E. Goldberg</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Although the cerebellum has been traditionally considered to be exclusively involved in motor control, recent anatomical and clinical studies show that it also has a role in reward-processing. However, the way in which the movement related and the reward related neural activity interact at the level of the cerebellar cortex and contribute towards learning is still unclear. Here, we studied the simple spike activity of Purkinje cells in the mid-lateral cerebellum when monkeys learned to associate a right or left-hand movement with one of two visual symbolic cues. These cells had distinctly different discharge patterns between an overtrained symbol-hand association and a novel symbol-hand association, responding in association with the movement of both hands, although the kinematics of the movement did not change between the two conditions. The activity change was not related to the pattern of the visual symbols, the movement kinematics, the monkeys’ reaction times or the novelty of the visual symbols. The simple spike activity changed with throughout the learning process, but the concurrent complex spikes did not instruct that change. Although these neurons also have reward-related activity, the reward-related and movement-related signals were independent. We suggest that this mixed-selectivity may facilitate the flexible learning of difficult reinforcement learning problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456160" rel="alternate" title="Mixed selectivity in the cerebellar Purkinje-cell response during visuomotor association learning (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456053</id><title>Humanoid robots are perceived as an evolutionary threat (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.901563+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhengde Wei</name></author><author><name>Ying Chen</name></author><author><name>Jiecheng Ren</name></author><author><name>Yi Piao</name></author><author><name>Pengyu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Rujing Zha</name></author><author><name>Bensheng Qiu</name></author><author><name>Daren Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yanchao Bi</name></author><author><name>Shihui Han</name></author><author><name>Chunbo Li</name></author><author><name>Xiaochu Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the grand challenges of successful social encounters with socially sophisticated robots and shaping the future development of robots in socially acceptable ways, we need to quantify people perception to the robots. The critical assumption at the perception to humanoid robots, namely that people perceive humanoid robots as an evolutionary threat, has not been directly confirmed. We assume the existence of behavioral and neural automaticity for humanoid robots that were previously only evident for evolutionary threats. Here, we observed a monocular advantage for the perception of humanoid robots the same as an evolutionary threat (i.e., snakes). Our neuroimaging analysis indicated that unconscious presentation of humanoid robot vs. human images led to significant left amygdala activation that was associated with negative implicit attitude to humanoid robots. After successfully weakening negative attitude, the left amygdala response to unconscious presentation of humanoid robot images decreased, and the decrease of left amygdala response was positively associated with the decrease of negative attitude. Our results reveal that processing of information about humanoid robots displays automaticity with regard to recruitment of visual pathway and amygdala activation. Our findings that humans may perceive humanoid robots as an evolutionary threat will guide the future direction of robots development and bring us closer to interacting with socially sophisticated robots.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456053" rel="alternate" title="Humanoid robots are perceived as an evolutionary threat (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455916</id><title>Peripheral sTREM2-related inflammatory activity alterations in early stage Alzheimer’s disease (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.901751+00:00</updated><author><name>Grace E. Weber</name></author><author><name>Maria Khrestian</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth D. Tuason</name></author><author><name>Yvonne Shao</name></author><author><name>Jagan Pillai</name></author><author><name>Stephen Rao</name></author><author><name>Hao Feng</name></author><author><name>Yadi Zhou</name></author><author><name>Feixiong Cheng</name></author><author><name>Tara M. DeSilva</name></author><author><name>Shaun Stauffer</name></author><author><name>James B. Leverenz</name></author><author><name>Lynn M. Bekris</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease (AD) has been linked to multiple immune system genetic variants, implicating potential broad alterations in inflammatory profiles in the disease. Triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 2 (TREM2) genetic variants are risk factors for AD and other neurodegenerative diseases. A soluble TREM2 isoform (sTREM2) is elevated in cerebrospinal fluid in the early stages of AD suggesting it may be a biomarker of progressive alterations in immune response to AD-related pathology. Multiple studies have reported an altered peripheral immune response in AD. However, less is known about the relationship between plasma sTREM2 and the altered peripheral immune response in AD. The objective of this exploratory study was to examine the relationship between sTREM2 and inflammatory activity in human participants defined by clinically characterized cognitive symptoms and groups defined by the cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers &lt;underline&gt;a&lt;/underline&gt;myloid beta, phosphorylated &lt;underline&gt;t&lt;/underline&gt;au, and &lt;underline&gt;n&lt;/underline&gt;eurodegeneration (NIA-AA Research Framework: “ATN continuum”.) The hypothesis of this exploratory study was that sTREM2 related inflammatory activity differs by AD stage. We observed different patterns of inflammatory activity across disease groups and ATN categories that implicates peripheral sTREM2 related inflammatory activity as altered in the early stages of AD. Notably, fractalkine showed a significant relationship with sTREM2 across different analyses in the control groups that was lost as disease progressed, and fractalkine, IL-5 and IL-17A were decreased in AD. These preliminary data provide important support to the hypothesis that sTREM2-related inflammatory activity is a stage-specific biomarker of AD progression, providing the groundwork for future studies and therapeutic strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455916" rel="alternate" title="Peripheral sTREM2-related inflammatory activity alterations in early stage Alzheimer’s disease (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456218</id><title>Phase-locking patterns underlying effective communication in exact firing rate models of neural networks (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.901945+00:00</updated><author><name>David Reyner-Parra</name></author><author><name>Gemma Huguet</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Macroscopic oscillations in the brain have been observed to be involved in many cognitive tasks but their role is not completely understood. One of the suggested functions of the oscillations is to dynamically modulate communication between neural circuits. The Communication Through Coherence (CTC) theory establishes that oscillations reflect rhythmic changes in excitability of the neuronal populations. Thus, populations need to be properly phase-locked so that input volleys arrive at the peaks of excitability of the receiving population to communicate effectively. Here, we present a modeling study to explore synchronization between neuronal circuits connected with unidirectional projections. We consider an Excitatory-Inhibitory (E-I) network of quadratic integrate-and-fire neurons modeling a Pyramidal-Interneuronal Network Gamma (PING) rhythm. The network receives an external periodic input from either one or two sources, simulating the inputs from other oscillating neural groups. We use recently developed mean-field models which provide an exact description of the macroscopic activity of the spiking network. This low-dimensional mean field model allows us to use tools from bifurcation theory to identify the phase-locked states between the input and the target population as a function of the amplitude, frequency and coherence of the inputs. We identify the conditions for optimal phaselocking and selective communication. We find that inputs with high coherence can entrain the network for a wider range of frequencies. Besides, faster oscillatory inputs than the intrinsic network gamma cycle show more effective communication than inputs with similar frequency. Our analysis further shows that the entrainment of the network by inputs with higher frequency is more robust to distractors, thus giving them an advantage to entrain the network. Finally, we show that pulsatile inputs can switch between attended inputs in selective attention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456218" rel="alternate" title="Phase-locking patterns underlying effective communication in exact firing rate models of neural networks (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456269</id><title>Gpnmb inhibits oligodendrocyte differentiation of adult neural stem cells by amplifying TGFβ1 signaling (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.902079+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Z Radecki</name></author><author><name>Albert R Wang</name></author><author><name>Abigail S Johnson</name></author><author><name>Christian A Overman</name></author><author><name>Madison M Thatcher</name></author><author><name>Gopal Iyer</name></author><author><name>Jayshree Samanta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gli1 expressing neural stem cells, in the subventricular zone of the adult mammalian brain, respond to demyelination injury by differentiating into oligodendrocytes. We have identified Gpnmb as a novel regulator of oligodendrogenesis in Gli1 neural stem cells, whose expression is induced by TGFβ1 signaling via Gli1, in response to a demyelinating injury. Upregulation of Gpnmb further activates the TGFβ1 pathway by increasing the expression of the TGFβ1 binding receptor subunit, TGFβR2. Thus the TGFβ1→Gli1→Gpnmb→TGFβR2 signaling pathway forms a feed forward loop for sustained activation of TGFβ1 signaling in Gli1 neural stem cells, resulting in inhibition of their differentiation into mature oligodendrocytes following demyelination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456269" rel="alternate" title="Gpnmb inhibits oligodendrocyte differentiation of adult neural stem cells by amplifying TGFβ1 signaling (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456209</id><title>The temporal dynamics of the Stroop effect from childhood to young and older adulthood (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.902239+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric Ménétré</name></author><author><name>Marina Laganaro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;It is well admitted that children and older adults tend to show longer response latencies at the Stroop task than young adults. The present study aims at clarifying the rational of such changes from childhood to adulthood and in ageing by comparing the impacted cognitive processes across age groups. More precisely, the aim was to clarify if all processes take more time to be executed, hence implying that longer latencies rely mainly on processing speed or if an additional process lengthens the resolution of the conflict in children and/or older adults. To this aim we recorded brain electrical activity using EEG in school-age children, young and older adults while they performed a classic verbal Stroop task. To decompose the signal in the underlying brain networks, we used microstates analyses and compared congruent, incongruent and neutral trials across the three age-groups. Behaviorally, children and older adults presented longer latencies and larger Stroop effects relative to young adults. The microstates results showed that children tend to present different brain configurations compared to both adult groups, even though some brain configurations remained identical among the three groups. In particular, additional brain networks were involved in children to perform the Stroop task, which party account for the longer latencies in this group. By contrast, in aging the results favor the general slowing hypothesis rather than a decline in a specific process since all involved brain networks were similar in the two adult groups but slowed down in the older one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456209" rel="alternate" title="The temporal dynamics of the Stroop effect from childhood to young and older adulthood (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456040</id><title>No evidence for three functionally specialized subregions in the subthalamic nucleus: A model-based 7 T fMRI study (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.902374+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Miletić</name></author><author><name>Max C. Keuken</name></author><author><name>Martijn Mulder</name></author><author><name>Robert Trampel</name></author><author><name>Gilles de Hollander</name></author><author><name>Birte U. Forstmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The subthalamic nucleus (STN) is a small, subcortical brain structure. It is a target for deep brain stimulation, an invasive treatment that reduces motor symptoms of Parkinson’s disease. Side effects of DBS are commonly explained using the tripartite model of STN organization, which proposes three functionally distinct subregions in the STN specialized in cognitive, limbic, and motor processing. However, evidence for the tripartite model exclusively comes from anatomical studies and functional studies using clinical patients. Here, we provide the first experimental tests of the tripartite model in healthy volunteers using ultra-high field 7 Tesla (T) functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). 34 participants performed a random-dot motion decision-making task with a difficulty manipulation and a choice payoff manipulation aimed to differentially affect cognitive and limbic networks. Moreover, participants responded with their left and right index finger, differentially affecting motor networks. We analysed BOLD signal in three subregions of equal volume of the STN along the dorsolateral-ventromedial axis, identified using manually delineated high resolution anatomical images. Our results indicate that all segments responded equally to the experimental manipulations, and did not support the tripartite model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456040" rel="alternate" title="No evidence for three functionally specialized subregions in the subthalamic nucleus: A model-based 7 T fMRI study (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456047</id><title>Sleep spindles, ripples, and interictal epileptiform discharges in the human anterior and mediodorsal thalamus (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.902530+00:00</updated><author><name>Orsolya Szalardy</name></author><author><name>Peter Simor</name></author><author><name>Peter Przemyslaw Ujma</name></author><author><name>Zsofia Jordan</name></author><author><name>Laszlo Halasz</name></author><author><name>Lorand Eross</name></author><author><name>Daniel Fabo</name></author><author><name>Robert Bodizs</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep spindles are major oscillatory components of Non-Rapid Eye Movement (NREM) sleep, reflecting hyperpolarization-rebound sequences of thalamocortical neurons, the inhibition of which is caused by the NREM-dependent activation of GABAergic neurons in the reticular thalamic nucleus. Reports suggest a link between sleep spindles and several forms of interictal epileptic discharges (IEDs) which are considered as expressions of pathological off-line neural plasticity in the central nervous system. Here we investigated the relationship between thalamic sleep spindles, IEDs and ripples in the anterior and mediodorsal nuclei (ANT and MD) of epilepsy patients. Whole-night LFP from the ANT and MD were co-registered with scalp EEG/polysomnography by using externalized leads in 15 epilepsy patients undergoing Deep Brain Stimulation protocol. Slow (~12 Hz) and fast (~14 Hz) sleep spindles were present in the human ANT and MD. Roughly, one third of thalamic sleep spindles were associated with IEDs or ripples. Both IED- and ripple-associated spindles were longer than pure spindles. IED-associated thalamic sleep spindles were characterized by broadband increase in thalamic and cortical activity, both below and above the spindle frequency range, whereas ripple-associated thalamic spindles exceeded pure spindles in terms of 80-200 Hz thalamic, but not cortical activity as indicated by time-frequency analysis. These result show that thalamic spindles coupled with IEDs are reflected at the scalp slow and beta-gamma oscillation as well. IED density during sleep spindles in the MD, but not in the ANT was identified as correlates of years spent with epilepsy, whereas no signs of pathological processes were correlated with measures of ripple and spindle association. Furthermore, the density of ripple-associated sleep spindles in the ANT showed a positive correlation with general intelligence. Our findings indicate the complex and multifaceted role of the human thalamus in sleep spindle-related physiological and pathological neural plasticity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456047" rel="alternate" title="Sleep spindles, ripples, and interictal epileptiform discharges in the human anterior and mediodorsal thalamus (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455607</id><title>Single molecule fingerprinting reveals different amplification properties of α-synuclein oligomers and preformed fibrils in seeding assay. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.902696+00:00</updated><author><name>Derrick Lau</name></author><author><name>Chloe Magnan</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Hill</name></author><author><name>Antony Cooper</name></author><author><name>Yann Gambin</name></author><author><name>Emma Sierecki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The quantification of α-synuclein (α-syn) aggregates has emerged as a promising biomarker for synucleinopathies. Assays that amplify and detect such aggregates have revealed the presence of seeding-competent species in biosamples of patients diagnosed with Parkinsons disease. However, multiple species such as oligomers and amyloid fibrils, are formed during the aggregation of α-synuclein and these species are likely to co-exist in biological samples and thus it remains unclear which species(s) are contributing to the signal detected in seeding assays. To identify which species can be detected in seeding assays, recombinant oligomers and preformed fibrils were produced and purified to characterise their individual biochemical and seeding potential. Here, we used single molecule spectroscopy to track the formation and purification of oligomers and fibrils at the single particle level and compare their respective seeding potential in an amplification assay. Single molecule detection validates that size-exclusion chromatography efficiently separates oligomers from fibrils. Oligomers were found to be seeding-competent but our results reveal that their seeding behaviour is very different compared to preformed fibrils in our amplification assay. Overall, our data suggest that even a low number of preformed fibrils present in biosamples are likely to dominate the response in seeding assays.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455607" rel="alternate" title="Single molecule fingerprinting reveals different amplification properties of α-synuclein oligomers and preformed fibrils in seeding assay. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456240</id><title>Drosophila nicotinic acetylcholine receptor subunits and their native interactions with insecticidal peptide toxins (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.902849+00:00</updated><author><name>Dagmara Korona</name></author><author><name>Benedict Dirnberger</name></author><author><name>Carlo N. G. Giachello</name></author><author><name>Rayner M. L. Queiroz</name></author><author><name>David-Paul Minde</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Deery</name></author><author><name>Glynnis Johnson</name></author><author><name>Karin H. Mueller</name></author><author><name>Lucy C. Firth</name></author><author><name>Fergus G. Earley</name></author><author><name>Steven Russell</name></author><author><name>Kathryn S. Lilley</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drosophila nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) are ligand-gated ion channels that present a target for insecticides. However, a better understanding of receptor subunit composition is needed for effective design of insecticides. Peptide neurotoxins are known to block nAChRs by binding to its target subunits. To facilitate the analysis of nAChRs we used a CRISPR/Cas9 strategy to generate null alleles for all ten nAChR subunit genes. We studied interactions of nAChR subunits with peptide neurotoxins by larval injections and styrene maleic acid lipid particles (SMALPs) pull-down assays. For the null alleles we determined the effects of α-Bungarotoxin (α-Btx) and ω-Hexatoxin-Hv1a (Hv1a) administration, identifying potential receptor subunits implicated in the binding of these toxins. We employed pull-down assays to confirm α-Btx interactions with the Dα5, Dα6, Dα7 subunits. Finally, we report the localization of fluorescent tagged endogenous Dα6 during nervous system development. Taken together this study elucidates native Drosophila nAChR subunit interactions with insecticidal peptide toxins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456240" rel="alternate" title="Drosophila nicotinic acetylcholine receptor subunits and their native interactions with insecticidal peptide toxins (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456140</id><title>Learning from the path not taken: Sensory prediction errors are sufficient for implicit adaptation of withheld movements (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.903037+00:00</updated><author><name>Olivia A Kim</name></author><author><name>Alexander D Forrence</name></author><author><name>Samuel D McDougle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Current theories of motor control emphasize forward models as a critical component of the brain's motor execution and learning networks. These internal models are thought to predict the consequences of movement before sensory feedback from these movements can reach the brain, allowing for smooth, continuous online motor performance and for the computation of prediction errors that drive implicit motor learning. Taking this framework to its logical extreme, we tested the hypothesis that movements are not necessary for the generation of predictions, the computation of prediction errors, and implicit motor adaptation. Human participants were cued to move a computer mouse to a visually displayed target and were subsequently cued to withhold those movements on a subset of trials. Visual errors displayed on both trials with and without movements to the target induced single-trial learning. Furthermore, learning on trials without movements persisted when accompanying movement trials were never paired with errors and when movement and sensory feedback trajectories were decoupled. These data provide compelling evidence supporting an internal model framework in which forward models generate sensory predictions independent of the generation of movements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456140" rel="alternate" title="Learning from the path not taken: Sensory prediction errors are sufficient for implicit adaptation of withheld movements (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455700</id><title>Molecular Changes in Prader-Willi Syndrome Neurons Reveals Clues About Increased Autism Susceptibility. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.903302+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna Kaitlyn Victor</name></author><author><name>Martin Donaldson</name></author><author><name>Daniel Johnson</name></author><author><name>Winston Miller</name></author><author><name>Lawrence Reiter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) is a neurodevelopmental disorder characterized by hormonal dysregulation, obesity, intellectual disability, and behavioral problems. Most PWS cases are caused by paternal interstitial deletions of 15q11.2-q13.1, while a smaller number of cases are caused by chromosome 15 maternal uniparental disomy (PW-UPD). Children with PW-UPD are at higher risk for developing autism spectrum disorder (ASD) than the neurotypical population. In this study, we used expression analysis of PW-UPD neurons to try to identify the molecular cause for increased autism risk. Methods: Dental pulp stem cells (DPSC) from neurotypical control and PWS subjects were differentiated to neurons for mRNA sequencing. Significantly differentially expressed transcripts among all groups were identified. Downstream protein analysis including immunocytochemistry and immunoblots were performed to confirm the transcript level data and pathway enrichment findings. Results: We identified 9 transcripts outside of the PWS critical region (15q11.2-q13.1) that may contribute to core PWS phenotypes. Moreover, we discovered a global reduction in mitochondrial transcripts in the PW-UPD +ASD group. We also found decreased mitochondrial abundance along with mitochondrial aggregates in the cell body and neural projections of +ASD neurons. Conclusions: The 9 transcripts we identified common to all PWS subtypes may reveal PWS specific defects during neurodevelopment. Importantly, we found a global reduction in mitochondrial transcripts in PW-UPD +ASD neurons versus control and other PWS subtypes. We then confirmed mitochondrial defects in neurons from individuals with PWS at the cellular level. Quantification of this phenotype supports our hypothesis that the increased incidence of ASD in PW-UPD subjects may arise from mitochondrial defects in developing neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455700" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Changes in Prader-Willi Syndrome Neurons Reveals Clues About Increased Autism Susceptibility. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456095</id><title>Subtle alterations in neonatal neurodevelopment following early or late exposure to prenatal maternal immune activation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.903471+00:00</updated><author><name>Elisa Guma</name></author><author><name>Emily Snook</name></author><author><name>Shoshana Spring</name></author><author><name>Jason P Lerch</name></author><author><name>Brian J Nieman</name></author><author><name>Gabriel A Devenyi</name></author><author><name>M Mallar Chakravarty</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prenatal exposure to maternal immune activation (MIA) is a risk factor for a variety of neurodevelopmental and psychiatric disorders. The timing of MIA-exposure has been shown to affect adolescent and adult offspring neurodevelopment, however, less is known about these effects in the neonatal period. To better understand the impact of MIA-exposure on neonatal brain development, we first assess neonate communicative abilities with the ultrasonic vocalization task, followed by high-resolution ex vivo magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) on the neonatal (postnatal day 8) brain. Early exposed offspring displayed decreased communicative ability, while brain anatomy appeared largely unaffected, apart from some subtle alterations. By integrating MRI and behavioural assays to investigate the effects of MIA-exposure on neonatal neurodevelopment we show that offspring neuroanatomy and behaviour are only subtly affected by both early and late exposure. This suggests that the deficits often observed in later stages of life may be dormant, not yet developed in the neonatal period, or not as easily detectable using a cross-sectional approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456095" rel="alternate" title="Subtle alterations in neonatal neurodevelopment following early or late exposure to prenatal maternal immune activation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>