<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular neurosciences preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.039335+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/neurosciences/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475081</id><title>Neuromaps: structural and functional interpretation of brain maps (241 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.039791+00:00</updated><author><name>Ross D Markello</name></author><author><name>Justine Y Hansen</name></author><author><name>Zhen-Qi Liu</name></author><author><name>Vincent Bazinet</name></author><author><name>Golia Shafiei</name></author><author><name>Laura Estefany Suarez</name></author><author><name>Nadia Blostein</name></author><author><name>Jakob Seidlitz</name></author><author><name>Sylvain Baillet</name></author><author><name>Theodore D Satterthwaite</name></author><author><name>Mallar Chakravarty</name></author><author><name>Armin Raznahan</name></author><author><name>Bratislav Misic</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Imaging technologies are increasingly used to generate high-resolution reference maps of brain structure and function. Modern scientific discovery relies on making comparisons between new maps (e.g. task activations, group structural differences) and these reference maps. Although recent data sharing initiatives have increased the accessibility of such brain maps, data are often shared in disparate coordinate systems (or ``spaces''), precluding systematic and accurate comparisons among them. Here we introduce the neuromaps toolbox, an open-access software package for accessing, transforming, and analyzing structural and functional brain annotations. We implement two registration frameworks to generate high-quality transformations between four standard coordinate systems commonly used in neuroimaging research. The initial release of the toolbox features &amp;gt;40 curated reference maps and biological ontologies of the human brain, including maps of gene expression, neurotransmitter receptors, metabolism, neurophysiological oscillations, developmental and evolutionary expansion, functional hierarchy, individual functional variability, and cognitive specialization. Robust quantitative assessment of map-to-map similarity is enabled via a suite of spatial autocorrelation-preserving null models. By combining open-access data with transparent functionality for standardizing and comparing brain maps, the neuromaps software package provides a systematic workflow for comprehensive structural and functional annotation enrichment analysis of the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475081" rel="alternate" title="Neuromaps: structural and functional interpretation of brain maps (241 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474865</id><title>Dissociating encoding of memory and salience by manipulating long-term synaptic potentiation (234 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.040195+00:00</updated><author><name>Konstantin Kaganovsky</name></author><author><name>Mark H. Plitt</name></author><author><name>Renzhi Yang</name></author><author><name>Richard Sando</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Giocomo</name></author><author><name>Jun B. Ding</name></author><author><name>Thomas C. Südhof</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Neural codes are thought to be reorganized during memory formation by long-term potentiation (LTP) of synapses. Here, using a novel approach for selectively blocking LTP, we found that eliminating LTP in hippocampal or striatal circuits only produces limited effects on learning and memory. To reconcile the discrepancy between the large physiological effect of blocking LTP and the absent effect on learning, we studied how LTP impacts neuronal computations in the hippocampus using &lt;italic&gt;in-vivo&lt;/italic&gt; Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;-imaging. Contrary to current conceptual frameworks, we found that hippocampal CA1-region LTP is not required for accurate representations of space in hippocampal neurons, but rather endows these neurons with reward- and novelty-coding properties. Thus, instead of driving formation of cognitive maps and memory engrams, CA1-region LTP incorporates salience information into cognitive representations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A novel approach for studying long-term potentiation reveals its surprising and selective role in salience encoding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474865" rel="alternate" title="Dissociating encoding of memory and salience by manipulating long-term synaptic potentiation (234 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474849</id><title>Texture-like representation of objects in human visual cortex (46 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.040428+00:00</updated><author><name>Akshay V. Jagadeesh</name></author><author><name>Justin L. Gardner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The human visual ability to recognize objects and scenes is widely thought to rely on representations in category-selective regions of visual cortex. These representations could support object vision by specifically representing objects, or, more simply, by representing complex visual features regardless of the particular spatial arrangement needed to constitute real world objects. That is, by representing visual textures. To discriminate between these hypotheses, we leveraged an image synthesis approach that, unlike previous methods, provides independent control over the complexity and spatial arrangement of visual features. We found that human observers could easily detect a natural object among synthetic images with similar complex features that were spatially scrambled. However, observer models built from BOLD responses from category-selective regions, as well as a model of macaque inferotemporal cortex and Imagenet-trained deep convolutional neural networks, were all unable to identify the real object. This inability was not due to a lack of signal-to-noise, as all of these observer models could predict human performance in image categorization tasks. How then might these texture-like representations in category-selective regions support object perception? An image-specific readout from category-selective cortex yielded a representation that was more selective for natural feature arrangement, showing that the information necessary for object discrimination is available. Thus, our results suggest that the role of human category-selective visual cortex is not to explicitly encode objects but rather to provide a basis set of texture-like features that can be infinitely reconfigured to flexibly learn and identify new object categories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Virtually indistinguishable metamers of visual textures, such as wood grain, can be synthesized by matching complex features regardless of their spatial arrangement (1–3). However, humans are not fooled by such synthetic images of scrambled objects. Thus, category-selective regions of human visual cortex might be expected to exhibit representational geometry preferentially sensitive to natural objects. Contrarily, we demonstrate that observer models based on category-selective regions, models of macaque inferotemporal cortex and Imagenet-trained deep convolutional neural networks do not preferentially represent natural images, even while they are able to discriminate image categories. This suggests the need to reconceptualize the role of category-selective cortex as representing a basis set of complex texture-like features, useful for a myriad of visual behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474849" rel="alternate" title="Texture-like representation of objects in human visual cortex (46 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474708</id><title>Integrated genomic analysis of AgRP neurons reveals that IRF3 regulates leptin’s hunger-suppressing effects (30 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.040636+00:00</updated><author><name>Frankie D. Heyward</name></author><author><name>Nan Liu</name></author><author><name>Christopher Jacobs</name></author><author><name>Rachael Ivison</name></author><author><name>Natalia Machado</name></author><author><name>Aykut Uner</name></author><author><name>Harini Srinivasan</name></author><author><name>Suraj J. Patel</name></author><author><name>Anton Gulko</name></author><author><name>Tyler Sermersheim</name></author><author><name>Stuart H. Orkin</name></author><author><name>Linus Tsai</name></author><author><name>Evan D. Rosen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;AgRP neurons in the arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus (ARC) coordinate homeostatic changes in appetite associated with fluctuations in food availability and leptin signaling. Identifying the relevant transcriptional regulatory pathways in these neurons has been a priority, yet such attempts have been stymied due to their low abundance and the rich cellular diversity of the ARC. Here we generated AgRP neuron-specific transcriptomic and chromatin accessibility profiles during opposing states of fasting-induced hunger and leptin-induced hunger suppression. Cis-regulatory analysis of these integrated datasets enabled the identification of 28 putative hunger-promoting and 29 putative hunger-suppressing transcriptional regulators in AgRP neurons, 16 of which were predicted to be transcriptional effectors of leptin. Within our dataset, Interferon regulatory factor 3 (IRF3) emerged as a leading candidate mediator of leptin-induced hunger-suppression. Gain- and loss-of-function experiments &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; confirm the role of IRF3 in mediating the acute satiety-evoking effects of leptin in AgRP neurons, while live-cell imaging &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; indicate that leptin can activate neuronal IRF3 in a cell autonomous manner. Finally, we employ CUT&amp;amp;RUN to uncover direct transcriptional targets of IRF3 in AgRP neurons &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. Thus, our findings identify AgRP neuron-expressed IRF3 as a key transcriptional effector of the hunger-suppressing effects of leptin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474708" rel="alternate" title="Integrated genomic analysis of AgRP neurons reveals that IRF3 regulates leptin’s hunger-suppressing effects (30 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475265</id><title>An emergent temporal basis set robustly supports cerebellar time-series learning (25 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.040903+00:00</updated><author><name>Jesse I Gilmer</name></author><author><name>Michael A Farries</name></author><author><name>Zachary P Kilpatrick</name></author><author><name>Ioannis Delis</name></author><author><name>Abigail L Person</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Learning plays a key role in the function of many neural circuits. The cerebellum is considered a learning machine essential for time interval estimation underlying motor coordination and other behaviors. Theoretical work has proposed that the cerebellar input recipient structure, the granule cell layer (GCL), performs pattern separation of inputs that facilitates learning in Purkinje cells (P-cells). However, the relationship between input reformatting and learning outcomes has remained debated, with roles emphasized for pattern separation features from sparsification to decorrelation. We took a novel approach by training a minimalist model of the cerebellar cortex to learn complex time-series data from naturalistic inputs, in contrast to traditional classification tasks. The model robustly produced temporal basis sets from naturalistic inputs, and the resultant GCL output supported learning of temporally complex target functions. Learning favored surprisingly dense granule cell activity, yet the key statistical features in GCL population activity that drove learning differed from those seen previously for classification tasks. Moreover, different cerebellar tasks were supported by diverse pattern separation features that matched the demands of the tasks. These findings advance testable hypotheses for mechanisms of temporal basis set formation and predict that population statistics of granule cell activity may differ across cerebellar regions to support distinct behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475265" rel="alternate" title="An emergent temporal basis set robustly supports cerebellar time-series learning (25 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474842</id><title>Mosquito Olfactory Response Ensemble: a curated database of behavioral and electrophysiological responses enables pattern discovery (19 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.041206+00:00</updated><author><name>Abhishek Gupta</name></author><author><name>Swikriti S. Singh</name></author><author><name>Aarush M. Mittal</name></author><author><name>Pranjul Singh</name></author><author><name>Shefali Goyal</name></author><author><name>Karthikeyan R. Kannan</name></author><author><name>Arjit K. Gupta</name></author><author><name>Nitin Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many experimental studies have examined behavioral and electrophysiological responses of mosquitoes to odors. However, the differences across studies in data collection, processing, and reporting make it difficult to perform large-scale analyses combining data from multiple studies. Here we extract and standardize data for 12 mosquito species, along with Drosophila melanogaster for comparison, from over 170 studies and curate the Mosquito Olfactory Response Ensemble (MORE), publicly available at https://neuralsystems.github.io/MORE. We demonstrate the ability of MORE in generating biological insights by finding patterns across studies. Our analyses reveal that ORs are tuned to specific ranges of several physicochemical properties of odorants; the empty-neuron recording technique for measuring OR responses is more sensitive than the Xenopus oocyte technique; there are systematic differences in the behavioral preferences reported by different types of assays; and odorants tend to become less attractive or more aversive at higher concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474842" rel="alternate" title="Mosquito Olfactory Response Ensemble: a curated database of behavioral and electrophysiological responses enables pattern discovery (19 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474970</id><title>Proteomic identification of phosphorylation dependent Septin 7 interactors that drive dendritic spine formation (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.041423+00:00</updated><author><name>Sujin Byeon</name></author><author><name>Bailey Werner</name></author><author><name>Reilly Falter</name></author><author><name>Kristian Davidsen</name></author><author><name>Calvin Snyder</name></author><author><name>Shao-En Ong</name></author><author><name>Smita Yadav</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Septins are a family of cytoskeletal proteins that regulate several important aspects of neuronal development. Septin 7 (Sept7) is enriched at the base of dendritic spines in excitatory neurons and mediates both spine formation and spine-synapse maturation. Phosphorylation at a conserved C-terminal tail residue of Sept7 mediates its translocation into the dendritic spine head to allow spine-synapse maturation. The mechanistic basis for postsynaptic stability and compartmentalization conferred by phosphorylated Sept7, however, is not known. We report herein the proteomic identification of Sept7 phosphorylation dependent neuronal interactors. Using Sept7 C-terminal phosphopeptide pulldown and biochemical assays, we show that the 14-3-3 family of proteins specifically interact with Sept7 when phosphorylated at the T426 residue. Biochemically, we validate the interaction between Sept7 and 14-3-3 isoform gamma, and show that 14-3-3 gamma is also enriched in mature dendritic spine head. Further, we demonstrate that interaction of phosphorylated Sept7 with 14-3-3 protects it from dephosphorylation, as expression of a 14-3-3 antagonist significantly decreases phosphorylated Sept7 in neurons. This study identifies 14-3-3 proteins as an important physiological regulator of Sept7 function in neuronal development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474970" rel="alternate" title="Proteomic identification of phosphorylation dependent Septin 7 interactors that drive dendritic spine formation (15 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474845</id><title>Volatile anesthetics inhibit presynaptic cGMP signaling to depress presynaptic excitability in rat hippocampal neurons (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.041630+00:00</updated><author><name>Iris Speigel</name></author><author><name>Vanessa Osman</name></author><author><name>Hugh C Hemmings</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Volatile anesthetics alter presynaptic function including effects on Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; influx and neurotransmitter release. These actions are proposed to play important roles in their pleiotropic neurophysiological effects including unconsciousness and amnesia. The nitric oxide and cyclic guanosine monophosphate (NO/cGMP) signaling pathway has been implicated in presynaptic mechanisms, and disruption of NO/cGMP signaling has been shown to alter sensitivity to volatile anesthetics &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt;. We investigated NO/cGMP signaling in relation to volatile anesthetic actions in cultured rat hippocampal neurons using pharmacological tools and genetically encoded biosensors of cGMP levels. Using the fluorescent biosensor cGull we found that electrical stmulation-evoked NMDA-type glutamate receptor-independent presynaptic cGMP transients were inhibited −33.2% by isoflurane (0.51 mM) and −23.8% by sevoflurane (0.57 mM) (p&amp;lt;0.0001) compared to a stimulation without anesthetic. Isoflurane and sevoflurane inhibition of stimulation-evoked increases in presynaptic Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; concentration, measured with synaptophysin-GCaMP6f, and synaptic vesicle exocytosis, measured with synaptophysin-pHlourin, were reduced by in neurons expressing the cGMP scavenger sponGee. This reduction in anesthetic effect was recapitulated by inhibiting HCN channels, a cGMP-modulated effector that can facilitate glutamate release. We propose that volatile anesthetics depress presynaptic cGMP signaling and downstream effectors like HCN channels that are essential to presynaptic function and excitability. These findings identify a novel mechanism by which volatile anesthetics depress synaptic transmission via second messenger signaling involving the NO/cGMP pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474845" rel="alternate" title="Volatile anesthetics inhibit presynaptic cGMP signaling to depress presynaptic excitability in rat hippocampal neurons (10 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475275</id><title>Exploring Functional Brain Network Modularity in Educational Contexts (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.041799+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam B Weinberger</name></author><author><name>Robert A Cortes</name></author><author><name>Richard F Betzel</name></author><author><name>Adam E Green</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The brain's modular functional organization facilitates adaptability. Modularity has been linked with a wide range of cognitive abilities such as intelligence, memory, and learning. However, much of this work has (1) considered modularity while a participant is at rest rather than during tasks conditions and/or (2) relied primarily on lab-based cognitive assessments. Thus, the extent to which modularity can provide information about real-word behavior remains largely unknown. Here, we investigated whether functional modularity during resting-state and task-based fMRI was associated with academic learning (measured by GPA) and ability (measured by PSAT) in a large sample of high school students. Additional questions concerned the extent to which modularity differs between rest and task conditions, and across spatial scales. Results indicated that whole-brain modularity during task conditions was significantly associated with academic learning. In contrast to prior work, no such associations were observed for resting-state modularity. We further showed that differences in modularity between task conditions and resting-state varied across spatial scales. Taken together, the present findings inform how functional brain network modularity - during task conditions and while at rest - relate to a range of cognitive abilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475275" rel="alternate" title="Exploring Functional Brain Network Modularity in Educational Contexts (9 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475126</id><title>Neuronal apoptosis drives remodeling states of microglia and shifts in survival pathway dependence (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.042019+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Rose Anderson</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline M Roberts</name></author><author><name>Nate Ghena</name></author><author><name>Emmalyn Irvin</name></author><author><name>Joon Schwakopf</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Cooperstein</name></author><author><name>Alejandra Bosco</name></author><author><name>Monica L Vetter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microglia serve critical remodeling roles that shape the developing nervous system, responding to the changing neural environment with phagocytosis or soluble factor secretion. Recent single-cell sequencing (scRNAseq) studies have revealed the context-dependent diversity in microglial properties and gene expression, but the cues promoting this diversity are not well defined. Here, we ask how interactions with apoptotic neurons shape microglial state, including lysosomal and lipid metabolism gene expression and independence from Colony-stimulating factor 1 receptor (CSF1R) for survival. Using early postnatal mouse retina, a CNS region undergoing significant developmental remodeling, we performed scRNAseq on microglia from mice that are wild-type, lack neuronal apoptosis (Bax KO), or are treated with CSF1R inhibitor (PLX3397). We find that interactions with apoptotic neurons drives multiple microglial remodeling states, subsets of which are resistant to CSF1R inhibition. We find that TAM receptor Mer and complement receptor 3 are required for clearance of apoptotic neurons, but that Mer does not drive expression of remodeling genes. We show TAM receptor Axl is negligible for phagocytosis or remodeling gene expression but is consequential for microglial survival in the absence of CSF1R signaling. Thus, interactions with apoptotic neurons shift microglia towards distinct remodeling states and through Axl, alters microglial dependence on survival pathway, CSF1R.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475126" rel="alternate" title="Neuronal apoptosis drives remodeling states of microglia and shifts in survival pathway dependence (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475186</id><title>Random Compressed Coding with Neurons (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.042260+00:00</updated><author><name>Simone Blanco Malerba</name></author><author><name>Mirko Pieropan</name></author><author><name>Yoram Burak</name></author><author><name>Rava Azeredo da Silveira</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Classical models of efficient coding in neurons assume simple mean responses--'tuning curves'--such as bell shaped or monotonic functions of a stimulus feature. Real neurons, however, can be more complex: grid cells, for example, exhibit periodic responses which impart the neural population code with high accuracy. But do highly accurate codes require fine tuning of the response properties? We address this question with the use of a benchmark model: a neural network with random synaptic weights which result in output cells with irregular tuning curves. Irregularity enhances the local resolution of the code but gives rise to catastrophic, global errors. For optimal smoothness of the tuning curves, when local and global errors balance out, the neural network compresses information from a high-dimensional representation to a low-dimensional one, and the resulting distributed code achieves exponential accuracy. An analysis of recordings from monkey motor cortex points to such 'compressed efficient coding'. Efficient codes do not require a finely tuned design--they emerge robustly from irregularity or randomness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475186" rel="alternate" title="Random Compressed Coding with Neurons (8 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474947</id><title>Resting-State Network Analysis of Suicide Attempt History in the UK Biobank (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.042440+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew F. Thompson</name></author><author><name>Marjan Ghahramanlou-Holloway</name></author><author><name>Mikela A. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Kanchana U. Perera</name></author><author><name>Chelsie Benca-Bachman</name></author><author><name>Rohan H. C. Palmer</name></author><author><name>Joshua C. Gray</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior research has identified altered brain structure and function in individuals at risk for self-directed violence thoughts and behaviors. However, these studies have largely utilized healthy controls and findings have been inconsistent. Thus, this study examined differences in resting-state functional network connectivity among individuals with lifetime suicide attempt(s) versus lifetime self-directed violence thoughts alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using data from the UK Biobank, this study utilized a series of linear regressions to compare individuals with lifetime suicide attempt(s) (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 566) versus lifetime self-directed violence thoughts alone (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 3,447) on within- and between-network resting-state functional connectivity subnetworks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were no significant between-group differences for between-network, within-network, or whole-brain functional connectivity after adjusting for age, sex, ethnicity, and body mass index and performing statistical corrections for multiple comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Resting-state network measures may not differentiate between individuals with lifetime suicide attempt(s) and lifetime self-directed violence thoughts alone. Null findings diverge from results reported in smaller neuroimaging studies of suicide risk, but are consistent with null findings in other large-scale studies and meta-analyses. Strengths of the study include its large sample size and stringent control group. Future research on a wider array of imaging, genetic, and psychosocial risk factors can clarify relative contributions of individual and combined variables to suicide risk and inform scientific understanding of ideation-to-action framework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474947" rel="alternate" title="Resting-State Network Analysis of Suicide Attempt History in the UK Biobank (6 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475032</id><title>Transcriptional and cell type profiles of cortical brain regions showing ultradian cortisol rhythm dependent responses to emotional face stimulation (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.042644+00:00</updated><author><name>Philippe C Habets</name></author><author><name>Konstantinos Kalafatakis</name></author><author><name>Oleh Dzyubachyk</name></author><author><name>Steven J.A. van der Werff</name></author><author><name>Arlin Keo</name></author><author><name>Jamini Thakrar</name></author><author><name>Ahmed Mahfouz</name></author><author><name>Alberto M Pereira</name></author><author><name>Georgina M Russell</name></author><author><name>Stafford L Lightman</name></author><author><name>Onno C Meijer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The characteristic endogenous circadian rhythm of plasma glucocorticoid concentrations is made up from an underlying ultradian pulsatile secretory pattern. Recent evidence has indicated that this ultradian cortisol pulsatility is crucial for normal emotional response in man. In this study, we investigate the anatomical transcriptional and cell type signature of brain regions sensitive to a loss of ultradian rhythmicity in the context of emotional processing. We combine human cell type and transcriptomic atlas data of high spatial resolution with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) data. We show that the loss of cortisol ultradian rhythm alters emotional processing response in cortical brain areas that are characterized by transcriptional and cellular profiles of GABAergic function. We find that two previously identified key components of rapid non- genomic GC signaling – the ANXA1 gene and retrograde endocannabinoid signaling – show top differential expression and the most significant enrichment. Our results further indicate that specific cell types, including a specific NPY- expressing GABAergic neuronal cell type, and specific G protein signaling cascades underly the cerebral effects of a loss of ultradian cortisol rhythm. Our results provide a biological mechanistic underpinning of our fMRI findings, indicating specific cell types and cascades as a target for manipulation in future experimental studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475032" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional and cell type profiles of cortical brain regions showing ultradian cortisol rhythm dependent responses to emotional face stimulation (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474836</id><title>Long-term dynamic changes of NMDA receptors following an excitotoxic challenge (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.042887+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Granzotto</name></author><author><name>Marco d’Aurora</name></author><author><name>Manuela Bomba</name></author><author><name>Valentina Gatta</name></author><author><name>Marco Onofrj</name></author><author><name>Stefano L. Sensi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Excitotoxicity is a form of neuronal death characterized by the sustained activation of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors (NMDARs) triggered by the excitatory neurotransmitter glutamate. NADPH-diaphorase neurons [also known as nNOS (+) neurons] are a subpopulation of aspiny interneurons, largely spared following excitotoxic challenges. Unlike nNOS (-) cells, nNOS (+) neurons fail to generate reactive oxygen species in response to NMDAR activation, a key divergent step in the excitotoxic cascade. However, additional mechanisms underlying the reduced vulnerability of nNOS (+) neurons to NMDAR-driven neuronal death have not been explored. Using functional, genetic, and molecular analysis in striatal cultures, we demonstrate that nNOS (+) neurons possess distinct NMDAR properties. These specific features are primarily driven by the peculiar redox milieu of this subpopulation. In addition, we found that nNOS (+) neurons exposed to a pharmacological maneuver set to mimic chronic excitotoxicity alter their responses to NMDAR-mediated challenges. These findings suggest the presence of mechanisms providing long-term dynamic regulation of NMDARs that can have critical implications in neurotoxic settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474836" rel="alternate" title="Long-term dynamic changes of NMDA receptors following an excitotoxic challenge (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475212</id><title>Neural correlate of reduced respiratory chemosensitivity during chronic epilepsy (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.043136+00:00</updated><author><name>Amol Bhandare</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Dale</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While central autonomic cardiorespiratory dysfunction underlies sudden unexpected death in epilepsy (SUDEP), the specific neural mechanisms that lead to SUDEP remain to be determined. Here we took an advantage of single cell neuronal Ca2+ imaging and intrahippocampal kainic acid (KA)-induced chronic epilepsy in mice to investigate progressive changes in key cardiorespiratory brainstem circuits during chronic epilepsy. Following induction of status epilepticus (SE), we observed that the adaptive ventilatory responses to hypercapnia were reduced in mice with chronic epilepsy for 5 weeks post-SE. These changes were paralleled by reduced chemosensitivity of neurons in the retrotrapezoid nucleus (RTN), an important centre for respiratory chemosensitivity. Over the same period, chemosensory responses of the presympathetic RVLM neurons showed a slower decrease. Mice with chronic epilepsy were more sensitive to chemoconvulsants and exhibited a greatly reduced latency to seizure induction compared to naive mice. This enhanced sensitivity to seizures, which invade the RTN, puts the chemosensory circuits at further risk and increases the chances of terminal apnoea. Our findings establish a dysfunctional breathing phenotype with its RTN neuronal correlate in mice with chronic epilepsy and suggests a functional non-invasive biomarker test, based on respiratory chemosensitivity, to identify people with epilepsy at risk of SUDEP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475212" rel="alternate" title="Neural correlate of reduced respiratory chemosensitivity during chronic epilepsy (5 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474940</id><title>Sleep slow-wave oscillations trigger seizures in a genetic epilepsy model of Dravet syndrome (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.043299+00:00</updated><author><name>Mackenzie A. Catron</name></author><author><name>Rachel K. Howe</name></author><author><name>Gai-Linn K. Besing</name></author><author><name>Emily K. St. John</name></author><author><name>Cobie Victoria Potesta</name></author><author><name>Martin J. Gallagher</name></author><author><name>Robert L. Macdonald</name></author><author><name>Chengwen Zhou</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sleep is the brain state when cortical activity decreases and memory consolidates. However, in human epileptic patients, including genetic epileptic seizures such as Dravet syndrome, sleep is the preferential period when epileptic spike-wave discharges (SWDs) appear, with more severe epileptic symptoms in female patients than male patients, which influencing patient sleep quality and memory. Currently, seizure onset mechanisms during sleep period still remain unknown. Our previous work has shown that the sleep-like state-dependent synaptic potentiation mechanism can trigger epileptic SWDs(Zhang et al., 2021). In this study, using one heterozygous (het) knock-in (KI) transgenic mice (GABA&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt; receptor γ2 subunit &lt;italic&gt;Gabrg2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Q390X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; mutation) and an optogenetic method, we hypothesized that slow-wave oscillations (SWOs) themselves &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; could trigger epileptic seizures. We found that epileptic SWDs in het &lt;italic&gt;Gabrg2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/Q390X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; KI mice exhibited preferential incidence during NREM sleep period, accompanied by motor immobility/ facial myoclonus/vibrissal twitching, with more frequent incidence in female het KI mice than male het KI mice. Optogenetic induced SWOs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; significantly increased epileptic seizure incidence in het &lt;italic&gt;Gabrg2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/Q390X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; KI mice with increased duration of NREM sleep or quiet-wakeful states. Furthermore, suppression of SWO-related homeostatic synaptic potentiation by 4- (diethylamino)-benzaldehyde (DEAB) injection (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;italic&gt;p&lt;/italic&gt;.) greatly decreased seizure incidence in het KI mice, suggesting that SWOs did trigger seizure activity in het KI mice. In addition, EEG delta-frequency (0.1-4 Hz) power spectral density during NREM sleep was significantly larger in female het &lt;italic&gt;Gabrg2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/Q390X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; KI mice than male het &lt;italic&gt;Gabrg2&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;+/Q390X&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; KI mice, which likely contributes to the gender difference in seizure incidence during NREM sleep/quiet-wake as that in human patients.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474940" rel="alternate" title="Sleep slow-wave oscillations trigger seizures in a genetic epilepsy model of Dravet syndrome (4 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475181</id><title>Individual coactivation patterns improve the subject identification and their behavior association (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.043508+00:00</updated><author><name>Hang Yang</name></author><author><name>Xing Yao</name></author><author><name>Hong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Chun Meng</name></author><author><name>Bharat B Biswal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Brain states can be characterized by recurring coactivation patterns (CAPs). Traditional CAP analysis is performed at the group-level, while the human brain is individualized and the functional connectome has shown the uniqueness as fingerprint. Whether stable individual CAPs could be obtained from a single fMRI scan and could individual CAPs improve the identification is unclear. An open dataset, the midnight scan club was used in this study to answer these questions. Four CAP states were identified at three distinct levels (group-, subject- and scan-level) separately, and the CAPs were then reconstructed for each scan. Identification rate and differential identifiability were used to evaluate the identification performance. Our results demonstrated that the individual CAPs were unstable when using a single scan. By maintaining high intra-subject similarity and inter-subject differences, subject-level CAPs achieved the best identification performance. Brain regions that contributed to the identifiability were mainly located in higher-order networks (e.g., frontal-parietal network). Besides, head motion reduced the intra-subject similarity, while its impact on identification rate was non-significant. Finally, a pipeline was developed to depict brain-behavior associations in dataset with few samples but dense sampling, and individualized CAP dynamics showed an above-chance level correlation with IQ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475181" rel="alternate" title="Individual coactivation patterns improve the subject identification and their behavior association (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475224</id><title>Examining the Neural Correlates of Error Awareness in a Large fMRI Study (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.043697+00:00</updated><author><name>Gezelle Dali</name></author><author><name>Meadhbh B. Brosnan</name></author><author><name>Jeggan Tiego</name></author><author><name>Beth Johnson</name></author><author><name>Mark Bellgrove</name></author><author><name>Rob Hester</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Goal-directed behaviour is dependent upon the ability to detect errors and implement appropriate post-error adjustments. Accordingly, several studies have explored the neural activity underlying error-monitoring processes, identifying the insula cortex as crucial for error awareness and reporting mixed findings with respect to the anterior cingulate cortex. Variable patterns of activation have previously been attributed to insufficient statistical power. We therefore sought to clarify the neural correlates of error awareness in a large event-related functional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) study. Four hundred and two healthy participants undertook the Error Awareness Task, a motor Go/No-Go response inhibition paradigm in which participants were required to indicate their awareness of commission errors. Compared to unaware errors, aware errors were accompanied by significantly greater activity in a network of regions including the insula cortex, supramarginal gyrus, and midline structures such as the anterior cingulate cortex and supplementary motor area. Error awareness activity was related to indices of task performance and dimensional measures of psychopathology in select regions including the insula, supramarginal gyrus and supplementary motor area. Taken together, we identified a robust and reliable neural network associated with error awareness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475224" rel="alternate" title="Examining the Neural Correlates of Error Awareness in a Large fMRI Study (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475196</id><title>Synchronization in the connectome: Metastable oscillatory modes emerge from interactions in the brain spacetime network (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.043900+00:00</updated><author><name>Joana Cabral</name></author><author><name>Francesca Castaldo</name></author><author><name>Jakub Vohryzek</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Litvak</name></author><author><name>Christian Bick</name></author><author><name>Renaud Lambiotte</name></author><author><name>Karl Friston</name></author><author><name>Morten L Kringelbach</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Deco</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A rich repertoire of oscillatory signals is detected from human brains with electro- and magnetoencephalography (EEG/MEG). However, the principles underwriting coherent oscillations and their link with neural activity remain unclear. Here, we hypothesise that the emergence of transient brain rhythms is a signature of weakly stable synchronization between spatially distributed brain areas, occurring at network-specific collective frequencies due to non-negligible conduction times. We test this hypothesis using a phenomenological network model to simulate interactions between neural mass potentials (resonating at 40Hz) in the structural connectome. Crucially, we identify a critical regime where metastable oscillatory modes emerge spontaneously in the delta (0.5-4Hz), theta (4-8Hz), alpha (8-13Hz) and beta (13-30Hz) frequency bands from weak synchronization of subsystems, closely approximating the MEG power spectra from 89 healthy individuals. Grounded in the physics of delay-coupled oscillators, these numerical analyses demonstrate the role of the spatiotemporal connectome in structuring brain activity in the frequency domain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475196" rel="alternate" title="Synchronization in the connectome: Metastable oscillatory modes emerge from interactions in the brain spacetime network (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474806</id><title>Seed-competent tau monomer initiates pathology in PS19 tauopathy mice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.044288+00:00</updated><author><name>Hilda Mirbaha</name></author><author><name>Dailu Chen</name></author><author><name>Vishruth Mullapudi</name></author><author><name>Sandi Jo Terpack</name></author><author><name>Charles L. White</name></author><author><name>Lukasz A. Joachimiak</name></author><author><name>Marc I. Diamond</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tau aggregation into ordered assemblies causes myriad neurodegenerative tauopathies. We previously reported that tau monomer exists in either inert (M&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;) or seed-competent (M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt;) conformational ensembles, and that M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; encodes strains, which are biologically active, self-propagating assemblies. We have previously isolated M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; from tauopathy brains, but it is unknown if disease begins with M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; formation followed by fibril assembly, or if M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; derives from fibrils and is an epiphenomenon. Consequently, we studied a tauopathy mouse model (PS19) that expresses full-length human (1N4R) tau containing a disease-associated mutation (P301S). Using tau repeat domain biosensor cells, we detected insoluble tau seeding activity at 2 months. We found insoluble tau protein assemblies by immunoblot at 3 months. We next immunopurified monomer from mice aged 1-6 weeks using size exclusion chromatography. We detected soluble seeding activity at 4 weeks, before insoluble material or larger assemblies, with assemblies ranging from n=1-3 tau units. By 5 and 6 weeks, large soluble assemblies had formed. This indicated the first detectable pathological forms of tau were M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt;. We next tested for post-translational modifications of tau monomer from 1-6 weeks. We detected no phosphorylation unique to M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; in PS19 or Alzheimer’s disease brain. We conclude that tauopathy begins with formation of M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; monomer, whose activity is phosphorylation-independent. M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; self-assembles to form oligomers before it forms insoluble fibrils. The conversion of tau monomer from M&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; to M&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; thus constitutes the first detectable step in the initiation of tauopathy in this mouse model, with obvious implications for origins of disease in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474806" rel="alternate" title="Seed-competent tau monomer initiates pathology in PS19 tauopathy mice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474910</id><title>Drosophila Mechanical Nociceptors Preferentially Sense Localized Poking (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.044527+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhen Liu</name></author><author><name>Qi-Xuan Wang</name></author><author><name>Meng-Hua Wu</name></author><author><name>Shao-Zhen Lin</name></author><author><name>Xi-Qiao Feng</name></author><author><name>Bo Li</name></author><author><name>Xin Liang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical nociception is an evolutionarily conserved sensory process required for the survival of living organisms. Previous studies have revealed much about the neural circuits and key sensory molecules in mechanical nociception, but the cellular mechanisms adopted by nociceptors in force detection remain elusive. To address this issue, we study the mechanosensation of a fly larval nociceptor (class IV da neurons, c4da) using a customized mechanical device. We find that c4da are sensitive to mN-scale forces and make uniform responses to the forces applied at different dendritic regions. Moreover, c4da showed a greater sensitivity to more localized forces, consistent with them being able to sense the poking of sharp objects, such as wasp ovipositor. Further analysis reveals that high morphological complexity, mechanosensitivity to lateral tension and active signal propagation in the dendrites altogether facilitate the mechanosensitivity and sensory features of c4da. In particular, we discover that Piezo and Ppk1/Ppk26, two key mechanosensory molecules, make differential but additive contributions to the mechanosensation of c4da. In all, our results provide updates into understanding how c4da process mechanical signals at the cellular level and reveal the contributions of key molecules.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474910" rel="alternate" title="Drosophila Mechanical Nociceptors Preferentially Sense Localized Poking (3 tweets)"/><category term="Neuroscience"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>