<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv developmental-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.763922+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.450860</id><title>ECM-integrin signalling instructs cellular position-sensing to pattern the early mouse embryo (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.764524+00:00</updated><author><name>Esther Jeong Yoon Kim</name></author><author><name>Lydia Sorokin</name></author><author><name>Takashi Hiiragi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Development entails patterned emergence of diverse cell types within the embryo. In mammals, cells positioned inside the embryo gives rise to the inner cell mass (ICM) that eventually forms the embryo proper. Yet the molecular basis of how these cells recognise their ‘inside’ position to instruct their fate is unknown. Here we show that cells perceive their position through extracellular matrix (ECM) and integrin-mediated adhesion. Provision of ECM to isolated embryonic cells induces ICM specification and alters subsequent spatial arrangement between epiblast (EPI) and primitive endoderm (PrE) cells that emerge within the ICM. Notably, this effect is dependent on integrin β1 activity and involves apical to basal conversion of cell polarity. We demonstrate that ECM-integrin activity is sufficient for ‘inside’ positional signalling and it is required for proper sorting of EPI/PrE cells. Our findings thus highlight the significance of ECM-integrin adhesion in enabling position-sensing by cells to achieve tissue patterning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.450860" rel="alternate" title="ECM-integrin signalling instructs cellular position-sensing to pattern the early mouse embryo (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>