<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv developmental-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.765728+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450501</id><title>Acquisition of alveolar fate and differentiation competence by human fetal lung epithelial progenitor cells (31 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.766264+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyungtae Lim</name></author><author><name>Walfred Tang</name></author><author><name>Dawei Sun</name></author><author><name>Peng He</name></author><author><name>Sarah A. Teichmann</name></author><author><name>John C. Marioni</name></author><author><name>Kerstin B. Meyer</name></author><author><name>Emma L. Rawlins</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Variation in lung alveolar development is strongly linked to disease susceptibility. However, the cellular and molecular mechanisms underlying alveolar development are difficult to study in humans. Using primary human fetal lungs we have characterized a tip progenitor cell population with alveolar fate potential. These data allowed us to benchmark a self-organising organoid system which captures key aspects of lung lineage commitment and can be efficiently differentiated to alveolar type 2 cell fate. Our data show that Wnt and FGF signalling, and the downstream transcription factors NKX2.1 and TFAP2C, promote human alveolar or airway fate respectively. Moreover, we have functionally validated cell-cell interactions in human lung alveolar patterning. We show that Wnt signalling from differentiating fibroblasts promotes alveolar type 2 cell identity, whereas myofibroblasts secrete the Wnt inhibitor, NOTUM, providing spatial patterning. Our organoid system recapitulates key aspects of human lung development allowing mechanistic experiments to determine the underpinning molecular regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450501" rel="alternate" title="Acquisition of alveolar fate and differentiation competence by human fetal lung epithelial progenitor cells (31 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450504</id><title>Proper migration of lymphatic endothelial cells requires survival and guidance cues from arterial mural cells (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.766663+00:00</updated><author><name>Di Peng</name></author><author><name>Koji Ando</name></author><author><name>Marleen Gloger</name></author><author><name>Renae Skoczylas</name></author><author><name>Naoki Mochizuki</name></author><author><name>Christer Betsholtz</name></author><author><name>Shigetomo Fukuhara</name></author><author><name>Katarzyna Koltowska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The migration of lymphatic endothelial cells (LECs) is key for the development of the complex and vast lymphatic vascular network that pervades most of the tissues in an organism. In zebrafish, arterial intersegmental vessels together with chemokines have been shown to promote lymphatic cell migration from the horizontal myoseptum (HM). Here we found that LECs departure from HM coincides with the emergence of mural cells around the intersegmental arteries, raising the possibility that arterial mural cells promote LEC migration. Our live imaging and cell ablation experiments revealed that LECs migrate slower and fail to establish the lymphatic vascular network in the absence of arterial mural cells. We determined that mural cells are a source for the C-X-C motif chemokine 12 (Cxcl12a and Cxcl12b) and vascular endothelial growth factor C (Vegfc). We showed that ERK, a downstream component of Vegfc-Vegfr3 singling cascade, is activated in migrating LECs and that both chemokine and growth factor signalling is required for the robust migration. Furthermore, Vegfc-Vegfr3 has a pro-survival role in LECs during the migration. Together, the identification of mural cells a source for signals that guide LEC migration and survival will be important in the future design for rebuilding lymphatic vessels in the disease contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450504" rel="alternate" title="Proper migration of lymphatic endothelial cells requires survival and guidance cues from arterial mural cells (14 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>