<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv developmental-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.492150+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.22.444626</id><title>Co-option of local and systemic immune responses by the hormonal signalling system triggering metamorphosis (20 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.492469+00:00</updated><author><name>Catarina Nunes</name></author><author><name>Takashi Koyama</name></author><author><name>Elio Sucena</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Insect metamorphosis is regulated by the production, secretion and degradation of two peripheral hormones: 20-hydroxyecdysone (ecdysone) and juvenile hormone (JH). In addition to their roles in developmental regulation, increasing evidence suggests that these hormones are involved in innate immunity processes, such as phagocytosis and the induction of antimicrobial peptide (AMP) production.  AMP regulation includes systemic responses and local responses, at surface epithelia that contact with the external environments. At pupariation, Drosophila melanogaster increases dramatically the expression of three AMP genes: drosomycin (drs), drosomycin-like 2 (drsl2) and drosomycin-like 5 (drsl5). Using D. melanogaster, we show that the expression of drs at pupariation is dependent on ecdysone signalling in the fat body. This systemic immune response involving drs expression in the fat body operates via the ecdysone downstream target, Broad-Z4. In parallel, ecdysone also regulates local responses, specifically through the activation of drsl2 expression in the gut. Finally, we establish the relevance of this ecdysone dependent AMP expression for the control of bacterial persistence by showing that flies lacking drs expression in the fat body have higher bacterial persistence over metamorphosis. Together, our data establishes a new role for ecdysone during pupariation. We propose that the co-option of immune mechanisms by the hormonal cascade responsible for controlling metamorphosis constitutes a pre-emptive mechanism to control bacterial numbers in the pupa and increase developmental success.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.22.444626" rel="alternate" title="Co-option of local and systemic immune responses by the hormonal signalling system triggering metamorphosis (20 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444930</id><title>Stem cells commit to differentiation following multiple induction events in the Drosophila testis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.493385+00:00</updated><author><name>Alice C Yuen</name></author><author><name>Kenzo-Hugo Hillion</name></author><author><name>Marc Amoyel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;How and when potential becomes restricted in differentiating stem cell daughters is poorly understood. While it is thought that signals from the niche are actively required to prevent differentiation, another model proposes that stem cells can reversibly transit between multiple states, some of which are primed, but not committed, to differentiate. In the Drosophila testis, somatic cyst stem cells (CySCs) generate cyst cells, which encapsulate the germline to support its development. We find that CySCs are maintained independently of niche self-renewal signals if activity of the PI3K/Tor pathway is inhibited. Conversely, PI3K/Tor is not sufficient alone to drive differentiation, suggesting that it acts to license cells for differentiation. Indeed, we find that the germline is required for differentiation of CySCs in response to PI3K/Tor elevation, indicating that final commitment to differentiation involves several steps and intercellular communication. We propose that CySC daughter cells are plastic, that their fate depends on the availability of neighbouring germ cells, and that PI3K/Tor acts to induce a primed state for CySC daughters to enable coordinated differentiation with the germline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.444930" rel="alternate" title="Stem cells commit to differentiation following multiple induction events in the Drosophila testis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>