<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv developmental-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.656272+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453456</id><title>Fast transcriptional activation of developmental signalling pathways during wound healing of the calcareous sponge Sycon ciliatum (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.657058+00:00</updated><author><name>Cüneyt Caglar</name></author><author><name>Alexander Ereskovsky</name></author><author><name>Mary Laplante</name></author><author><name>Daria Tokina</name></author><author><name>Sven Leininger</name></author><author><name>Ilya Borisenko</name></author><author><name>Genevieve Aisbett</name></author><author><name>Di Pan</name></author><author><name>Marcin Adamski</name></author><author><name>Maja Adamska</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability to regenerate lost or damaged body parts is an ancient animal characteristic with a wide yet variable distribution across all phyla. Sponges, likely the sister group to all other animals, have remarkable regenerative abilities including whole body regeneration and re-development from dissociated cells. The calcareous sponge &lt;italic&gt;Sycon ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt; has been subject to various regeneration studies since the beginning of the last century. However, the early steps of wound healing of &lt;italic&gt;S. ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt; have not been addressed from the molecular perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we combined electron microscopy with gene expression analysis to investigate wound healing after transverse sectioning of &lt;italic&gt;S. ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt;. Microscopic analysis revealed massive transdifferentiation and collective migration behaviour of choanocytes and pinacocytes early upon injury (6-12h) as the main mechanisms for quick closure of the wound surface. RNA-sequencing identified upregulation of components of the conserved metazoan Wnt and TGFβ signalling pathways within 3h, preceding morphologically detectable wound healing events. De novo upregulation after a decline in expression coincides with morphologically visible polarity establishment. Moreover, by integrating the new wound healing data set with previously published data derived from intact sponge, we demonstrate similarity between gene activity during early wound healing and osculum maintenance. Whole mount &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt; hybridisation of the TGFβ signalling pathway ligand SciTGFβU and signal transducer SciSmadRa show that the early activation of both is initially encompassing a large area surrounding the cut surface with gradual restriction to the edge of the forming regenerative membrane as wound healing progresses. While SciTGFβU transcripts are localised to exo- and endopinacocytes, SciSmadRa expression appears across all cell types. Using an EdU cell proliferation assay, we found that a global increase in cell proliferation is not visible before 12h into wound healing. Hence, the initial stages to cover the injury site including cell transdifferentiation and migration seem to be executed by cells remaining after injury. Gene expression clustering coupled with GO term enrichment analysis confirmed that expression of genes involved in processes related to cell proliferation, DNA repair as well as apoptotic processes at 3 and 6h of wound healing was not upregulated. On the other hand, genes associated with positive regulation of transcription, signal transduction, actin filament and chromatin organisation, as well as the Wnt signalling pathway are upregulated at early wound healing stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have analysed wound healing in the calcareous sponge &lt;italic&gt;Sycon ciliatum&lt;/italic&gt; using microscopic and genomic methods. This study highlights a remarkable mechanism of interplay between cell transdifferentiation and collective migration we hypothesise to be regulated by conserved metazoan developmental pathways and numerous taxonomically restricted genes. Expression of these genes in regenerating and intact sponges sheds light on the long-standing question whether embryonic developmental pathways are redeployed in regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453456" rel="alternate" title="Fast transcriptional activation of developmental signalling pathways during wound healing of the calcareous sponge Sycon ciliatum (7 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>