<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv developmental-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.435720+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/developmental-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445819</id><title>ERK1/2 is an ancestral organising signal in spiral cleavage (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.436190+00:00</updated><author><name>Océane Seudre</name></author><author><name>Allan M. Carrillo-Baltodano</name></author><author><name>Yan Liang</name></author><author><name>José M. Martín-Durán</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Embryonic organisers are signalling centres that instruct the establishment of body plans during animal embryogenesis, thus underpinning animal morphological diversity. In spiral cleavage – a stereotypic developmental programme ancestral to 14, nearly half, of the major animal groups (e.g., molluscs, annelids and flatworms), a cell known as the D-quadrant organiser defines cell fates and the body axes. ERK1/2 specifies the embryonic organiser in molluscs, yet how this signalling cascade exerts organising activity and whether this role is conserved in other spiral cleaving groups is unclear. Here, we demonstrate that ERK1/2 promotes the specification and inductive activity of the D-quadrant organiser in &lt;italic&gt;Owenia fusiformis&lt;/italic&gt;, an early-branching annelid exhibiting ancestral developmental traits. In this species, active di-phosphorylated ERK1/2 mediated by FGF receptor activity localises to the 4d micromere, establishing the bilateral symmetry and specifying the hindgut and trunk mesodermal progenitor. Accordingly, impairing FGFR and ERK1/2 activity, as well as cell communication results in embryos developing anteroventrally radialised. Differential transcriptomic profiling shows the ParaHox &lt;italic&gt;cdx&lt;/italic&gt; and the Notch ligand &lt;italic&gt;delta&lt;/italic&gt; as FGFR/ERK1/2 downstream targets in 4d, further revealing that 4d specification instructs the expression of mesodermal and posterodorsal genes in neighbouring cells, putatively via the Notch pathway. The instructing role of ERK1/2 in the D-quadrant organiser is thus shared between &lt;italic&gt;O. fusiformis&lt;/italic&gt; and molluscs, representing an ancestral trait of spiral cleavage. Altogether, our study begins to dissect the gene network promoting axial patterning and posterior growth in spiral cleavage, revealing extensive mechanistic diversification in body plan specification despite overall conservation of cleavage patterns in Spiralia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445819" rel="alternate" title="ERK1/2 is an ancestral organising signal in spiral cleavage (45 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445940</id><title>BRD9-containing non-canonical BAF complexes safeguard cell identity and prevent reprogramming (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.436557+00:00</updated><author><name>Kenan Sevinc</name></author><author><name>Gülben Gürhan Sevinç</name></author><author><name>Ayşe Derya Cavga</name></author><author><name>Martin Philpott</name></author><author><name>Simge Kelekçi</name></author><author><name>Hazal Can</name></author><author><name>Adam P. Cribbs</name></author><author><name>Enes Sefa Ayar</name></author><author><name>Dilşad Hilal Arabacı</name></author><author><name>James P Dunford</name></author><author><name>Ata B Demir</name></author><author><name>Logan Sigua</name></author><author><name>Jun Qi</name></author><author><name>Udo Oppermann</name></author><author><name>Tamer T. Önder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic reprogramming requires extensive remodeling of chromatin landscapes to silence cell-type specific gene expression programs. ATP-dependent chromatin-remodeling complexes are important regulators of chromatin structure and gene expression; however, the role of Bromodomain-containing protein 9 (BRD9) and the associated ncBAF (non-canonical BRG1-associated factors) complex in reprogramming remains unknown. Here, we show that genetic suppression of BRD9 as well as ncBAF complex subunit GLTSCR1, but not the closely related BRD7, increase the efficiency by which induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) can be generated from human somatic cells. Chemical inhibition and acute degradation of BRD9 phenocopied this effect. Interestingly, we find that BRD9 is dispensable for establishment and maintenance of human pluripotency but required for mesendodermal lineage commitment during differentiation. Mechanistically, BRD9 inhibition downregulates somatic cell type-specific genes and decreases chromatin accessibility at somatic enhancers. Collectively, these results establish BRD9 as an important safeguarding factor for somatic cell identity whose inhibition lowers chromatin-based barriers to reprogramming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445940" rel="alternate" title="BRD9-containing non-canonical BAF complexes safeguard cell identity and prevent reprogramming (16 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446177</id><title>Maternal hyperglycemia impedes second heart field-derived cardiomyocyte differentiation to elevate the risk of congenital heart defects (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.437647+00:00</updated><author><name>Sathiyanarayanan Manivannan</name></author><author><name>Corrin Mansfield</name></author><author><name>Xinmin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Karthik M. Kodigepalli</name></author><author><name>Uddalak Majumdar</name></author><author><name>Vidu Garg</name></author><author><name>Madhumita Basu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Congenital heart disease (CHD) is the most frequently occurring structural malformations of the heart affecting ~1% of live births. Besides genetic predisposition, embryonic exposure to teratogens during pregnancy increases the risk of CHD. However, the dose and cell-type-specific responses to an adverse maternal environment remain poorly defined. Here, we report a dose-response relationship between maternal glucose levels and phenotypic severity of CHD in offspring, using a chemically-induced pregestational diabetes mellitus (PGDM) mouse model. Embryos from dams with low-level maternal hyperglycemia (matHG) displayed trabeculation defects, ventricular wall thinning, and ventricular septal defects (VSD). On the other hand, embryos from dams with high-level matHG display outflow tract malformations, ventricular wall thinning and an increased rate of VSD. Our findings show that increasing levels of matHG exacerbates CHD occurrence and severity in offspring compared to control embryos. We applied single-cell RNA- sequencing to define matHG-related transcriptional differences in E9.5 and E11.5 hearts as comparing to controls. Disease-dependent gene-expression changes were observed in Isl1+ second heart field (SHF) and Tnnt2+ cardiomyocyte subpopulations. Lineage tracing studies in Isl1-Cre; RosamTmG embryonic hearts showed Isl1+-SHF-derived cardiomyocyte differentiation was impaired with matHG. This study highlights the influence of matHG-dosage on cardiac morphogenesis and identifies perturbations in the Isl1-dependent gene-regulatory network that affect SHF-derived cardiomyocyte differentiation contributing to matPGDM-induced CHD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446177" rel="alternate" title="Maternal hyperglycemia impedes second heart field-derived cardiomyocyte differentiation to elevate the risk of congenital heart defects (9 tweets)"/><category term="Developmental Biology"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>