<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.611532+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447573</id><title>Endosperm evolution by duplicated and neofunctionalized Type I MADS-box transcription factors (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.611782+00:00</updated><author><name>Yichun Qiu</name></author><author><name>Claudia Köhler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MADS-box transcription factors (TFs) are present in nearly all major eukaryotic groups. They are divided into Type I and Type II that differ in domain structure, functional roles, and rates of evolution. In flowering plants, major evolutionary innovations like flowers, ovules and fruits have been closely connected to Type II MADS-box TFs. The role of Type I MADS-box TFs in angiosperm evolution remains to be identified. Here, we show that the formation of angiosperm-specific Type I MADS-box clades of Mγ and Mγ-interacting Mα genes (Mα*) can be tracked back to the ancestor of all angiosperms. Angiosperm-specific Mγ and Mα* genes were preferentially expressed in the endosperm, consistent with their proposed function as heterodimers in the angiosperm-specific embryo-nourishing endosperm tissue. We propose that duplication and diversification of Type I MADS-genes underpins the evolution of the endosperm, a developmental innovation closely connected to the origin and success of angiosperms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.08.447573" rel="alternate" title="Endosperm evolution by duplicated and neofunctionalized Type I MADS-box transcription factors (29 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448081</id><title>Bamboos flower after the return of an appropriate sun-moon phasing (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.611998+00:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Clerget</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All Asian woody bamboo species of economic importance are semelparous. They remain vegetative during time intervals that are specific to each species and range from three to 120 years, with notable concentrations around a series of values (3, 7-8, 14-17, 29-36, 42-48, 61-64, and 120 years). Then, they flower gregariously within a short period. As with all grasses, they are monocarpic and produce a large quantity of seeds before dying. Entire forests temporarily disappear during these periods, and the dates of these dramatic events have been recorded over the last 200 years. I have found that the concentrations of flowering cycles were highly correlated with the series of successive returns of almost the same sun-moon phasing as at seedling emergence. On basis of knowledge on plant photoperiod sensitivity, I hypothesize that bamboo plants i) run a lunar cellular clock that is set at the full moon, ii) retain in their cellular memory the exact sun-moon phasing of the year of their emergence as seedlings, and iii) inhibit flowering until the occurrence of a unique, species-specific sun-moon phasing that is shifted by a precise amount from the sun-moon phasing at their emergence. Recent evidence of plant responses to lunar cycles supports this hypothesis, for which experimental evidence is now anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.11.448081" rel="alternate" title="Bamboos flower after the return of an appropriate sun-moon phasing (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447312</id><title>Changes In Ploidy Affect Vascular Allometry And Hydraulic Function In Trees (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.612166+00:00</updated><author><name>M Barceló-Anguiano</name></author><author><name>NM Holbrook</name></author><author><name>JI Hormaza</name></author><author><name>JM Losada</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The enucleated vascular elements of the xylem and the phloem offer an excellent system to test the effect of ploidy on plant function because variation in vascular geometry has a direct influence on transport efficiency. However, evaluations of conduit sizes in polyploid plants have remained elusive, most remarkably in woody species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We used a combination of molecular, physiological, and microscopy techniques to model the hydraulic resistance between source and sinks in tetraploid and diploid mango trees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tetraploids exhibited larger chloroplasts, mesophyll cells, and stomatal guard cells, resulting in higher leaf elastic modulus and lower dehydration rates despite the high water potentials of both ploidies in the field. Both the xylem and the phloem displayed a scaling of conduits with ploidy, revealing attenuated hydraulic resistance in tetraploids.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conspicuous wall hygroscopic moieties in the cells involved in processes of transpiration and transport advocates a role in volumetric adjustments due to turgor change in polyploids, which, together with the enlargement of organelles, cells, and tissues that are critical for water and photo assimilate transport at long distances, imply major physiological novelties of polyploidy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447312" rel="alternate" title="Changes In Ploidy Affect Vascular Allometry And Hydraulic Function In Trees (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>