<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.275473+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472330</id><title>Yield is negatively correlated with nucleotide-binding leucine-rich repeat gene content in soybean (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.275844+00:00</updated><author><name>Philipp E. Bayer</name></author><author><name>Haifei Hu</name></author><author><name>Jakob Petereit</name></author><author><name>Mark C Derbyshire</name></author><author><name>Rajeev K. Varshney</name></author><author><name>Babu Valliyodan</name></author><author><name>Henry T. Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline Batley</name></author><author><name>David Edwards</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The availability of increasing quantities of crop pangenome data permits the detailed association of gene content with agronomic traits. Here, we investigate disease resistance gene content of diverse soybean cultivars and report a significant negative correlation between the number of NLR resistance (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;) genes and yield. We find no association between &lt;italic&gt;R-&lt;/italic&gt;genes with seed weight, oil or protein content, and we find no correlation between yield and the number of RLK, RLP genes, or the total number of genes. These results suggest that recent yield improvement in soybean may be partially associated with the selective loss of NLR genes. Three quarters of soybean NLR genes do not show presence/absence variation, limiting the ability to select for their absence, and so the deletion or disabling of select NLR genes may support future yield improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472330" rel="alternate" title="Yield is negatively correlated with nucleotide-binding leucine-rich repeat gene content in soybean (34 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472499</id><title>The structural repertoire of Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. lycopersici effectors revealed by experimental and computational studies (27 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.276095+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel S. Yu</name></author><author><name>Megan A. Outram</name></author><author><name>Ashley Smith</name></author><author><name>Carl L. McCombe</name></author><author><name>Pravin B. Khambalkar</name></author><author><name>Sharmin A. Rima</name></author><author><name>Xizhe Sun</name></author><author><name>Lisong Ma</name></author><author><name>Daniel J. Ericsson</name></author><author><name>David A. Jones</name></author><author><name>Simon J. Williams</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plant pathogens secrete proteins, known as effectors, that function in the apoplast and inside plant cells to promote virulence. Effectors can also be detected by cell-surface and cytosolic receptors, resulting in the activation of defence pathways and plant immunity. Our understanding of fungal effector function and detection by immunity receptors is limited largely due to high sequence diversity and lack of identifiable sequence motifs precluding prediction of structure or function. Recent studies have demonstrated that fungal effectors can be grouped into structural classes despite significant sequence variation. Using protein x-ray crystallography, we identify a new structural class of effectors hidden within the secreted in xylem (SIX) effectors from &lt;italic&gt;Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. lycopersici&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Fol&lt;/italic&gt;). The recognised effectors Avr1 (SIX4) and Avr3 (SIX1) represent the founding members of the Fol dual-domain (FOLD) effector class. Using AlphaFold ab initio protein structure prediction, benchmarked against the experimentally determined structures, we demonstrate SIX6 and SIX13 are FOLD effectors. We show that the conserved N-domain of Avr1 and Avr3 is sufficient for recognition by their corresponding, but structurally-distinct, immunity receptors. Additional structural prediction and comparison indicate that 11 of the 14 SIX effectors group into four structural families. This revealed that genetically linked effectors are related structurally, and we provide direct evidence for a physical association between one divergently-transcribed effector pair. Collectively, these data indicate that Fol secretes groups of structurally-related molecules during plant infection, an observation that has broad implications for our understanding of pathogen virulence and the engineering of plant immunity receptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.14.472499" rel="alternate" title="The structural repertoire of Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. lycopersici effectors revealed by experimental and computational studies (27 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472773</id><title>Regulation of effector gene expression as concerted waves in Leptosphaeria maculans: a two-players game (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.276287+00:00</updated><author><name>Colin Clairet</name></author><author><name>Elise J Gay</name></author><author><name>Antoine Porquier</name></author><author><name>Françoise Blaise</name></author><author><name>Claire-Line Marais</name></author><author><name>Marie-Hélène Balesdent</name></author><author><name>Thierry Rouxel</name></author><author><name>Jessica L. Soyer</name></author><author><name>Isabelle Fudal</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;During infection, plant pathogenic fungi secrete a set of molecules collectively known as effectors, involved in overcoming the host immune system and in disease establishment. Effector genes are concertedly expressed as waves all along plant pathogenic fungi lifecycle. However, little is known about how coordinated expression of effector genes is regulated. Since many effector genes are located in repeat-rich regions, the role of chromatin remodeling in the regulation of effector expression was recently investigated. In &lt;italic&gt;Leptosphaeria maculans&lt;/italic&gt;, causing stem canker of oilseed rape, we established that the repressive histone modification H3K9me3 (trimethylation of Lysine 9 of Histone H3), deposited by the histone methyltransferase KMT1, was involved in the regulation of expression of genes highly expressed during infection, including effectors. Nevertheless, inactivation of &lt;italic&gt;KMT1&lt;/italic&gt; did not induce expression of these genes at the same level as observed during infection of oilseed rape, suggesting that a second regulator, such as a transcription factor (TF), might be involved. Pf2, a TF belonging to the Zn2Cys6 fungal specific TF family, was described in several Dothideomycete species as essential for pathogenicity and effector gene expression. We identified the orthologue of Pf2 in &lt;italic&gt;L. maculans&lt;/italic&gt;, LmPf2, and investigated the role of LmPf2 together with KMT1, by inactivating and over-expressing LmPf2 in a wild type (WT) strain and a &lt;italic&gt;∆kmt1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. Functional analyses of the corresponding transformants highlighted an essential role of LmPf2 in the establishment of pathogenesis. Transcriptomic analyses during axenic growth showed that LmPf2 is involved in the control of effector gene expression. We observed an enhanced effect of the over-expression of &lt;italic&gt;LmPf2&lt;/italic&gt; on effector gene expression in a &lt;italic&gt;∆kmt1&lt;/italic&gt; background, suggesting an antagonist role between KMT1 and LmPf2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472773" rel="alternate" title="Regulation of effector gene expression as concerted waves in Leptosphaeria maculans: a two-players game (15 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472848</id><title>Flv3A facilitates O2 photoreduction and affects H2 photoproduction independently of Flv1A in diazotrophic Anabaena filaments (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.276475+00:00</updated><author><name>Anita Santana Sanchez</name></author><author><name>Lauri Nikkanen</name></author><author><name>Gabor Toth</name></author><author><name>Maria Ermakova</name></author><author><name>Sergey Kosourov</name></author><author><name>Julia Walter</name></author><author><name>Meilin He</name></author><author><name>Eva-Mari Aro</name></author><author><name>Yagut Allahverdiyeva</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The model heterocyst-forming filamentous cyanobacterium, Anabaena sp. PCC 7120 (Anabaena) represents multicellular organisms capable of simultaneously performing oxygenic photosynthesis in vegetative cells and the O2-sensitive N2-fixation inside the heterocysts. The flavodiiron proteins (FDPs) have been shown to participate in photoprotection of photosynthesis by driving excess electrons to O2 (Mehler-like reaction). Here, we addressed the physiological relevance of the vegetative cell-specific Flv1A and Flv3A on the bioenergetic processes occurring in the diazotrophic Anabaena under variable CO2. We demonstrate that both Flv1A and Flv3A are required for proper induction of the Mehler-like reaction upon a sudden change in light intensity, which is likely important for the activation of carbon-concentrating mechanisms (CCM) and CO2 fixation. Nevertheless, Flv3A showed a more important role in photoprotection than Flv1A. Under low CO2 diazotrophic conditions, Flv3A is capable of mediating moderate O2 photoreduction, independently of Flv1A, but in coordination with Flv2 and Flv4. Strikingly, the lack of Flv3A resulted in strong downregulation of the heterocyst-specific uptake hydrogenase, which led to enhanced H2 photoproduction under both oxic and micro-oxic conditions. These results reveal a novel regulatory network between the Mehler-like reaction and the H2 metabolism, which is of great interest for future photobiological production of H2 in Anabaena.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472848" rel="alternate" title="Flv3A facilitates O2 photoreduction and affects H2 photoproduction independently of Flv1A in diazotrophic Anabaena filaments (12 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.472861</id><title>OPEN leaf: an open-source cloud-based phenotyping system for tracking dynamic changes at leaf-specific resolution in Arabidopsis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.276629+00:00</updated><author><name>Landon Gary Alan Swartz</name></author><author><name>Suxing Liu</name></author><author><name>Drew Dahlquist</name></author><author><name>Emily S Walter</name></author><author><name>Skyler Kramer</name></author><author><name>Sam McInturf</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bucksch</name></author><author><name>David Mendoza-Cozatl</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The first draft of the Arabidopsis genome was released more than 20 years ago and despite intensive molecular research, more than 30% of Arabidopsis genes remained uncharacterized or without an assigned function. This is in part due to gene redundancy within gene families or the essential nature of genes, where their deletion results in lethality (i.e., the dark genome). High-throughput plant phenotyping (HTPP) offers an automated and unbiased approach to characterize subtle or transient phenotypes resulting from gene redundancy or inducible gene silencing; however, commercial HTPP platforms remain unaffordable. Here we describe the design and implementation of OPEN leaf, an open-source HTPP system with cloud connectivity and remote bilateral communication to facilitate data collection, sharing and processing. OPEN leaf, coupled with the SMART imaging processing package was able to consistently document and quantify dynamic morphological changes over time at the whole rosette level and also at leaf-specific resolution when plants experienced changes in nutrient availability. The modular design of OPEN leaf allows for additional sensor integration. Notably, our data demonstrate that VIS sensors remain underutilized and can be used in high-throughput screens to identify characterize previously unidentified phenotypes in a leaf-specific manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.472861" rel="alternate" title="OPEN leaf: an open-source cloud-based phenotyping system for tracking dynamic changes at leaf-specific resolution in Arabidopsis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473023</id><title>Auxin-driven ecophysiological diversification of leaves in domesticated tomato (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.276776+00:00</updated><author><name>Juliene dos Reis Moreira</name></author><author><name>Bruno Luan Rosa</name></author><author><name>Bruno S. Lira</name></author><author><name>Joni E. Lima</name></author><author><name>Ludmila N. Souza</name></author><author><name>Wagner C. Otoni</name></author><author><name>Antonio Figueira</name></author><author><name>Luciano Freschi</name></author><author><name>Tetsu Sakamoto</name></author><author><name>Lazaro Peres</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Rossi</name></author><author><name>Agustin Zsogon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The study of crop diversification has focussed mainly on the genetic changes underlying traits favoured by humans. However, the passage from natural habitats to agronomic settings probably operated changes beyond those comprising the classical domestication syndrome. A deeper understanding of these traits and their genetic signature would be valuable to inform conventional crop breeding and de novo domestication of crop wild relatives. Heterobaric leaves have bundle sheath extensions (BSEs) that compartmentalise the sub-stomatal cavity whereas homobaric leaves do not; BSE development is known to be controlled by the OBSCURAVENOSA (OBV) locus and the obv mutant lacks BSEs whereas leaves carrying the wild type allele have BSEs. Here we identify a non-synonymous amino acid change in the OBV gene that exists as a rare balanced polymorphism in the natural range of wild tomatoes, but has increased in frequency in domesticated tomatoes, suggesting that the latter diversified into heterobaric and homobaric leaf types. The mutation disrupts a C2H2 zinc finger motif in the OBV protein, resulting in the absence of BSEs in leaves and here we show that this and other pleiotropic effects, including changes in leaf insertion angle, leaf margin serration, minor vein density and fruit shape, are controlled by OBV via changes in auxin signalling. Loss of function of the transcriptional regulator AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR (ARF4) also results in defective BSE development, revealing an additional component of a novel genetic module controlling aspects of leaf development important for ecological adaptation and subject to breeding selections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473023" rel="alternate" title="Auxin-driven ecophysiological diversification of leaves in domesticated tomato (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473009</id><title>Towards a global perspective for Salvia L: Phylogeny, diversification, and floral evolution (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.276948+00:00</updated><author><name>Fatemeh Moein</name></author><author><name>Ziba Jamzad</name></author><author><name>Mohammadreza Rahiminejad</name></author><author><name>Jacob Brian Landis</name></author><author><name>Mansour Mirtadzadini</name></author><author><name>Douglas Edward Soltis</name></author><author><name>Pamela Sue Soltis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Premise of this study: Salvia is the most species-rich genus in Lamiaceae, encompassing approximately 1000 species distributed all over the world. We sought a new evolutionary perspective for Salvia by employing macroevolutionary analyses to address the tempo and mode of diversification. To study the association of floral traits with speciation and extinction, we modeled and explored the evolution of corolla length and the lever-mechanism pollination system across our Salvia phylogeny. 
Methods: We reconstructed a multigene phylogeny for 366 species of Salvia in the broad sense including all major recognized lineages and numerous species from Iran, a region previously overlooked in studies of the genus. Our phylogenetic data in combination with divergence time estimates were used to examine the evolution of corolla length, woody vs. herbaceous habit, and presence vs. absence of a lever mechanism. We investigated the timing and dependence of Salvia diversification related to corolla length evolution through a disparity test and BAMM analysis. A HiSSE model was used to evaluate the dependency of diversification on the lever-mechanism pollination system in Salvia.
Key Results: Based on recent investigations and classifications, Salvia is monophyletic and comprises ~1000 species. Our inclusion, for the first time, of a comprehensive sampling for Iranian species of Salvia provides higher phylogenetic resolution for southwestern Asian species than obtained in previous studies. A medium corolla length (15-18mm) was reconstructed as the ancestral state for Salvia with multiple shifts to shorter and longer corollas. Macroevolutionary model analyses indicate that corolla length disparity is high throughout Salvia evolution, significantly different from expectations under a Brownian motion model during the last 28 million years of evolution. Our analyses show evidence of a higher diversification rate of corolla length for some Andean species of Salvia compared to other members of the genus. Based on our tests of diversification models, we reject the hypothesis of a direct effect of the lever mechanism on Salvia diversification.
Conclusions: Using a broader species sampling than previous studies, we obtained a well-resolved phylogeny for southwest Asian species of Salvia. Corolla length is an adaptive trait throughout the Salvia phylogeny with a higher rate of diversification in the South American clade. Our results suggest caution in considering the lever-mechanism pollination system as one of the main drivers of speciation in Salvia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473009" rel="alternate" title="Towards a global perspective for Salvia L: Phylogeny, diversification, and floral evolution (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>