<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.200460+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470347</id><title>SCARECROW is deployed in distinct developmental contexts during rice and maize leaf development (62 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.200843+00:00</updated><author><name>Thomas. E. Hughes</name></author><author><name>Jane A. Langdale</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The flexible deployment of developmental regulators is an increasingly appreciated aspect of plant development and evolution. The GRAS transcription factor SCARECROW (SCR) regulates the development of the endodermis in Arabidopsis and maize roots, but during leaf development it regulates the development of distinct cell-types; bundle-sheath in Arabidopsis and mesophyll in maize. In rice, SCR is implicated in stomatal patterning, but it is unknown whether this function is additional to a role in inner leaf patterning. Here, we demonstrate that two duplicated &lt;italic&gt;SCR&lt;/italic&gt; genes function redundantly in rice. Contrary to previous reports, we show that these genes are necessary for stomatal development, with stomata virtually absent from leaves that are initiated after germination of mutants. The stomatal regulator OsMUTE is down-regulated in &lt;italic&gt;Osscr1;Osscr2&lt;/italic&gt; mutants indicating that OsSCR acts early in stomatal development. Notably, &lt;italic&gt;Osscr1;Osscr2&lt;/italic&gt; mutants do not exhibit the inner leaf patterning perturbations seen in &lt;italic&gt;Zmscr1;Zmscr1h&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and &lt;italic&gt;Zmscr1;Zmscr1h&lt;/italic&gt; mutants do not exhibit major perturbations in stomatal patterning. Taken together, these results indicate that SCR was deployed in different developmental contexts after the divergence of rice and maize around 50 million years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transcription factor SCARECROW patterns stomata in rice leaves whereas in maize it predominantly patterns the inner leaf.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470347" rel="alternate" title="SCARECROW is deployed in distinct developmental contexts during rice and maize leaf development (62 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470717</id><title>A new protocol for speed vernalisation of winter cereals (46 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.201121+00:00</updated><author><name>Jin-Kyung Cha</name></author><author><name>Kathryn O’Connor</name></author><author><name>Samir Alahmad</name></author><author><name>Jong-Hee Lee</name></author><author><name>Eric Dinglasan</name></author><author><name>Hyeonjin Park</name></author><author><name>So-Myeong Lee</name></author><author><name>Dominique Hirsz</name></author><author><name>Soon-Wook Kwon</name></author><author><name>Youngho Kwon</name></author><author><name>Kyeong-Min Kim</name></author><author><name>Jong-Min Ko</name></author><author><name>Lee T. Hickey</name></author><author><name>Dongjin Shin</name></author><author><name>Laura E. Dixon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are many challenges facing the development of high-yielding, nutritious crops for future environments. One limiting factor is generation time, which prolongs research and plant breeding timelines. Recent advances in speed breeding protocols have dramatically reduced generation time for many short-day and long-day species by optimising light and temperature conditions during plant growth. However, winter crops with a vernalisation requirement still require up to 6–10 weeks in low-temperature conditions before transition to reproductive development. Here, we tested a suite of environmental conditions and protocols to investigate if vernalisation can be satisfied more efficiently. We identified a vernalisation method consisting of exposing seeds at the soil surface to an extended photoperiod of 22 h day:2 h night at 10°C with transfer to speed breeding conditions that dramatically reduces generation time in both winter wheat (&lt;italic&gt;Triticum aestivum&lt;/italic&gt;) and winter barley (&lt;italic&gt;Hordeum vulgare&lt;/italic&gt;). Implementation of this protocol achieved up to five generations per year for winter wheat or barley, instead of the two typically obtained under standard vernalisation and plant growth conditions. The protocol has great potential to enhance training and to accelerate research, pre-breeding, and breeding outcomes focussed on winter crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470717" rel="alternate" title="A new protocol for speed vernalisation of winter cereals (46 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470438</id><title>Differential EDS1 requirement for cell death activities of plant TIR-domain proteins (46 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.201532+00:00</updated><author><name>Oliver Johanndrees</name></author><author><name>Erin L. Baggs</name></author><author><name>Charles Uhlmann</name></author><author><name>Federica Locci</name></author><author><name>Henriette L. Läßle</name></author><author><name>Katharina Melkonian</name></author><author><name>Kiara Käufer</name></author><author><name>Joram A. Dongus</name></author><author><name>Hirofumi Nakagami</name></author><author><name>Ksenia V. Krasileva</name></author><author><name>Jane E. Parker</name></author><author><name>Dmitry Lapin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Toll/interleukin-1 Receptor (TIR) domains are integral to immune systems across all domains of life. TIRs exist as single-domain and as larger receptor or adaptor proteins. In plants, TIRs constitute N-terminal domains of nucleotide-binding leucine-rich repeat (NLR) immune receptors. Although TIR-NLR and TIR signaling requires the Enhanced disease susceptibility 1 (EDS1) protein family, TIR domains persist in species that have incomplete or no EDS1 members. To assess whether particular TIR groups appear with EDS1, we searched for TIR-EDS1 co-occurrence patterns. Using a large-scale phylogenetic analysis of TIR domains from 39 algae and land plant species, we identify four conserved TIR groups, two of which are TIR-NLRs present in eudicots and two are more widespread. Presence of one TIR-only protein group is highly correlated with EDS1 and members of this group elicit &lt;italic&gt;EDS1&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent cell death. By contrast, a more widely represented TIR group of TIR-NB-WD40/TPR (TNP) proteins (formerly called XTNX) has at least one member which can induce &lt;italic&gt;EDS1&lt;/italic&gt;-independent cell death. Our data provide a new phylogeny-based plant TIR classification and identify TIR groups that appear to have evolved with and are dependent on &lt;italic&gt;EDS1&lt;/italic&gt;, while others have &lt;italic&gt;EDS1&lt;/italic&gt;-independent activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Land plants have evolved four conserved TIR groups&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.29.470438" rel="alternate" title="Differential EDS1 requirement for cell death activities of plant TIR-domain proteins (46 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470751</id><title>Overexpression of NDR1 Leads to Pathogen Resistance at Elevated Temperatures (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.202000+00:00</updated><author><name>Saroopa P. Samaradivakara</name></author><author><name>Huan Chen</name></author><author><name>Yi-Ju Lu</name></author><author><name>Pai Li</name></author><author><name>Yongsig Kim</name></author><author><name>Kenichi Tsuda</name></author><author><name>Akira Mine</name></author><author><name>Brad Day</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abiotic and biotic environments influence a myriad of plant-related processes, including growth, development, and the establishment and maintenance of interaction(s) with microbes. As a driver of this signaling between plants and microbes, the role of plant hormones in both surveillance and signaling has emerged as a point of intersection between plant-abiotic and -biotic responses. In the current study, we elucidate a role for NON-RACE-SPECIFIC DISEASE RESISTANCE1 (NDR1) by exploiting effector-triggered immunity (ETI) to define the regulation of plant host immunity in response to both pathogen infection and elevated temperature. We generated time-series RNA sequencing data of WT Col-0, a NDR1 overexpression line, as well as ndr1 and ics1-2 mutant plants under elevated temperature. Not surprisingly, the NDR1-overexpression line showed genotype-specific gene expression changes related to defense response and immune system function. Interestingly, overexpression of NDR1 revealed a role for NDR1 in immune system function; specifically, we describe a mechanism that intersects with &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt;, type-III effector translocation, R-protein signaling complex stabilization, and sustained levels of SA at elevated temperature during ETI. The results described herein support a role for NDR1 in maintaining cell signaling during simultaneous exposure to elevated temperature and avirulent pathogen stressors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;NDR1 is required for &lt;italic&gt;Pst&lt;/italic&gt;-AvrRpt2 triggered ETI at elevated temperature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470751" rel="alternate" title="Overexpression of NDR1 Leads to Pathogen Resistance at Elevated Temperatures (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470564</id><title>MSD2, an apoplastic Mn-SOD, contributes to root skotomorphogenic growth by modulating ROS distribution in Arabidopsis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.202324+00:00</updated><author><name>Huize Chen</name></author><author><name>Jinsu Lee</name></author><author><name>Jung-Min Lee</name></author><author><name>Minsoo Han</name></author><author><name>Aurélia Emonet</name></author><author><name>Jiyoun Lee</name></author><author><name>Xingtian Jia</name></author><author><name>Yuree Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reactive oxygen species (ROS) play essential roles as a second messenger in various physiological processes in plants. Due to their oxidative nature, ROS can also be harmful. Thus, the generation and homeostasis of ROS are tightly controlled by multiple enzymes. Membrane-localized NADPH oxidases are well known to generate ROS during developmental and stress responses, but the metabolic pathways of the superoxide (O2·&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;) generated by them in the apoplast are poorly understood, and the identity of the apoplastic superoxide dismutase (SOD) is unknown in Arabidopsis. Here, we show that a putative manganese SOD, MSD2 is secreted and possesses a SOD activity that can be inhibited by nitration at tyrosine 68. The expression of &lt;italic&gt;MSD2&lt;/italic&gt; in roots is light condition-dependent, suggesting that MSD2 may act on ROS metabolism in roots during the light-to-dark transition. Root architecture is governed by ROS distribution that exhibits opposite gradient of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and O2·&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;, which is indeed altered in etiolated &lt;italic&gt;msd2&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and accompanied by changes in the onset of differentiation. These results provide a missing link in our understanding of ROS metabolism and suggest that MSD2 plays a role in root skotomorphogenesis by regulating ROS distribution, thereby playing a pivotal role in plant growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470564" rel="alternate" title="MSD2, an apoplastic Mn-SOD, contributes to root skotomorphogenic growth by modulating ROS distribution in Arabidopsis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470728</id><title>A novel PSII photosynthetic control is activated in anoxic cultures of green algae (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.202643+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuval Milrad</name></author><author><name>Valéria Nagy</name></author><author><name>Szilvia Z. Tóth</name></author><author><name>Iftach Yacoby</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Photosynthetic green algae face an ever-changing environment of fluctuating light as well as unstable oxygen levels, which via the production of free radicals constantly challenges the integrity of the photosynthetic complexes. To face such challenges, a complex photosynthetic control network monitors and tightly control the membrane redox potential. Here, we show that not only that the photosynthetic control set the rate limiting step of photosynthetic linear electron flow, but also, upon its ultimate dissipation, it triggers intrinsic alternations in the activity of the photosynthetic complexes. These changes have a grave and prolonged effect on the activity of photosystem II, leading to a massive 3-fold decrease in its electron output. We came into this conclusion via studying a variety of green algae species and applying advance mass-spectrometry and diverse spectroscopic techniques. Our results shed new light on the mechanism of photosynthetic regulation, and provide new target for improving photosynthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470728" rel="alternate" title="A novel PSII photosynthetic control is activated in anoxic cultures of green algae (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470923</id><title>A nuclear import pathway exploited by viroid RNAs (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.202927+00:00</updated><author><name>Junfei Ma</name></author><author><name>Shachinthaka D. Dissanayaka Mudiyanselage</name></author><author><name>Woong June Park</name></author><author><name>Mo Wang</name></author><author><name>Ryuta Takeda</name></author><author><name>Bin Liu</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While most RNAs traffic to the cytoplasm or stay in the nucleus for function, emerging evidence illustrates numerous functional RNAs trafficking in the reverse direction from the cytoplasm to the nucleus. However, the mechanism underlying the RNA nuclear import process has not been well elucidated. Using nuclear-replicating viroids as a model, we showed that cellular Importin alpha-4 and Virp1 likely work in the same pathway for viroid RNA nuclear import. We also demonstrated that a conserved C-loop in nuclear-replicating viroids directly interacts with Virp1 in regulating nuclear import. Further, C-loop exists in a viral satellite RNA that relies on Virp1 for nuclear import. These results have significant implications for understanding the infection process of viroids, a peculiar group of plant pathogens. In addition, our data outline a cellular pathway for the nuclear import of subviral RNAs and uncover a 3-dimensional RNA motif-based regulation over RNA nuclear import.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470923" rel="alternate" title="A nuclear import pathway exploited by viroid RNAs (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470680</id><title>A stepwise route to domesticate rice by controlling seed shattering and panicle shape (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.203302+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryo Ishikawa</name></author><author><name>Cristina Cobo Castillo</name></author><author><name>Than Myint Htun</name></author><author><name>Koji Numaguchi</name></author><author><name>Kazuya Inoue</name></author><author><name>Yumi Oka</name></author><author><name>Miki Ogasawara</name></author><author><name>Shohei Sugiyama</name></author><author><name>Natsumi Takama</name></author><author><name>Chhourn Orn</name></author><author><name>Chizuru Inoue</name></author><author><name>Ken-ichi Nonomura</name></author><author><name>Robin G Allaby</name></author><author><name>Dorian Q Fuller</name></author><author><name>Takashige Ishii</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rice (Oryza sativa L.) is consumed by more than half of the world's population, but despite its global importance the mechanisms of domestication remain unclear. During domestication, wild rice (O. rufipogon Griff.) was transformed by acquiring non-seed-shattering behaviour, an important genetic change that allowed humans to increase grain yield. However, we show previously identified loci, sh4 and qSH3, are individually insufficient to explain loss of seed shattering nor increases in harvest yield in wild rice. We identify the complementary interaction of key mutations for abscission layer interruption and panicle architecture that were causal in the early domestication of Asian rice. An interruption of abscission layer formation requires both sh4 and qSH3, which presents an apparent barrier to selection of shattering loss. We identified the causal single nucleotide polymorphism at qSH3 within a seed-shattering gene OsSh1 conserved in indica and japonica subspecies, but absent in the circum-aus group of rice. We demonstrate through harvest experiments that seed-shattering alone does not significantly impact yield. Instead, we observed yield increases under a SPR3-controlled closed panicle formation, which is augmented by the integration of sh4 and qSH3 alleles causing a slight inhibition of abscission layer. Complementary manipulation of seed shattering and panicle shape result in a panicle structure that is mechanically stable. We propose a stepwise route in the earliest phase of rice domestication in which selection for visible SPR3-controlled closed panicle morphology was instrumental in the sequential recruitment of sh4 and qSH3 and leading to loss of shattering.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470680" rel="alternate" title="A stepwise route to domesticate rice by controlling seed shattering and panicle shape (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470706</id><title>Rice leaves undergo a rapid metabolic reconfiguration during a specific stage of primordium development (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.203735+00:00</updated><author><name>Naomi Cox</name></author><author><name>Heather J. Walker</name></author><author><name>James K. Pitman</name></author><author><name>W. Paul Quick</name></author><author><name>Lisa M. Smith</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Fleming</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Leaf development is crucial to establish the photosynthetic competency of plants. It is a process that requires coordinated changes in cell number and differentiation, transcriptomes, metabolomes and physiology. However, despite the importance of leaf formation for our major crops, early developmental processes for rice have not been comprehensively described. Here we detail the temporal developmental trajectory of early rice leaf development and connect morphological changes to metabolism. In particular, a developmental index based on the patterning of epidermal differentiation visualised by electron microscopy enabled high resolution staging of early growth for single primordium metabolite profiling. These data demonstrate that a switch in the constellation of tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle metabolites defines a narrow window towards the end of the P3 stage of leaf development. Taken in the context of other data in the literature, our results substantiate that this phase of rice leaf growth, equivalent to a change of primordium length from around 5 to 7.5 mm, defines a major shift in rice leaf determination towards a photosynthetically defined structure. We speculate that efforts to engineer rice leaf structure should focus on the developmental window prior to these determining events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlight&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rice leaves undergo a shift in fundamental metabolism during a very early and narrow developmental window which co-incides with them acquiring the ability to capture light for photosynthesis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470706" rel="alternate" title="Rice leaves undergo a rapid metabolic reconfiguration during a specific stage of primordium development (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470752</id><title>CURT1A and CURT1C mediate distinct stages of plastid conversion in Arabidopsis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.204062+00:00</updated><author><name>Zizhen Liang</name></author><author><name>Wai Tsun Yeung</name></author><author><name>Keith Ka Ki Mai</name></author><author><name>Juncai Ma</name></author><author><name>Zhongyuan Liu</name></author><author><name>Yau-Lun Felix Chong</name></author><author><name>Byung-Ho Kang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The crystalline structure of prolamellar bodies (PLBs) and light-induced etioplasts-to-chloroplasts transformation have been investigated with electron microscopy methods. However, these studies suffer from chemical fixation artifacts and limited volumes of tomographic reconstruction. We have examined &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; cotyledon samples preserved by high-pressure freezing with scanning transmission electron tomography to visualize larger volumes in etioplasts and their conversion into chloroplasts. PLB tubules were arranged in a zinc blende-type lattice like carbon atoms in diamonds. Within 2 hours after illumination, the lattice collapsed from the PLB exterior and the disorganized tubules merged to form fenestrated sheets that eventually matured into lamellar thylakoids. These planar thylakoids emerging from PLBs overlapped or folded into grana stacks in PLBs’ vicinity. Since the nascent lamellae had curved membrane at their tips, we examined the localization of CURT1 proteins. &lt;italic&gt;CURT1A&lt;/italic&gt; transcript was most abundant in de-etiolating cotyledon samples, and CURT1A concentrated at the peripheral PLB. In &lt;italic&gt;curt1a&lt;/italic&gt; mutant etioplasts, thylakoid sheets were swollen and failed to develop stacks. In &lt;italic&gt;curt1c&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, however, PLBs had cracks in their lattices, indicating that CURT1C contributes to cubic crystal growth under darkness. Our data provide evidence that CURT1A and CURT1C play distinct roles in the etioplast and chloroplast biogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470752" rel="alternate" title="CURT1A and CURT1C mediate distinct stages of plastid conversion in Arabidopsis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>