<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.052124+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474801</id><title>Improving disease resistance in plants by editing the epigenome (83 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.052591+00:00</updated><author><name>Kira M. Veley</name></author><author><name>Kiona Elliott</name></author><author><name>Greg Jensen</name></author><author><name>Zhenhui Zhong</name></author><author><name>Suhua Feng</name></author><author><name>Marisa Yoder</name></author><author><name>Kerrigan B. Gilbert</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey C. Berry</name></author><author><name>Basudev Ghoshal</name></author><author><name>Javier Gallego- Bartolomé</name></author><author><name>Joanna Norton</name></author><author><name>Sharon Motomura-Wages</name></author><author><name>James C. Carrington</name></author><author><name>Steven E. Jacobsen</name></author><author><name>Rebecca S. Bart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathogens rely on expression of host susceptibility (S) genes to promote infection and disease. As DNA methylation is an epigenetic modification that affects gene expression, blocking access to S genes through targeted methylation could increase disease resistance. &lt;italic&gt;Xanthomonas axonopodis&lt;/italic&gt; pv. &lt;italic&gt;manihotis&lt;/italic&gt;, the causal agent of cassava bacterial blight (CBB), uses transcription activator-like20 (TAL20) to induce expression of the S gene &lt;italic&gt;MeSWEET10a.&lt;/italic&gt; We directed methylation to the TAL20 effector binding element within the &lt;italic&gt;MeSWEET10a&lt;/italic&gt; promoter using a synthetic zinc-finger DNA binding domain fused to a component of the RNA-directed DNA methylation pathway. We demonstrate that this methylation prevents TAL20 binding, blocks transcriptional activation of &lt;italic&gt;MeSWEET10a in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; and that these plants display increased resistance to CBB while maintaining normal growth and development. This work establishes epigenome editing as a new strategy for crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improving disease resistance with epigenomic editing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474801" rel="alternate" title="Improving disease resistance in plants by editing the epigenome (83 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474791</id><title>Dynamic evolution of small signaling peptide compensation in plant stem cell control (18 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.053223+00:00</updated><author><name>Choon-Tak Kwon</name></author><author><name>Lingli Tang</name></author><author><name>Xingang Wang</name></author><author><name>Iacopo Gentile</name></author><author><name>Anat Hendelman</name></author><author><name>Gina Robitaille</name></author><author><name>Joyce Van Eck</name></author><author><name>Cao Xu</name></author><author><name>Zachary B. Lippman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene duplications are a hallmark of plant genome evolution and a foundation for genetic interactions that shape phenotypic diversity&lt;sup&gt;1–5&lt;/sup&gt;. Compensation is a major form of paralog interaction&lt;sup&gt;6–8&lt;/sup&gt;, but how compensation relationships change as allelic variation accumulates is unknown. Here, we leveraged genomics and genome editing across the Solanaceae family to capture the evolution of compensating paralogs. Mutations in the stem cell regulator &lt;italic&gt;CLV3&lt;/italic&gt; cause floral organs to overproliferate in many plants&lt;sup&gt;9–11&lt;/sup&gt;. In tomato, this phenotype is partially suppressed by transcriptional upregulation of a closely related paralog&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;. Tobacco lost this paralog, resulting in no compensation and extreme &lt;italic&gt;clv3&lt;/italic&gt; phenotypes. Strikingly, the paralogs of petunia and groundcherry nearly completely suppress &lt;italic&gt;clv3&lt;/italic&gt;, indicating a potent ancestral state of compensation. Cross-species transgenic complementation analyses show this potent compensation partially degenerated in tomato due to a single amino acid change in the paralog and &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory variation that limits its transcriptional upregulation. Our findings show how genetic interactions are remodeled following duplications, and suggest that dynamic paralog evolution is widespread over short time scales and impacts phenotypic variation from natural and engineered mutations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474791" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic evolution of small signaling peptide compensation in plant stem cell control (18 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475203</id><title>Integrative time-scale and multi-omic analysis of host-responses to Hop stunt viroid infection (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.053646+00:00</updated><author><name>Joan Marquez-Molins</name></author><author><name>Pascual Villalba-Bermell</name></author><author><name>Julia Corell-Sierra</name></author><author><name>Vicente Pallas</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Gomez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Constricted by an extreme biological simplicity, viroids are compelled to subvert host regulatory networks in order to accomplish their infectious process. Most of the studies focused on the response to viroid infection have only addressed a specific host regulatory level and considered a unique infection time. Thus, much remains to be done if we want to understand the temporal evolution and complex nature of viroid-host interactions. Here we present an integrative analysis of the timing and intensity of the genome-wide alterations in cucumber plants infected with Hop stunt viroid (HSVd). Differential host transcriptome, sRNAnome and methylome were integrated to determine the temporal response to viroid-infection. Our results support that HSVd promotes a dynamic redesign of the cucumber regulatory pathways predominantly affecting specific regulatory layers at different infection phases. Remarkably, the initial response was characterized by a reconfiguration of the host transcriptome by differential exon usage, followed by a predominant down-regulation of the transcriptional activity possibly modulated by the host epigenetic changes associated to infection and characterized by an increased hypermethylation. The silencing of at least three cucumber transcripts potential targets of vd-sRNAs was also observed. The alteration in host sRNA and miRNA metabolism was marginal. We expect that these data constituting the first comprehensive map of the cucumber-response to HSVd could contribute to elucidate the molecular basis of the host alterations triggered by viroid infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475203" rel="alternate" title="Integrative time-scale and multi-omic analysis of host-responses to Hop stunt viroid infection (11 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475278</id><title>Extracellular ATP plays an important role in systemic wound response activation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.053922+00:00</updated><author><name>Ronald Myers</name></author><author><name>Yosef Fichman</name></author><author><name>Gary Stacey</name></author><author><name>Ron Mittler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical wounding occurs in plants during biotic (e.g., herbivore or pathogen attack) or abiotic (e.g., wind damage or freezing) stresses and is associated with the activation of multiple signaling pathways. These initiate many wound responses at the wounded tissues, as well as trigger long-distance signaling pathways that activate wound responses in tissues that were not affected by the initial wounding event (termed systemic wound response). Among the different systemic signals activated by wounding are electric signals, calcium and reactive oxygen species (ROS) waves, and different plant hormones such as jasmonic acid. The release of glutamate from cells at the wounded tissues was recently proposed to trigger several different systemic signal transduction pathways via glutamate-like receptors (GLRs). However, the role of another important compound released from cells during wounding (i.e., extracellular ATP; eATP) in triggering systemic responses is not clear. Here we show that eATP that accumulates in wounded leaves and is sensed by the purinoreceptor kinase P2K is required for the activation of the ROS wave during wounding. Application of eATP to unwounded leaves triggered the ROS wave, and the activation of the ROS wave by wounding or eATP application was suppressed in mutants deficient in P2K (i.e., p2k1-3, p2k2, and p2k1-3p2k2). In addition, the expression of several systemic wound response transcripts was suppressed in mutants deficient in P2K during wounding. Our findings reveal that in addition to sensing glutamate via GLRs, eATP sensed by P2Ks is playing a key role in the triggering of systemic wound responses in plants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475278" rel="alternate" title="Extracellular ATP plays an important role in systemic wound response activation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474142</id><title>Limited consequences for loss of RNA-directed DNA methylation in Setaria viridis domains rearranged methyltransferase (DRM) mutants (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.054258+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Read</name></author><author><name>Trevor Weiss</name></author><author><name>Peter A Crisp</name></author><author><name>Zhikai Liang</name></author><author><name>Jaclyn Noshay</name></author><author><name>Claire C Menard</name></author><author><name>Chunfang Wang</name></author><author><name>Meredith Song</name></author><author><name>Candice N Hirsch</name></author><author><name>Nathan M Springer</name></author><author><name>Feng Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Domains Rearranged Methyltransferases (DRMs) are crucial for RNA-directed DNA methylation (RdDM) in plant species. &lt;italic&gt;Setaria viridis&lt;/italic&gt; is a model monocot species with a relatively compact genome that has limited transposable element content. CRISPR-based genome editing approaches were used to create loss-of-function alleles for the two putative functional DRM genes in &lt;italic&gt;S. viridis&lt;/italic&gt; to probe the role of RdDM. The analysis of &lt;italic&gt;drm1ab&lt;/italic&gt; double mutant plants revealed limited morphological consequences for the loss of RdDM. Whole-genome methylation profiling provided evidence for wide-spread loss of methylation in CHH sequence contexts, particularly in regions with high CHH methylation in wild-type plants. Evidence was also found for locus-specific loss of CG and CHG methylation, even in some regions that lack CHH methylation. Transcriptome profiling identified a limited number of genes with altered expression in the &lt;italic&gt;drm1ab&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. The majority of genes with elevated CHH methylation directly surrounding the transcription start site or in nearby promoter regions do not have altered expression in the &lt;italic&gt;drm1ab&lt;/italic&gt; mutant even when this methylation is lost, suggesting limited regulation of gene expression by RdDM. Detailed analysis of the expression of transposable elements identified several transposons that are transcriptionally activated in &lt;italic&gt;drm1ab&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. These transposons likely require active RdDM for maintenance of transcriptional repression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Methylation profiling of &lt;italic&gt;Setaria viridis&lt;/italic&gt; plants that lack functional Domains Rearranged Methyltransferase genes reveal widespread loss of DNA methylation in the CHH sequence context. Transcriptome analysis reveals a small set of genes and transposons that are silenced by RNA-directed DNA methylation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.474142" rel="alternate" title="Limited consequences for loss of RNA-directed DNA methylation in Setaria viridis domains rearranged methyltransferase (DRM) mutants (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475064</id><title>Tobacco HY5, NtHY5, positively regulates flavonoid biosynthesis and enhances salt stress tolerance (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.054537+00:00</updated><author><name>Deeksha Singh</name></author><author><name>Hiteshwari Singh</name></author><author><name>Nivedita Singh</name></author><author><name>Shambhavi Dwivedi</name></author><author><name>Prabodh Kumar Trivedi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plants have evolved complex signaling networks to regulate their growth and development. Some of these signaling components also play a crucial role in secondary metabolite biosynthesis. Among the signaling components identified to date, ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL 5 (HY5), a bZIP family transcription factor is the most investigated and known as the center of transcriptional network hub. However, HY5 has not been characterized from plants known to synthesize important secondary metabolites. In this study, based on homology search and phylogenetic analysis, HY5 has been identified from Nicotiana tobaccum, and characterized for its role in secondary plant product biosynthesis and stress response through developing overexpressing lines and CRISPR/Cas9-based knockout mutant plants. NtHY5 was able to complement the Arabidopsis thaliana hy5 mutant at molecular, morphological and biochemical levels. Overexpression of NtHY5 in tobacco led to the up-regulation of the phenylpropanoid pathway genes and enhanced the flavonoid content, whereas mutant plants had the opposite effect. Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA) suggested that NtHY5 interacts with the promoter of NtMYB12, a transcription factor known to regulate flavonoid biosynthesis. In addition, NtHY5 enhanced the abiotic stress tolerance as evident by the salt tolerance ability of HY5 overexpressing lines by diminishing the ROS accumulation after salt treatment. These data provide credible evidence about the potential role of NtHY5 in light-mediated flavonoid biosynthesis, plant growth and abiotic stress tolerance in tobacco. The photomorphogenic mutant, Nthy5, developed in this study, will help in elucidating the role of the HY5 in different biological processes in tobacco.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475064" rel="alternate" title="Tobacco HY5, NtHY5, positively regulates flavonoid biosynthesis and enhances salt stress tolerance (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475031</id><title>MethylScore, a pipeline for accurate and context-aware identification of differentially methylated regions from population-scale plant WGBS data (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.054831+00:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Hüther</name></author><author><name>Jörg Hagmann</name></author><author><name>Adam Nunn</name></author><author><name>Ioanna Kakoulidou</name></author><author><name>Rahul Pisupati</name></author><author><name>David Langenberger</name></author><author><name>Detlef Weigel</name></author><author><name>Frank Johannes</name></author><author><name>Sebastian J Schultheiss</name></author><author><name>Claude Becker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) is the standard method for profiling DNA methylation at single-nucleotide resolution. Many WGBS-based studies aim to identify biologically relevant loci that display differential methylation between genotypes, treatment groups, tissues, or developmental stages. Over the years, different tools have been developed to extract differentially methylated regions (DMRs) from whole-genome data. Often, such tools are built upon assumptions from mammalian data and do not consider the substantially more complex and variable nature of plant DNA methylation. Here, we present MethylScore, a pipeline to analyze WGBS data and to account for plant-specific DNA methylation properties. MethylScore processes data from genomic alignments to DMR output and is designed to be usable by novice and expert users alike. It uses an unsupervised machine learning approach to segment the genome by classification into states of high and low methylation, substantially reducing the number of necessary statistical tests while increasing the signal-to-noise ratio and the statistical power. We show how MethylScore can identify DMRs from hundreds of samples and how its data-driven approach can stratify associated samples without prior information. We identify DMRs in the A. thaliana 1001 Genomes dataset to unveil known and unknown genotype-epigenotype associations. MethylScore is an accessible pipeline for plant WGBS data, with unprecedented features for DMR calling in small- and large-scale datasets; it is built as a Nextflow pipeline and its source code is available at https://github.com/Computomics/MethylScore.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475031" rel="alternate" title="MethylScore, a pipeline for accurate and context-aware identification of differentially methylated regions from population-scale plant WGBS data (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475193</id><title>Dynamic changes in gas solubility of xylem sap reiterate the enigma of plant water transport under negative pressure (3 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:02.055176+00:00</updated><author><name>Luciano Pereira</name></author><author><name>Steven Jansen</name></author><author><name>Marcela Trevenzoli Miranda</name></author><author><name>Vinicius Sacramento Pacheco</name></author><author><name>Lucian Kaack</name></author><author><name>Gabriel Silva Pires</name></author><author><name>Xinyi Guan</name></author><author><name>Juliana Lischka Mayer</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Caruso Machado</name></author><author><name>H. Jochen Schenk</name></author><author><name>Rafael Ribeiro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite a long research history, we do not fully understand why plants are able to transport xylem sap under negative pressure without constant failure. Microbubble formation via direct gas entry is assumed to cause hydraulic failure, while the concentration of gas dissolved in xylem sap is traditionally supposed to be constant, following Henry's law. Here, the concentration of soluble gas in xylem sap was estimated in vivo using well-watered Citrus plants under varying levels of air temperature and photoperiodic exposure, and compared to modelled data. The gas concentration in xylem sap showed non-equilibrium curves, with a minimum over-or undersaturation of 5% compared to gas solubility based on Henry's law. A similar diurnal pattern was obtained from the gas concentration in the cut-open conduits and discharge tube, and oversolubility was strongly associated with decreasing xylem water potentials during transpiration. Although our model did not explain the daily changes in gas solubility for an anisobaric situation, oversolubility characterises nanoconfined liquids, such as sap inside cell walls. Thus, plants are able to transport sap under negative pressure with relatively high amounts of dissolved gas, providing them with a buffering capacity to prevent hydraulic failure, despite diurnal changes in pressure and temperature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475193" rel="alternate" title="Dynamic changes in gas solubility of xylem sap reiterate the enigma of plant water transport under negative pressure (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>