<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.949235+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.24.449808</id><title>Methods for in situ quantitative root biology (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.949525+00:00</updated><author><name>Taras Pasternak</name></author><author><name>Jose Manuel Perez-Perez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When dealing with plant roots, a multi-scale description of the functional root structure is needed. Since the beginning of XXI century, new devices like laser confocal microscopes have been accessible for coarse root structure measurements, including 3D reconstruction. Most re-searchers are familiar with using simple 2D geometry visualization that does not allow quantitatively determination of key morphological features from an organ-like perspective. We provide here a detailed description of the quantitative methods available for three-dimensional (3D) analysis of root features at single cell resolution, including root asymmetry, lateral root analysis, xylem and phloem structure, cell cycle kinetics, and chromatin determination. Quantitative maps of the distal and proximal root meristems are shown for different species, including Arabidopsis thaliana, Nicotiana tabacum and Medicago sativa. A 3D analysis of the primary root tip showed divergence in chromatin organization and cell volume distribution between cell types and precisely mapped root zonation for each cell file. Detailed protocols are also provided. Possible pitfalls in the usage of the marker lines are discussed. Therefore, researchers who need to improve their quantitative root biology portfolio can use them as a reference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.24.449808" rel="alternate" title="Methods for in situ quantitative root biology (18 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.25.449942</id><title>Intraspecific diversity observed in the wild tomato species Solanum chilense in initial immune responses towards a glucan elicitor. (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.949710+00:00</updated><author><name>Parvinderdeep S. Kahlon</name></author><author><name>Andrea Förner</name></author><author><name>Michael Muser</name></author><author><name>Mhaned Oubounyt</name></author><author><name>Michael Gigl</name></author><author><name>Richard Hammerl</name></author><author><name>Jan Baumbach</name></author><author><name>Ralph Hückelhoven</name></author><author><name>Corinna Dawid</name></author><author><name>Remco Stam</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Natural plant populations are highly polymorphic and often show intraspecific quantitative, variation in resistance properties against pathogens. The activation of the underlying defence responses can depend on the perception of conserved pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs). To dissect and understand such variation, we evaluated the diversity of responses induced by laminarin (representing a general glucan elicitor of plant immune responses) in the wild tomato species Solanum chilense. We confirm considerable overlap of the plant's global transcriptional responses to laminarin and to the oomycete pathogen Phytophthora infestans. We further measured key components of basal defence responses such as reactive oxygen species (ROS) production and levels of diverse phytohormones and their derivatives upon elicitation with laminarin in 83 plants originating from nine natural populations of S. chilense from distinct geographic origin. We found high diversity in these components at basal and elicitor-induced levels. We generated generalised linear mixed models (GLMMs) with these components to explain the observed resistance phenotype against P. infestans in the plants and found that additive effects of multiple components best explain resistance at the species level. For individual components, we observed the strongest positive correlation between the resistance phenotype and ethylene (ET) production upon laminarin elicitation. The strength of this correlation differed between individual populations. Chemical inhibition of ET production in individuals from a population, in which ET production was associated with resistance, provoked more severe disease symptoms. Our findings reveal high diversity in the strength of induced defence responses within a species and in the basal levels of other stress-related phytohormones. We show the involvement of multiple components with a quantitatively different contribution of individual components to resistance in geographically separated populations of S. chilense against P. infestans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.25.449942" rel="alternate" title="Intraspecific diversity observed in the wild tomato species Solanum chilense in initial immune responses towards a glucan elicitor. (15 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.21.449293</id><title>An artificial host system enables the obligate parasitic plant Cuscuta campestris to grow and complete its life cycle in vitro (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.949917+00:00</updated><author><name>Vivian Bernal-Galeano</name></author><author><name>James H. Westwood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Cuscuta campestris&lt;/italic&gt; is an obligate parasitic plant that requires a host to complete its lifecycle. Parasite-host connections occur via an haustorium, a unique organ that acts as a bridge for the uptake of water, nutrients and macromolecules. Research on &lt;italic&gt;Cuscuta&lt;/italic&gt; is often complicated by host influences, but comparable systems for growing the parasite in the absence of a host do not exist. We developed an axenic method to grow &lt;italic&gt;C. campestris&lt;/italic&gt; on an Artificial Host System (AHS). We evaluated the effects of nutrients and phytohormones on parasite haustoria development and growth. Haustorium morphology and gene expression were characterized. The AHS consists of an inert, fibrous stick that mimics a host stem, wicking water and nutrients to the parasite. It enables &lt;italic&gt;C. campestris&lt;/italic&gt; to exhibit a parasitic habit and develop through all stages of its lifecycle, including production of new shoots and viable seeds. Phytohormones NAA and BA affect haustoria morphology, and increase parasite fresh weight and biomass. Gene expression in AHS haustoria reflect process similar to those in haustoria on actual host plants. The AHS is a methodological improvement for studying &lt;italic&gt;Cuscuta&lt;/italic&gt; biology by avoiding specific host effects on parasite and giving researchers full control of the parasite environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.21.449293" rel="alternate" title="An artificial host system enables the obligate parasitic plant Cuscuta campestris to grow and complete its life cycle in vitro (14 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449625</id><title>High quality, phased genomes of Phytophthora ramorum clonal lineages NA1 and EU1 (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.950171+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas C. Carleson</name></author><author><name>Caroline M. Press</name></author><author><name>Niklaus J. Grünwald</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Phytophthora ramorum&lt;/italic&gt; is the causal agent of sudden oak death in West Coast forests and currently two clonal lineages, NA1 and EU1, cause epidemics in Oregon forests. Here, we report on two high-quality genomes of individuals belonging to the NA1 and EU1 clonal lineages respectively, using PacBio long-read sequencing. The NA1 strain Pr102, originally isolated from coast live oak in California, is the current reference genome and was previously sequenced independently using either Sanger (&lt;italic&gt;P. ramorum&lt;/italic&gt; v1) or PacBio (&lt;italic&gt;P. ramorum&lt;/italic&gt; v2) technology. The EU1 strain PR-15-019 was obtained from tanoak in Oregon. These new genomes have a total size of 57.5 Mb, with a contig N50 length of ~3.5-3.6 Mb and encode ~15,300 predicted protein-coding genes. Genomes were assembled into 27 and 28 scaffolds with 95% BUSCO scores and are considerably improved relative to the current JGI reference genome with 2,575 or the PacBio genomes with 1,512 scaffolds. These high-quality genomes provide a valuable resource for studying the genetics, evolution, and adaptation of these two clonal lineages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.23.449625" rel="alternate" title="High quality, phased genomes of Phytophthora ramorum clonal lineages NA1 and EU1 (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.24.449551</id><title>PpRPK2 modulates auxin homeostasis and transport to specify stem cell identity and plant shape in the moss Physcomitrella (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-28T06:31:59.950449+00:00</updated><author><name>Zoe Nemec Venza</name></author><author><name>Connor Madden</name></author><author><name>Amy Stewart</name></author><author><name>Wei Liu</name></author><author><name>Ondrej Novak</name></author><author><name>Ales Penik</name></author><author><name>Andrew C Cuming</name></author><author><name>Yasuko Kamisugi</name></author><author><name>C Jill Harrison</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plant shape is determined by the activity of stem cells in the growing tips, and evolutionary changes in shape are linked to changes in stem cell function. The CLAVATA pathway is a key regulator of stem cell function in the multicellular shoot tips of Arabidopsis, acting via the WUSCHEL transcription factor to modulate hormone homeostasis. Broad scale evolutionary comparisons have shown that CLAVATA is a conserved regulator of land plant stem cell function, but CLAVATA acts independently of WUSCHEL-like (WOX) proteins in bryophytes, raising questions about the evolution of stem cell function and the role of the CLAVATA pathway. Here we show that the moss (Physcomitrella) CLAVATA pathway affects stem cell activity and overall plant shape by modulating hormone homeostasis. CLAVATA pathway components are expressed in the tip cells of filamentous tissues, regulating cell identity, filament branching patterns and plant spread. The PpRPK2 receptor-like kinase plays the major role and is expressed more strongly than other receptor-encoding genes. Pprpk2 mutants have abnormal responses to cytokinin, and auxin transport inhibition and show reduced PIN auxin transporter expression. We propose a model whereby PpRPK2 modulates PIN activity to determine stem cell identity and overall plant form in Physcomitrella. Our data indicate that CLAVATA-mediated auxin homeostasis is a fundamental property of plant stem cell function likely exhibited by the last shared common ancestor of land plants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.24.449551" rel="alternate" title="PpRPK2 modulates auxin homeostasis and transport to specify stem cell identity and plant shape in the moss Physcomitrella (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>