<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.972911+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468476</id><title>Uncovering natural variation in root system architecture and growth dynamics using a robotics-assisted phenomics platform (153 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.973134+00:00</updated><author><name>Therese LaRue</name></author><author><name>Heike Lindner</name></author><author><name>Ankit Srinivas</name></author><author><name>Moises Exposito-Alonso</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Ramon Lobet</name></author><author><name>Jose Ramon Dinneny</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The plant kingdom contains a stunning array of complex morphologies easily observed above ground, but largely unexplored below-ground. Understanding the magnitude of diversity in root distribution within the soil, termed root system architecture (RSA), is fundamental to determining how this trait contributes to species adaptation in local environments. Roots are the interface between the soil environment and the shoot system and therefore play a key role in anchorage, resource uptake, and stress resilience. Previously, we presented the GLO-Roots (Growth and Luminescence Observatory for Roots) system to study the RSA of soil-grown Arabidopsis thaliana plants from germination to maturity. In this study, we present the automation of GLO-Roots using robotics and the development of image analysis pipelines in order to examine the natural variation of RSA in Arabidopsis over time. This dataset describes the developmental dynamics of 93 accessions and reveals highly complex and polygenic RSA traits that show significant correlation with climate variables.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.13.468476" rel="alternate" title="Uncovering natural variation in root system architecture and growth dynamics using a robotics-assisted phenomics platform (153 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467771</id><title>New insights into the evolution of glutamine synthetase isoenzymes in plants (76 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.973315+00:00</updated><author><name>José Miguel Valderrama-Martín</name></author><author><name>Francisco Ortigosa</name></author><author><name>Concepción Ávila</name></author><author><name>Francisco M. Cánovas</name></author><author><name>Bertrand Hirel</name></author><author><name>Francisco R. Cantón</name></author><author><name>Rafael A. Cañas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glutamine synthetase (GS) is a key enzyme responsible for the incorporation of inorganic nitrogen in the form of ammonium into the amino acid glutamine. The genes encoding GS are among the oldest existing genes in living organisms. In plants, two groups of functional GS enzymes are found: eubacterial &lt;italic&gt;GSIIb&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;GLN2&lt;/italic&gt;) and eukaryotic &lt;italic&gt;GSIIe&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;GLN1&lt;/italic&gt;/&lt;italic&gt;GS&lt;/italic&gt;). Phylogenetic analyses have shown that the &lt;italic&gt;GLN2&lt;/italic&gt; group originated from bacteria following horizontal gene transfer. Only &lt;italic&gt;GLN1/GS&lt;/italic&gt; genes are found in vascular plants, which suggests that they are involved in the final adaptation of plants to terrestrial life. The present phylogenetic study reclassifies the different GS of seed plants into three clusters: &lt;italic&gt;GS1a, GS1b&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;GS2&lt;/italic&gt;. The presence of genes encoding GS2 has been expanded to Cycadopsida gymnosperms, which suggests the origin of this gene in a common ancestor of Cycadopsida, Ginkgoopsida and angiosperms. &lt;italic&gt;GS1a&lt;/italic&gt; genes have been identified in all gymnosperms, basal angiosperms and some Magnoliidae species. Previous studies in conifers and the gene expression profiles obtained in ginkgo and magnolia in the present work could explain the absence of GS1a in more recent angiosperm species (e.g., monocots and eudicots) due to the redundant roles of GS1a and GS2 in photosynthetic cells. Altogether, the results provide a better understanding of the evolution of plant GS isoenzymes and their physiological roles, which is valuable for improving crop nitrogen use efficiency and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467771" rel="alternate" title="New insights into the evolution of glutamine synthetase isoenzymes in plants (76 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468112</id><title>Timing of gene expression and recruitment in independent origins of CAM in the Agavoideae (Asparagaceae). (34 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.973481+00:00</updated><author><name>Karolina Heyduk</name></author><author><name>Edward McAssey</name></author><author><name>James Leebens-Mack</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CAM photosynthesis has evolved repeatedly across the plant tree of life, yet our understanding of the genetic convergence across independent origins remains hampered by the lack of comparative studies. CAM is furthermore thought to be closely linked to the circadian clock in order to achieve temporal separation of carboxylation and sugar production. Here, we explore gene expression profiles in eight species from the Agavoideae (Asparagaceae) encompassing three independent origins of CAM. Using comparative physiology and transcriptomics, we examined the variable modes of CAM in this subfamily and the changes in gene expression across time of day and between well-watered and drought-stressed treatments. We further assessed gene expression and molecular evolution of genes encoding phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase (PPC), an enzyme required for primary carbon fixation in CAM. Most time-of-day expression profiles are largely conserved across all eight species and suggest that large perturbations to the central clock are not required for CAM evolution. In contrast, transcriptional response to drought is highly lineage specific. Yucca and Beschorneria have CAM-like expression of PPC2, a copy of PPC that has never been shown to be recruited for CAM in angiosperms, and evidence of positive selection in PPC genes implicates mutations that may have facilitated the recruitment for CAM function early in the evolutionary history of the Agavoideae. Together the physiological and transcriptomic comparison of closely related C3 and CAM species reveals similar gene expression profiles, with the notable exception of differential recruitment of carboxylase enzymes for CAM function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468112" rel="alternate" title="Timing of gene expression and recruitment in independent origins of CAM in the Agavoideae (Asparagaceae). (34 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467746</id><title>Loss of function of bHLH transcription factor Nrd1 in tomato induces an arabinogalactan protein-encoding gene and enhances resistance to Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.973616+00:00</updated><author><name>Ning Zhang</name></author><author><name>Chloe Hecht</name></author><author><name>Xuepeng Sun</name></author><author><name>Zhangjun Fei</name></author><author><name>Gregory B. Martin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) transcription factors constitute a superfamily in eukaryotes but their roles in plant immunity remain largely uncharacterized. We found that the transcript abundance in tomato leaves of one bHLH transcription factor-encoding gene, &lt;italic&gt;Nrd1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;underline&gt;n&lt;/underline&gt;egative &lt;underline&gt;r&lt;/underline&gt;egulator of resistance to &lt;underline&gt;D&lt;/underline&gt;C3000 &lt;underline&gt;1&lt;/underline&gt;), was significantly increased after treatment with the immunity-inducing flgII-28 peptide. Plants carrying a loss-of-function mutation in &lt;italic&gt;Nrd1&lt;/italic&gt; (Λnrd1) showed enhanced resistance to &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt; pv. &lt;italic&gt;tomato&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Pst&lt;/italic&gt;) DC3000 although early pattern-triggered immunity responses such as generation of reactive oxygen species and activation of mitogen-activated protein kinases after treatment with flagellin-derived flg22 and flgII-28 peptides were unaltered compared to wild-type plants. An RNA-Seq analysis identified a gene, &lt;italic&gt;Agp1&lt;/italic&gt;, whose expression is strongly suppressed in an &lt;italic&gt;Nrd1&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent manner. &lt;italic&gt;Agp1&lt;/italic&gt; encodes an arabinogalactan protein and overexpression of the &lt;italic&gt;Agp1&lt;/italic&gt; gene in &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; led to ∼10-fold less &lt;italic&gt;Pst&lt;/italic&gt; growth compared to the control. These results suggest that the Nrd1 protein promotes tomato susceptibility to &lt;italic&gt;Pst&lt;/italic&gt; by suppressing the defense gene &lt;italic&gt;Agp1&lt;/italic&gt;. RNA-Seq also revealed that loss of Nrd1 function has no effect on the transcript abundance of immunity-associated genes including &lt;italic&gt;Bti9, Core, Fls2, Fls3&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Wak1&lt;/italic&gt; upon &lt;italic&gt;Pst&lt;/italic&gt; inoculation, suggesting that the enhanced immunity observed in the Δnrd1 mutants is due to the activation of key PRR signaling components as well as loss of Nrd1-regulated suppression of &lt;italic&gt;Agp1&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467746" rel="alternate" title="Loss of function of bHLH transcription factor Nrd1 in tomato induces an arabinogalactan protein-encoding gene and enhances resistance to Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>