<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.684841+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.454952</id><title>High expression of VRT2 during wheat spikelet initiation increases the number of rudimentary basal spikelets (56 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.685668+00:00</updated><author><name>Anna E. Backhaus</name></author><author><name>Ashleigh Lister</name></author><author><name>Melissa Tomkins</name></author><author><name>Nikolai M. Adamski</name></author><author><name>James Simmonds</name></author><author><name>Iain Macaulay</name></author><author><name>Richard J. Morris</name></author><author><name>Wilfried Haerty</name></author><author><name>Cristobal Uauy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spikelets are the fundamental building blocks of &lt;italic&gt;Poaceae&lt;/italic&gt; inflorescences and their development and branching patterns determine the various inflorescence architectures and grain yield of grasses. In wheat, the central spikelets produce the most and largest grains, while spikelet size gradually decreases acro- and basipetally, giving rise to the characteristic lanceolate shape of wheat spikes. The acropetal gradient correlates with the developmental age of spikelets, however the basal spikelets are developed first and the cause of their small size and rudimentary development is unclear. Here, we adapted G&amp;amp;T-seq, a low-input transcriptomics approach, to characterise gene expression profiles within spatial sections of individual spikes before and after the establishment of the lanceolate shape. We observed larger differences in gene expression profiles between the apical, central and basal sections of a single spike than between any section belonging to consecutive developmental timepoints. We found that &lt;italic&gt;SVP&lt;/italic&gt; MADS-box transcription factors, including &lt;italic&gt;VRT-A2&lt;/italic&gt;, are expressed highest in the basal section of the wheat spike and display the opposite expression gradient to flowering E-class &lt;italic&gt;SEP1&lt;/italic&gt; genes. Based on multi-year field trials and transgenic lines we show that higher expression of &lt;italic&gt;VRT-A2&lt;/italic&gt; in the basal sections of the spike is associated with increased numbers of rudimentary basal spikelets. Our results, supported by computational modelling, suggest that the delayed transition of basal spikelets from vegetative to floral developmental programmes results in the lanceolate shape of wheat spikes. This study highlights the value of spatially resolved transcriptomics to gain new insights into developmental genetics pathways of grass inflorescences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large transcriptional differences exist &lt;italic&gt;within&lt;/italic&gt; a wheat spike and are associated with rudimentary basal spikelet development, resulting in the characteristic lanceolate shape of wheat spikes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.454952" rel="alternate" title="High expression of VRT2 during wheat spikelet initiation increases the number of rudimentary basal spikelets (56 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455283</id><title>Integrating omics approaches to discover and prioritize candidate genes involved in oil biosynthesis in soybean (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.686242+00:00</updated><author><name>Dayana K. Turquetti-Moraes</name></author><author><name>Kanhu C. Moharana</name></author><author><name>Fabricio Almeida-Silva</name></author><author><name>Francisnei Pedrosa-Silva</name></author><author><name>Thiago M. Venancio</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soybean is one of the major sources of edible protein and oil. Oil content is a quantitative trait that is significantly determined by genetic and environmental factors. Over the past 30 years, a large volume of soybean genetic, genomic, and transcriptomic data have been accumulated. Nevertheless, integrative analyses of such data remain scarce, in spite of their importance for crop improvement. We hypothesized that the co-occurrence of genomic regions for oil-related traits in different studies may reveal more stable regions encompassing important genetic determinants of oil content and quality in soybean. We integrated publicly available data, obtained with distinct techniques, to discover and prioritize candidate genes involved in oil biosynthesis and regulation in soybean. We detected key fatty acid biosynthesis genes (e.g., BCCP and ACCase, FADs, KAS family proteins) and several transcripton factors, which are likely regulators of oil biosynthesis. In addition, we identified new candidates for seed oil accumulation and quality, such as Glyma.03G213300 and Glyma.19G160700, which encode a translocator protein and a histone acetyltransferase, respectively. Further, oil and protein genomic hotspots are strongly associated with breeding and not with domestication, suggesting that soybean domestication prioritized other traits. The genes identified here are promising targets for breeding programs and for the development of soybean lines with increased oil content and quality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455283" rel="alternate" title="Integrating omics approaches to discover and prioritize candidate genes involved in oil biosynthesis in soybean (13 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455130</id><title>Allelopathy as an evolutionarily stable strategy (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.686586+00:00</updated><author><name>Rachel M. McCoy</name></author><author><name>Joshua R. Widhalm</name></author><author><name>Gordon G. McNickle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In plants, most competition is resource competition, where one plant simply pre-empts the resources away from its neighbours. Interference competition, as the name implies, is a form of direct interference to prevent resource access. Interference competition is common among animals who can physically fight, but in plants, one of the main mechanisms of interference competition is Allelopathy. allelopathic plants release of cytotoxic chemicals into the environment which can increase their ability to compete with surrounding organisms for limited resources. The circumstances and conditions favoring the development and maintenance of allelochemicals, however, is not well understood. Particularly, it seems strange that, despite the obvious benefits of allelopathy, it seems to have only rarely evolved. To gain insight into the cost and benefit of allelopathy, we have developed a 2 × 2 matrix game to model the interaction between plants that produce allelochemicals and plants that do not. Production of an allelochemical introduces novel cost associated with synthesis and detoxifying a toxic chemical but may also convey a competitive advantage. A plant that does not produce an allelochemical will suffer the cost of encountering one. Our model predicts three cases in which the evolutionarily stable strategies are different. In the first, the non-allelopathic plant is a stronger competitor, and not producing allelochemicals is the evolutionarily stable strategy. In the second, the allelopathic plant is the better competitor and production of allelochemicals is the more beneficial strategy. In the last case, neither is the evolutionarily stable strategy. Instead, there are alternating stable states, depending on whether the allelopathic or non-allelopathic plant arrived first. The generated model reveals circumstances leading to the evolution of allelochemicals and sheds light on utilizing allelochemicals as part of weed management strategies. In particular, the wide region of alternative stable states in most parameterizations, combined with the fact that the absence of allelopathy is likely the ancestral state, provides an elegant answer to the question of why allelopathy rarely evolves despite its obvious benefits. Allelopathic plants can indeed outcompete non-allelopathic plants, but this benefit is simply not great enough to allow them to go to fixation and spread through the population. Thus, most populations would remain purely non-allelopathic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.04.455130" rel="alternate" title="Allelopathy as an evolutionarily stable strategy (9 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454802</id><title>Cytokinin- microbiome interactions regulate developmental functions (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-13T12:54:26.686886+00:00</updated><author><name>Rupali Gupta</name></author><author><name>Dorin Elkabetz</name></author><author><name>Meirav Leibman-Markus</name></author><author><name>Elie Jami</name></author><author><name>Maya Bar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The interaction of plants with the complex microbial networks that inhabit them is important for plant health. While the reliance of plants on their microbial inhabitants for defense against invading pathogens is well documented, the acquisition of data concerning the relationships between plant developmental stage or aging, and microbiome assembly, is still underway. In this work, we observed developmental-age dependent changes in the phyllopshere microbiome of tomato. The plant hormone cytokinin (CK) regulates various plant growth and developmental processes. Here, we show that age-related shifts in microbiome content vary based on content of, or sensitivity to, CK. We observed a developmental age associated decline in microbial richness and diversity, accompanied by a decline in the presence of growth promoting and resistance inducing bacilli in the phyllosphere. This decline was absent from CK-rich or CK-hypersensitive genotypes. Bacillus isolates we obtained from CK rich genotypes were found to re-program the transcriptome to support morphogenesis and alter the leaf developmental program when applied to seedlings, and enhance yield and agricultural productivity when applied to mature plants. Our results support the notion that CK-dependent effects on microbiome content support developmental functions, suggesting that these are mediated by CK in part via the bacterial community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.02.454802" rel="alternate" title="Cytokinin- microbiome interactions regulate developmental functions (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>