<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.223267+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465363</id><title>A Null Allele of the Pol IV Second Subunit is Viable in Oryza sativa (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.223512+00:00</updated><author><name>Tania Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Joshua T. Trujillo</name></author><author><name>Timmy Kendall</name></author><author><name>Rebecca A. Mosher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All eukaryotes possess three DNA-dependent RNA polymerases, Pols I-III, while land plants possess two additional polymerases, Pol IV and Pol V. Derived through duplication of Pol II subunits, Pol IV produces 24-nt siRNAs that interact with Pol V transcripts to target &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; DNA methylation and silence transcription of transposons. Members of the grass family encode additional duplicated subunits of Pol IV and V, raising questions regarding the function of each paralog. In this study, we identify a null allele of the putative Pol IV second subunit, &lt;italic&gt;NRPD2&lt;/italic&gt;, and demonstrate that NRPD2 is the sole subunit functioning with NRPD1 in small RNA production and CHH methylation in leaves. Homozygous &lt;italic&gt;nrpd2&lt;/italic&gt; mutants have neither gametophytic defects, nor embryo lethality, although adult plants are dwarf and sterile.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465363" rel="alternate" title="A Null Allele of the Pol IV Second Subunit is Viable in Oryza sativa (14 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465099</id><title>The superior salinity tolerance of wheat cultivar Shanrong No. 3 cannot be attributed to elevated Ta-sro1 poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase activity (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.223744+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Vogt</name></author><author><name>Karla Feijs</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Hosch</name></author><author><name>Raffaella De Masi</name></author><author><name>Ruth Lintermann</name></author><author><name>Bernhard Loll</name></author><author><name>Lennart Wirthmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Saline soils limit the production of important staple crops such as wheat, particularly in arid and semiarid regions. Salt tolerance is a multi-gene trait and this complicates breeding of wheat varieties that deliver high yields under saline soil conditions. Notably, the elevated salinity tolerance of wheat cultivar Shanrong No. 3 (SR3) has been linked to a specific proteoform of the wheat SIMILAR TO RCD1 ONE (SRO1) protein that was created in an asymmetric genome hybridization with tall wheat grass. The two amino acid polymorphisms of the Ta-sro1 proteoform enhance the poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) activity of the protein suggesting that altered poly-ADP-ribosylation of unknown substrate proteins or nucleic acids underlie the elevated salinity tolerance of cultivar SR3. To elucidate the molecular basis for the elevated PARP activity of the Ta-sro1 proteoform we solved a crystal structure of the catalytic PARP domain. Surprisingly, the structure revealed that the postulated binding site for the co-substrate NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; substantially differs from the structurally conserved NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; binding sites of canonical PARP enzymes. Consistently, we find that Ta-sro1 does not bind NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and lacks ADP-ribosyltransferase activity. Therefore, although the structure revealed that one of the polymorphic amino acids is located close to the proposed active site, the elevated salinity tolerance of cultivar SR3 cannot be explained by altered ADP-ribosyltransferase activity of Ta-sro1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465099" rel="alternate" title="The superior salinity tolerance of wheat cultivar Shanrong No. 3 cannot be attributed to elevated Ta-sro1 poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase activity (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465103</id><title>Highly efficient generation of canker resistant sweet orange enabled by an improved CRISPR/Cas9 system (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.224091+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoen Huang</name></author><author><name>Nian Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sweet orange (&lt;italic&gt;Citrus sinensis&lt;/italic&gt;) is the most economically important species for the citrus industry. However, it is susceptible to many diseases including citrus bacterial canker caused by &lt;italic&gt;Xanthomonas citri&lt;/italic&gt; subsp. citri (&lt;italic&gt;Xcc&lt;/italic&gt;) that triggers devastating effects on citrus production. Conventional breeding has not met the challenge to improve disease resistance of sweet orange due to the long juvenility and other limitations. CRISPR-mediated genome editing has shown promising potentials for genetic improvements of plants. Generation of biallelic/homozygous mutants remains difficult for sweet orange due to low transformation rate, existence of heterozygous alleles for target genes and low biallelic editing efficacy using the CRISPR technology. Here, we report improvements in the CRISPR/Cas9 system for citrus gene editing. Based on the improvements we made previously (dicot codon optimized Cas9, tRNA for multiplexing, a modified sgRNA scaffold with high efficiency, CsU6 to drive sgRNA expression), we further improved our CRISPR/Cas9 system by choosing superior promoters (CmYLCV or CsUbi promoter) to drive Cas9 and optimizing culture temperature. This system was able to generate a biallelic mutation rate of up to 89% for Carrizo citrange and 79% for Hamlin sweet orange. Consequently, this system was used to generate canker resistant Hamlin sweet orange by mutating the effector binding element (EBE) of canker susceptibility gene &lt;italic&gt;CsLOB1&lt;/italic&gt;, which is required for causing canker symptoms by &lt;italic&gt;Xcc&lt;/italic&gt;. Six biallelic Hamlin sweet orange mutant lines in the EBE were generated. The biallelic mutants are resistant to &lt;italic&gt;Xcc&lt;/italic&gt;. Biallelic mutation of the EBE region abolishes the induction of &lt;italic&gt;CsLOB1&lt;/italic&gt; by &lt;italic&gt;Xcc&lt;/italic&gt;. This study represents a significant improvement in sweet orange gene editing efficacy and generating disease resistant varieties via CRISPR-mediated genome editing. This improvement in citrus genome editing makes genetic studies and manipulations of sweet orange more feasible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465103" rel="alternate" title="Highly efficient generation of canker resistant sweet orange enabled by an improved CRISPR/Cas9 system (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>