<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.132602+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462495</id><title>Dominant Awn Inhibitor, which encodes an ALOG protein in sorghum, suppresses awn formation in rice (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.133166+00:00</updated><author><name>Hideki Takanashi</name></author><author><name>Hiromi Kajiya-Kanegae</name></author><author><name>Asuka Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Junko Yamada</name></author><author><name>Motoyuki Ishimori</name></author><author><name>Masaaki Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Kentaro Yano</name></author><author><name>Hiroyoshi Iwata</name></author><author><name>Nobuhiro Tsutsumi</name></author><author><name>Wataru Sakamoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The awn, a needle-like structure that extends from the tip of the lemma in grass species, is believed to play a role in environmental adaptation and fitness. Wild species of cereal crops tend to have longer awns, whereas modern cultivars display a variety of awn lengths and morphologies. Awns in some crops seem to have been eliminated during domestication, and genes controlling awn formation have been reported. Interestingly, a few single dominant factors that eliminate awns are already known; in sorghum (&lt;italic&gt;Sorghum bicolor&lt;/italic&gt;), for example, the dominant awn inhibitor has been known for a century, though its molecular identity remains uncharacterized. In this study, we conducted quantitative trait locus (QTL) analysis and a genome-wide association study of awn-related traits in sorghum. Among the three QTLs controlling awn presence and length, one of them, mapped on chromosome 3, had an extraordinary effect on eliminating awns. We provide a line of evidence demonstrating that this QTL corresponds to &lt;italic&gt;Dominant Awn Inhibitor&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt;), encoding an ALOG family protein that potentially acts as a transcription factor. Detailed analysis of the ALOG protein family in cereals revealed that &lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt; was considered to originate from a gene duplication of its twin paralogue on chromosome 10. Interestingly, heterologous expression of &lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt; with its own promoter in rice inhibited awn formation in the awned cultivar Kasalath. Our finding that &lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt; was born by gene duplication provides an interesting example of gain-of-function, which occurs only in sorghum but shares its functionality with rice and sorghum.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462495" rel="alternate" title="Dominant Awn Inhibitor, which encodes an ALOG protein in sorghum, suppresses awn formation in rice (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462608</id><title>Cost-effective, high-throughput phenotyping system for 3D reconstruction of fruit form (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.133655+00:00</updated><author><name>Mitchell J. Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Amy Tabb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reliable phenotyping methods that are simple to operate and in-expensive to deploy are critical for studying quantitative traits in plants. Traditional fruit shape phenotyping relies on human raters or 2D analyses to assess form, e.g., size and shape. Systems for 3D imaging using multi-view stereo have been implemented, but frequently rely on commercial software and/or specialized hardware, which can lead to limitations in accessibility and scalability. We present a complete system constructed of consumer-grade components for capturing, calibrating, and reconstructing the 3D form of small-to-moderate sized fruits and tubers. Data acquisition and image capture sessions are 9 seconds to capture 60 images. The initial prototype cost was $1600 USD. We measured accuracy by comparing reconstructed models of 3D printed ground truth objects to the original digital files of those same ground truth objects. The &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; between length of the primary, secondary, and tertiary axes, volume, and surface area of the ground-truth object and the reconstructed models was &lt;italic&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/italic&gt; 0.97 and root-mean square error (RMSE) was &lt;italic&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/italic&gt;3mm for objects without locally concave regions. Measurements from 1mm and 2mm resolution reconstructions were consistent (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/italic&gt; 0.99). Qualitative assessments were performed on 48 fruit and tubers, including 18 strawberries, 12 potatoes, 5 grapes, 7 peppers, and 4 Bosch and 2 red Anjou pears. Our proposed phenotyping system is fast, relatively low cost, and has demonstrated accuracy for certain shape classes, and could be used for the 3D analysis of fruit form.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462608" rel="alternate" title="Cost-effective, high-throughput phenotyping system for 3D reconstruction of fruit form (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>