<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.317853+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470094</id><title>Chloroplast transit peptides often require downstream unstructured sequence in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.318193+00:00</updated><author><name>Oliver D Caspari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The N-terminal sequence stretch that defines subcellular targeting for most nuclear encoded chloroplast proteins is usually considered identical to the sequence that is cleaved upon import. Yet here this study shows that for nine out of ten tested Chlamydomonas chloroplast transit peptides, additional sequence past the cleavage site is required to enable chloroplast targeting. Using replacements of native post-cleavage residues with alternative sequences points to a role for unstructured sequence at mature protein N-termini.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470094" rel="alternate" title="Chloroplast transit peptides often require downstream unstructured sequence in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (14 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470062</id><title>Spatial resolution of an integrated C4+CAM photosynthetic metabolism (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.318363+00:00</updated><author><name>Jose J Moreno-Villena</name></author><author><name>Haoran Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ian S Gilman</name></author><author><name>S. Lori Tausta</name></author><author><name>C. Y. Maurice Cheung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and CAM photosynthesis have repeatedly evolved in plants over the past 30 million years. Because both repurpose the same set of enzymes but differ in their spatial and temporal deployment, they have long been considered as distinct and incompatible adaptations. Remarkably, Portulaca contains multiple C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; species that perform CAM when droughted. Spatially explicit analyses of gene expression reveal that C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and CAM systems are completely integrated in P. oleracea, with CAM and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; carbon fixation occurring in the same cells and CAM-generated metabolites likely incorporated directly into the C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; cycle. Flux balance analysis corroborates the gene expression and predicts an integrated C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;+CAM system under drought. This first spatially explicit description of a C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;+CAM photosynthetic metabolism presents a new blueprint for crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470062" rel="alternate" title="Spatial resolution of an integrated C4+CAM photosynthetic metabolism (12 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469708</id><title>A newly-evolved chimeric lysin motif receptor-like kinase in Medicago truncatula spp. tricycla R108 extends its Rhizobia symbiotic partnership (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.318551+00:00</updated><author><name>Thi-Bich Luu</name></author><author><name>Anna Ourth</name></author><author><name>Cécile Pouzet</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Pauly</name></author><author><name>Julie Cullimore</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rhizobial lipochitooligosaccharidic Nod factors, specified by &lt;italic&gt;nod&lt;/italic&gt; genes, are the primary determinants of host specificity in the legume-Rhizobia symbiosis. A &lt;italic&gt;Sinorhizobium meliloti nodF/nodL&lt;/italic&gt; mutant produces Nod factors that differ from wild-type ones in lacking an &lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-acetate, and with a different acyl chain on the terminal non-reducing sugar. This mutant is defective in nodulation with various &lt;italic&gt;Medicago&lt;/italic&gt; hosts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We examined the nodulation ability of &lt;italic&gt;M. truncatula&lt;/italic&gt; cv Jemalong A17 and &lt;italic&gt;M. truncatula&lt;/italic&gt; ssp. &lt;italic&gt;tricycla&lt;/italic&gt; R108 with the &lt;italic&gt;nodF/nodL&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. We then applied genetic and functional approaches to study the genetic basis and mechanism of nodulation of R108 by this mutant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that the &lt;italic&gt;nodF/nodL&lt;/italic&gt; mutant can nodulate R108 but not A17. Using genomics and reverse genetics, we identified a newly-evolved gene in R108, &lt;italic&gt;LYK2bis&lt;/italic&gt;, which is responsible for the phenotype. Transformation with &lt;italic&gt;LYK2bis&lt;/italic&gt; allows A17 to gain nodulation with the &lt;italic&gt;nodF/nodL&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. We found that LYK2bis is involved in specific NF signalling and interacts with the key receptor protein NFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings reveal that a newly-evolved gene in R108, &lt;italic&gt;LYK2bis&lt;/italic&gt;, extends nodulation specificity to strains producing non-&lt;italic&gt;O&lt;/italic&gt;-acetylated NFs. Interaction between LYK2bis and NFP provides a means of integrating the nodulation signalling pathways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469708" rel="alternate" title="A newly-evolved chimeric lysin motif receptor-like kinase in Medicago truncatula spp. tricycla R108 extends its Rhizobia symbiotic partnership (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469029</id><title>Characterization of the grape powdery mildew genetic resistance loci in Muscadinia rotundifolia Trayshed (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.318694+00:00</updated><author><name>Mélanie Massonnet</name></author><author><name>Amanda M. Vondras</name></author><author><name>Noé Cochetel</name></author><author><name>Summaira Riaz</name></author><author><name>Dániel Pap</name></author><author><name>Andrea Minio</name></author><author><name>Rosa Figueroa-Balderas</name></author><author><name>M. Andrew Walker</name></author><author><name>Dario Cantu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Muscadinia rotundifolia&lt;/italic&gt; cv. Trayshed is a valuable source of resistance to grape powdery mildew (PM). It carries two PM resistance (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;) loci, &lt;italic&gt;Run1.2&lt;/italic&gt; on chromosome 12 and &lt;italic&gt;Run2.2&lt;/italic&gt; on chromosome 18. This study identified the nucleotide-binding leucine-rich repeat (NLR) genes composing each &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; locus and their associated defense mechanisms. Evaluation of PM disease development showed that introgression of both loci confers resistance to PM in a &lt;italic&gt;V. vinifera&lt;/italic&gt; background, but with varying speed and intensity of the response. To better understand the effect of NLR composition on PM resistance, both haplotypes of each &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; locus were reconstructed and the gene models within each haplotype were manually refined. We found that the number and classes of NLR genes differed between &lt;italic&gt;Run1.2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Run2.2&lt;/italic&gt; loci and between the haplotypes of each &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; locus. In addition, NLR genes composing &lt;italic&gt;Run1.2b&lt;/italic&gt; or &lt;italic&gt;Run2.2&lt;/italic&gt; loci exhibited different levels of gene expression, pointing to candidate NLR genes responsible for PM resistance in Trayshed. Finally, a transcriptomic analysis that included six additional &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; loci showed differences in the defense mechanisms associated with &lt;italic&gt;Run1.2b&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Run2.2&lt;/italic&gt; in response to PM and at constitutive level. Altogether, our results reveal that Trayshed’s &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt; loci are composed of distinct NLRs that trigger different plant defense mechanisms in response to PM and at constitutive level, which would explain the variation of pathogen restriction between the two loci.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469029" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of the grape powdery mildew genetic resistance loci in Muscadinia rotundifolia Trayshed (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469474</id><title>A chromosome-level reference genome of Ensete glaucum gives insight into diversity, chromosomal and repetitive sequence evolution in the Musaceae (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.318853+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziwei Wang</name></author><author><name>Mathieu Rouard</name></author><author><name>Manosh Kumar Biswas</name></author><author><name>Gaetan Droc</name></author><author><name>Dongli Cui</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Roux</name></author><author><name>Franc-Christophe Baurens</name></author><author><name>Xue-Jun Ge</name></author><author><name>Trude Schwarzacher</name></author><author><name>Pat (J.S.) Heslop-Harrison</name></author><author><name>Qing Liu</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Ensete glaucum&lt;/italic&gt; (2&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt; = 2&lt;italic&gt;x&lt;/italic&gt; = 18) is a giant herbaceous monocotyledonous plant in the small Musaceae family along with banana (&lt;italic&gt;Musa&lt;/italic&gt;). A high-quality reference genome sequence of &lt;italic&gt;E. glaucum&lt;/italic&gt; offers a vital genomic resource for functional and evolutionary studies of &lt;italic&gt;Ensete&lt;/italic&gt;, the Musaceae, and more widely in the Zingiberales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a combination of Illumina and Oxford Nanopore Technologies (ONT) sequencing, genome-wide chromosome conformation capture (Hi-C), and RNA survey sequence, we report a high-quality assembly of the 481.5Mb genome with 9 pseudochromosomes and 36,836 genes (BUSCO 94.7%). A total of 55% of the genome is composed of repetitive sequences with LTR-retroelements (37%) and DNA transposons (7%) predominant. The 5S and 45S rDNA were each present at one locus, and the 5S rDNA had an exceptionally long monomer length of c.1,056 bp, contrasting with the c. 450 bp monomer at multiple loci in &lt;italic&gt;Musa&lt;/italic&gt;. A tandemly repeated c. 134 bp satellite, 1.1% of the genome (with no similar sequence in &lt;italic&gt;Musa&lt;/italic&gt;), was present around all nine centromeres, with a LINE retroelement also found at &lt;italic&gt;Musa&lt;/italic&gt; centromeres. The assembly, including centromeric positions, enabled us to characterize in detail the chromosomal rearrangements occurring between the &lt;italic&gt;x&lt;/italic&gt; = 9 species and &lt;italic&gt;x&lt;/italic&gt; = 11 species of &lt;italic&gt;Musa&lt;/italic&gt;. Only one chromosome has the same gene content as &lt;italic&gt;M. acuminata&lt;/italic&gt; (ma). Three ma chromosomes represent part of only one &lt;italic&gt;E. glaucum&lt;/italic&gt; (eg) chromosome, while the remaining seven ma chromosomes are fusions of parts of two, three, or four eg chromosomes, demonstrating complex and multiple evolutionary rearrangements in the change between &lt;italic&gt;x&lt;/italic&gt; = 9 and &lt;italic&gt;x&lt;/italic&gt; = 11.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The advance towards a Musaceae pangenome including &lt;italic&gt;E. glaucum,&lt;/italic&gt; tolerant of extreme environments, makes a complete set of gene alleles available for crop breeding and understanding environmental responses. The chromosome-scale genome assembly show how chromosome number evolves, and features of the rapid evolution of repetitive sequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469474" rel="alternate" title="A chromosome-level reference genome of Ensete glaucum gives insight into diversity, chromosomal and repetitive sequence evolution in the Musaceae (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470170</id><title>Two Liberibacter Effectors Combine to Suppress Critical Innate Immune Defenses and Facilitate Huanglongbing Pathogenesis in Citrus (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.319020+00:00</updated><author><name>Supratim Basu</name></author><author><name>Loan Huynh</name></author><author><name>Shujian Zhang</name></author><author><name>Roel Rabara</name></author><author><name>jeanette velasquez</name></author><author><name>Hau Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Guixia Hao</name></author><author><name>Godfrey Miles</name></author><author><name>Qingchun Shi</name></author><author><name>Ed Stover</name></author><author><name>Goutam Gupta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome sequence analyses predicted the presence of effectors in the gram-negative Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus (CLas) even without the presence of a classical type III secretion system.  Since CLas is not culturable, it is not possible to perform traditional gene knockout experiments to determine the role of various effectors in Huanglongbing (HLB) pathogenesis.  Therefore, we followed an alternative functional genomics approach to examine the role of the CLas effectors in HLB pathogenesis in general and more specifically in suppressing citrus innate immune response.  Here, we focused on the CLas effectors, P235 and Effector 3, to perform the following studies.  First, proteomic studies by LC-MS/MS were conducted to screen the putative interacting citrus protein partners of P235 and Effector 3 from the healthy and CLas-infected Hamlin extracts and the most probable candidates were identified based upon their high protein scores from LC-MS/MS.  Second, a transgenic tobacco split GFP system was designed for in planta detection of the most probable citrus interacting protein partners of P235 and Effector 3.  Third, in vitro and in planta studies were performed to show that each of two effectors interacts with and inhibits the functions of multiple citrus proteins belonging to the innate immune pathways.  These inhibitory interactions led to a high level of reactive oxygen species (ROS), blocking of bactericidal lipid binding protein (LTP), and induction of premature programmed cell death (PCD), thereby supporting CLas infection and HLB pathogenesis.  Finally, an LTP mimic was designed to sequester and block the CLas effector and to rescue the bactericidal activity of LTP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470170" rel="alternate" title="Two Liberibacter Effectors Combine to Suppress Critical Innate Immune Defenses and Facilitate Huanglongbing Pathogenesis in Citrus (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469751</id><title>Seed bio-priming with phosphate solubilizing bacteria strains to improve rice (Oryza sativa L. var. FARO 44) growth under ferruginous ultisol conditions (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.319183+00:00</updated><author><name>Musa Saheed Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Beckley Ikhajiagbe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The research investigated the possibility of phosphate solubilizing bacteria (PSB) with plant growth-promoting (PGP) capabilities to improve growth properties of rice plant under ferruginous ultisol (FU) condition through bio-priming strategy. The PSB with PGP properties used in this research were &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; strain GGBSU-1, &lt;italic&gt;Proteus mirabilis&lt;/italic&gt; strain TL14-1 and &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella variicola&lt;/italic&gt; strain AUH-KAM-9 that were previously isolated and characterized following the 16S rRNA gene sequencing. Biosafety analysis of the PSB isolates was conducted using blood agar. The rice seeds were then bio-primed with the PSBs at 3, 12 and 24 hours priming durations and then sown in a composite FU soil sample. Differences in germination bioassay involving SEM, morphology, physiology and biomass parameters were investigated for 15 weeks after bio-priming. The composite FU soil used in the study had high pH, low bioavailable phosphorus, low water holding capacity and high iron levels which has led to a low growth properties of rice seeds without bio-priming in FU soil. Germination parameters was better in seeds bio-primed with the PSBs, especially at 12h priming duration as against seeds without priming. SEM showed more bacterial colonization in the PSB bio-primed seeds. Seed bio-priming of rice seed with &lt;italic&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/italic&gt; strain GGBSU-1, &lt;italic&gt;Proteus mirabilis&lt;/italic&gt; strain TL14-1 and &lt;italic&gt;Klebsiella variicola&lt;/italic&gt; strain AUH-KAM-9 under FU soil condition significantly improved seed microbiome, rhizocolonization and soil nutrient properties, thereby enhancing growth properties of the rice plant. This suggest the ability of PSB to solubilize and mineralize soil phosphate and improve its availability and soil property for optimum plant usage in phosphate stressed and iron toxic soils.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469751" rel="alternate" title="Seed bio-priming with phosphate solubilizing bacteria strains to improve rice (Oryza sativa L. var. FARO 44) growth under ferruginous ultisol conditions (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470209</id><title>A conserved long intergenic non-coding RNA containing snoRNA sequences, lncCOBRA1, affects Arabidopsis germination and development (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.319296+00:00</updated><author><name>Marianne C Kramer</name></author><author><name>Hee Jong Kim</name></author><author><name>Kyle R Palos</name></author><author><name>Benjamin A Garcia</name></author><author><name>Eric Lyons</name></author><author><name>Mark A Beilstein</name></author><author><name>Andrew D.L. Nelson</name></author><author><name>Brian D Gregory</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are an increasingly studied group of non-protein-coding transcripts with a wide variety of molecular functions gaining attention for their roles in numerous biological processes. Nearly 6,000 lncRNAs have been identified in Arabidopsis thaliana but many have yet to be studied. Here, we examine a class of previously uncharacterized lncRNAs termed CONSERVED IN BRASSICA RAPA (lncCOBRA) transcripts that were previously identified for their high level of sequence conservation in the related crop species Brassica rapa, their nuclear-localization and protein-bound nature. In particular, we focus on lncCOBRA1 and demonstrate that its abundance is highly tissue and developmental specific, with particularly high levels early in germination. lncCOBRA1 contains two snoRNAs domains within it, making it the first sno-lincRNA example in a non-mammalian system. However, we find that it is processed differently than its mammalian counterparts. We further show that plants lacking lncCOBRA1 display patterns of delayed gemination and are overall smaller than wild-type plants. Lastly, we identify the proteins that interact with lncCOBRA1 and examine the protein-protein interaction network of lncCOBRA1-interacting proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470209" rel="alternate" title="A conserved long intergenic non-coding RNA containing snoRNA sequences, lncCOBRA1, affects Arabidopsis germination and development (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469749</id><title>Influence of selected plant growth stimulators in enhancing germinability and germination parameters of Zea mays L. under microgravity conditions simulated by a two-dimensional clinostat (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.319442+00:00</updated><author><name>Beckley Ikhajiagbe</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey O. Anoliefo</name></author><author><name>Alexander O. Orukpe</name></author><author><name>Saheed I. Musa</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The earth has become increasingly overcrowded as a result of rapid urbanization and population growth, predicting that its carrying capacity could be overstretched. As a result, it is important to test the possibilities of growing plants under space exploration conditions, especially gravitational balance. Since microgravity impedes plant development, to what extent can plant growth stimulators reverse or enhance this trend? A total of 12 maize seeds were weighed and placed sideways in petri dish and inoculated with plant growth stimulators such as indole acetic acid (IAA), gibberellic acid (GA), and ascorbate (AA) and the clinorotated at different rates (0.5, 1.0 and 2.0 rpm), while control seeds were just placed on a table. Results showed that at 72 hrs, the maize seeds under microgravity showed reduced germination percentage with increasing clinorotation rates as against the control. But when stimulated with IAA, GA and AA, improved germination percentage was observed as against the control even under microgravity condition. The seedling dry weight, germination time and other germination parameters also showed similar improvements. Comparatively, the three growth stimulators showed no major variations in their ability to improve germination percentage under microgravitational impact. However, IAA showed more improvement on seedling vigor as against others, while GA showed more effect on the peak time and rate of germination. This research confirmed the possibilities of improving germinability of maize seeds under space exploration condition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469749" rel="alternate" title="Influence of selected plant growth stimulators in enhancing germinability and germination parameters of Zea mays L. under microgravity conditions simulated by a two-dimensional clinostat (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>