<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.932803+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456832</id><title>The genome of stress tolerant crop wild relative Paspalum vaginatum leads to increased biomass productivity in the crop Zea mays (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.933015+00:00</updated><author><name>Guangchao Sun</name></author><author><name>Nishikant Wase</name></author><author><name>Shengqiang Shu</name></author><author><name>Jerry Jenkins</name></author><author><name>Bangjun Zhou</name></author><author><name>Cindy Chen</name></author><author><name>Laura Sandor</name></author><author><name>Chris Plott</name></author><author><name>Yuko Yoshinga</name></author><author><name>Christopher Daum</name></author><author><name>Peng Qi</name></author><author><name>Kerrie Barry</name></author><author><name>Anna Lipzen</name></author><author><name>Luke Berry</name></author><author><name>Thomas Gottilla</name></author><author><name>Ashley Foltz</name></author><author><name>Huihui Yu</name></author><author><name>Ronan O’Malley</name></author><author><name>Chi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Katrien M. Devos</name></author><author><name>Brandi Sigmon</name></author><author><name>Bin Yu</name></author><author><name>Toshihiro Obata</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Schmutz</name></author><author><name>James C. Schnable</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A number of crop wild relatives can tolerate extreme stressed to a degree outside the range observed in their domesticated relatives. However, it is unclear whether or how the molecular mechanisms employed by these species can be translated to domesticated crops. Paspalum &lt;italic&gt;Paspalum vaginatum&lt;/italic&gt; is a self-incompatible and multiply stress-tolerant wild relative of maize and sorghum. Here we describe the sequencing and pseudomolecule level assembly of a vegetatively propagated accession of &lt;italic&gt;P. vaginatum&lt;/italic&gt;. Phylogenetic analysis based on 6,151 single-copy syntenic orthologous conserved in 6 related grass species placed paspalum as an outgroup of the maize-sorghum clade demonstrating paspalum as their closest sequenced wild relative. In parallel metabolic experiments, paspalum, but neither maize nor sorghum, exhibited significant increases in trehalose when grown under nutrient-deficit conditions. Inducing trehalose accumulation in maize, imitating the metabolic phenotype of paspalum, resulting in autophagy dependent increases in biomass accumulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456832" rel="alternate" title="The genome of stress tolerant crop wild relative Paspalum vaginatum leads to increased biomass productivity in the crop Zea mays (19 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.457018</id><title>Cellulose synthase-like D (CSLD) proteins move in the plasma membrane and their targeting to cell tips, but not cell plates, depends on the actin cytoskeleton (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.933319+00:00</updated><author><name>Shu-Zon Wu</name></author><author><name>Arielle M. Chaves</name></author><author><name>Rongrong Li</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Bezanilla</name></author><author><name>Alison W. Roberts</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellulose Synthase-Like D (CSLD) proteins are implicated in cell wall remodeling during tip growth and cell division in plants, and are known to generate β-1,4-glucan. It is unknown whether they form complexes and move in the plasma membrane like members of the Cellulose Synthase (CESA) family. We used the genetically tractable moss &lt;italic&gt;Physcomitrium patens&lt;/italic&gt;, which has a filamentous protonemal stage that undergoes both tip growth and cell division and is amenable to high resolution live cell imaging, to investigate CSLD function and intracellular trafficking. &lt;italic&gt;CSLD2&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;CSLD6&lt;/italic&gt; are highly expressed in gametophores and are redundantly required for gametophore cellular patterning. Live cell imaging revealed that CSLD6 is also expressed in protonemata where it moves in the plasma membrane and localizes to cell plates and cell tips. Notably, delivery to the apical plasma membrane, but not the cell plate, depends on actin. By comparing the behavior of endogenously tagged CSLD6 and CESA10, we discovered that CSLD6 movements in the plasma membrane were significantly faster, shorter in duration and less linear than CESA10 movements and were insensitive to the cellulose synthesis inhibitor isoxaben. These data suggest that CSLD6 and CESA10 function within different structures and may thus produce structurally distinct cellulose microfibrils.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.457018" rel="alternate" title="Cellulose synthase-like D (CSLD) proteins move in the plasma membrane and their targeting to cell tips, but not cell plates, depends on the actin cytoskeleton (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>