<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.658683+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453319</id><title>Pectin remodeling belongs to a homeostatic system and triggers transcriptomic and hormonal modulations (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.659420+00:00</updated><author><name>François Jobert</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Guénin</name></author><author><name>Aline Voxeur</name></author><author><name>Kieran J. D. Lee</name></author><author><name>Sophie Bouton</name></author><author><name>Fabien Sénéchal</name></author><author><name>Ludivine Hocq</name></author><author><name>Gaëlle Mongelard</name></author><author><name>Hervé Demailly</name></author><author><name>Petra Amakorová</name></author><author><name>Miroslav Strnad</name></author><author><name>Samantha Vernhettes</name></author><author><name>Gregory Mouille</name></author><author><name>Serge Pilard</name></author><author><name>J. Paul Knox</name></author><author><name>Ondřej Novák</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Pelloux</name></author><author><name>Laurent Gutierrez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pectins occur in primary cell walls and consist of multiblock co-polymers among which homogalacturonan (HG) is the simplest and most abundant form. Methylesterification patterns of HG are tuned by pectin methylesterases (PMEs), the activities of which are controlled by specific inhibitors (PMEIs). By impacting cell wall mechanical properties, PME-mediated regulation of HG methylesterification plays a major role in several developmental processes, including seed germination and dark-grown hypocotyl elongation. Arabidopsis &lt;italic&gt;PME36&lt;/italic&gt; is preferentially expressed during the late stage of seed development and, using the knock-out mutant &lt;italic&gt;pme36-1&lt;/italic&gt;, we show here that PME36 is required to implement the characteristic pattern of de-methylesterified pectin in the mature seed. Surprisingly, while this pattern is strongly impaired in &lt;italic&gt;pme36-1&lt;/italic&gt; mature seed, no phenotypical effect is observed in the mutant during seed germination and dark-grown hypocotyl elongation, suggesting the existence of a compensatory mechanism overcoming the defect in pectin de-methylesterification. By analyzing hormone contents and gene expression, a strong, dynamic, and long-lasting physiological disorder is revealed in the mutant. These results suggest the existence of complex connections between pectin remodeling, transcriptomic regulations and hormonal homeostasis, modulating several physiological parameters to ensure the maintenance of a normal seed-to-seedling developmental program in &lt;italic&gt;pme36-1&lt;/italic&gt;. Considered for a long time as an end-point passive effector mainly involved in modification of cell wall mechanics, the role of pectin methylesterification needs to be reconsidered as a modulator acting upstream of diverse regulatory pathways involved in plant development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453319" rel="alternate" title="Pectin remodeling belongs to a homeostatic system and triggers transcriptomic and hormonal modulations (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>