<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.064885+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468391</id><title>An atypical NLR protein modulates the NRC immune receptor network (97 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.065124+00:00</updated><author><name>Hiroaki Adachi</name></author><author><name>Toshiyuki Sakai</name></author><author><name>Adeline Harant</name></author><author><name>Cian Duggan</name></author><author><name>Tolga O Bozkurt</name></author><author><name>Chih-hang Wu</name></author><author><name>Sophien Kamoun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The NRC immune receptor network has evolved in asterid plants from a pair of linked genes into a genetically dispersed and phylogenetically structured network of sensor and helper NLR (nucleotide-binding domain and leucine-rich repeat-containing) proteins. In some species, such as the model plant &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; and other Solanaceae, the NRC network forms up to half of the NLRome, and NRCs are scattered throughout the genome in gene clusters of varying complexities. Here, we describe NRCX, an atypical, but essential member of the NRC family that lacks canonical features of these NLR helper proteins, such as a functional N-terminal MADA motif and the capacity to trigger autoimmunity. In contrast to other NRCs, systemic gene silencing of &lt;italic&gt;NRCX&lt;/italic&gt; markedly impairs plant growth resulting in a dwarf phenotype. Remarkably, dwarfism of &lt;italic&gt;NRCX&lt;/italic&gt; silenced plants is partially dependent on NRCX paralogs NRC2 and NRC3, but not NRC4. Despite its negative impact on plant growth when silenced systemically, transient RNA interference of &lt;italic&gt;NRCX&lt;/italic&gt; in mature &lt;italic&gt;N. benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; leaves doesn’t result in visible cell death phenotypes. However, alteration of &lt;italic&gt;NRCX&lt;/italic&gt; expression modulates the hypersensitive response mediated by NRC2 and NRC3 in a manner consistent with a negative role for NRCX in the NRC network. We conclude that NRCX is an atypical member of the NRC network that has evolved to contribute to the homeostasis of this genetically unlinked NLR network.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468391" rel="alternate" title="An atypical NLR protein modulates the NRC immune receptor network (97 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.468202</id><title>Smart soils to observe hidden rhizosphere processes (53 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.065309+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Patko</name></author><author><name>Qizhi Yang</name></author><author><name>Yangminghao Liu</name></author><author><name>Panagiotis Falireas</name></author><author><name>Benoit Briou</name></author><author><name>Bhausaheb V Tawade</name></author><author><name>Timothy S George</name></author><author><name>Tim J Daniell</name></author><author><name>Michael P MacDonald</name></author><author><name>Vincent Ladmiral</name></author><author><name>Bruno Ameduri</name></author><author><name>Lionel Xavier Dupuy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Agriculture must reduce green-house gas emission and pollution, produce safer and healthier food, closer to home, reducing waste whilst delivering more diverse diets to a growing world population. Soils could enable this transformation, but unfortunately, they have a hugely complex and opaque structure and studies of its myriad of mechanisms are difficult. Here, the fabrication of smart soils for the screening of below-ground bio-processes is demonstrated. Particles were generated from fluoropolymer waste with functionalisation converting them into sensors able to report on key chemical dynamics. Tailored functionalization was obtained by radical terpolymerisation to improve growth conditions and sensing capabilities. The study demonstrates the potential for the development of accelerated genetic or agrochemical screens and could pave the way for controlled indoor soil bio-production systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.19.468202" rel="alternate" title="Smart soils to observe hidden rhizosphere processes (53 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469135</id><title>Automated assembly scaffolding elevates a new tomato system for high-throughput genome editing (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.065489+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Alonge</name></author><author><name>Ludivine Lebeigle</name></author><author><name>Melanie Kirsche</name></author><author><name>Sergey Aganezov</name></author><author><name>Xingang Wang</name></author><author><name>Zachary B. Lippman</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Schatz</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Soyk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advancing crop genomics requires efficient genetic systems enabled by high-quality personalized genome assemblies. Here, we introduce RagTag, a toolset for automating assembly scaffolding and patching, and we establish chromosome-scale reference genomes for the widely used tomato genotype M82 along with Sweet-100, a rapid-cycling genotype that we developed to accelerate functional genomics and genome editing. This work outlines strategies to rapidly expand genetic systems and genomic resources in other plant species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469135" rel="alternate" title="Automated assembly scaffolding elevates a new tomato system for high-throughput genome editing (29 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468560</id><title>Shade suppresses wound-induced leaf repositioning through a mechanism involving PHYTOCHROME KINASE SUBSTRATE (PKS) genes (26 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.065639+00:00</updated><author><name>Anne-Sophie Fiorucci</name></author><author><name>Olivier Michaud</name></author><author><name>Emanuel Schmid-Siegert</name></author><author><name>Martine Trevisan</name></author><author><name>Laure Allenbach Petrolati</name></author><author><name>Yetkin Çaka Ince</name></author><author><name>Christian Fankhauser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Shaded plants challenged with herbivores or pathogens prioritize growth over defense. However, most experiments have focused on the effect of shading light cues on defense responses. To investigate the potential interaction between shade-avoidance and wounding-induced Jasmonate (JA)-mediated signaling on leaf growth and movement, we used repetitive mechanical wounding of leaf blades to mimic herbivore attacks. Phenotyping experiments with combined treatments on &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; rosettes revealed that shade strongly inhibits the wound effect on leaf elevation. By contrast, petiole length is reduced by wounding both in the sun and in the shade. Thus, the relationship between the shade and wounding/JA pathways varies depending on the physiological response, implying that leaf growth and movement can be uncoupled. Using RNA-sequencing, we identified genes with expression patterns matching the hyponastic response (opposite regulation by both stimuli, interaction between treatments with shade dominating the wound signal). Among them were genes from the &lt;italic&gt;PKS&lt;/italic&gt; (Phytochrome Kinase Substrate) family, which was previously studied for its role in phototropism and leaf positioning. Interestingly, we observed reduced shade suppression of the wounding effect in &lt;italic&gt;pks2pks4&lt;/italic&gt; double mutants while a &lt;italic&gt;PKS4&lt;/italic&gt; overexpressing line showed constitutively elevated leaves and was less sensitive to wounding. Our results indicate a trait-specific interrelationship between shade and wounding cues on Arabidopsis leaf growth and positioning. Moreover, we identify &lt;italic&gt;PKS&lt;/italic&gt; genes as integrators of external cues in the control of leaf hyponasty further emphasizing the role of these genes in aerial organ positioning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plants face different types of stressful situations without the ability to relocate to favorable environments. For example, increasing plant density reduces access to sunlight as plants start to shade each other. Foliar shading represents a stress that many plants cope with by changing their morphology. This includes elongation of stem-like structures and repositioning of leaves to favor access to unfiltered sunlight. Plants also defend themselves against various pathogens including herbivores. Defense mechanisms include the production of deterrent chemical and morphological adaptations such as stunted growth and downwards leaf repositioning. Here we studied the morphological response of plants when simultaneously facing shade and herbivore stress. When facing both stresses petiole growth was intermediate between the shade-enhanced and wound-repressed response. In contrast, the shade cue overrides the wounding cue leading to a similar upwards leaf repositioning in the combined treatments or in the response to shade alone. Using gene expression analyses and genetics we identified two members of the Phytochrome Kinase Substrate family as playing a signal integration role when plants simultaneously faced both stresses. This contributes to our understanding of the mechanisms underlying plant morphological adaptations when facing multiple stresses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468560" rel="alternate" title="Shade suppresses wound-induced leaf repositioning through a mechanism involving PHYTOCHROME KINASE SUBSTRATE (PKS) genes (26 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468702</id><title>Effector loss drives adaptation of Pseudomonas syringae pv. actinidiae to Actinidia arguta (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.065786+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren M. Hemara</name></author><author><name>Jay Jayaraman</name></author><author><name>Paul W. Sutherland</name></author><author><name>Mirco Montefiori</name></author><author><name>Saadiah Arshed</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Chatterjee</name></author><author><name>Ronan Chen</name></author><author><name>Mark Andersen</name></author><author><name>Carl H. Mesarich</name></author><author><name>Otto van der Linden</name></author><author><name>Magan M. Schipper</name></author><author><name>Joel L. Vanneste</name></author><author><name>Cyril Brendolise</name></author><author><name>Matthew D. Templeton</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A pandemic isolate of &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt; pv. &lt;italic&gt;actinidiae&lt;/italic&gt; biovar 3 (Psa3) has devastated kiwifruit orchards growing cultivars of &lt;italic&gt;Actinidia chinensis&lt;/italic&gt;. In contrast, &lt;italic&gt;A. arguta&lt;/italic&gt; (kiwiberry) is resistant to Psa3. This resistance is mediated via effector-triggered immunity, as demonstrated by induction of the hypersensitive response in infected &lt;italic&gt;A. arguta&lt;/italic&gt; leaves, observed by microscopy and quantified by ion-leakage assays. Isolates of Psa3 that cause disease in &lt;italic&gt;A. arguta&lt;/italic&gt; have been isolated and analyzed, revealing a 49 kb deletion in the exchangeable effector locus (EEL). This natural EEL-mutant isolate and strains with synthetic knockouts of the EEL were more virulent in &lt;italic&gt;A. arguta&lt;/italic&gt; plantlets than wild-type Psa3. Screening of a complete library of Psa3 effector knockout strains identified increased growth &lt;italic&gt;in planta&lt;/italic&gt; for knockouts of four effectors – AvrRpm1a, HopF1c, HopZ5a, and the EEL effector HopAW1a – suggesting a resistance response in &lt;italic&gt;A. arguta&lt;/italic&gt;. Hypersensitive response (HR) assays indicate that three of these effectors trigger a host species-specific HR. A Psa3 strain with all four effectors knocked out escaped host recognition, but a cumulative increase in bacterial pathogenicity and virulence was not observed. These avirulence effectors can be used in turn to identify the first cognate resistance genes in &lt;italic&gt;Actinidia&lt;/italic&gt; for breeding durable resistance into future kiwifruit cultivars.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468702" rel="alternate" title="Effector loss drives adaptation of Pseudomonas syringae pv. actinidiae to Actinidia arguta (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469146</id><title>Profile of the in silico secretome of the palm dieback pathogen, a fungus that puts natural oases at risk (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.065970+00:00</updated><author><name>Maryam Rafiqi</name></author><author><name>Lukas Jelonek</name></author><author><name>Aliou M. Diouf</name></author><author><name>AbdouLahat Mbaye</name></author><author><name>Martijn Rep</name></author><author><name>Alhousseine Diarra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding biotic changes that occur alongside climate change constitute a research priority of global significance. Here, we address a plant pathogen that poses a serious threat to life on natural oases, where climate change is already taking a toll and severely impacting human subsistence. &lt;italic&gt;Fusarium oxysporum&lt;/italic&gt; f. sp. &lt;italic&gt;albedinis&lt;/italic&gt; is a pathogen that causes dieback disease on date palms, a tree that provides several critical ecosystem services in natural oases; and consequently, of major importance in this vulnerable habitat. Here, we assess the current state of global pathogen spread, we annotate the genome of a sequenced pathogen strain isolated from the native range and we analyse its &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; secretome. The palm dieback pathogen secretes a large arsenal of effector candidates including a variety of toxins, a distinguished profile of secreted in xylem proteins (SIX) as well as an expanded protein family with an N-terminal conserved motif [SG]PC[KR]P that could be involved in interactions with host membranes. Using agrobiodiversity as a strategy to decrease pathogen infectivity, while providing short term resilient solutions, seems to be widely overcome by the pathogen. Hence, the urgent need for future mechanistic research on the palm dieback disease and a better understanding of pathogen genetic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469146" rel="alternate" title="Profile of the in silico secretome of the palm dieback pathogen, a fungus that puts natural oases at risk (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469149</id><title>Heat stress leads to rapid lipid remodelling and transcriptional adaptations in Nicotiana tabacum pollen tubes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.066109+00:00</updated><author><name>Hannah E Krawczyk</name></author><author><name>Alexander Helmut Rotsch</name></author><author><name>Cornelia Herrfurth</name></author><author><name>Patricia Scholz</name></author><author><name>Orr Shomroni</name></author><author><name>Gabriela Salinas-Riester</name></author><author><name>Ivo Feussner</name></author><author><name>Till Ischebeck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;After reaching the stigma, pollen grains germinate and form a pollen tube that transports the sperm cells to the ovule. Due to selection pressure between pollen tubes, they likely evolved mechanisms to quickly adapt to temperature changes to sustain an elongation at the highest possible rate. We investigated these adaptions in Nicotiana tabacum pollen tubes grown in vitro under 22 °C and 37 °C by a multi-omic approach including lipidomic, metabolomic and transcriptomic analysis. Both glycerophospholipids and galactoglycerolipids increased in saturated acyl chains under heat stress while triacylglycerols changed less in respect to desaturation but showed higher levels. Free sterol composition was altered, and sterol ester levels decreased. The levels of sterylglycosides and several sphingolipid classes and species were augmented. Most amino acids increased during heat stress, including the non-codogenic amino acids γ-amino butyrate and pipecolate. Furthermore, the sugars sedoheptulose and sucrose showed higher levels. Also the transcriptome underwent pronounced changes with 1,570 of 24,013 genes being differentially up- and 813 being downregulated. Transcripts coding for heat shock proteins and many transcriptional regulators were most strongly upregulated, but also transcripts that have so far not been linked to heat stress. Transcripts involved in triacylglycerol synthesis were increased, while the modulation of acyl chain desaturation seemed not to be transcriptionally controlled indicating other means of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.18.469149" rel="alternate" title="Heat stress leads to rapid lipid remodelling and transcriptional adaptations in Nicotiana tabacum pollen tubes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468678</id><title>A cell wall-associated gene network shapes leaf boundary domains (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.066257+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathalie Bouré</name></author><author><name>Alexis Peaucelle</name></author><author><name>Magali Goussot</name></author><author><name>Bernard Adroher</name></author><author><name>Ludivine Soubigou-Taconnat</name></author><author><name>Eric Biot</name></author><author><name>Zakia Tariq</name></author><author><name>Marie-Laure Martin-Magniette</name></author><author><name>Patrick Laufs</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Arnaud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Boundary domains delimit and organize organ growth throughout plant development almost relentlessly building plant architecture and morphogenesis. Boundary domains display reduced growth and orchestrate development of adjacent tissues in a non-cell autonomous manner. How these two functions are achieved remains elusive despite the identification of several boundary-specific genes. Here, we show using morphometrics at the organ and cellular levels that leaf boundary domain development requires SPINDLY (SPY), an O-fucosyltransferase, to act as cell growth repressor. Further we show that SPY acts redundantly with the CUP-SHAPED COTYLEDON transcription factors (CUC2 and CUC3), which are major determinants of boundaries development. Accordingly at the molecular level, CUC2 and SPY repress a common set of genes involved in cell wall loosening providing a molecular framework for the growth repression associated with boundary domains. Atomic force microscopy (AFM) confirmed that young leaf boundary domain cells have stiffer cell walls than marginal outgrowth. This differential cell wall stiffness was reduced in &lt;italic&gt;spy&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. Taken together our data reveal a concealed &lt;italic&gt;CUC2&lt;/italic&gt; cell wall associated gene network linking tissue patterning with cell growth and mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decreased cell-wall loosening gene expression contributes to the coordination of cell growth and mechanics with tissue patterning thus driving boundary development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.15.468678" rel="alternate" title="A cell wall-associated gene network shapes leaf boundary domains (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.467977</id><title>Towards a catalog of pome tree architecture genes: the draft 'd'Anjou' genome (Pyrus communis L.) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.066418+00:00</updated><author><name>Huiting Zhang</name></author><author><name>Eric K Wafula</name></author><author><name>Jon Eilers</name></author><author><name>Alex Harkess</name></author><author><name>Paula E Ralph</name></author><author><name>Prakash Raj Timilsena</name></author><author><name>Claude dePamphilis</name></author><author><name>Jessica Waite</name></author><author><name>Loren A Honaas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rapid development of sequencing technologies has led to a deeper understanding of horticultural plant genomes. However, experimental evidence connecting genes to important agronomic traits is still lacking in most non-model organisms. For instance, the genetic mechanisms underlying plant architecture are poorly understood in pome fruit trees, creating a major hurdle in developing new cultivars with desirable architecture, such as dwarfing rootstocks in European pear (Pyrus communis). Further, the quality and content of genomes vary widely. Therefore, it can be challenging to curate a list of genes with high-confidence gene models across reference genomes. This is often an important first step towards identifying key genetic factors for important traits. Here we present a draft genome of P. communis 'd'Anjou' and an improved assembly of the latest P. communis 'Bartlett' genome. To study gene families involved in tree architecture in European pear and other rosaceous species, we developed a workflow using a collection of bioinformatic tools towards curation of gene families of interest across genomes. This lays the groundwork for future functional studies in pear tree architecture. Importantly, our workflow can be easily adopted for other plant genomes and gene families of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.17.467977" rel="alternate" title="Towards a catalog of pome tree architecture genes: the draft 'd'Anjou' genome (Pyrus communis L.) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468555</id><title>Genome-wide H3K9 Acetylation Level Increases with Age-Dependent Senescence of Flag Leaf in Rice (Oryza sativa) (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.066568+00:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yanyun Li</name></author><author><name>Yuanyuan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zeyu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Deyu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Xiaonan Wang</name></author><author><name>Binfan Lai</name></author><author><name>Dandan Huang</name></author><author><name>Lianfeng Gu</name></author><author><name>Yakun Xie</name></author><author><name>Ying Miao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Flag leaf senescence is an important biological process that drives the remobilization of nutrients to the growing organs of rice. Leaf senescence is controlled by genetic information via gene expression and epigenetic modification, but the precise mechanism is as of yet unclear. Here, we analyzed genome-wide acetylated lysine residue 9 of histone H3 (H3K9ac) enrichment by chromatin immunoprecipitation-sequencing (ChIP-seq) and examined its association with transcriptomes by RNA-seq during flag leaf aging in rice (&lt;italic&gt;Oryza sativa&lt;/italic&gt;). We found that genome-wide H3K9 acetylation levels increased with age-dependent senescence in rice flag leaf, and there was a positive correlation between the density and breadth of H3K9ac and gene expression and transcript elongation. A set of 1,249 up-regulated, differentially expressed genes (DEGs) and 996 down-regulated DEGs showing a strong relationship between temporal changes in gene expression and gain/loss of H3K9ac was observed during rice flag leaf aging. We produced a landscape of H3K9 acetylation-modified gene expression targets that includes known senescence-associated genes, metabolism-related genes, as well as miRNA biosynthesis-related genes. Our findings reveal a complex regulatory network of metabolism- and senescence-related pathways mediated by H3K9ac and also elucidate patterns of H3K9ac-mediated regulation of gene expression during flag leaf aging in rice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide H3K9 acetylation levels increased with age-dependent senescence in rice flag leaf, and positively correlation the density and breadth of H3K9ac with transcript elongation and expression. Identified numerous H3K9 acetylation-modified gene expression targets reveal a complex regulatory network and metabolism-mediated senescence network that are associated with H3K9ac during leaf aging in rice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.14.468555" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide H3K9 Acetylation Level Increases with Age-Dependent Senescence of Flag Leaf in Rice (Oryza sativa) (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468878</id><title>The evidence for anthocyanins in the betalain-pigmented genus Hylocereus is weak (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-22T12:05:40.066730+00:00</updated><author><name>Boas Pucker</name></author><author><name>Samuel F. Brockington</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here we respond to Zhou et al., 2020 “Combined Transcriptome and Metabolome analysis of Pitaya fruit unveiled the mechanisms underlying Peel and pulp color formation” published in BMC Genomics. Given the evolutionary conserved anthocyanin biosynthesis pathway in betalain-pigmented species, we are open to the idea that species with both anthocyanins and betalains might exist. However, in absence of LC-MS/MS spectra, apparent lack of biological replicates, and no comparison to authentic standards, the findings of Zhou et al., 2020 are not a strong basis to propose the presence of anthocyanins in betalain-pigmented pitaya. In addition, our re-analysis of the datasets indicates the misidentification of important genes and the omission of key anthocyanin synthesis genes &lt;italic&gt;ANS&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;DFR&lt;/italic&gt;. Finally, our re-analysis of the RNA-Seq dataset reveals no correlation between anthocyanin biosynthesis gene expression and pigment status.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.16.468878" rel="alternate" title="The evidence for anthocyanins in the betalain-pigmented genus Hylocereus is weak (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>