<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.381941+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476148</id><title>Identification of candidate virulence loci in Striga hermonthica, a devastating parasite of African cereal crops (17 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.382022+00:00</updated><author><name>Suo Qiu</name></author><author><name>James M. Bradley</name></author><author><name>Peijun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Roy Chaudhuri</name></author><author><name>Mark Blaxter</name></author><author><name>Roger K. Butlin</name></author><author><name>Julie Diane Scholes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parasites have evolved suites of proteins, Virulence Factors (VFs), that are delivered into host plants to facilitate colonization. Whilst VFs mediating plant-microbe and plant-nematode interactions have been characterised extensively, less is known about VFs mediating parasitic plant interactions with their hosts. Striga hermonthica is an obligate, root-parasitic plant capable of parasitizing multiple cereal hosts in sub-Saharan Africa, causing devastating losses in yields. An understanding of the molecular nature and allelic variation of VFs in S. hermonthica is essential for breeding durable resistance and delaying the evolution of parasite virulence. To address this issue, we assembled a genome for Striga hermonthica and identified candidate VFs by combining in silico prediction of secreted proteins with pooled sequencing of parasites growing on a susceptible and a strongly resistant rice host. Consistent with predictions for parasites, like S. hermonthica, that can interact with multiple hosts, we identified multiple loci, potentially with a wide range of functions, implicated in overcoming host resistance. Extremely different allele frequencies were observed at 152 non-secreted and 38 putatively secreted VFs between S. hermonthica parasitising the resistant and susceptible rice varieties. Our candidate, secreted VFs encompassed functions such as host cell wall modification, protease inhibitors, oxidoreductase and kinase activities, as well as several with unknown functions. Consistent with maintenance of variation at virulence loci by balancing selection the candidate loci had significantly higher Tajima’s D on average than the genomic background. Our results show that diverse strategies are used by   S. hermonthica   to overcome different layers of host resistance. Understanding the maintenance of variation at virulence loci by balancing selection will be critical to managing the evolution of virulence as a part of a sustainable control strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476148" rel="alternate" title="Identification of candidate virulence loci in Striga hermonthica, a devastating parasite of African cereal crops (17 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475850</id><title>coveR: An R package for processing Digital Cover Photography images to retrieve forest canopy attributes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.382235+00:00</updated><author><name>Francesco Chianucci</name></author><author><name>Carlotta Ferrara</name></author><author><name>Nicola Puletti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Digital Cover Photography (DCP) is an increasingly popular tool for estimating canopy cover and leaf area index (LAI). However, existing solutions to process canopy images are predominantly tailored for fisheye photography, whereas open-access tools for DCP are lacking. We developed an R package (coveR) to support the whole processing of DCP images in an automated, fast and reproducible way. The package functions, which are designed for step-by-step single-image analysis, can be performed  sequentially in a pipeline and also allow simple implementation of batch-processing bunches of images. A case study is presented to demonstrate the reliability of canopy attributes derived from coveR in pure beech (Fagus sylvatica L.) stands with variable canopy density and structure. Estimates of gap fraction and effective LAI from DCP were validated against reference measurements obtained from terrestrial laser scanning. By providing a simple, transparent and flexible image processing procedure, coveR supported the use of DCP for routine measurements and monitoring of forest canopy attributes.  This, combined with the implementability of DCP in many devices, including smartphones, micro-cameras, and remote trail cameras, can greatly expand the accessibility of the method also to non-experts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.475850" rel="alternate" title="coveR: An R package for processing Digital Cover Photography images to retrieve forest canopy attributes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.474522</id><title>Ocimum sanctum, OscWRKY1, regulates phenylpropanoid pathway genes and promotes resistance to pathogen infection in Arabidopsis (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.382317+00:00</updated><author><name>Ashutosh Joshi</name></author><author><name>Gajendra Singh Jeena</name></author><author><name> Shikha</name></author><author><name>Ravi Kumar</name></author><author><name>Alok Pandey</name></author><author><name>Rakesh Kumar Shukla</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;WRKY transcription factor (TF) family regulates various developmental and physiological functions in plants. &lt;italic&gt;PAL&lt;/italic&gt; genes encode enzymes which are involved in plant defense responses, but the direct regulation of &lt;italic&gt;PAL&lt;/italic&gt; genes and phenylpropanoid pathway through WRKY TF’s is not well characterized. In the present study, we have characterized an &lt;italic&gt;OscWRKY1&lt;/italic&gt; gene from &lt;italic&gt;O. sanctum&lt;/italic&gt; which shows induced expression after methyl jasmonate (MeJA), salicylic acid (SA), and wounding. Recombinant OscWRKY1 protein binds to the W-box &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-element TTGAC[C/T] and activates the reporter gene in yeast. Overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;OscWRKY1&lt;/italic&gt; enhances Arabidopsis resistance towards &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato Pst&lt;/italic&gt; DC3000. Upstream activator sequences of &lt;italic&gt;PAL&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;C4H&lt;/italic&gt; have identified the conserved W-box &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-element (TTGACC) in both &lt;italic&gt;O. sanctum&lt;/italic&gt; and Arabidopsis. OscWRKY1 was found to interact with W-box &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-element present in the &lt;italic&gt;PAL&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;C4H&lt;/italic&gt; promoters. Silencing of &lt;italic&gt;OscWRKY1&lt;/italic&gt; using VIGS resulted in reduced expression of &lt;italic&gt;PAL, C4H, COMT, F5H&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;4CL&lt;/italic&gt; transcripts. &lt;italic&gt;OscWRKY1&lt;/italic&gt; silenced plants exhibit reduced PAL activity, whereas, the overexpression lines of &lt;italic&gt;OscWRKY1&lt;/italic&gt; in Arabidopsis exhibit increased PAL activity. These results revealed that &lt;italic&gt;OscWRKY1&lt;/italic&gt; positively regulates the phenylpropanoid pathway genes and enhances the resistance against bacterial pathogen in Arabidopsis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.474522" rel="alternate" title="Ocimum sanctum, OscWRKY1, regulates phenylpropanoid pathway genes and promotes resistance to pathogen infection in Arabidopsis (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476201</id><title>The role of LHCBM1 in non-photochemical quenching in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.382406+00:00</updated><author><name>Xin Liu</name></author><author><name>Wojciech J Nawrocki</name></author><author><name>Roberta Croce</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) is the process that protects photosynthetic organisms from photodamage by dissipating the energy absorbed in excess as heat. In the model green alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii, NPQ was abolished in the knock-out mutants of the pigment-protein complexes LHCSR3 and LHCBM1. However, while LHCSR3 was shown to be a pH sensor and switching to a quenched conformation at low pH, the role of LHCBM1 in NPQ has not been elucidated yet. In this work, we combine biochemical and physiological measurements to study short-term high light acclimation of npq5, the mutant lacking LHCBM1. We show that while in low light in the absence of this complex, the antenna size of PSII is smaller than in its presence, this effect is marginal in high light, implying that a reduction of the antenna is not responsible for the low NPQ. We also show that the mutant expresses LHCSR3 at the WT level in high light, indicating that the absence of this complex is also not the reason. Finally, NPQ remains low in the mutant even when the pH is artificially lowered to values that can switch LHCSR3 to the quenched conformation. It is concluded that both LHCSR3 and LHCBM1 need to be present for the induction of NPQ and that LHCBM1 is the interacting partner of LHCSR3. This interaction can either enhance the quenching capacity of LHCSR3 or connect this complex with the PSII supercomplex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476201" rel="alternate" title="The role of LHCBM1 in non-photochemical quenching in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475946</id><title>Abscisic Acid Increases Hydrogen Peroxide in Multiple Subcellular Compartments to Drive Stomatal Closure (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.382472+00:00</updated><author><name>Anthony E. Postiglione</name></author><author><name>Gloria K. Muday</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stomatal closure regulates transpiration and gas exchange in response to environmental cues. Drought upregulates ABA signaling, which elevates levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS). However, the subcellular location and identity of these ROS has received limited study. We found that in guard cells, ABA increased fluorescence of the general redox sensor, dichlorofluorescein (DCF), in distinct subcellular locations including chloroplasts, cytosol, nuclei, and cytosolic puncta. These changes were lost in an ABA-insensitive quintuple receptor mutant and accentuated in an ABA-hypersensitive mutant. ABA induced ROS accumulation in these subcellular compartments was lost in mutants with defects in genes encoding H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; elevating respiratory burst oxidase homolog (RBOH) enzymes and guard cells treated with the RBOH inhibitor VAS2870, while exogenous H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; treatment is sufficient to close guard cells. The H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-selective probe, peroxy orange 1, also showed ABA-dependent increases in chloroplasts and cytosolic puncta. Using the more sensitive genetically-encoded H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reporter roGFP-Orp1, we also detected significant H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; increases in the cytosol and nucleus. These cytosolic puncta accumulate ROS after ABA treatment and show colocalization with Mitotracker and with a mitochondrial targeted mt-roGFP2-Orp1, which also reports ABA-increased H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in mitochondria. These results indicate that elevated H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; after ABA treatment in these subcellular compartments is necessary and sufficient to drive stomatal closure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475946" rel="alternate" title="Abscisic Acid Increases Hydrogen Peroxide in Multiple Subcellular Compartments to Drive Stomatal Closure (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>