<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.536112+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461608</id><title>The ectomycorrhizal basidiomycete Laccaria bicolor releases a GH28 polygalacturonase that plays a key role in symbiosis establishment (22 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.536627+00:00</updated><author><name>Feng Zhang</name></author><author><name>Aurore Labourel</name></author><author><name>Mireille Haon</name></author><author><name>Minna Kemppainen</name></author><author><name>Emilie Da Silva Machado</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Brouilly</name></author><author><name>Claire Veneault-Fourrey</name></author><author><name>Annegret Kohler</name></author><author><name>Marie-Noëlle Rosso</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Pardo</name></author><author><name>Bernard Henrissat</name></author><author><name>Jean-Guy Berrin</name></author><author><name>Francis Martin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;In ectomycorrhiza, root penetration and colonization of the intercellular space by symbiotic hyphae is thought to rely on the mechanical force that results from hyphal tip growth, enhanced by the activity of secreted cell-wall-degrading enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we characterize the biochemical properties of the symbiosis-induced polygalacturonase LbGH28A from the ectomycorrhizal fungus &lt;italic&gt;Laccaria bicolor&lt;/italic&gt;. The transcriptional regulation of &lt;italic&gt;LbGH28A&lt;/italic&gt; was measured by qPCR. The biological relevance of &lt;italic&gt;LbGH28A&lt;/italic&gt; was confirmed by generating RNAi-silenced &lt;italic&gt;LbGH28A&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. We localized the LbGH28A protein by immunofluorescence confocal and immunogold cytochemical microscopy in poplar ectomycorrhizal roots.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;qPCR confirmed the induced expression of &lt;italic&gt;LbGH28A&lt;/italic&gt; during ectomycorrhiza formation. &lt;italic&gt;L. bicolor&lt;/italic&gt; RNAi mutants have a lower ability to establish ectomycorrhiza confirming the key role of this enzyme in symbiosis. The purified recombinant LbGH28A has its highest activity towards pectin and polygalacturonic acid. &lt;italic&gt;In situ&lt;/italic&gt; localization of LbGH28A indicates that this endopolygalacturonase is located in both fungal and plant cell walls at the symbiotic hyphal front.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The present findings suggest that the symbiosis-induced pectinase LbGH28A is involved in the Hartig net formation and is an important determinant for successful symbiotic colonization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461608" rel="alternate" title="The ectomycorrhizal basidiomycete Laccaria bicolor releases a GH28 polygalacturonase that plays a key role in symbiosis establishment (22 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.460861</id><title>small RNA can move long distances through plant vasculature to influence gene expression in shoot apical meristems (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.537111+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark A. A. Minow</name></author><author><name>Viktoriya Coneva</name></author><author><name>Victoria Lesy</name></author><author><name>Max Misyura</name></author><author><name>Joseph Colasanti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In plants, small RNA (sRNA) can regulate gene expression via post transcriptional gene silencing (PTGS) or through RNA-directed DNA methylation (RdDM) leading to transcriptional gene silencing (TGS). sRNA is mobile throughout the plant, with movement occurring short distances from cell-to-cell as well as long distances through the vasculature via phloem trafficking. The range of long-distance sRNA mediated signaling from the vasculature to the shoot apical meristem (SAM) is not clear. To investigate this, two independent transgenic approaches were used to examine trafficking of phloem-expressed sRNA to the SAM in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;. First, the phloem companion-cell specific promoter &lt;italic&gt;SUC2&lt;/italic&gt; was used to drive expression of an inverted repeat complementary to &lt;italic&gt;FLOWERING LOCUS D&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;FD)&lt;/italic&gt;, a flowering time regulator expressed exclusively in the SAM. In a separate experiment, the &lt;italic&gt;SUC2&lt;/italic&gt; promoter was used to express an artificial microRNA (aMiR) designed to target a synthetic &lt;italic&gt;CLAVATA3&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;CLV3&lt;/italic&gt;) target in the SAM stem cells. Both systems provide evidence of a phloem-to-SAM sRNA communication axis connecting distal regions of the plant to the stem cells of the SAM, which ultimately gives rise to all shoot tissues, including gametes. Thus, phloem-to-SAM sRNA movement defines an important link between sRNA expressed in distal regions of the plant and the growing shoot. Importantly, phloem-to-SAM sRNA trafficking may allow somatic sRNA to direct SAM RdDM, fixing transient sRNA expression events into stable epigenetic changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.460861" rel="alternate" title="small RNA can move long distances through plant vasculature to influence gene expression in shoot apical meristems (19 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461843</id><title>The helper NLR immune protein NRC3 mediates the hypersensitive cell death caused by the cell-surface receptor Cf-4 (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.537285+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiorgos Kourelis</name></author><author><name>Mauricio P. Contreras</name></author><author><name>Adeline Harant</name></author><author><name>Hiroaki Adachi</name></author><author><name>Lida Derevnina</name></author><author><name>Chih-Hang Wu</name></author><author><name>Sophien Kamoun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell surface pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) activate immune responses that can include the hypersensitive cell death. However, the pathways that link PRRs to the cell death response are poorly understood. Here, we show that the cell surface receptor-like protein Cf-4 requires the intracellular nucleotide-binding domain leucine-rich repeat containing receptor (NLR) NRC3 to trigger a confluent cell death response upon detection of the fungal effector Avr4 in leaves of &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt;. This NRC3 activity requires an intact N-terminal MADA motif, a conserved signature of coiled-coil (CC)-type plant NLRs that is required for resistosome-mediated immune responses. A chimeric protein with the N-terminal α1 helix of Arabidopsis ZAR1 swapped into NRC3 retains the capacity to mediate Cf-4 hypersensitive cell death. Pathogen effectors acting as suppressors of NRC3 can suppress Cf-4-triggered hypersensitive cell-death. Our findings link the NLR resistosome model to the hypersensitive cell death caused by a cell surface PRR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.461843" rel="alternate" title="The helper NLR immune protein NRC3 mediates the hypersensitive cell death caused by the cell-surface receptor Cf-4 (17 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461440</id><title>The necrotrophic effector ToxA from Parastagonospora nodorum interacts with wheat NHL proteins to facilitate Tsn1-mediated necrosis (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.537530+00:00</updated><author><name>Bayantes Dagvadorj</name></author><author><name>Megan A. Outram</name></author><author><name>Simon J. Williams</name></author><author><name>Peter S. Solomon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The plant pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Parastagonospora nodorum&lt;/italic&gt; secretes necrotrophic effectors to promote disease. These effectors induce cell death on wheat cultivars carrying dominant susceptibility genes in an inverse gene-for-gene manner. However, the molecular mechanisms underpinning these interactions and resulting cell death remain unclear. Here, we used a yeast-two-hybrid library approach to identify wheat proteins that interact with the necrotrophic effector ToxA. Using this strategy, we identified an interaction between ToxA and a wheat transmembrane NDR/HIN1-like protein (TaNHL10) and confirmed the interaction using &lt;italic&gt;in-planta&lt;/italic&gt; co-immunoprecipitation and confocal microscopy co-localization analysis. We showed that the C-terminus of TaNHL10 is extracellular whilst the N-terminus was localized in the cytoplasm. Further analyses using yeast-two-hybrid and confocal microscopy co-localization showed that ToxA interacts with the C-terminal LEA2 extracellular domain of TaNHL10. Random mutagenesis was then used to identify a ToxA mutant, ToxA&lt;sup&gt;N109D&lt;/sup&gt;, which was unable to interact with TaNHL10 in yeast-two-hybrid assays. Subsequent heterologous expression and purification of ToxA&lt;sup&gt;N109D&lt;/sup&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiania benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; revealed that the mutated protein was unable to induce necrosis on &lt;italic&gt;Tsn1&lt;/italic&gt;-dominant wheat cultivars confirming that the interaction of ToxA with TaNHL10 is required to induce cell death. Collectively, these data advance our understanding on how ToxA induces cell death during infection and further highlights the importance of host cell surface interactions in necrotrophic pathosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461440" rel="alternate" title="The necrotrophic effector ToxA from Parastagonospora nodorum interacts with wheat NHL proteins to facilitate Tsn1-mediated necrosis (14 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461718</id><title>Inactivation of the entire Arabidopsis group II GH3s confers tolerance to salinity and drought (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.537701+00:00</updated><author><name>Rubén Casanova-Sáez</name></author><author><name>Eduardo Mateo-Bonmatí</name></author><author><name>Jan Šimura</name></author><author><name>Aleš Pěnčík</name></author><author><name>Ondřej Novák</name></author><author><name>Paul Staswick</name></author><author><name>Karin Ljung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) controls a plethora of developmental processes. Thus, regulation of their levels is of great relevance for plant performance. Cellular IAA concentration depends on the combined result of its transport, biosynthesis and various redundant pathways to inactivate IAA, including oxidation and conjugation. Group II members of the GRETCHEN HAGEN 3 (GH3) gene family code for acyl acid amido synthetases catalysing the conjugation of IAA to amino acids. However, the high level of functional redundancy among them has hampered thorough analysis of their roles in plant development. In this work, we generated an Arabidopsis &lt;italic&gt;gh3.1,2,3,4,5,6,9,17&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;gh3oct&lt;/italic&gt;) mutant to knock-out the group II GH3 pathway. The &lt;italic&gt;gh3oct&lt;/italic&gt; plants had an improved root architecture, were more tolerant to osmotic stresses due to locally increased IAA levels and were more drought tolerant. IAA metabolite quantification in &lt;italic&gt;gh3oct&lt;/italic&gt; plants suggested the existence of additional GH3-like enzymes in IAA metabolism. Moreover, our data suggested that oxIAA production depends, at least partly, on the GH3 pathway. Targeted stress-hormone analysis further suggested an involvement of ABA in the differential response to salinity of &lt;italic&gt;gh3oct&lt;/italic&gt; plants. Taken together, our data provide new insights into the roles of group II GH3s in IAA metabolism and hormone-regulated plant development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461718" rel="alternate" title="Inactivation of the entire Arabidopsis group II GH3s confers tolerance to salinity and drought (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461886</id><title>Different plasticity of bud outgrowth at cauline and rosette nodes in Arabidopsis thaliana (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.537893+00:00</updated><author><name>Franziska Fichtner</name></author><author><name>Francois F. Barbier</name></author><author><name>Stephanie C. Kerr</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Dudley</name></author><author><name>Pilar Cubas</name></author><author><name>Colin Turnbull</name></author><author><name>Philip B. Brewer</name></author><author><name>Christine A. Beveridge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Shoot branching is a complex mechanism in which secondary shoots grow from buds that are initiated from meristems established in leaf axils. The model plant &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; has a rosette leaf growth pattern in the vegetative stage. After flowering initiation, the main stem starts to elongate with the top leaf primordia developing into cauline leaves. Meristems in arabidopsis are initiated in the axils of rosette or cauline leaves, giving rise to rosette or cauline buds, respectively. Plasticity in the process of shoot branching is regulated by resource and nutrient availability as well as by plant hormones. However, few studies have attempted to test whether cauline and rosette branching are subject to the same plasticity. Here, we addressed this question by phenotyping cauline and rosette branching in three arabidopsis ecotypes and several arabidopsis mutants with varied shoot architectures. Our results show that there is no negative correlation between cauline and rosette branch numbers in arabidopsis, demonstrating that there is no trade-off between cauline and rosette bud outgrowth. Through investigation of the altered branching pattern of flowering pathway mutants and arabidopsis ecotypes grown in various photoperiods and light regimes, we further elucidated that the number of cauline branches is closely related to flowering time. The number or rosette branches has an enormous plasticity compared with cauline branches and is influenced by genetic background, flowering time, light intensity and temperature. Our data reveal different plasticity in the regulation of branching at rosette and cauline nodes and promote a framework for future branching analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Different plasticity of branching at cauline and rosette nodes of arabidopsis is revealed through detailed correlative analyses of branching under varied genetic and environmental contexts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461886" rel="alternate" title="Different plasticity of bud outgrowth at cauline and rosette nodes in Arabidopsis thaliana (10 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461554</id><title>Glutathione contributes to plant defense against parasitic cyst nematodes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.538123+00:00</updated><author><name>M. Shamim Hasan</name></author><author><name>Divykriti Chopra</name></author><author><name>Anika Damm</name></author><author><name>Anna Koprivova</name></author><author><name>Stanislav Kopriva</name></author><author><name>Andreas J. Meyer</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Müller-Schüssele</name></author><author><name>Florian M.W. Grundler</name></author><author><name>Shahid Siddique</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cyst nematodes (CNs) are an important group of root-infecting sedentary endoparasites that severely damage many crop plants worldwide. An infective CN juvenile enters the host’s roots and migrates towards the vascular cylinder, where it induces the formation of syncytial feeding cells, which nourish the CN throughout its parasitic stages. Here, we examined the role of glutathione (L-γ-glutamyl-L-cysteinylglycine, GSH) in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; upon infection with the CN &lt;italic&gt;Heterodera schachtii&lt;/italic&gt;. Arabidopsis lines with mutations &lt;italic&gt;pad2, cad2&lt;/italic&gt;, or &lt;italic&gt;zir1&lt;/italic&gt; in the glutamate–cysteine ligase (&lt;italic&gt;GSH1&lt;/italic&gt;) gene, which encodes the first enzyme in the glutathione biosynthetic pathway, displayed enhanced CN susceptibility, but susceptibility was reduced for &lt;italic&gt;rax1&lt;/italic&gt;, another GSH1 allele. Biochemical analysis revealed differentially altered thiol levels in these mutants that was independent of nematode infection. All GSH-deficient mutants exhibited impaired activation of defense marker genes as well as genes for biosynthesis of the antimicrobial compound camalexin early in infection. Further analysis revealed a link between glutathione-mediated plant susceptibility to CN infection and the production of camalexin upon nematode infection. These results suggest that GSH levels affects plant susceptibility to CN by fine-tuning the balance between the cellular redox environment and the production of compounds related to defense against infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461554" rel="alternate" title="Glutathione contributes to plant defense against parasitic cyst nematodes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461987</id><title>miPEP858/miR858-MYB3-PSK4 module regulates growth and development in Arabidopsis (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.538338+00:00</updated><author><name>Poorwa Kamal Badola</name></author><author><name>Ashish Sharma</name></author><author><name>Himanshi Gautam</name></author><author><name>Prabodh Kumar Trivedi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Small molecules, peptides and miRNAs, are the crucial regulators of plant growth. Here, we show the importance of cross-talk between miPEP858a/miR858a and Phytosulfokine (PSK4) in regulating plant growth and development in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt;. Genome-wide expression analysis suggested modulated expression of PSK4 in miR858 mutant and overexpression, miR858OX, plants. The silencing of PSK4 in miR858OX plants compromised the growth, whereas over-expression of PSK4 in miR858 mutant rescued the developmental defects. The exogenous application of synthetic PSK4 further complemented the plant development in mutant plants. Exogenous treatment of synthetic miPEP858a in PSK4 mutant led to clathrin-mediated internalization of the peptide however did not enhance growth as in the case of wild-type plants. We also demonstrate that the MYB3 is an important molecular component participating in miPEP858a/miR858a-PSK4 module. Finally, our work highlights the signalling between miR858/miPEP858-MYB3-PSK4 in modulating the expression of key elements involved in auxin responses leading to the regulation of growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Signaling network between small molecules, miPEP858a/miR858a and phytosulfokine, regulates plant growth in Arabidopsis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461987" rel="alternate" title="miPEP858/miR858-MYB3-PSK4 module regulates growth and development in Arabidopsis (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461784</id><title>Attachment strength of seed mucilage prevents seed dislodgement in high surface flow: a mechanistic investigation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.538553+00:00</updated><author><name>Vincent S. Pan</name></author><author><name>Cecilia Girvin</name></author><author><name>Eric F. LoPresti</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seed mucilage is a common and highly diverse trait shared among thousands of angiosperms. While long recognized that mucilage allows seeds to anchor to substrates (antitelechory), we still lack a mechanistic understanding of this process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a mechanistic model of how mucilage affects substrate anchorage and fluid resistance, ultimately contributing to antitelechory. To test this model, we subjected mucilaginous seeds of 52 species, varying in eight measured seed traits, to a week of continuous water flow at a range of erosion potentials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporting our model, mucilage mass increased both dry and wet attachment strength, which explained time to erosion well. A standard deviation increase in log mucilage mass increased seed time to dislodgement by 280 times. Fluid resistance was largely dependent on speed of water flow and the seed’s modified drag coefficient, but not the quality of the seed or seed mucilage. Neither mucilage expansion speed nor mucilage decay rate explained dislodgement potential well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our results suggest that the high substrate anchorage strength is the primary role of mucilage in fostering seed establishment in highly erosive environments. In contrast, other seed and mucilage trait differences among species are of lesser importance to antitelechory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461784" rel="alternate" title="Attachment strength of seed mucilage prevents seed dislodgement in high surface flow: a mechanistic investigation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461262</id><title>A plastidial retrograde-signal potentiates biosynthesis of systemic stress response activators (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.538798+00:00</updated><author><name>Liping Zeng</name></author><author><name>Jin-Zheng Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiang He</name></author><author><name>Haiyan Ke</name></author><author><name>Mark Lemos</name></author><author><name>William M. Gray</name></author><author><name>Katayoon Dehesh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plants employ an array of intricate and hierarchical signaling cascades to perceive and transduce informational cues to synchronize and tailor adaptive responses. Systemic stress response (SSR) is a recognized complex signaling and response network quintessential to plant’s local and distal responses to environmental triggers, however, the identity of the initiating signals has remained fragmented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we show that both biotic (aphids and viral pathogens) and abiotic (high-light and wounding) stresses induce accumulation of the plastidial-retrograde-signaling metabolite, methylerythritol cyclodiphosphate (MEcPP), leading to reduction of the phytohormone, auxin, and the subsequent decreased expression of the phosphatase, &lt;italic&gt;PP2C.D1&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This enables phosphorylation of mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPK3/6), and the consequential induction of the downstream events ultimately resulting in biosynthesis of the two SSR priming metabolites, pipecolic- and N-hydroxy-pipecolic acid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work identifies plastids as the initiation site, and the plastidial retrograde-signal, MEcPP as the initiator of a multi-component signaling cascade potentiating the biosynthesis of SSR activators, in response to biotic and abiotic triggers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461262" rel="alternate" title="A plastidial retrograde-signal potentiates biosynthesis of systemic stress response activators (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462495</id><title>Dominant Awn Inhibitor, which encodes an ALOG protein in sorghum, suppresses awn formation in rice (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.539014+00:00</updated><author><name>Hideki Takanashi</name></author><author><name>Hiromi Kajiya-Kanegae</name></author><author><name>Asuka Nishimura</name></author><author><name>Junko Yamada</name></author><author><name>Motoyuki Ishimori</name></author><author><name>Masaaki Kobayashi</name></author><author><name>Kentaro Yano</name></author><author><name>Hiroyoshi Iwata</name></author><author><name>Nobuhiro Tsutsumi</name></author><author><name>Wataru Sakamoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The awn, a needle-like structure that extends from the tip of the lemma in grass species, is believed to play a role in environmental adaptation and fitness. Wild species of cereal crops tend to have longer awns, whereas modern cultivars display a variety of awn lengths and morphologies. Awns in some crops seem to have been eliminated during domestication, and genes controlling awn formation have been reported. Interestingly, a few single dominant factors that eliminate awns are already known; in sorghum (&lt;italic&gt;Sorghum bicolor&lt;/italic&gt;), for example, the dominant awn inhibitor has been known for a century, though its molecular identity remains uncharacterized. In this study, we conducted quantitative trait locus (QTL) analysis and a genome-wide association study of awn-related traits in sorghum. Among the three QTLs controlling awn presence and length, one of them, mapped on chromosome 3, had an extraordinary effect on eliminating awns. We provide a line of evidence demonstrating that this QTL corresponds to &lt;italic&gt;Dominant Awn Inhibitor&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt;), encoding an ALOG family protein that potentially acts as a transcription factor. Detailed analysis of the ALOG protein family in cereals revealed that &lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt; was considered to originate from a gene duplication of its twin paralogue on chromosome 10. Interestingly, heterologous expression of &lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt; with its own promoter in rice inhibited awn formation in the awned cultivar Kasalath. Our finding that &lt;italic&gt;DAI&lt;/italic&gt; was born by gene duplication provides an interesting example of gain-of-function, which occurs only in sorghum but shares its functionality with rice and sorghum.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462495" rel="alternate" title="Dominant Awn Inhibitor, which encodes an ALOG protein in sorghum, suppresses awn formation in rice (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461724</id><title>The Fe-S cluster assembly factors NFU4 and NFU5 are primarily required for protein lipoylation in mitochondria (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.539282+00:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Przybyla-Toscano</name></author><author><name>Andrew E. Maclean</name></author><author><name>Marina Franceschetti</name></author><author><name>Daniela Liebsch</name></author><author><name>Florence Vignols</name></author><author><name>Olivier Keech</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Rouhier</name></author><author><name>Janneke Balk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plants have evolutionarily conserved NFU-domain proteins that are targeted to plastids or mitochondria. The ‘plastid-type’ NFU1, NFU2 and NFU3 in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; play a role in iron-sulfur (Fe-S) cluster assembly in this organelle, whereas the type-II NFU4 and NFU5 proteins have not been subjected to mutant studies in any plant species to determine their biological role. Here we confirm that NFU4 and NFU5 are targeted to the mitochondria. The proteins are constitutively produced in all parts of the plant, suggesting a housekeeping function. Double &lt;italic&gt;nfu4 nfu5&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mutants were embryonic lethal, and depletion of the proteins led to growth arrest of young seedlings. Biochemical analyses revealed that NFU4 and NFU5 are required for lipoylation of the H proteins of the glycine decarboxylase complex and the E2 subunits of other mitochondrial dehydrogenases, with little impact on Fe-S cluster-containing respiratory complexes and aconitase. Consequently, the Gly-to-Ser ratio was increased in mutant seedlings and early growth was improved by elevated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. In addition, pyruvate, 2-oxoglutarate and branched-chain amino acids accumulated in the &lt;italic&gt;nfu4 nfu5&lt;/italic&gt; mutants, further supporting defects in the other three mitochondrial lipoate-dependent enzyme complexes. NFU4 and NFU5 interacted with mitochondrial lipoyl synthase (LIP1) in yeast 2-hybrid and bimolecular fluorescence complementation assays. These data indicate that NFU4 and NFU5 have a more specific function than previously thought, in providing Fe-S clusters to lipoyl synthase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A pair of evolutionarily conserved proteins involved in iron-sulfur cofactor assembly have a specific role in lipoate biosynthesis for mitochondrial dehydrogenases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461724" rel="alternate" title="The Fe-S cluster assembly factors NFU4 and NFU5 are primarily required for protein lipoylation in mitochondria (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461803</id><title>Large-scale comparative small RNA analyses reveal genomic structural variants in driving expression dynamics and differential selection pressures on distinct small RNA classes during tomato domestication (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.539476+00:00</updated><author><name>You Qing</name></author><author><name>Yi Zheng</name></author><author><name>Sizolwenkosi Mlotshwa</name></author><author><name>Heather N. Smith</name></author><author><name>Xin Wang</name></author><author><name>Xuyang Zhai</name></author><author><name>Esther van der Knaap</name></author><author><name>Ying Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhangjun Fei</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tomato has undergone extensive selections during domestication. Recent progress has shown that genomic structural variants (SVs) have contributed to gene expression dynamics during tomato domestication, resulting in changes of important traits. Here, through comprehensive analyses of small RNAs (sRNAs) from nine representative tomato accessions, we demonstrate that SVs substantially contribute to the dynamic expression of the three major classes of plant sRNAs: microRNAs (miRNAs), phased secondary short interfering RNAs (phasiRNAs), and 24-nt heterochromatic siRNAs (hc-siRNAs). Changes in the abundance of phasiRNAs and 24-nt hc-siRNAs likely contribute to the alteration of mRNA gene expression during tomato’s recent evolution, particularly for genes associated with biotic and abiotic stress tolerance. We also observe that miRNA expression dynamics are associated with imprecise processing, alternative miRNA-miRNA* selections, and SVs. SVs mainly affect the expression of less-conserved miRNAs that do not have established regulatory functions or low abundant members in highly expressed miRNA families, highlighting different selection pressures on miRNAs compared to phasiRNAs and 24-nt hc-siRNAs. Our findings provide insights into plant sRNA evolution as well as SV-based gene regulation during crop domestication. Furthermore, our dataset provides a rich resource for mining the sRNA regulatory network in tomato.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461803" rel="alternate" title="Large-scale comparative small RNA analyses reveal genomic structural variants in driving expression dynamics and differential selection pressures on distinct small RNA classes during tomato domestication (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461768</id><title>Drought Stress Induces Morpho-physiological and Proteome Changes of Pandanus amaryllifolius (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.539673+00:00</updated><author><name>Muhammad Asyraf Mohd Amnan</name></author><author><name>Wan Mohd Aizat</name></author><author><name>Fiqri Dizar Khaidizar</name></author><author><name>Boon Chin Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drought is one of the significant threats to the agricultural sector. However, there is limited knowledge on the plant response to drought stress and post-drought recovery. &lt;italic&gt;Pandanus amaryllifolius&lt;/italic&gt;, a moderate drought-tolerant plant, is well known for its ability to survive in low-level soil moisture conditions. Understanding the molecular regulation of drought stress signaling in this plant could help guide the rational design of crop plants to counter this environmental challenge. This study aimed to determine the morpho-physiological, biochemical and protein changes of &lt;italic&gt;P. amaryllifolius&lt;/italic&gt; in response to drought stress and during recovery. Drought significantly reduced leaf relative water content of &lt;italic&gt;P. amaryllifolius&lt;/italic&gt;. In contrast, relative electrolyte leakage, proline and malondialdehyde contents, and the activities of antioxidant enzymes in the drought-treated and recovered samples were relatively higher than the well-watered sample. The protein changes between drought-stressed, well-watered, and recovered plants were evaluated using tandem mass tags (TMT)-based quantitative proteomics. Of the 1,415 differentially abundant proteins, 74 were significantly altered. The majority of proteins differing between them were related to carbon metabolism, photosynthesis, stress response, and antioxidant activity. This is the first study that reports the protein changes in response to drought stress in &lt;italic&gt;Pandanus&lt;/italic&gt;. The data generated provide an insight into the drought-responsive mechanisms in &lt;italic&gt;P. amaryllifolius&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461768" rel="alternate" title="Drought Stress Induces Morpho-physiological and Proteome Changes of Pandanus amaryllifolius (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462608</id><title>Cost-effective, high-throughput phenotyping system for 3D reconstruction of fruit form (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.539916+00:00</updated><author><name>Mitchell J. Feldmann</name></author><author><name>Amy Tabb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reliable phenotyping methods that are simple to operate and in-expensive to deploy are critical for studying quantitative traits in plants. Traditional fruit shape phenotyping relies on human raters or 2D analyses to assess form, e.g., size and shape. Systems for 3D imaging using multi-view stereo have been implemented, but frequently rely on commercial software and/or specialized hardware, which can lead to limitations in accessibility and scalability. We present a complete system constructed of consumer-grade components for capturing, calibrating, and reconstructing the 3D form of small-to-moderate sized fruits and tubers. Data acquisition and image capture sessions are 9 seconds to capture 60 images. The initial prototype cost was $1600 USD. We measured accuracy by comparing reconstructed models of 3D printed ground truth objects to the original digital files of those same ground truth objects. The &lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; between length of the primary, secondary, and tertiary axes, volume, and surface area of the ground-truth object and the reconstructed models was &lt;italic&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/italic&gt; 0.97 and root-mean square error (RMSE) was &lt;italic&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/italic&gt;3mm for objects without locally concave regions. Measurements from 1mm and 2mm resolution reconstructions were consistent (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/italic&gt; 0.99). Qualitative assessments were performed on 48 fruit and tubers, including 18 strawberries, 12 potatoes, 5 grapes, 7 peppers, and 4 Bosch and 2 red Anjou pears. Our proposed phenotyping system is fast, relatively low cost, and has demonstrated accuracy for certain shape classes, and could be used for the 3D analysis of fruit form.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462608" rel="alternate" title="Cost-effective, high-throughput phenotyping system for 3D reconstruction of fruit form (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462050</id><title>PIN-FORMED1 polarity in the shoot is insensitive to the polarity of neighbouring cells (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.540096+00:00</updated><author><name>Abdul Kareem</name></author><author><name>Neha Bhatia</name></author><author><name>Carolyn Ohno</name></author><author><name>Marcus G. Heisler</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell polarity patterns associated with plant phyllotaxis are thought to be determined by mechanical signals or auxin flux&lt;sup&gt;1–6&lt;/sup&gt;. Here we use mosaic expression of the serine threonine kinase PINOID (PID) in the shoot to investigate the flux hypothesis. We find that PID promotes changes in PIN1 polarity irrespective of initial or neighboring cell polarities, arguing against a role for flux in regulating phyllotaxis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462050" rel="alternate" title="PIN-FORMED1 polarity in the shoot is insensitive to the polarity of neighbouring cells (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461997</id><title>LORE homomerization is required for 3-OH-C10:0 induced immune signaling (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.540449+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabine Eschrig</name></author><author><name>Milena Schäffer</name></author><author><name>Tina Illig</name></author><author><name>Sonja Eibel</name></author><author><name>Lin-Jie Shu</name></author><author><name>Atiara Fernandez</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Ranf</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Perception and processing of various internal and external signals is essential for all living organisms. Plants have an expanded and diversified repertoire of cell surface-localized receptor-like kinases (RLKs) that transduce signals across the plasma membrane. RLKs often assemble into higher-order receptor complexes with co-receptors, regulators and scaffolds to convert extracellular stimuli into cellular responses. To date, the only S-domain-RLK from &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; with a known ligand and function is &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;LORE, a pattern recognition receptor that senses bacterial 3-hydroxy fatty acids of medium chain length, such as 3-hydroxy decanoic acid (3-OH-C10:0), to activate pattern-triggered immunity. Here we show that &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;LORE forms receptor homomers, which is essential for 3-OH-C10:0-induced immune signaling. &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;LORE homomerization is mediated by the transmembrane and extracellular domain. We show natural variation in the perception of 3-OH-C10:0 within the Brassicaceae family. &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis lyrata&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis halleri&lt;/italic&gt; do not respond to 3-OH-C10:0, although they possess a putative LORE orthologue. We found that LORE orthologues of these 3-OH-C10:0 nonresponsive species have defective extracellular domains that can bind the 3-OH-C10:0 ligand but lack the ability to homomerize. Our findings shed light on the activation mechanisms of &lt;italic&gt;At&lt;/italic&gt;LORE and explain natural variation of 3-OH-C10:0 perception within the Brassicaceae family.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461997" rel="alternate" title="LORE homomerization is required for 3-OH-C10:0 induced immune signaling (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461799</id><title>Tasselyzer, a machine learning method to quantify anther extrusion in maize, based on PlantCV (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.540648+00:00</updated><author><name>Chong Teng</name></author><author><name>Noah Fahlgren</name></author><author><name>Blake C. Meyers</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Male fertility in maize is controlled by development and genetic programming and is directly impacted by environmental factors such as light, temperature, water, and nutrient availability; the control of this trait has substantial agronomic utility. Maize anthers emerge from male florets, which are clustered to form the tassel at the top of the plant separated from the female ear. Quantification of anther extrusion is one important aspect in the determination of male fertility. To address the lack of an automated method to measure anther extrusion on a large scale, we developed ‘Tasselyzer’, a quantitative, image-based color trait analysis pipeline for tassel image segmentation, based on the existing PlantCV platform, and we applied it to determine the proportion of anther extrusion. We evaluated Tasselyzer in maize during the seven-day period of pollen shedding as well as in the temperature-sensitive male sterile mutant &lt;italic&gt;dcl5&lt;/italic&gt;. With tassel images obtained with a smart phone camera, we show that the anther scores positively correlate with anther extrusion, and such methods can be used to measure environmental impacts on the &lt;italic&gt;dcl5&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. Altogether, this work establishes an automated and inexpensive method to quantify anther extrusion in maize, which would be useful for research and breeding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tasselyzer is a novel image-based segmentation tool, to address the lack of an automated method to measure anther extrusion, and the impact of genetic and environment variation on male fertility in maize.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461799" rel="alternate" title="Tasselyzer, a machine learning method to quantify anther extrusion in maize, based on PlantCV (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461038</id><title>Arabidopsis iron superoxide dismutase 1 protects against methyl viologen-induced oxidative stress in a copper-dependent manner (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.540805+00:00</updated><author><name>Pavol Melicher</name></author><author><name>Petr Dvořák</name></author><author><name>Yuliya Krasylenko</name></author><author><name>Alexey Shapiguzov</name></author><author><name>Jaakko Kangasjärvi</name></author><author><name>Jozef Šamaj</name></author><author><name>Tomáš Takáč</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Iron superoxide dismutase 1 (FSD1) was recently characterized as a plastidial, cytoplasmic, and nuclear superoxide dismutase with osmoprotective and antioxidative functions. However, its role in oxidative stress tolerance is not well understood. Here, we characterized the role of FSD1 in response to methyl viologen (MV)-induced oxidative stress in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;. The findings demonstrated that the antioxidative function of FSD1 depends on the availability of Cu&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; in growth media. Prolonged MV exposure led to a decreased accumulation rate of superoxide, higher levels of hydrogen peroxide production, and higher protein carbonylation in the &lt;italic&gt;fsd1&lt;/italic&gt; mutants and transgenic plants lacking a plastidial pool of FSD1, compared to the wild type. MV led to a rapid increase in FSD1 activity, followed by a decrease. Chloroplastic localization of FSD1 is necessary for these changes. Proteomic analysis showed that the sensitivity of the &lt;italic&gt;fsd1&lt;/italic&gt; mutants coincided with decreased abundance of ferredoxin and light PSII harvesting complex proteins, with altered levels of signaling proteins. Collectively, the study provides evidence for the conditional antioxidative function of FSD1 and its possible role in signaling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461038" rel="alternate" title="Arabidopsis iron superoxide dismutase 1 protects against methyl viologen-induced oxidative stress in a copper-dependent manner (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462158</id><title>A merger between compatible but divergent genomes supports allopolyploidization in the Brassicaceae family (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.540982+00:00</updated><author><name>Hosub Shin</name></author><author><name>Jeong Eun Park</name></author><author><name>Hye Rang Park</name></author><author><name>Woo Lee Choi</name></author><author><name>Seung Hwa Yu</name></author><author><name>Wonjun Koh</name></author><author><name>Seungill Kim</name></author><author><name>Hye Yeon Soh</name></author><author><name>Nomar Espinosa Waminal</name></author><author><name>Hadassah Roa Belandres</name></author><author><name>Joo Young Lim</name></author><author><name>Gibum Yi</name></author><author><name>Jong Hwa Ahn</name></author><author><name>June-Sik Kim</name></author><author><name>Yong-Min Kim</name></author><author><name>Namjin Koo</name></author><author><name>Kyunghee Kim</name></author><author><name>Sampath Perumal</name></author><author><name>Taegu Kang</name></author><author><name>Junghyo Kim</name></author><author><name>Hosung Jang</name></author><author><name>Dong Hyun Kang</name></author><author><name>Ye Seul Kim</name></author><author><name>Hyeon-Min Jeong</name></author><author><name>Junwoo Yang</name></author><author><name>Somin Song</name></author><author><name>Suhyoung Park</name></author><author><name>Jin A Kim</name></author><author><name>Yong Pyo Lim</name></author><author><name>Beom-Seok Park</name></author><author><name>Tzung-Fu Hsieh</name></author><author><name>Tae-Jin Yang</name></author><author><name>Doil Choi</name></author><author><name>Hyun Hee Kim</name></author><author><name>Soo-Seong Lee</name></author><author><name>Jin Hoe Huh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hybridization and polyploidization are pivotal to plant evolution. Genetic crosses between distantly related species rarely occur in nature mainly due to reproductive barriers but how such hurdles can be overcome is largely unknown. x&lt;italic&gt;Brassicoraphanus&lt;/italic&gt; is a fertile intergeneric allopolyploid synthesized between &lt;italic&gt;Brassica rapa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Raphanus sativus&lt;/italic&gt; in the Brassicaceae family. Genomes of &lt;italic&gt;B. rapa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;R. sativus&lt;/italic&gt; are diverged enough to suppress synapsis formation between non-homologous progenitor chromosomes during meiosis, and we found that both genomes reside in the single nucleus of x&lt;italic&gt;Brassicoraphanus&lt;/italic&gt; without genome loss or rearrangement. Expressions of syntenic orthologs identified in &lt;italic&gt;B. rapa&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;R. sativus&lt;/italic&gt; were adjusted to a hybrid nuclear environment of x&lt;italic&gt;Brassicoraphanus&lt;/italic&gt;, which necessitates reconfiguration of transcription network by rewiring &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-&lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt; interactions. &lt;italic&gt;B. rapa&lt;/italic&gt; coding sequences have a higher level of gene-body methylation than &lt;italic&gt;R. sativus&lt;/italic&gt;, and such methylation asymmetry is maintained in x&lt;italic&gt;Brassicoraphanus&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;B. rapa&lt;/italic&gt;-originated transposable elements were transcriptionally silenced in x&lt;italic&gt;Brassicoraphanus&lt;/italic&gt;, rendered by gain of CHG methylation &lt;italic&gt;in trans&lt;/italic&gt; via small RNAs derived from the same sequences of &lt;italic&gt;R. sativus&lt;/italic&gt; subgenome. Our work proposes that not only transcription compatibility but also a certain extent of genome divergence supports hybrid genome stabilization, which may explain great diversification and expansion of angiosperms during evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462158" rel="alternate" title="A merger between compatible but divergent genomes supports allopolyploidization in the Brassicaceae family (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462019</id><title>The APC/CCCS52A2 E3-Ligase Complex targeted PKN1 Protein is a Plant Lineage-Specific Driver of Cell Division (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.541586+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Willems</name></author><author><name>Yuanke Liang</name></author><author><name>Jefri Heyman</name></author><author><name>Thomas Eekhout</name></author><author><name>Hilde Van den Daele</name></author><author><name>Ilse Vercauteren</name></author><author><name>Lieven De Veylder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The anaphase-promoting complex/cyclosome (APC/C) marks key cell cycle proteins for proteasomal breakdown, thereby ensuring unidirectional progression through the cell cycle. Its target recognition is temporally regulated by activating subunits, one of which is called CELL CYCLE SWITCH 52 A2 (CCS52A2). We sought to expand the knowledge of identified APC/C targets by using the severe growth phenotypes of &lt;italic&gt;CCS52A2&lt;/italic&gt;-deficient &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; plants as a readout in a suppressor mutagenesis screen, resulting in the identification of the previously undescribed gene called &lt;italic&gt;PIKMIN1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;PKN1&lt;/italic&gt;). PKN1 deficiency rescues the disorganized root stem cell phenotype of the &lt;italic&gt;ccs52a2-1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, whereas an excess of PKN1 inhibits growth of &lt;italic&gt;ccs52a2-1&lt;/italic&gt; plants, indicating the importance of PKN1 abundance for proper development. Accordingly, the lack of PKN1 in a wild-type background negatively impacts cell division, while its ectopic expression promotes proliferation. PKN1 shows a cell cycle phase-dependent accumulation pattern, localizing to microtubular structures, including the preprophase band, the mitotic spindle, and phragmoplast. &lt;italic&gt;PKN1&lt;/italic&gt; is conserved throughout the plant kingdom, with its function in cell division being evolutionary conserved in the liverwort &lt;italic&gt;Marchantia polymorpha&lt;/italic&gt;. Our data thus demonstrate that PKN1 represents a novel, plant-specific gene with a rate-limiting role in cell division, which is proteolytically controlled by the CCS52A2-activated APC/C.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-Sentence Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PKN1 is a conserved plant-specific protein that is rate-limiting for cell division, likely through its interaction with microtubuli, and is proteolytically controlled by APC/C&lt;sup&gt;CCS52A2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462019" rel="alternate" title="The APC/CCCS52A2 E3-Ligase Complex targeted PKN1 Protein is a Plant Lineage-Specific Driver of Cell Division (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461852</id><title>Plant-based biosensors for detecting CRISPR-mediated genome engineering (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.541777+00:00</updated><author><name>Guoliang Yuan</name></author><author><name>Md. Mahmudul Hassan</name></author><author><name>Tao Yao</name></author><author><name>Haiwei Lu</name></author><author><name>Michael Melesse Vergara</name></author><author><name>Jesse L. Labbé</name></author><author><name>Wellington Muchero</name></author><author><name>Changtian Pan</name></author><author><name>Jin-Gui Chen</name></author><author><name>Gerald A. Tuskan</name></author><author><name>Yiping Qi</name></author><author><name>Paul E. Abraham</name></author><author><name>Xiaohan Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CRISPR/Cas has recently emerged as the most reliable system for genome engineering in various species. However, concerns about risks associated with CRISPR/Cas9 technology are increasing on potential unintended DNA changes that might accidentally arise from CRISPR gene editing. Developing a system that can detect and report the presence of active CRIPSR/Cas tools in biological systems is therefore very necessary. Here, we developed the real-time detection systems that can spontaneously indicate CRISPR-Cas tools for genome editing and gene regulation including CRISPR/Cas9 nuclease, base editing, prime editing and CRISPRa in plants. Using the fluorescence-based molecular biosensors, we demonstrated that the activities of CRISPR/Cas9 nuclease, base editing, prime editing and CRIPSRa can be effectively detected in transient expression via protoplast transformation and leaf infiltration (in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt;, poplar, and tobacco) and stable transformation in &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461852" rel="alternate" title="Plant-based biosensors for detecting CRISPR-mediated genome engineering (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462026</id><title>Multiple metals influence distinct properties of the Arabidopsis circadian clock (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.542072+00:00</updated><author><name>Jessica K. Hargreaves</name></author><author><name>Rachael J. Oakenfull</name></author><author><name>Amanda M. Davis</name></author><author><name>Freya Pullen</name></author><author><name>Marina I. Knight</name></author><author><name>Jon W. Pitchford</name></author><author><name>Seth J. Davis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Circadian rhythms coordinate endogenous events with external signals, and are essential to biological function. When environmental contaminants affect these rhythms, the organism may experience fitness consequences such as reduced growth or increased susceptibility to pathogens. In their natural environment plants may be exposed to a wide range of industrial and agricultural pollutants. Here, we investigate how the addition of various metal salts to the environment can impact plant-circadian rhythms, via the promoter:luciferase system. The consequences of these environmental changes were found to be varied and complex. Therefore, in addition to Fourier-based analyses, we apply novel wavelet-based spectral hypothesis testing and clustering methodologies to organize and understand the data. We are able to classify broad sets of responses to environmental contaminants, including pollutants which increase, or decrease, the period, or which induce a lack of precision or disrupt any meaningful periodicity. The methods are general, and may be applied to discover common responses and hidden structures within a wide range of biological time series data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462026" rel="alternate" title="Multiple metals influence distinct properties of the Arabidopsis circadian clock (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461951</id><title>Dynamics of deep water and N uptake under varied N and water supply (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.542790+00:00</updated><author><name>Guanying Chen</name></author><author><name>Camilla Ruø Rasmussen</name></author><author><name>Dorte Bodin Dresbøll</name></author><author><name>Abraham George Smith</name></author><author><name>Kristian Thorup-Kristensen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Aims&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enhanced nitrogen (N) and water uptake from deep soil layers may increase resource use efficiency whilst maintaining yield under stressed conditions. Winter oilseed rape (&lt;italic&gt;Brassica napus&lt;/italic&gt; L.) can develop deep roots and access deep-stored resources such as N and water, while this potential has large uncertainties in variable environments. In this study, we aimed to evaluate the effects of reduced N and water supply on deep N and water uptake.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oilseed rape plants grown in outdoor rhizotrons were supplied with 240 and 80 kg N ha&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; respectively in 2019 whereas a well-watered and a water-deficit treatment were established in 2020. To track deep water and N uptake, a mixture of &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O and Ca(&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was injected into the soil column at 0.5 and 1.7 m depths. δ&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;H in transpiration water and δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N in leaves were measured after injection. δ&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N in biomass samples were also measured.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Differences in N or water supply had little effect on root growth. The low N treatment reduced water uptake throughout the soil profile, but caused a non-significant increment in &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N uptake efficiency at both 0.5 and 1.7 m. Water deficit in the upper soil layers led to compensatory deep water, while N uptake was not altered by soil water status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our findings demonstrate that for winter oilseed rape, high N application and water deficiency in shallow layers increases deep water uptake, and that the efficiency of deep N uptake is mainly sensitive to N supply rather than water supply.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461951" rel="alternate" title="Dynamics of deep water and N uptake under varied N and water supply (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462089</id><title>Inhibition of chloroplast translation as a new target for herbicides (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.543558+00:00</updated><author><name>Kirill V. Sukhoverkov</name></author><author><name>Karen J. Breese</name></author><author><name>Aleksandra W. Debowski</name></author><author><name>Monika W. Murcha</name></author><author><name>Keith A. Stubbs</name></author><author><name>Joshua S. Mylne</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The rise in herbicide resistance over recent decades threatens global agriculture and food security and so discovery of new modes of action is increasingly important. Here we reveal linezolid, an oxazolidinone antibiotic that inhibits microbial translation, is also herbicidal. To validate the herbicidal mode of action of linezolid we confirmed its micromolar inhibition is specific to chloroplast translation and did not affect photosynthesis directly. To assess the herbicide potential of linezolid, testing against a range of weed and crop species found it effective pre- and post-emergence. Using structure-activity analysis we identified the critical elements for herbicidal activity, but importantly also show, using antimicrobial susceptibility assays, that separation of antibacterial and herbicidal activities was possible. Overall these results validate chloroplast translation as a viable herbicidal target.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.28.462089" rel="alternate" title="Inhibition of chloroplast translation as a new target for herbicides (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461614</id><title>Sieve tube structural variation in Austrobaileya scandens and its significance for lianescence (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.543896+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan M. Losada</name></author><author><name>Zhe He</name></author><author><name>N. Michele Holbrook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Lianas are characterized by large leaf areas and slender stems, a combination of features that require an efficient vascular system. The only extant member of the Austrobaileyaceae, is an endemic twining liana of the tropical Australian forests with well-known xylem hydraulic traits. However, the vascular phloem continuum through aerial organs remains understudied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed the structure of phloem conduits across leaf veins and stems of &lt;italic&gt;A. scandens&lt;/italic&gt;, combining topological data obtained through light and electron microscopy, with current models of phloem transport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leaves displayed a low xylem to phloem ratio compared with leaves of other angiosperms, with vascular elements invariant in diameter along the midrib, but tapered across vein hierarchies. Sieve plate pore radii were extremely small: 0.08 µm in minor veins, increasing to 0.12µm in the petiole and only to 0.20µm at the base of the stem, tens of meters away. Searcher branches contained tube shaped phloem conduits with a pectin-rich wall, whereas twining stems displayed sieve elements with tangential connections that displayed a greater fraction of the tubes populated with an astonishing number of sieve plates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hydraulic segmentation of the leaves in Austrobaileyaceae correlate with vesseless leaves that benefit photoassimilate export through volumetric scaling of the sieve tube elements. Yet, compared with canopy dominant trees, the geometrical properties of the sieve tube in twining stems, restrict considerably energy distribution in the sub-canopy layers, potentially favoring the allocation of assimilates toward the elongating branches. Thus, the conductive xylem of twining stems contrasts with a poorly conductive phloem that meets the mechanical constraints of lianescence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461614" rel="alternate" title="Sieve tube structural variation in Austrobaileya scandens and its significance for lianescence (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>