<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.513239+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471931</id><title>A fungal plant pathogen overcomes conserved broad-spectrum disease resistance by rapid gene loss (38 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.513744+00:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Kusch</name></author><author><name>Lamprinos Frantzeskakis</name></author><author><name>Birthe D. Lassen</name></author><author><name>Florian Kümmel</name></author><author><name>Lina Pesch</name></author><author><name>Mirna Barsoum</name></author><author><name>Hongpo Wu</name></author><author><name>Kim D. Walden</name></author><author><name>Ralph Panstruga</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hosts and pathogens typically engage in an evolutionary arms race. This also applies to phytopathogenic powdery mildew fungi, which can rapidly overcome plant resistance and perform host jumps. Using experimental evolution, we show that the powdery mildew pathogen &lt;italic&gt;Blumeria graminis&lt;/italic&gt; f.sp. &lt;italic&gt;hordei&lt;/italic&gt; is capable of breaking the agriculturally important broad-spectrum resistance conditioned by barley loss-of-function &lt;italic&gt;mlo&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. Partial &lt;italic&gt;mlo&lt;/italic&gt; virulence is associated with a distinctive pattern of adaptive mutations, including small-sized (8-40 kb) deletions, one of which likely affects spore morphology. The detected mutational spectrum comprises the same loci in at least two independent &lt;italic&gt;mlo&lt;/italic&gt;-virulent isolates, indicating convergent multigenic evolution. This work highlights the dynamic genome evolution of an obligate biotrophic plant pathogen with a transposonenriched genome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471931" rel="alternate" title="A fungal plant pathogen overcomes conserved broad-spectrum disease resistance by rapid gene loss (38 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471439</id><title>Control of Leaf Vein Patterning by Regulated Plasmodesma Aperture (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.513978+00:00</updated><author><name>Nguyen Manh Linh</name></author><author><name>Enrico Scarpella</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To form tissue networks, animal cells migrate and interact through proteins protruding from their plasma membranes. Plant cells can do neither, yet plants form vein networks. How plants do so is unclear, but veins are thought to form by the coordinated action of the polar transport and signal transduction of the plant hormone auxin. However, plants inhibited in both pathways still form veins. Patterning of vascular cells into veins is instead prevented in mutants lacking the function of the &lt;italic&gt;GNOM&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;GN&lt;/italic&gt;) regulator of auxin transport and signaling, suggesting the existence of at least one more &lt;italic&gt;GN&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent vein-patterning pathway. Here we show that pathway depends on the movement of an auxin signal through plasmodesmata (PDs) intercellular channels. PD permeability is high where veins are forming, lowers between veins and nonvascular tissues, but remains high between vein cells. Impaired ability to regulate PD aperture leads to defects in auxin transport and signaling, ultimately leading to vein patterning defects that are enhanced by inhibition of auxin transport or signaling. &lt;italic&gt;GN&lt;/italic&gt; controls PD aperture regulation, and simultaneous inhibition of auxin signaling, auxin transport, and regulated PD aperture phenocopies null &lt;italic&gt;gn&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. Therefore, veins are patterned by the coordinated action of three &lt;italic&gt;GN&lt;/italic&gt;-dependent pathways: auxin signaling, polar auxin transport, and movement of an auxin signal through PDs. We have identified all the key vein-patterning pathways in plants and an unprecedented mechanism of tissue network formation in multicellular organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471439" rel="alternate" title="Control of Leaf Vein Patterning by Regulated Plasmodesma Aperture (18 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471425</id><title>XopQ induced stromule formation in Nicotiana benthamiana is causally linked to ETI signaling and depends on ADR1 and NRG1 (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.514137+00:00</updated><author><name>Jennifer Prautsch</name></author><author><name>Jessica Lee Erickson</name></author><author><name>Sedef Özyürek</name></author><author><name>Rahel Gormanns</name></author><author><name>Lars Franke</name></author><author><name>Jane E. Parker</name></author><author><name>Johannes Stuttmann</name></author><author><name>Martin Hartmut Schattat</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt;, expression of the &lt;italic&gt;Xanthomonas&lt;/italic&gt; effector XopQ triggers ROQ1-dependent ETI responses and in parallel accumulation of plastids around the nucleus and the formation of stromules. Both processes were proposed to contribute to ETI-related hypersensitive cell death and thereby to plant immunity. Whether these reactions are directly connected to ETI signaling events has not been tested. Here we utilized transient expression experiments to determine whether XopQ-mediated plastid reactions are a result of XopQ perception by ROQ1 or a consequence of XopQ virulence activity. We find that &lt;italic&gt;N. benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; mutants lacking ROQ1, both RNLs (NRG1 and ADR1) or EDS1, fail to elicit XopQ-dependent host cell death and stromule formation. Mutants lacking only NRG1 lost XopQ-dependent cell death but retained some stromule induction that was abolished in the RNL double mutant. This analysis aligns XopQ-induced stromules with the ETI signaling cascade but not to host programmed cell death. Furthermore, data reveal that XopQ-triggered plastid clustering is not strictly linked to stromule formation during ETI. Our data suggest that stromule formation, in contrast to chloroplast peri-nuclear dynamics, is an integral part of the &lt;italic&gt;N. benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; ETI response and that both RNL sub-types play a role in this ETI response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic analysis aligns effector triggered immunity (ETI) induced stromule formation with the ETI signaling cascade but not programmed cell death and questions stromule guided peri-nuclear plastid clustering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471425" rel="alternate" title="XopQ induced stromule formation in Nicotiana benthamiana is causally linked to ETI signaling and depends on ADR1 and NRG1 (11 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471623</id><title>The UV RESISTANCE LOCUS 8-Mediated UV-B Response Is Required Alongside CRYPTOCHROME1 For Plant Survival Under Sunlight In The Field (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.514372+00:00</updated><author><name>Reinhold Stockenhuber</name></author><author><name>Reiko Akiyama</name></author><author><name>Nicolas Tissot</name></author><author><name>Misako Yamazaki</name></author><author><name>Michele Wyler</name></author><author><name>Adriana B. Arongaus</name></author><author><name>Roman Podolec</name></author><author><name>Yasuhiro Sato</name></author><author><name>Stefan Milosavljevic</name></author><author><name>Alex Widmer</name></author><author><name>Roman Ulm</name></author><author><name>Kentaro K. Shimizu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As sessile organisms, plants are subjected to fluctuating sunlight including potentially detrimental ultraviolet-B radiation (UV-B). In &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;, experiments under controlled conditions have shown that &lt;italic&gt;UV RESISTANCE LOCUS 8&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;UVR8&lt;/italic&gt;) controls photomorphogenic responses for acclimation and tolerance to UV-B; however, its long-term impacts on plant performance remain poorly understood in naturally fluctuating environments. Here we quantified the survival and reproduction of different &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt; mutant genotypes in diverse field and laboratory conditions. We found that &lt;italic&gt;uvr8&lt;/italic&gt; mutants produced more fruits than wild type in growth chambers with artificial low UV-B conditions but not in natural field conditions. Importantly, independent double mutants of &lt;italic&gt;UVR8&lt;/italic&gt; and the blue-light photoreceptor gene &lt;italic&gt;CRYPTOCHROME 1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;CRY1&lt;/italic&gt;) in two genetic backgrounds showed a drastic reduction in fitness in the field. UV-B attenuation experiments in field conditions and supplemental UV-B in growth chambers demonstrated that UV-B caused the conditional &lt;italic&gt;cry1 uvr8&lt;/italic&gt; lethality phenotype. RNA sequencing in different conditions revealed a large number of genes with statistical interaction of &lt;italic&gt;UVR8&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;CRY1&lt;/italic&gt; mutations in the presence of UV-B in the field. Among them, Gene Ontology analysis identified enrichment of categories related to UV-B response, oxidative stress, photoprotection and DNA damage repair. Our study demonstrates the functional importance of the &lt;italic&gt;UVR8&lt;/italic&gt;-mediated response across life stages &lt;italic&gt;in natura&lt;/italic&gt;, which is partially redundant with &lt;italic&gt;CRY1&lt;/italic&gt;, and provides an integral picture of gene expression associated with plant environmental responses under diverse environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471623" rel="alternate" title="The UV RESISTANCE LOCUS 8-Mediated UV-B Response Is Required Alongside CRYPTOCHROME1 For Plant Survival Under Sunlight In The Field (11 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471294</id><title>Quantitative genetic analysis of interactions in the pepper-Phytophthora capsici pathosystem (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.514556+00:00</updated><author><name>Gregory Vogel</name></author><author><name>Garrett Giles</name></author><author><name>Kelly R. Robbins</name></author><author><name>Michael A. Gore</name></author><author><name>Christine D. Smart</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of pepper cultivars with durable resistance to the oomycete &lt;italic&gt;Phytophthora capsici&lt;/italic&gt; has been challenging due to differential interactions between the species that allow certain pathogen isolates to cause disease on otherwise resistant host genotypes. Currently, little is known about the pathogen genes that are involved in these interactions. To investigate the genetic basis of &lt;italic&gt;P. capsici&lt;/italic&gt; virulence on individual pepper genotypes, we inoculated sixteen pepper accessions – representing commercial varieties, sources of resistance, and host differentials – with 117 isolates of &lt;italic&gt;P. capsici&lt;/italic&gt;, for a total of 1,864 host-pathogen combinations. Analysis of disease outcomes revealed a significant effect of inter-species genotype-by-genotype interactions, although these interactions were quantitative rather than qualitative in scale. Isolates were classified into five pathogen subpopulations, as determined by their genotypes at over 60,000 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). While absolute virulence levels on certain pepper accessions significantly differed between subpopulations, a multivariate phenotype reflecting relative virulence levels on certain pepper genotypes compared to others showed the strongest association with pathogen subpopulation. A genome-wide association study (GWAS) identified four pathogen loci significantly associated with virulence, two of which colocalized with putative RXLR effector genes and another with a polygalacturonase gene cluster. All four loci appeared to represent broad-spectrum virulence genes, as significant SNPs demonstrated consistent effects regardless of the host genotype tested. Host genotype-specific virulence variants in &lt;italic&gt;P. capsici&lt;/italic&gt; may be difficult to map via GWAS, perhaps controlled by many genes of small effect or by multiple alleles that have arisen independently at the same loci.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471294" rel="alternate" title="Quantitative genetic analysis of interactions in the pepper-Phytophthora capsici pathosystem (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471910</id><title>NITROGEN LIMITATION ADAPTATION functions as a negative regulator of Arabidopsis immunity (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.514689+00:00</updated><author><name>Beatriz Val Torregrosa</name></author><author><name>Mireia Bundo</name></author><author><name>Tzyy Jen Chiou</name></author><author><name>Victor Flors</name></author><author><name>Blanca San Segundo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Phosphorus is an important macronutrient required for plant growth and development. It is absorbed through the roots in the form of inorganic phosphate (Pi). To cope with Pi limitation, plants have evolved an array of adaptive mechanisms to facilitate Pi acquisition and protect them from stress caused by Pi starvation. The NITROGEN LIMITATION ADAPTION (NLA) gene plays a key role in the regulation of phosphate starvation responses (PSR), its expression being regulated by the microRNA miR827. Stress caused by Pi limiting conditions might also affect the plant response to pathogen infection. However, cross-talk between phosphate signaling pathways and immune responses remains unclear. 
Results: In this study, we investigated whether NLA plays a role in Arabidopsis immunity. We show that loss-of-function of NLA and MIR827 overexpression causes an increase in phosphate (Pi) content which results in resistance to infection by the fungal pathogen Plectosphaerella cucumerina. The nla mutant plants accumulated callose in their leaves, a response that is also observed in wild-type plants that have been treated with high Pi. We also show that pathogen infection and treatment with fungal elicitors is accompanied by transcriptional activation of MIR827 and down-regulation of NLA. Upon pathogen challenge, nla plants exhibited higher levels of the phytoalexin camalexin compared to wild type plants. Camalexin level also increases in wild type plants treated with high Pi. Furthermore, the nla mutant plants accumulated salicylic acid (SA) and jasmonic acid (JA) in the absence of pathogen infection whose levels further increased upon pathogen. 
Conclusions: This study shows that NLA acts as a negative regulator of Arabidopsis immunity. Overaccumulation of Pi in nla plants positively affects resistance to infection by fungal pathogens. This piece of information reinforces the idea of signaling convergence between Pi and immune responses for the regulation of disease resistance in Arabidopsis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471910" rel="alternate" title="NITROGEN LIMITATION ADAPTATION functions as a negative regulator of Arabidopsis immunity (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471912</id><title>Iron treatment induces defense responses and disease resistance against Magnaporthe oryzae in rice (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.514821+00:00</updated><author><name>Ferran Sanchez-Sanuy</name></author><author><name>Roberto Mateluna Cuadra</name></author><author><name>Kazunori Okada</name></author><author><name>Gian Attilio Sacchi</name></author><author><name>Sonia Campo</name></author><author><name>Blanca San Segundo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Iron is an essential micronutrient required for plant growth and development. The impact of iron in plant-pathogen interactions is also well recognized. However, the molecular basis underlying the effect of plant iron status and immune function in plants is poorly understood. Here, we investigated the impact of treatment with high iron in rice immunity at the cellular and molecular level.
Results: We show that treatment with high iron confers resistance to infection by the blast fungus &lt;italic&gt;M. oryzae&lt;/italic&gt; in rice. Histochemical staining of &lt;italic&gt;M. oryzae&lt;/italic&gt;-infected leaves revealed that iron and Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) accumulate at high levels in cells in the vicinity of the infection site. During pathogen infection, a stronger induction of defense-related genes occurs in leaves of iron-treated plants. Notably, a superinduction of phytoalexin biosynthetic genes, both diterpene phytoalexins and sakuranetin, is observed in iron-treated plants during pathogen infection. As a consequence, phytoalexin accumulation was higher in iron-treated plants compared with control plants. Transcriptional alterations of iron homeostasis-related genes and a reduction in apoplastic iron content were observed in leaves of Fe-treated rice plants. 
Conclusions: These results illustrate that the iron status plays a key role in the response of rice plants to pathogen infection, while reinforcing the notion that iron signaling and defense signaling must operate in a coordinated manner in controlling disease resistance in plants. This information provides a basis to better understand the molecular mechanisms involved in rice immunity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471912" rel="alternate" title="Iron treatment induces defense responses and disease resistance against Magnaporthe oryzae in rice (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>