<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.158294+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.05.459049</id><title>Vulnerability to cavitation is linked to home climate precipitation across eight eucalypt species (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.158668+00:00</updated><author><name>David Coleman</name></author><author><name>Andrew Merchant</name></author><author><name>William T. Salter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Vulnerability to cavitation in leaves is the result of highly adaptive anatomical and physiological traits that can be linked to water availability in a species’ climate of origin. Despite similar gross leaf morphology, eucalypt species are often confined to specific climate envelopes across the variable rainfall environments of Australia. In this study, we investigate how the progression of cavitation differs among eucalypts and whether this is related to other hydraulic and physical leaf traits. We used the Optical Visualisation technique to capture cavitation progression across the leaves of eight eucalypt species (&lt;italic&gt;Angophora crassifolia, Corymbia tessellaris, Eucalyptus atrata, Eucalyptus grandis, Eucalyptus laevopinea, Eucalyptus longifolia, Eucalyptus macrandra, Eucalyptus tereticornis&lt;/italic&gt;) from a wide range of climates and grown in a common garden setting. Vulnerability to cavitation, represented by the leaf water potential required for 50% cavitation of leaf vessels, varied significantly among species (−3.48 MPa to −8.25 MPa) and correlated linearly with home climate precipitation and leaf SLA (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of 0.64 and 0.75, respectively). P12-P88, the range of water potentials between which 12% to 88% of cavitation occurs, was decoupled from P50 but also correlated with leaf SLA (&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of 0.72). We suggest the magnitude of P12-P88 may be representative of a species’ drought strategy – a large P12-P88 signifying leaves that exhibit drought tolerance (retention of leaves under drought conditions) and a small P12-P88 signifying drought avoidance (leaf shedding after a threshold of drought is reached). Our results agree with other studies that highlight these cavitation metrics as genetically fixed traits. Turgor loss point, on the other hand, may be more plastic, as evidenced by the low variability of this trait across these eucalypt species grown in a common garden environment. Further study will help to establish the SLA-related anatomical traits that impart cavitation resistance and to extend these conclusions to a greater number of species and home climates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.05.459049" rel="alternate" title="Vulnerability to cavitation is linked to home climate precipitation across eight eucalypt species (11 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459666</id><title>Multiplex knockout of trichome-regulating MYBs in poplar affects light sensitivity and triterpene accumulation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.158954+00:00</updated><author><name>W. Patrick Bewg</name></author><author><name>Scott A Harding</name></author><author><name>Nancy Engle</name></author><author><name>Brajesh N Vaidya</name></author><author><name>Jingyin Yu</name></author><author><name>Ran Zhou</name></author><author><name>Jacob Reeves</name></author><author><name>Thomas W Horn</name></author><author><name>Nirmal Joshee</name></author><author><name>Jerry W Jenkins</name></author><author><name>Shengqiang Shu</name></author><author><name>Kerrie W. Barry</name></author><author><name>Yuko Yoshinaga</name></author><author><name>Jane Grimwood</name></author><author><name>Robert J. Schmitz</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Schmutz</name></author><author><name>Timothy Tschaplinski</name></author><author><name>Chung-Jui Tsai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Hair-like trichomes cover the aerial organs of many plant species and act as a barrier between a plant and its environment. They function in defense against biotic and abiotic stresses, while also serving as sites for synthesis and storage of secondary metabolites. Previously, the transcription factor PtaMYB186 was identified as a positive regulator of trichome initiation during early stages of leaf development in Populus tremula x P. alba (IRNA 717-1B4). However, trichome regulation in poplar remains largely unexplored, as does the functional redundancy of duplicated poplar genes. Here, we employed CRISPR/Cas9 to target a consensus region of PtaMYB186 and its close paralogs for knockout. Regeneration of glabrous mutants suggested their essential roles in poplar trichome development. No apparent differences in growth and leaf transpiration rates between the mutants and the controls were observed, but trichomeless poplars showed increased insect pest susceptibility. RNA-seq analysis revealed widespread down-regulation of circadian- and light-responsive genes in the mutants. When exposed to a high light regime, trichomeless mutants accumulated significantly higher levels of photoprotective anthocyanins. Cuticular wax and whole leaf analyses showed a complete absence of triterpenes in the mutants, suggesting biosynthesis and storage of triterpenes in poplar occurs in the non-glandular trichomes. This work also demonstrates that a single gRNA with SNP-aware design is sufficient for multiplex targeting of paralogous genes in outcrossing and/or hybrid species with unexpected copy number variations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.09.459666" rel="alternate" title="Multiplex knockout of trichome-regulating MYBs in poplar affects light sensitivity and triterpene accumulation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.05.459032</id><title>The potyviral protein 6K1 reduces plant protease activity during Turnip mosaic virus infection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.159216+00:00</updated><author><name>Sayanta Bera</name></author><author><name>Gabriella D. Arena</name></author><author><name>Swayamjit Ray</name></author><author><name>Sydney Flannigan</name></author><author><name>Clare L Casteel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Potyviral genomes encode just 11 major proteins and multifunctionality is associated to most of these proteins at different stages of virus life cycle. The potyviral protein 6K1 is required for potyvirus replication at the early stages of viral infection and may mediate cell-to-cell movement at later stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our study demonstrates that the 6K1 protein from &lt;italic&gt;Turnip mosaic virus&lt;/italic&gt; (TuMV) reduces the abundance of transcripts related to jasmonic acid biosynthesis and transcripts that encode cysteine protease inhibitors when expressed in &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt; in &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/italic&gt; relative to controls. Furthermore, 6K1 stability increases when lipoxygenase and cysteine protease activity is inhibited chemically, linking a mechanism to the rapid turnover of 6K1 when expressed in &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using transient expression, we show 6K1 is degraded rapidly at early time points in the infection process, whereas at later stages of infection protease activity is reduced and 6K1 becomes more stable, resulting in higher TuMV accumulation in systemic leaves. There was no impact of 6K1 transient expression on TuMV accumulation in local leaves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together, these results suggest a novel function for the TuMV 6K1 protein which has not been reported previously and enhances our understanding of the complex interactions occurring between plants and potyviruses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.05.459032" rel="alternate" title="The potyviral protein 6K1 reduces plant protease activity during Turnip mosaic virus infection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>