<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.831111+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.448858</id><title>Introgression of type-IV glandular trichomes from Solanum galapagense to cultivated tomato reveals genetic complexity for the development of acylsugar-based insect resistance (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.831423+00:00</updated><author><name>Eloisa Vendemiatti</name></author><author><name>Rodrigo Therezan</name></author><author><name>Mateus Henrique Vicente</name></author><author><name>Maisa de Siqueira Pinto</name></author><author><name>Nick Bergau</name></author><author><name>Lina Yang</name></author><author><name>Walter Fernando Bernardi</name></author><author><name>Severino Matias de Alencar</name></author><author><name>Agustin Zsogon</name></author><author><name>Alain Tissier</name></author><author><name>Vagner Benedito</name></author><author><name>Lazaro Peres</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Glandular trichomes are involved in the production of food- and medicine-relevant chemicals in plants, besides being associated with pest resistance. In some wild &lt;italic&gt;Solanum&lt;/italic&gt; species closely related to the cultivated tomato (&lt;italic&gt;S. lycopersicum&lt;/italic&gt;), the presence of type-IV glandular trichomes leads to the production of high levels of insecticide acylsugars (AS). Conversely, low AS production observed in the cultivated tomato is attributed to its incapacity to develop type-IV trichomes in adult organs. Therefore, we hypothesized that cultivated tomatoes engineered to harbor type-IV trichomes on the leaves of mature plants can be pest resistant. We introgressed into the tomato cultivar Micro-Tom (MT) the capability of &lt;italic&gt;S. galapagense&lt;/italic&gt; to maintain the development of type-IV trichomes throughout all plant stages, thus creating a line named "&lt;italic&gt;Galapagos enhanced trichomes&lt;/italic&gt;" (MT-&lt;italic&gt;Get&lt;/italic&gt;). Mapping-by-sequencing of MT-&lt;italic&gt;Get&lt;/italic&gt; revealed that five chromosomal regions of &lt;italic&gt;S. galapagense&lt;/italic&gt; were present in MT-&lt;italic&gt;Get&lt;/italic&gt;. Further mapping reveled that &lt;italic&gt;S. galapagense&lt;/italic&gt; alleles on chromosomes 1, 2 and 3 are sufficient for the presence of type-IV trichomes, but in lower densities. GC-MS, LC-MS, and gene expression analyses demonstrated that the increased density of type-IV trichomes was accompanied by high AS production and exudation in MT-&lt;italic&gt;Get&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, MT-&lt;italic&gt;Get&lt;/italic&gt; did not differ from MT in its susceptibility to whitefly (&lt;italic&gt;Bemisia tabaci&lt;/italic&gt;). Our findings demonstrates that type-IV glandular trichome development along with AS production and exudation are partially uncoupled at the genetic level. The MT-&lt;italic&gt;Get&lt;/italic&gt; genotype represents a valuable resource for further studies involving the biochemical manipulation of type-IV trichome content through either genetic introgression or transgenic approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.18.448858" rel="alternate" title="Introgression of type-IV glandular trichomes from Solanum galapagense to cultivated tomato reveals genetic complexity for the development of acylsugar-based insect resistance (13 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448837</id><title>Autopolyploidization affects transcript patterns and gene targeting frequencies in Physcomitrella (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.831738+00:00</updated><author><name>Christine Rempfer</name></author><author><name>Gertrud Wiedemann</name></author><author><name>Gabriele Schween</name></author><author><name>Klaus L. Kerres</name></author><author><name>Jan M. Lucht</name></author><author><name>Ralf Horres</name></author><author><name>Eva L. Decker</name></author><author><name>Ralf Reski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Qualitative changes in gene expression after an autopolyploidization event, a pure duplication of the whole genome, might be relevant for a different regulation of molecular mechanisms between angiosperms growing in a life cycle with a dominant diploid sporophytic stage and the haploid-dominant bryophytes. Whereas angiosperms repair DNA double strand breaks (DSB) preferentially via non-homologous end joining (NHEJ), in bryophytes homologous recombination (HR) is the main DNA-DSB repair pathway facilitating the precise integration of foreign DNA into the genome via gene targeting (GT). Here, we studied the influence of ploidy on gene expression patterns and GT efficiency in the moss Physcomitrella using haploid plants and autodiploid plants, generated via an artificial duplication of the whole genome. Single cells (protoplasts) were transfected with a GT construct and material from different time-points after transfection was analysed by microarrays and SuperSAGE sequencing. In the SuperSAGE data, we detected 3.7% of the Physcomitrella genes as differentially expressed in response to the whole genome duplication event. Among the differentially expressed genes involved in DNA-DSB repair was an upregulated gene encoding the X-ray repair cross-complementing protein 4 (XRCC4), a key player in NHEJ. Analysing the GT efficiency, we observed that autodiploid plants were significantly GT suppressed (p&amp;lt;0.001) attaining only one third of the expected GT rates. Hence, an alteration of global transcript patterns, including genes related to DNA repair, in autodiploid Physcomitrella plants correlated with a drastic suppression of HR.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448837" rel="alternate" title="Autopolyploidization affects transcript patterns and gene targeting frequencies in Physcomitrella (8 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448567</id><title>A Co-Fractionation Mass Spectrometry-based Prediction of Protein Complex Assemblies in the Developing Rice Aleurone-subaleurone (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.832055+00:00</updated><author><name>Youngwoo Lee</name></author><author><name>Thomas W. Okita</name></author><author><name>Daniel B. Szymanski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Multiprotein complexes execute and coordinate diverse cellular processes such as organelle biogenesis, vesicle trafficking, cell signaling, and metabolism. Knowledge about their composition and localization provides useful clues about the mechanisms of cellular homeostasis and systems-level control. This is of great biological importance and practical significance in heterotrophic rice endosperm and aleurone-subaleurone tissues that are a primary source of seed vitamins and stored energy. Dozens of protein complexes have been implicated in the synthesis, transport, and storage of seed proteins, lipids, vitamins, and minerals. Mutations in protein complexes that control RNA transport result in aberrant endosperm with shrunken and floury phenotypes, significantly reducing seed yield and quality. The purpose of this research is to broadly predict protein complex composition in the aleurone-subaleurone layers of developing rice seeds using co-fractionation mass spectrometry. Following orthogonal chromatographic separations of biological replicates, thousands of protein elution profiles were subjected to distance-based clustering to enable a large-scale determination of multimerization state and complex composition. Predictions included evolutionarily conserved proteins across diverse functional categories, including novel heteromeric RNA binding protein complexes that influence seed quality. This effective and open-ended proteomics pipeline provides useful clues about systems-level controls in the early stage of rice seed development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One-sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A co-fractionation mass spectrometry pipeline predicts compositions of cytosolic protein complexes present in the early stages of rice seed development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.16.448567" rel="alternate" title="A Co-Fractionation Mass Spectrometry-based Prediction of Protein Complex Assemblies in the Developing Rice Aleurone-subaleurone (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>