<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.682907+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.01.474684</id><title>Concerted expansion and contraction of immune receptor gene repertoires in plant genomes (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.683324+00:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Pok Man Ngou</name></author><author><name>Robert Heal</name></author><author><name>Michele Wyler</name></author><author><name>Marc W Schmid</name></author><author><name>Jonathan DG Jones</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent reports suggest that cell-surface and intracellular immune receptors function synergistically to activate robust defence against pathogens, but whether or not they co-evolve is unclear. Here we determined the copy numbers of cell-surface and intracellular immune receptors in 208 species. Surprisingly, these receptor gene families contract and/or expand together in plant genomes, suggesting the mutual potentiation of immunity initiated by cell-surface and intracellular receptors is reflected in the concerted co-evolution of the size of their repertoires across plant species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.01.474684" rel="alternate" title="Concerted expansion and contraction of immune receptor gene repertoires in plant genomes (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474618</id><title>Apoplastic CBM1-interacting proteins bind conserved carbohydrate binding module 1 motifs in fungal hydrolases to counter pathogen invasion (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.683607+00:00</updated><author><name>Takumi Takeda</name></author><author><name>Machiko Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Motoki Shimizu</name></author><author><name>Yu Sugihara</name></author><author><name>Hiromasa Saitoh</name></author><author><name>Koki Fujisaki</name></author><author><name>Kazuya Ishikawa</name></author><author><name>Hiroe Utsushi</name></author><author><name>Eiko Kanzaki</name></author><author><name>Yuichi Sakamoto</name></author><author><name>Akira Abe</name></author><author><name>Ryohei Terauchi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When infecting plants, fungal pathogens secrete cell wall degrading enzymes (CWDEs) that break down cellulose and hemicellulose, the primary components of plant cell walls. Some fungal CWDEs contain a unique domain, named the carbohydrate binding module (CBM), that facilitates their access to polysaccharides. However, little is known about how plants counteract pathogen degradation of their cell walls. Here, we show that the rice cysteine-rich repeat secretion protein OsCBMIP binds to and inhibits xylanase MoCel10A of the blast fungus pathogen Magnaporthe oryzae, interfering with its access to the rice cell wall and degradation of rice xylan. We found binding of OsCBMIP to various CBM1-containing enzymes, suggesting it has a general role in inhibiting the catalytic activities of fungal enzymes. OsCBMIP is localized to the apoplast, and its expression is strongly induced in leaves infected with M. oryzae. Remarkably, knockdown of OsCBMIP reduced rice defense against M. oryzae, demonstrating that inhibition of CBM1-containing fungal enzymes by OsCBMIP is crucial for rice defense. We also identified additional CBMIP-related proteins from Arabidopsis thaliana and Setaria italica, indicating that a wide range of plants counteract pathogens through this mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.31.474618" rel="alternate" title="Apoplastic CBM1-interacting proteins bind conserved carbohydrate binding module 1 motifs in fungal hydrolases to counter pathogen invasion (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2022-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>