<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.850122+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464636</id><title>Automatic identification and annotation of MYB gene family members in plants (88 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.850401+00:00</updated><author><name>Boas Pucker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: MYBs are among the largest transcription factor families in plants. Consequently, members of this family are involved in a plethora of processes including development and specialized metabolism. The MYB families of many plant species were investigated in the last two decades since the first investigation looked at Arabidopsis thaliana. This body of knowledge and characterized sequences provide the basis for the identification, classification, and functional annotation of candidate sequences in new genome and transcriptome assemblies.
Results: A pipeline for the automatic identification and functional annotation of MYBs in a given sequence data set was implemented in Python. MYB candidates are identified, screened for the presence of a MYB domain and other motifs, and finally placed in a phylogenetic context with well characterized sequences. In addition to technical benchmarking based on existing annotation, the transcriptome assembly of Croton tiglium and the annotated genome sequence of Castanea crenata were screened for MYBs. Results of both analyses are presented in this study to illustrate the potential of this application. The analysis of one species takes only a few minutes depending on the number of predicted sequences and the size of the MYB gene family. This pipeline, the required bait sequences, and reference sequences for a classification are freely available on github: https://github.com/bpucker/MYB_annotator.
Conclusions: This automatic annotation of the MYB gene family in novel assemblies makes genome-wide investigations consistent and paves the way for comparative studies in the future. Candidate genes for in-depth analyses are presented based on their orthology to previously characterized sequences which allows the functional annotation of the newly identified MYBs with high confidence. The identification of orthologs can also be harnessed to detect duplication and deletion events.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464636" rel="alternate" title="Automatic identification and annotation of MYB gene family members in plants (88 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464316</id><title>CAR modulates plasma membrane nano-organization and immune signaling downstream of RALF1-FERONIA ligand-receptor signaling system (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.850572+00:00</updated><author><name>Weijun Chen</name></author><author><name>Huina Zhou</name></author><author><name>Fan Xu</name></author><author><name>Meng Yu</name></author><author><name>Alberto Coego</name></author><author><name>Lesia Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Yuqing Lu</name></author><author><name>Qijun Xie</name></author><author><name>Qiong Fu</name></author><author><name>Jia Chen</name></author><author><name>Lan Li</name></author><author><name>Guoyun Xu</name></author><author><name>Dousheng Wu</name></author><author><name>Xiushan Li</name></author><author><name>Shaojun Dai</name></author><author><name>Xiaojuan Li</name></author><author><name>Yvon Jaillais</name></author><author><name>Pedro L. Rodriguez</name></author><author><name>Feng Yu</name></author><author><name>Sirui Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The highly selective segregation of molecules at the plasma membrane (PM) to form domains is a widespread phenomenon. But how distinct signaling platforms are established and maintained by specific signals remains unclear. Here, we show that the receptor of Rapid Alkalinization Factor 1 (RALF1), the FERONIA (FER) receptor kinase, physically interacts with C2 domain ABA-related (CAR) proteins to control the nano-organization of the PM and to regulate extracellular signal transduction in Arabidopsis. During this process, the RALF1-FER pathway upregulates CAR protein synthesis, which then controls the membrane lipid order. This might act as a rapid feedforward loop to stabilize FER in PM nanodomains. FER then interacts with and phosphorylates CARs, reducing their lipid-binding ability, which might break the feedback regulation and downregulate CAR activity at latter time point. Similar to fer mutant, a pentuple car14569 mutant inhibits flg22-induced FLS2-BAK1 complex formation, which ultimately impacts plant immunity. Together, we proposed that the FER-CAR module controls the dynamics of the PM nano-organization during RALF signaling through a self-contained amplifying loop including both positive and negative feedbacks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.13.464316" rel="alternate" title="CAR modulates plasma membrane nano-organization and immune signaling downstream of RALF1-FERONIA ligand-receptor signaling system (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.463719</id><title>The quantitative contribution of different Photosystem II compartments to non-photochemical quenching in Arabidopsis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.850836+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Nicol</name></author><author><name>Vincenzo Mascoli</name></author><author><name>Herbert van Amerongen</name></author><author><name>Roberta Croce</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Excess excitation energy in the light-harvesting antenna of Photosystem II (PSII) can cause irreversible damage to the photosynthetic apparatus. In periods of high light intensity, a feedback mechanism known as non-photochemical quenching (NPQ), induces the formation of quenchers which can safely dissipate excess excitation energy as heat. Although quenchers have been identified in more than one compartment of the PSII supercomplex, there is currently no quantitative description of how much NPQ is occurring at each of these locations. Here, we perform time-resolved fluorescence measurements on WT and antenna mutants lacking LHCII (NoL) and all peripheral antenna (Ch1 and Ch1lhcb5). By combining the results with those of steady-state fluorescence experiments we are able to estimate the intrinsic rate of NPQ for each plant and each PSII compartment. It is concluded that 60-70% of quenching occurs in LHCII, 15-20% in the minor antenna and 15-20% in the PSII core.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.17.463719" rel="alternate" title="The quantitative contribution of different Photosystem II compartments to non-photochemical quenching in Arabidopsis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464670</id><title>Old and ancient trees are life history lottery winners and act as evolutionary buffers against long-term environmental change (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.850999+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles H Cannon</name></author><author><name>Gianluca Piovesan</name></author><author><name>Sergi Munne-Bosch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Trees can live many centuries with sustained fecundity and death is largely stochastic. We use a neutral stochastic model to examine the demographic patterns that emerge over time, across a range of population sizes and empirically observed mortality rates. A small proportion of trees (~1% at 1.5% mortality) are life-history lottery winners, achieving ages &amp;gt;10-20x median age. Maximum age increases with bigger populations and lower mortality rates. One quarter of trees (~24%) achieve ages that are 3-4 times greater than median age. Three age classes (Mature, Old, and Ancient) contribute unique historical diversity across complex environmental cycles. Ancient trees are an emergent property of forests that requires many centuries to generate. They radically change generation time variance and population fitness, bridging infrequent environmental cycles. These life-history lottery winners are vital to future forest dynamics and invaluable data about environmental history and individual longevity. Old-growth forests contain trees that cannot be replaced through restoration or regeneration in the near future. They simply must be protected to preserve their unique diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.16.464670" rel="alternate" title="Old and ancient trees are life history lottery winners and act as evolutionary buffers against long-term environmental change (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>