<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.765281+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451212</id><title>The Phytochemical Diversity of Commercial Cannabis in the United States (67 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.766019+00:00</updated><author><name>Christiana J. Smith</name></author><author><name>Daniela Vergara</name></author><author><name>Brian Keegan</name></author><author><name>Nick Jikomes</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The legal status of &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; is changing, fueling an increased diversity of &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt;-derived products. Because &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; contains dozens of chemical compounds with potential psychoactive or medicinal effects, understanding its phytochemical diversity is crucial. The legal &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; industry heavily markets products to consumers based on widely used labelling systems purported to predict the effects of different &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; “strains.” We analyzed the cannabinoid and terpene content of tens of thousands of commercial &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; samples across six US states, finding distinct chemical phenotypes (chemotypes) which are reliably present. After careful descriptive analysis of the phytochemical diversity and comparison to the commercial labels commonly attached to &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; samples, we show that commercial labels do not consistently align with the observed chemical diversity. However, certain labels are statistically overrepresented for specific chemotypes. These results have important implications for the classification of commercial &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt;, the design of animal and human research, and the regulation of legal &lt;italic&gt;Cannabis&lt;/italic&gt; marketing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.05.451212" rel="alternate" title="The Phytochemical Diversity of Commercial Cannabis in the United States (67 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.04.451080</id><title>ProXs drive the formation of membraneless organelles in plants (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.766597+00:00</updated><author><name>Honghong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Fangyu Peng</name></author><author><name>Yan Liu</name></author><author><name>Haiteng Deng</name></author><author><name>Xiaofeng Fang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Membraneless organelles (MLOs) are non-membranous structures inside cells that organize cellular space and processes. The recent discovery that MLOs can be assembled via liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS) advanced our understanding of these structures. However, the proteins that are capable of forming MLOs are largely unknown, especially in plants. In this study, we developed a method to identify proteins that we referred as ProXs (Proteins enriched by b-iso&lt;underline&gt;X&lt;/underline&gt;) in Arabidopsis. Heterologous expression in yeast cells showed that most ProXs were capable of forming MLOs autonomously. We applied this method to several model and crop species including early and higher plants. This allowed us to generate an atlas of ProXs for studying plant MLOs. Analysis of ProXs from different species revealed high degree of conservation, supporting that they play important roles in cellular functions and are positively selected during evolution. Our method will be a valuable tool to characterize novel MLOs from desired cells and the data generated in present study will be instrumental for the plant research community to investigate MLO biology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.04.451080" rel="alternate" title="ProXs drive the formation of membraneless organelles in plants (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>