<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.490119+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466255</id><title>Plasticity in stomatal behavior across a gradient of water supply is consistent among field-grown maize inbred lines with varying stomatal patterning (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.490876+00:00</updated><author><name>Risheng Ding</name></author><author><name>Jiayang Xie</name></author><author><name>Dustin Mayfield-Jones</name></author><author><name>Yanqun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shaozhong Kang</name></author><author><name>Andrew Leakey</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stomata regulate leaf CO2 assimilation (A) and water loss. The Ball-Berry and Medlyn models predict stomatal conductance (gs) with a slope parameter (m or g1) that reflects sensitivity of gs to A, atmospheric CO2 and humidity, and is inversely related to water use efficiency (WUE). This study addressed knowledge gaps about what the values of m and g1 are in C4 crops under field conditions, as well as how they vary among genotypes and with drought stress. m and g1 were unexpectedly consistent in four inbred maize genotypes across a gradient of water supply. This was despite genotypic variation in stomatal patterning, A and gs. m and g1 were strongly correlated with soil water content, moderately correlated with pre-dawn leaf water potential (Ψpd), and weakly correlated with midday leaf water potential (Ψmd). This implied that m and g1 respond to long-term water supply more than short-term drought stress. The conserved nature of m and g1 across anatomically diverse genotypes and water supplies suggests there is flexibility in structure-function relationships underpinning WUE. This evidence can guide simulation of maize gs across a range of water supply in the primary maize growing region and inform efforts to improve WUE.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466255" rel="alternate" title="Plasticity in stomatal behavior across a gradient of water supply is consistent among field-grown maize inbred lines with varying stomatal patterning (23 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465752</id><title>SCARECROW maintains the stem cell niche in Arabidopsis root by ensuring telomere integrity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.491267+00:00</updated><author><name>Bingxin Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiaowen Shi</name></author><author><name>Jingbo Gao</name></author><author><name>Rui Liao</name></author><author><name>Jing Fu</name></author><author><name>Juan Bai</name></author><author><name>Hongchang Cui</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stem cells are the ultimate source of the cells in various tissues and organs, and thus are essential to postembryonic plant growth and development. SCARECROW (SCR) is a plant-specific transcription regulator well known for its role in stem-cell renewal in plant roots, but the mechanism by which SCR exerts this function is still unclear. To address this question, we carried out a genetic screen for mutants that no longer express SCR in the stem-cell niche in the Arabidopsis root, and one of the mutants is characterized herein. Using marker-assisted mapping, whole genome sequencing, and complementation tests, we pinpointed the causal mutation in this mutant at &lt;italic&gt;TEN1&lt;/italic&gt;, which encodes telomere-end protecting factor. By sequence alignment of TEN1 homologs in a wide range of eukaryotes, we identified two novel motifs. The importance of these motifs was examined through site-directed mutagenesis of a conserved amino acid, and through complementation tests, which showed that G100 is required for TEN1 stability. Interestingly, we found that &lt;italic&gt;TEN1&lt;/italic&gt; expression was dramatically reduced in the &lt;italic&gt;scr&lt;/italic&gt; mutant. Two components in the same protein complex as TEN1, STN1 and CTC1, were found to be also dramatically downregulated in &lt;italic&gt;scr&lt;/italic&gt;, as well as telomerase. Further studies showed that loss of STN1, CTC1 and telomerase also caused defects in the root stem cells. In line with these findings, the &lt;italic&gt;scr&lt;/italic&gt; mutant was hypersensitive to DNA damage reagents such as Zeocin. These results together suggest that SCR maintains root stem cells by promoting expression of genes that ensures genome integrity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study reveals a role for the root development regulator SCARECROW in maintaining the expression of telomere-end protecting factors and a connection between genome integrity and stem-cell maintenance in Arabidopsis root.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465752" rel="alternate" title="SCARECROW maintains the stem cell niche in Arabidopsis root by ensuring telomere integrity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465169</id><title>Genome-wide association study reveals complex genetic architecture of cadmium and mercury accumulation and tolerance traits in Medicago truncatula (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.491610+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Paape</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Heiniger</name></author><author><name>Miguel Santo Domingo</name></author><author><name>Michael Clear</name></author><author><name>M. Mercedes Lucas</name></author><author><name>Jose Pueyo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Heavy metals are an increasing problem due to contamination from human sources that and can enter the food chain by being taken up by plants. Understanding the genetic basis of accumulation and tolerance in plants is important for reducing the uptake of toxic metals in crops and crop relatives, as well as for removing heavy metals from soils by means of phytoremediation. Following exposure of Medicago truncatula seedlings to cadmium (Cd) and mercury (Hg), we conducted a genome-wide association study using relative root growth (RRG) and leaf accumulation measurements. Cd and Hg accumulation and RRG had heritability ranging 0.44 - 0.72 indicating high genetic diversity for these traits. The Cd and Hg trait associations were broadly distributed throughout the genome, indicated the traits are polygenic and involve several quantitative loci. For all traits, candidate genes included several membrane associated ATP-binding cassette transporters, P-type ATPase transporters, several oxidative stress response genes and stress related UDP-glycosyltransferases. The P-type ATPase transporters and ATP-binding cassette protein-families have roles in vacuole transport of heavy metals, and our findings support their wide use in physiological plant responses to heavy metals and abiotic stresses.  We also found associations between Cd RRG with the genes CAX3 and PDR3, two linked adjacent genes, and leaf accumulation of Hg associated with the genes NRAMP6 and CAX9. When plant genotypes with the most extreme phenotypes were compared, we found significant divergence in genomic regions using population genomics methods that contained metal transport and stress response gene ontologies. Several of these genomic regions show high linkage disequilibrium (LD) among candidate genes suggesting they have evolved together. Minor allele frequency (MAF) and effect size of the most significant SNPs was negatively correlated with large effect alleles being most rare. This is consistent with purifying selection against alleles that increase toxicity and abiotic stress.  Conversely, the alleles with large affect that had higher frequencies that were associated with the exclusion of Cd and Hg. Overall, macroevolutionary conservation of heavy metal and stress response genes is important for improvement of forage crops by harnessing wild genetic variants in gene banks such as the Medicago HapMap collection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.465169" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide association study reveals complex genetic architecture of cadmium and mercury accumulation and tolerance traits in Medicago truncatula (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466326</id><title>Efficient, selectable marker free gene targeting in soybean using novel Ochrobactrum haywardense-mediated delivery (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.491937+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandeep Kumar</name></author><author><name>Zhan-Bin Lui</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Sanyour-Doyel</name></author><author><name>Brian Landerts</name></author><author><name>Andrew Worden</name></author><author><name>Ajith Anand</name></author><author><name>Hyeon-Je Cho</name></author><author><name>Jyothi Bolar</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Harris</name></author><author><name>Lingxia Huang</name></author><author><name>Aiqiu Xing</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Richardson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report robust selectable marker-free gene targeting (GT) system in soybean, one of the most economically important crops. A novel efficient Ochrobactrum haywardense-mediated embryonic axis transformation method was used for the delivery of CRISPR-Cas9 components and donor template to regenerate T0 plants in 6-8 weeks after transformation. This approach generated up to 3.4% targeted insertion of the donor sequence into the target locus in T0 plants, with ~ 90% mutation rate observed at the genomic target site. The GT was demonstrated in two genomic sites using two different donor DNA templates without a need of a selectable marker within the template. High-resolution Southern by Sequencing (SbS) analysis identified T1 plants with precise targeted insertion and without unintended plasmid DNA. Unlike previous low-frequency GT reports in soybean that involved particle bombardment-mediated delivery and extensive selection, the method described here is fast, efficient, reproducible, does not require selectable marker within the donor DNA, and generates non-chimeric plants with heritable GT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466326" rel="alternate" title="Efficient, selectable marker free gene targeting in soybean using novel Ochrobactrum haywardense-mediated delivery (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465862</id><title>Transcriptome Dynamics of Floral Organs Approaching Blooming in the Flowering Cherry (Cerasus × yedoensis) Cultivar ‘Somei-Yoshino’ (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.492300+00:00</updated><author><name>Kenta Shirasawa</name></author><author><name>Tomoya Esumi</name></author><author><name>Akihiro Itai</name></author><author><name>Sachiko Isobe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;To gain insights into the genetic mechanisms underlying blooming and petal movement in flowering cherry (&lt;italic&gt;Cerasus&lt;/italic&gt; × &lt;italic&gt;yedoensis&lt;/italic&gt;), we performed time-course RNA-seq analysis of the floral buds and open-flowers of the most popular flowering cherry cultivar, ‘Somei-Yoshino’. Independent biological duplicate samples of floral buds and open-flowers were collected from ‘Somei-Yoshino’ trees grown at three different locations in Japan. RNA-seq reads obtained from floral bud and open-flower samples collected in the current study (in 2019) and in a previous study (in 2017) were aligned against the genome sequence of ‘Somei-Yoshino’ to quantify gene transcript levels. Clustering analysis of RNA-seq reads revealed dynamic changes in the transcriptome, with genes in seven modules predominantly expressed at specific time points, ranging from 5 weeks before flowering to 2 weeks after flowering. Based on the identified gene modules and Gene Ontology (GO) terms enriched at different floral stages, we speculate that the genetic mechanisms underlying petal movement and flower opening in cherry involve the processes of development, cell wall organization, reproduction, and metabolism, which are executed by genes encoding transcription factors, phytohormones, transporters, and polysaccharide metabolic enzymes. Furthermore, we propose a method for cherry bloom forecasting, based on gene expression levels at different time points before flowering as RNA markers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.26.465862" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptome Dynamics of Floral Organs Approaching Blooming in the Flowering Cherry (Cerasus × yedoensis) Cultivar ‘Somei-Yoshino’ (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466056</id><title>Automated hyperspectral vegetation index derivation using a hyperparameter optimization framework for high-throughput plant phenotyping (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.492606+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua C.O. Koh</name></author><author><name>Bikram P. Banerjee</name></author><author><name>German Spangenberg</name></author><author><name>Surya Kant</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperspectral vegetation indices (VIs) are widely deployed in agriculture remote sensing and plant phenotyping to estimate plant biophysical and biochemical traits. However, existing VIs consist mainly of simple 2-band indices which limits the net performance and often do not generalize well for other traits than they were originally designed for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present an automated hyperspectral vegetation index (AutoVI) system for the rapid generation of novel 2- to 6-band trait-specific indices in a streamlined process covering model selection, optimization and evaluation driven by the tree parzen estimator algorithm. Its performance was tested in generating novel indices to estimate chlorophyll and sugar contents in wheat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results show that AutoVI can rapidly generate complex novel VIs (≥4-band index) which correlated strongly (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;gt; 0.8) with measured chlorophyll and sugar contents in wheat. AutoVI-derived indices were used as features in simple and stepwise multiple linear regression for chlorophyll and sugar content estimation, and outperformed results achieved with existing 47 VIs and those provided by partial least squares regression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The AutoVI system can deliver novel trait-specific VIs readily adoptable in high-throughput plant phenotyping platforms and should appeal to plant scientists and breeders. A graphical user interface of AutoVI is herein provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466056" rel="alternate" title="Automated hyperspectral vegetation index derivation using a hyperparameter optimization framework for high-throughput plant phenotyping (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466161</id><title>NON-SPECIFIC EFFECTS OF A CINNAMATE-4-HYDROXYLASE INHIBITOR ON AUXIN HOMEOSTASIS (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.492896+00:00</updated><author><name>Ilias El Houari</name></author><author><name>Petr Klíma</name></author><author><name>Alexandra Baekelandt</name></author><author><name>Paul Staswick</name></author><author><name>Veselina Uzunova</name></author><author><name>Charo I. Del Genio</name></author><author><name>Ward Steenackers</name></author><author><name>Petre I. Dobrev</name></author><author><name>Ondrej Novák</name></author><author><name>Richard Napier</name></author><author><name>Jan Petrášek</name></author><author><name>Dirk Inzé</name></author><author><name>Wout Boerjan</name></author><author><name>Bartel Vanholme</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chemical inhibitors are often implemented for the functional characterization of genes to overcome the limitations associated with genetic approaches. Although being a powerful tool, off-target effects of these inhibitors are easily overlooked in a complex biological setting. Here we illustrate the implications of such secondary effects by focusing on piperonylic acid (PA), an inhibitor of CINNAMATE-4-HYDROXYLASE (C4H) that is often used to investigate the involvement of lignin during plant growth and development. When supplied to plants, we found that PA is recognized as a substrate by GRETCHEN HAGEN 3.6 (GH3.6), an amido synthetase involved in the formation of the auxin catabolite indole-3-acetic acid (IAA)-Asp. By competing for the same enzyme, PA interferes with auxin conjugation, resulting in an increase in cellular auxin concentrations. These increased auxin levels likely further contribute to an increase in adventitious rooting previously observed upon PA-treatment. Despite the focus on GH3.6 in this report, PA is conjugated by an array of enzymes and their subsequent reduced activity on native substrates could potentially affect a whole set of physiological processes in the plant. We conclude that surrogate occupation of the endogenous conjugation machinery in the plant by exogenous compounds is likely a more general phenomenon that is rarely considered in pharmacological studies. Our results hereby provide an important basis for future reference in studies using chemical inhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466161" rel="alternate" title="NON-SPECIFIC EFFECTS OF A CINNAMATE-4-HYDROXYLASE INHIBITOR ON AUXIN HOMEOSTASIS (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466245</id><title>The Loroxanthin cycle: A new type of xanthophyll cycle in green algae (Chlorophyta) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.493503+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom E van den Berg</name></author><author><name>Roberta Croce</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Xanthophyll cycles have proven to be major contributors to photoacclimation for many organisms. This work describes a light-driven xanthophyll cycle operating in the chlorophyte Chlamydomonas reinhardtii and involving the xanthophylls Lutein (L) and Loroxanthin (Lo). Pigments were quantified during a switch from high to low light and at different time points from cells grown in Day/night cycle. Trimeric LHCII was purified from cells acclimated to high or low light and their pigment content and spectroscopic properties were characterized. The Lo/(L+Lo) ratio in the cells varies by a factor of 10 between cells grown in low or high light leading to a change in the Lo/(L+Lo) ratio in trimeric LHCII from 0.5 in low light to 0.07 in high light. Trimeric LhcbMs binding Loroxanthin have 5+/-1% higher excitation energy transfer from carotenoid to Chlorophyll as well as higher thermo- and photostability than trimeric LhcbMs that only bind Lutein. The Loroxanthin cycle operates on long time scales (hours to days) and likely evolved as a shade adaptation. It has many similarities with the Lutein-epoxide - Lutein cycle of plants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466245" rel="alternate" title="The Loroxanthin cycle: A new type of xanthophyll cycle in green algae (Chlorophyta) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466391</id><title>Characterization of γ-Glutamyl Peptidases and γ-Glutamyl Cyclotransferases for Glutathione Degradation in Arabidopsis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.493740+00:00</updated><author><name>Takehiro Ito</name></author><author><name>Taisuke Kitaiwa</name></author><author><name>Kosuke Nishizono</name></author><author><name>Minori Umahashi</name></author><author><name>Shunsuke Miyaji</name></author><author><name>Shin-ichiro Agake</name></author><author><name>Kana Kuwahara</name></author><author><name>Tadashi Yokoyama</name></author><author><name>Akiko Maruyama-Nakashita</name></author><author><name>Ryosuke Sugiyama</name></author><author><name>Masami Yokota Hirai</name></author><author><name>Naoko Ohkama-Ohtsu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Organic sulfur is stored as glutathione (GSH) in plants. In &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt;, γ-glutamyl cyclotransferases (GGCT2;1, GGCT2;2, and GGCT2;3) degrade cytosolic GSH, but they do not fully explain the rapid GSH turnover. Here, we demonstrate that γ-glutamyl peptidases, GGP1 and GGP3, play a substantial role in degrading GSH in the cytosol. We conducted yeast complementation assay and activity assay of recombinant proteins to identify the novel GSH degradation enzymes. The expression patterns were investigated by RT-qPCR. GSH concentrations in the mutants were also analyzed. &lt;italic&gt;GGP1&lt;/italic&gt; complemented the yeast phenotype. Recombinant GGP1 and GGP3 showed reasonable &lt;italic&gt;K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/italic&gt; values considering cytosolic GSH concentration, and their activity was comparable to that of GGCTs. The &lt;italic&gt;GGP1&lt;/italic&gt; transcript was highly abundant in mature organs such as rosette leaves. The expression of &lt;italic&gt;GGCT2;1&lt;/italic&gt; was conspicuously enhanced under sulfur deficiency. GSH concentration was higher in &lt;italic&gt;ggp1&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mutants regardless of nutritional conditions; the concentration was higher in &lt;italic&gt;ggct2;1&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mutants under sulfur-deficient conditions. We propose a model wherein cytosolic GSH is degraded fundamentally by GGP1. The degradation is accelerated by GGCT2;1 under sulfur deficiency. Given the energy cost throughout the reactions, GGPs could render a more efficient route for GSH degradation than GGCTs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.29.466391" rel="alternate" title="Characterization of γ-Glutamyl Peptidases and γ-Glutamyl Cyclotransferases for Glutathione Degradation in Arabidopsis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>