<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.917545+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467437</id><title>PHOSPHATE STARVATION RESPONSE enables arbuscular mycorrhiza symbiosis (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.918519+00:00</updated><author><name>Debatosh Das</name></author><author><name>Michael Paries</name></author><author><name>Karen Hobecker</name></author><author><name>Michael Gigl</name></author><author><name>Corinna Dawid</name></author><author><name>Hon-Ming Lam</name></author><author><name>Jianhua Zhang</name></author><author><name>Moxian Chen</name></author><author><name>Caroline Gutjahr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Arbuscular mycorrhiza (AM) is a widespread symbiosis between roots of the majority of land plants and Glomeromycotina fungi. AM is important for ecosystem health and functioning as the fungi critically support plant performance by providing essential mineral nutrients, particularly the poorly accessible phosphate, in exchange for organic carbon. AM fungi colonize the inside of roots and this is promoted at low but inhibited at high plant phosphate status, while the mechanistic basis for this phosphate-dependence remained obscure. Here we demonstrate that a major transcriptional regulator of phosphate starvation responses in rice PHOSPHATE STARVATION RESPONSE 2 (PHR2) regulates AM. Root colonization of phr2 mutants is drastically reduced, and PHR2 is required for root colonization, mycorrhizal phosphate uptake, and yield increase in field soil. PHR2 promotes AM by targeting genes required for pre-contact signaling, root colonization, and AM function. Thus, this important symbiosis is directly wired to the PHR2-controlled plant phosphate starvation response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467437" rel="alternate" title="PHOSPHATE STARVATION RESPONSE enables arbuscular mycorrhiza symbiosis (30 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467332</id><title>Functional characterization of mutants deficient in N-terminal phosphorylation of the CF1 subunit beta (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.918951+00:00</updated><author><name>Ralph Bock</name></author><author><name>Deserah D Strand</name></author><author><name>Daniel Karcher</name></author><author><name>Stephanie Ruf</name></author><author><name>Anne Schadach</name></author><author><name>Mark Aurel Schöttler</name></author><author><name>Omar Sandoval-Ibáñez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the regulation of photosynthetic light harvesting and electron transfer is of great importance to efforts to improve the ability of the electron transport chain to supply downstream metabolism. The central regulator of the electron transport chain is the ATP synthase, the molecular motor that harnesses the chemiosmotic potential generated from proton coupled electron transport to synthesize ATP. The ATP synthase is regulated both thermodynamically and post-translationally, with proposed phosphorylation sites on multiple subunits. In this study we focused on two N-terminal serines on the catalytic subunit beta, previously proposed to be important for dark inactivation of the complex to avoid ATP hydrolysis at night. Here we show that there is no clear role for phosphorylation in the dark inactivation of ATP synthase. Instead, mutation of one of the two phosphorylated serine residues to aspartate strongly decreased ATP synthase abundance. We propose that the loss of N-terminal phosphorylation of ATP beta may be involved in proper ATP synthase accumulation during complex assembly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.04.467332" rel="alternate" title="Functional characterization of mutants deficient in N-terminal phosphorylation of the CF1 subunit beta (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467370</id><title>Efficient transformation and genome editing of watermelon assisted by genes that encode developmental regulators (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-08T11:02:17.919594+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenbo Pan</name></author><author><name>Zhentao Cheng</name></author><author><name>Zhiguo Han</name></author><author><name>Hong Yang</name></author><author><name>Wanggen Zhang</name></author><author><name>Huawei Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The Cucurbitaceae contains multiple species of important food plants. But most of them are difficult to be genetically transformed. Watermelon is one of the most important fruit species of Cucurbitaceae, and it is a model horticulture crops. Its low transgenic efficiency is the major bottleneck in functional genome research and genome editing-based breeding. Here, with the help of genes that encode developmental regulators (DRs), in particular AtGRF5, and an appropriate Agrobacterium strain (GV3101), we have significantly increased the transformation efficiency of watermelon to about 25%, which is a 40-fold increase compared with a traditional vector. AtGRF5-mediated transformation increased the number of transformable watermelon genotypes without causing obvious side effects. Moreover, when applying this strategy to CRISPR/Cas9-mediated genome editing, clpds knockout mutants were generated in the T0 generation. Our results show that AtGRF5 is a powerful and robust tool to effectively create transgenic plants or knockout mutations in watermelon. Similar strategies using DRs might also be able to overcome the transformation barriers in many other Cucurbitaceae species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.05.467370" rel="alternate" title="Efficient transformation and genome editing of watermelon assisted by genes that encode developmental regulators (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>