<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.818349+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.462716</id><title>Expression dynamics of ARGONAUTE proteins during meiosis in Arabidopsis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.818698+00:00</updated><author><name>Cecilia Oliver</name></author><author><name>German Martinez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Meiosis is a specialized cell division that is key for reproduction and genetic diversity in sexually reproducing plants. Recently, different RNA silencing pathways have been proposed to carry a specific activity during meiosis, but the pathways involved during this process remain unclear. Here, we explored the subcellular localization of different ARGONAUTE (AGO) proteins, the main effectors of RNA silencing, during male meiosis in Arabidopsis thaliana using immunolocalizations with commercially available antibodies. We detected the presence of AGO proteins associated with posttranscriptional gene silencing (AGO1, 2 and 5) in the cytoplasm or the nucleus, while AGOs associated with transcriptional gene silencing (AGO4 and 9) localized exclusively in the nucleus. These results indicate that the localization of different AGOs correlates with their predicted roles at the transcriptional and posttranscriptional levels and provide an overview of their timing and potential role during meiosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.462716" rel="alternate" title="Expression dynamics of ARGONAUTE proteins during meiosis in Arabidopsis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463455</id><title>Vernalization-triggered expression of the antisense transcript COOLAIR is mediated by CBF genes (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.818909+00:00</updated><author><name>Myeongjune Jeon</name></author><author><name>Goowon Jeong</name></author><author><name>Youbong Hyun</name></author><author><name>Ilha Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many plants undergo vernalization, a long-term winter-triggered acceleration of flowering, to align their flowering time with spring. In Arabidopsis thaliana, this is achieved by silencing a floral repressor, FLOWERING LOCUS C (FLC). COOLAIR, an antisense noncoding RNA expressed at the FLC locus, is induced during the early phase of vernalization, preceding FLC suppression. However, the mechanism by which long-term cold induces COOLAIR is not well understood. Here, we showed that C-repeat (CRT)/dehydration-responsive elements (DREs) at the 3′-end of FLC and CRT/DRE-binding factors (CBFs) are required for vernalization-induced COOLAIR activation. The CBFs bind to CRT/DREs at the 3′-end of FLC, both in vitro and in vivo, and the CBFs levels increased gradually during vernalization. Additionally, vernalization-induced COOLAIR expression was highly suppressed in the cbfs mutant, in which all CBFs were knocked-out. Contrastingly, CBF-overexpressing plants showed COOLAIR upregulation, even at warm temperatures. We propose that COOLAIR is induced by CBFs in the early phase of vernalization but is downregulated as CBFs are evicted from closed FLC chromatin during the late vernalization phase. We also demonstrated that cbfs and COOLAIR mutants have a normal vernalization response, although they show defects in vernalization-induced COOLAIR activation, indicating that COOLAIR is not necessary for this process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463455" rel="alternate" title="Vernalization-triggered expression of the antisense transcript COOLAIR is mediated by CBF genes (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463563</id><title>LysM receptors in Coffea arabica: identification, characterization, and gene expression in response to Hemileia vastatrix (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.819098+00:00</updated><author><name>Mariana de Lima Santos</name></author><author><name>Mário Lúcio Vilela de Resende</name></author><author><name>Bárbara Alves dos Santos Ciscon</name></author><author><name>Natália Chagas Freitas</name></author><author><name>Matheus Henrique de Brito Pereira</name></author><author><name>Tharyn Reichel</name></author><author><name>Sandra Marisa Mathioni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) are recognized by pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) localized on the host plant cell wall. These receptors activate a broad-spectrum and durable defense, which are desired characteristics for disease resistance in plant breeding programs. In this study, candidate sequences for PRRs with lysin motifs (LysM) were investigated in the &lt;italic&gt;Coffea arabica&lt;/italic&gt; genome. For this, approaches based on the principle of sequence similarity, conservation of motifs and domains, phylogenetic analysis, and modulation of gene expression in response to &lt;italic&gt;Hemileia vastatrix&lt;/italic&gt; were used. The candidate sequences for PRRs in &lt;italic&gt;C. arabica&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;Ca1-LYP, Ca2-LYP, Ca1-CERK1, Ca2-CERK1, Ca-LYK4, Ca1-LYK5&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Ca2-LYK5&lt;/italic&gt;) showed high similarity with the reference PRRs used: &lt;italic&gt;Os-CEBiP, At-CERK1, At-LYK4&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;At-LYK5&lt;/italic&gt;. Moreover, the ectodomains of these sequences showed high identity or similarity with the reference sequences, indicating structural and functional conservation. The studied sequences are also phylogenetically related to the reference PRRs described in Arabidopsis, rice, and other plant species. All candidates for receptors had their expression induced after the inoculation with &lt;italic&gt;H. vastatrix&lt;/italic&gt;, since the first time of sampling at 6 hours post-inoculation (hpi). At 24 hpi, there was a significant increase in expression, for most of the receptors evaluated, and at 48 hpi, a suppression. The results showed that the candidate sequences for PRRs in the &lt;italic&gt;C. arabica&lt;/italic&gt; genome display high homology with fungal PRRs already described in the literature. Besides, they respond to pathogen inoculation and seem to be involved in the perception or signaling of fungal chitin, acting as receptors or coreceptors of this molecule. These findings represent an advance in the understanding of the basal immunity of this species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.07.463563" rel="alternate" title="LysM receptors in Coffea arabica: identification, characterization, and gene expression in response to Hemileia vastatrix (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>