<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.850790+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455944</id><title>A CCaMK/Cyclops response element in the promoter of L. japonicus Calcium-Binding Protein 1 (CBP1) mediates transcriptional activation in root symbioses (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.851033+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoyun Gong</name></author><author><name>Elaine Jensen</name></author><author><name>Simone Bucerius</name></author><author><name>Martin Parniske</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Early gene expression in arbuscular mycorrhiza (AM) and the nitrogen-fixing root nodule symbiosis (RNS) is governed by a shared regulatory complex. Yet many symbiosis-induced genes are specifically activated in only one of the two symbioses. The &lt;italic&gt;Lotus japonicus&lt;/italic&gt; T-DNA insertion line T90, carrying a promoterless &lt;italic&gt;uidA&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;GUS&lt;/italic&gt;) gene in the promoter of &lt;italic&gt;Calcium Binding Protein1&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;italic&gt;CBP1&lt;/italic&gt;) is exceptional as it exhibits GUS activity in both root endosymbioses. To identify the responsible &lt;italic&gt;cis-&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;trans&lt;/italic&gt;-acting factors, we subjected deletion/modification series of &lt;italic&gt;CBP1&lt;/italic&gt; promoter:reporter fusions to transactivation and spatio-temporal expression analysis and screened EMS-mutagenized T90 populations for aberrant &lt;italic&gt;GUS&lt;/italic&gt; expression. We identified one &lt;italic&gt;cis-&lt;/italic&gt;regulatory element required for &lt;italic&gt;GUS&lt;/italic&gt; expression in the epidermis and a second element, necessary and sufficient for transactivation by the Calcium and Calmodulin-dependent protein kinase (CCaMK) in combination with the transcription factor Cyclops and conferring gene expression during both AM and RNS. Lack of &lt;italic&gt;GUS&lt;/italic&gt; expression in T90 &lt;italic&gt;white&lt;/italic&gt; mutants could be traced to DNA hypermethylation detected in and around this element. We concluded that the CCaMK/Cyclops complex can contribute to at least three distinct gene expression patterns on its direct target promoters &lt;italic&gt;NIN&lt;/italic&gt; (RNS), &lt;italic&gt;RAM1&lt;/italic&gt; (AM), and &lt;italic&gt;CBP1&lt;/italic&gt; (AM and RNS), calling for yet-to-be identified specificity-conferring factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455944" rel="alternate" title="A CCaMK/Cyclops response element in the promoter of L. japonicus Calcium-Binding Protein 1 (CBP1) mediates transcriptional activation in root symbioses (23 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455939</id><title>Reference genome and resequencing of 305 accessions provide insights into spinach evolution, domestication and genetic basis of agronomic traits (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.851327+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaofeng Cai</name></author><author><name>Xuepeng Sun</name></author><author><name>Chenxi Xu</name></author><author><name>Honghe Sun</name></author><author><name>Xiaoli Wang</name></author><author><name>Chenhui Ge</name></author><author><name>Zhonghua Zhang</name></author><author><name>Quanxi Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhangjun Fei</name></author><author><name>Chen Jiao</name></author><author><name>Quanhua Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Spinach is a nutritious leafy vegetable belonging to the family Chenopodiaceae. Here we report a chromosome-scale reference genome assembly of spinach, which has a total size of 894.3 Mb and an N50 contig size of 23.8 Mb, with 98.3% anchored and ordered on the six chromosomes. Reconstruction of ancestral Chenopodiaceae karyotype indicates substantial genome rearrangements in spinach after its divergence from ancestral Chenopodiaceae, coinciding with high repeat content in the spinach genome. Resequencing the genomes of 305 cultivated and wild spinach accessions provides insights into spinach genetic diversity and population differentiation. Genome-wide association studies of 20 agronomical traits identify numerous significantly associated regions and candidate genes for these traits. Domestication sweeps in the spinach genome are identified, some of which are associated with important traits (e.g., leaf phenotype, bolting and flowering), demonstrating the role of artificial selection in shaping spinach phenotypic evolution. This study provides not only insights into the spinach evolution and domestication but also valuable resources for facilitating spinach breeding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455939" rel="alternate" title="Reference genome and resequencing of 305 accessions provide insights into spinach evolution, domestication and genetic basis of agronomic traits (12 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455529</id><title>Genetic compensation of triacylglycerol biosynthesis in the green microalga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.851576+00:00</updated><author><name>Yi-Ying Lee</name></author><author><name>Rudolph Park</name></author><author><name>Stephen M. Miller</name></author><author><name>Yantao Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic compensation has been proposed to explain phenotypic differences between gene knockouts and knockdowns in several metazoan and plant model systems. With the rapid development of reverse genetic tools such as CRISPR/Cas9 and RNAi in microalgae, it is increasingly important to assess whether genetic compensation affects the phenotype of engineered algal mutants. While exploring triacylglycerol (TAG) biosynthesis pathways in the model alga &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt;, it was discovered that knockout of certain genes catalyzing rate-limiting steps of TAG biosynthesis, type-2 diacylglycerol acyltransferase genes (&lt;italic&gt;DOTTs&lt;/italic&gt;), triggered genetic compensation under abiotic stress conditions. Genetic compensation of a &lt;italic&gt;DGTT1&lt;/italic&gt; null mutation by a related &lt;italic&gt;PDAT&lt;/italic&gt; gene was observed regardless of the strain background or mutagenesis approach, e.g., CRISPR/Cas 9 or insertional mutagenesis. However, no compensation was found in the &lt;italic&gt;PDAT&lt;/italic&gt; knockout mutant. The effect of &lt;italic&gt;PDAT&lt;/italic&gt; knockout was evaluated in a &lt;italic&gt;Δvtc1&lt;/italic&gt; mutant, in which &lt;italic&gt;PDAT&lt;/italic&gt; was up-regulated under stress, resulting in a 90% increase in TAG content. Knockout of &lt;italic&gt;PDAT&lt;/italic&gt; in the &lt;italic&gt;Δvtc1&lt;/italic&gt; background induced a 12.8-fold upregulation of &lt;italic&gt;DGTT1&lt;/italic&gt; and a 272.3% increase in TAG content in &lt;italic&gt;Δvtc1/pdat1&lt;/italic&gt; cells, while remaining viable. These data suggest that genetic compensation contributes to the genetic robustness of microalgal TAG biosynthetic pathways, maintaining lipid and redox homeostasis in the knockout mutants under abiotic stress. This work demonstrates examples of genetic compensation in microalgae, implies the physiological relevance of genetic compensation in TAG biosynthesis under stress, and provides guidance for future genetic engineering and mutant characterization efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genetic compensation systems have been discovered in several metazoan and plant systems to buffer deleterious mutations. With the rapid development of reverse genetic tools in microalgae, it is increasingly important to assess whether genetic compensation affects the phenotype of engineered algal mutants. We report that knockout of certain genes catalyzing rate-limiting steps of triacylglyceroal (TAG) biosynthesis triggers up-regulation of homologous genes to buffer the effect of a null mutation in &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt; under abiotic stress conditions. This work provides evidence to show physiological relevance of genetic compensation in TAG biosynthesis in the green lineage, and paves the way for future gene function analysis in microalgae.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455529" rel="alternate" title="Genetic compensation of triacylglycerol biosynthesis in the green microalga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456185</id><title>A mathematical framework for analyzing wild tomato root architecture (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.851736+00:00</updated><author><name>Arjun Chandrasekhar</name></author><author><name>Magdalena M Julkowska</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The root architecture of wild tomato, Solanum pimpinellifolium, can be viewed as a network connecting the main root to various lateral roots. Several constraints have been proposed on the structure of such biological networks, including minimizing the total amount of wire necessary for constructing the root architecture (wiring cost), and minimizing the distances (and by extension, resource transport time) between the base of the main root and the lateral roots (conduction delay). For a given set of lateral root tip locations, these two objectives compete with each other --- optimizing one results in poorer performance on the other --- raising the question how well S. pimpinellifolium root architectures balance this network design trade-off in a distributed manner. Here, we describe how well S. pimpinellifolium roots resolve this trade-off using the theory of Pareto optimality. We describe a mathematical model for characterizing the network structure and design trade-offs governing the structure of S. pimpinellifolium root architecture. We demonstrate that S. pimpinellifolium arbors construct architectures that are more optimal than would be expected by chance. Finally, we use this framework to quantify structural differences between arbors grown in the presence of salt stress, classify arbors into four distinct architectural ideotypes, and test for heritability of variation in root architecture structure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456185" rel="alternate" title="A mathematical framework for analyzing wild tomato root architecture (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456063</id><title>Gametogenesis in the green seaweed Ulva mutabilis coincides with massive transcriptional restructuring (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.851879+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaojie Liu</name></author><author><name>Jonas Blomme</name></author><author><name>Kenny Bogaert</name></author><author><name>Sofie Dhondt</name></author><author><name>Thomas Wichard</name></author><author><name>Olivier De Clerck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The molecular mechanism underlying sexual reproduction in land plants is well understood in model plants and is a target for crop improvement. However, unlike land plants, the genetic basis involved in triggering reproduction and gamete formation remains elusive in most seaweeds, which are increasingly viewed as an alternative source of functional food and feedstock for energy applications. Here, gametogenesis of Ulva mutabilis, a model organism for green seaweeds, is studied. We analyze transcriptome dynamics at different time points during gametogenesis following induction of reproduction by fragmentation and removal of sporulation inhibitors. Analyses demonstrate that 45% of the genes in the genome are differentially expressed during gametogenesis. We identified several transcription factors that potentially play a key role in the early gametogenesis of Ulva given the function of their homologs in higher plants and microalgae. In particular, the detailed expression pattern of an evolutionary conserved transcription factor containing an RWP-RK domain suggests a key role during Ulva gametogenesis. The identification of putative master regulators of gametogenesis provides a starting point for further functional characterization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456063" rel="alternate" title="Gametogenesis in the green seaweed Ulva mutabilis coincides with massive transcriptional restructuring (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455832</id><title>Stress-induced collective behavior leads to the formation of multicellular structures and the survival of the unicellular alga Chlamydomonas (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.852041+00:00</updated><author><name>Félix de Carpentier</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Maes</name></author><author><name>Christophe H. Marchand</name></author><author><name>Céline Chung</name></author><author><name>Cyrielle Durand</name></author><author><name>Pierre Crozet</name></author><author><name>Stéphane D. Lemaire</name></author><author><name>Antoine Danon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Depending on their nature, living organisms use various strategies to adapt to environmental stress conditions. Multicellular organisms implement a set of reactions involving signaling and cooperation between different types of cells. Unicellular organisms on the other hand must activate defense systems, which involve collective behaviors between individual organisms. In the unicellular model alga &lt;italic&gt;Chlamydomonas reinhardtii&lt;/italic&gt;, the existence and the function of collective behavior mechanisms in response to stress remain largely unknown. Here we report the discovery of a mechanism of abiotic stress response that Chlamydomonas can trigger to form large multicellular structures that can comprise several thousand cells. We show that these aggregates constitute an effective bulwark within which the cells are efficiently protected from the toxic environment. We have generated the first family of mutants that aggregate spontaneously, the &lt;italic&gt;socializer&lt;/italic&gt; mutants (&lt;italic&gt;saz&lt;/italic&gt;), of which we describe here in detail &lt;italic&gt;saz1&lt;/italic&gt;. We took advantage of the &lt;italic&gt;saz&lt;/italic&gt; mutants to implement a large scale multiomics approach that allowed us to show that aggregation is not the result of passive agglutination, but rather genetic reprogramming and substantial modification of the secretome. The reverse genetic analysis we conducted on some of the most promising candidates allowed us to identify the first positive and negative regulators of aggregation and to make hypotheses on how this process is controlled in Chlamydomonas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455832" rel="alternate" title="Stress-induced collective behavior leads to the formation of multicellular structures and the survival of the unicellular alga Chlamydomonas (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456097</id><title>Phylogenetic, ecological and intraindividual variability patterns in grass phytolith shape (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T08:34:31.852214+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristyna Hoskova</name></author><author><name>Jiri Neustupa</name></author><author><name>Petr Pokorny</name></author><author><name>Adela Pokorna</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Grass silica short cell (GSSC) phytoliths appear to be the most reliable source of fossil evidence for tracking the evolutionary history and paleoecology of grasses. In recent years, modern techniques have been used to quantitatively assess phytolith shape variation. This progress has widened opportunities with respect to the classification of grass fossil phytoliths. However, phylogenetic, ecological and intraindividual variability patterns in phytolith shape remain largely unexplored. The full range of intraindividual phytolith shape variation (3650 2D outlines) from 73 extant grass species, 48 genera, 18 tribes, and 8 subfamilies (with special attention paid to Pooideae) was analysed using the geometric morphometric analysis based on the semilandmarks spanning phytolith outlines. Although we showed that 2D phytolith shape is mainly driven by deep-time diversification of grass subfamilies, a closer look uncovered distinct phytolith shape variation in early-diverging lineages of Pooideae. The phylogenetic pattern in phytolith shape was successfully revealed by applying geometric morphometrics to 2D phytolith shape outlines. This finding strengthens the potential of phytoliths to track the evolutionary history and paleoecology of grasses. Moreover, geometric morphometrics of 2D phytolith shape proved to be an excellent tool for analysis requiring large sums of phytolith outlines, making it useful for quantitative palaeoecological reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456097" rel="alternate" title="Phylogenetic, ecological and intraindividual variability patterns in grass phytolith shape (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>