<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.780010+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.12.459767</id><title>Drought stress increases the expression of barley defence genes with negative consequences for infesting cereal aphids (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.780338+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel J. Leybourne</name></author><author><name>Tracy A Valentine</name></author><author><name>Kirsty Binnie</name></author><author><name>Anna Taylor</name></author><author><name>Alison J Karley</name></author><author><name>Jorunn IB Bos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Crops are exposed to myriad abiotic and biotic stressors with negative consequences. Two stressors that are expected to increase under climate change are drought and infestation with herbivorous insects, including important aphid species. Expanding our understanding of the impact drought has on the plant-aphid relationship will become increasingly important under future climate scenarios. Here we use a previously characterised plant-aphid system comprising a susceptible variety of barley, a wild relative of barley with partial-aphid resistance, and the bird cherry-oat aphid to examine the drought-plant-aphid relationship. We show that drought has a negative effect on plant physiology and aphid fitness and provide evidence to suggest that plant resistance influences aphid responses to drought stress, with the expression of aphid detoxification genes increasing under drought when feeding on the susceptible plant but decreasing on the partially-resistant plant. Furthermore, we show that the expression of thionin genes, plant defensive compounds that contribute aphid resistance, increase ten-fold in susceptible plants exposed to drought stress but remain at constant levels in the partially-resistant plant, suggesting they play an important role in modulating aphid populations. This study highlights the role of plant defensive processes in mediating the interactions between the environment, plants, and herbivorous insects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.12.459767" rel="alternate" title="Drought stress increases the expression of barley defence genes with negative consequences for infesting cereal aphids (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.16.460688</id><title>Comparative transcriptomics of seven Impatiens species (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.780583+00:00</updated><author><name>Mária Šurinová</name></author><author><name>Štepán Stočes</name></author><author><name>Tomáš Dostálek</name></author><author><name>Andrea Jarošová</name></author><author><name>Zuzana Münzbergová</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Impatiens&lt;/italic&gt; is a genus containing more than 1000 species. Thanks to its size, it is a unique system for studying species diversification in natural populations. This study focused on the characterization of novel transcriptomes from seven &lt;italic&gt;Impatiens&lt;/italic&gt; species originating from Nepal. Leave transcriptome of &lt;italic&gt;Impatines balsamina&lt;/italic&gt; L.&lt;italic&gt;, I. racemosa&lt;/italic&gt; DC.&lt;italic&gt;, I. bicornuta&lt;/italic&gt; Wall&lt;italic&gt;, I. falcifer&lt;/italic&gt; Hook&lt;italic&gt;, I. devendrae&lt;/italic&gt; Pusalkar, &lt;italic&gt;I. scullyi&lt;/italic&gt; Hook and &lt;italic&gt;I. scabrida&lt;/italic&gt; DC were sequenced and compared. Reads were &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; assembled and aligned to 92 035-226 081 contigs. We identified 14 728 orthology groups shared among all the species and 3 020 which were unique to a single species. In single species, 2536-3009 orthology groups were under selection from which 767 were common for all species. Six of the seven investigated species shared 77% of gene families with &lt;italic&gt;I. bicornuta&lt;/italic&gt; being the most distinct species. Specific gene families involved in response to different environmental stimuli were closely described. &lt;italic&gt;Impatiens bicornuta&lt;/italic&gt; selection profile shared selection on zing finger protein structures and flowering regulation and stress response proteins with the other investigated species. Overall, the study showed substantial similarity in patterns of selections on transcribed genes across the species suggesting similar evolutionary pressures. This suggests that the species group may have evolved via adaptive radiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.16.460688" rel="alternate" title="Comparative transcriptomics of seven Impatiens species (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460013</id><title>Detecting Phytophthora cinnamomi associated with dieback disease on Carya cathayensis using loop-mediated isothermal amplification (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.780752+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaoqing Tong</name></author><author><name>Jiayi Wu</name></author><author><name>Li Mei</name></author><author><name>Yongjun Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chinese hickory (&lt;italic&gt;Carya cathayensis&lt;/italic&gt; Sarg.) is an economically and ecologically important nut plant in China. Dieback and basal stem necrosis have been observed in the plants since 2016, and its recent spread has significantly affected plant growth and nut production. Therefore, a survey was conducted to evaluate the disease incidence at five sites in Linan County, China. The highest incidence was recorded at the Tuankou site at up to 11.39% in 2019. The oomycete, &lt;italic&gt;Phytophthora cinnamomi&lt;/italic&gt;, was isolated from symptomatic plant tissue and plantation soil using baiting and selective media-based detection methods and identified. Artificial infection with the representative &lt;italic&gt;P. cinnamomi&lt;/italic&gt; ST402 isolate produced vertically elongated discolorations in the outer xylem and necrotic symptoms in &lt;italic&gt;C. cathayensis&lt;/italic&gt; seedlings in a greenhouse trial. Molecular detections based on loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) specific to &lt;italic&gt;P. cinnamomi&lt;/italic&gt; ST402 were conducted. Result indicated that LAMP detection showed a high coherence level with the baiting assays for &lt;italic&gt;P. cinnamomi&lt;/italic&gt; detection in the field. This study provides the evidence of existence of high-pathogenic &lt;italic&gt;P. cinnamomi&lt;/italic&gt; in the &lt;italic&gt;C. cathayensis&lt;/italic&gt; plantation soil in China and the insights into a convenient tool developed for conducting field monitoring of this aggressive pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460013" rel="alternate" title="Detecting Phytophthora cinnamomi associated with dieback disease on Carya cathayensis using loop-mediated isothermal amplification (3 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>