<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.439323+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445531</id><title>The Phtheirospermum japonicum isopentenyltransferase PjIPT1a regulates host cytokinin responses in Arabidopsis (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.439755+00:00</updated><author><name>Anne Greifenhagen</name></author><author><name>Isabell Braunstein</name></author><author><name>Jens Pfannstiel</name></author><author><name>Satoko Yoshida</name></author><author><name>Ken Shirasu</name></author><author><name>Andreas Schaller</name></author><author><name>Thomas Spallek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The hemiparasitic plant &lt;italic&gt;Phtheirospermum japonicum&lt;/italic&gt; is a nutritional specialist that supplements its nutrient requirements by parasitizing other plants through haustoria. During parasitism, the &lt;italic&gt;Phtheirospermum&lt;/italic&gt; haustorium transfers hypertrophy-inducing cytokinins (CKs) to the infected host root. The CK biosynthesis genes required for haustorium-derived CKs and the induction of hypertrophy are still unknown. We searched for haustorium-expressed isopentenyltransferases (IPTs) that catalyse the first step of CK biosynthesis, confirmed the specific expression by &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; imaging of a promoter-reporter, and further analysed the subcellular localization, the enzymatic function, and contribution to inducing hypertrophy by studying CRISPR-Cas9 induced &lt;italic&gt;Phtheirospermum&lt;/italic&gt; mutants. &lt;italic&gt;PjIPT1a&lt;/italic&gt; was specifically expressed in intrusive cells of the haustorium close to the host vasculature. PjIPT1a and its closest homolog PjIPT1b located to the cytosol and showed isopentenyltransferases activity &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; with differences in substrate specificity. Mutating &lt;italic&gt;PjIPT1a&lt;/italic&gt; abolished parasite-induced CK responses in the host. A homolog of &lt;italic&gt;PjIPT1a&lt;/italic&gt; with shared characteristics was also identified in the related weed &lt;italic&gt;Striga hermonthica&lt;/italic&gt;. With &lt;italic&gt;PjIPT1a&lt;/italic&gt; we identified a &lt;italic&gt;bona fide&lt;/italic&gt; parasitism gene. We propose that &lt;italic&gt;PjIPT1a&lt;/italic&gt; exemplifies how parasitism-related functions evolve through gene duplications and neofunctionalization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445531" rel="alternate" title="The Phtheirospermum japonicum isopentenyltransferase PjIPT1a regulates host cytokinin responses in Arabidopsis (18 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445367</id><title>Distinct changes in mature root and growing root tip proteomes underlie physiological responses of bread wheat to salinity stress (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.440125+00:00</updated><author><name>Bhagya M. Dissanayake</name></author><author><name>Christiana Staudinger</name></author><author><name>Rana Munns</name></author><author><name>Nicolas L. Taylor</name></author><author><name>A. Harvey Millar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The impact of salinity on wheat plants is often studied by analysis of shoot responses, even though the main mechanism of tolerance is shoot Na&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; exclusion. There is a need to understand the molecular responses of root tissues that directly experience rising NaCl concentrations. We have combined analysis of root growth, ion content and respiration with proteome responses in wheat root tip and mature root tissues under saline conditions. We find significant changes in translation and protein synthesis, energy metabolism and amino acid metabolism in a root tissue specific manner. Translation and protein synthesis related proteins showed significant decreases in abundance only in root tips, as did most of the glycolytic enzymes and selected TCA cycle enzymes and ATP synthase subunits. This selective root tip proteome response indicates protein synthesis capacity and energy production were impaired under salt stress, correlating with the anatomical response of roots and reduced root tip respiration rate. Wheat roots respond directly to soil salinity, therefore shoot responses such as reduction in shoot growth and photosynthetic capacity need to be considered in light of these effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445367" rel="alternate" title="Distinct changes in mature root and growing root tip proteomes underlie physiological responses of bread wheat to salinity stress (13 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445476</id><title>Natural variation in a short region of the Acidovorax citrulli type III-secreted effector AopW1 is associated with differences in cytotoxicity (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.440470+00:00</updated><author><name>Irene Jiménez-Guerrero</name></author><author><name>Monica Sonawane</name></author><author><name>Noam Eckshtain-Levi</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Mateus Da Silva</name></author><author><name>Francisco Pérez-Montaño</name></author><author><name>Meirav Leibman-Markus</name></author><author><name>Lianet Noda-Garcia</name></author><author><name>Maya Bar</name></author><author><name>Saul Burdman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial fruit blotch (BFB) is a serious disease of melon and watermelon caused by the Gram-negative bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Acidovorax citrulli&lt;/italic&gt;. The strains of the pathogen can be divided into two major genetic groups, I and II. While group I strains are strongly associated with melon, group II strains are more aggressive on watermelon. Like many pathogenic bacteria, &lt;italic&gt;A. citrulli&lt;/italic&gt; secretes a variety of protein effectors to the host cell via the type III secretion system. In the present study, we characterized AopW1, an &lt;italic&gt;A. citrulli&lt;/italic&gt; type III-secreted effector that shares similarity with the actin cytoskeletondisrupting effector HopW1 of &lt;italic&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/italic&gt; and with effectors from other plant-pathogenic bacterial species. &lt;italic&gt;aopW1&lt;/italic&gt; is present in group I and II strains, encoding products of 485 amino acids. Although highly conserved in most of the sequence, AopW1 has a highly variable region (HVR) within amino acid positions 147 to 192, including 14 amino acid differences between groups. Here we show that group I AopW1 is more toxic to yeast and plant cells than group II AopW1, having a stronger actin filament disruption activity, and increased ability to reduce plant callose deposition. We demonstrate the role of some of these 14 amino acid positions in determining the phenotypic differences between the two versions of the effector. Moreover, cellular analyses revealed that in addition to the interaction with actin filaments, AopW1 is localized to the endoplasmic reticulum, chloroplasts, and early and recycling plant endosomes, with differences observed between the two AopW1 versions. Finally, we show that overexpression of the endosome-associated protein EHD1 that increases cellular recycling, attenuates the toxic effects exerted by AopW1 and increases defence responses. This study provides insights into the HopW1 family of bacterial effectors and their interactions with the plant cell and provides first evidence on the involvement of EHD1 in response to biotic stress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445476" rel="alternate" title="Natural variation in a short region of the Acidovorax citrulli type III-secreted effector AopW1 is associated with differences in cytotoxicity (13 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445633</id><title>Sorghum Root Epigenetic Landscape During Limiting Phosphorus Conditions (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.441011+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Gladman</name></author><author><name>Barbara Hufnagel</name></author><author><name>Michael Regulski</name></author><author><name>Zhigang Liu</name></author><author><name>Xiaofei Wang</name></author><author><name>Kapeel Chougule</name></author><author><name>Leon Kochian</name></author><author><name>Jurandir Magalhaes</name></author><author><name>Doreen Ware</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Efficient acquisition and use of available phosphorus from the soil is crucial for plant growth, development, and yield. With an ever-increasing acreage of croplands with suboptimal available soil phosphorus, genetic improvement of sorghum germplasm for enhanced phosphorus acquisition from soil is crucial to increasing agricultural output and reducing inputs, while confronted with a growing world population and uncertain climate. Sorghum bicolor is a globally important commodity for food, fodder, and forage. Known for robust tolerance to heat, drought, and other abiotic stresses, its capacity for optimal phosphorus use efficiency (PUE) is still being investigated for optimized root system architectures (RSA). Whilst a few RSA-influencing genes have been identified in sorghum and other grasses, the epigenetic impact on expression and tissue-specific activation of candidate PUE genes remains elusive. Here, we present transcriptomic, epigenetic, and regulatory network profiling of RSA modulation in the BTx623 sorghum background in response to limiting phosphorus (LP) conditions. We show that during LP, sorghum RSA is remodeled to increase root length and surface area, likely enhancing its ability to acquire P. Global DNA 5-methylcytosine and H3K4 and H3K27 trimethylation levels decrease in response to LP, while H3K4me3 peaks and DNA hypomethylated regions contain recognition motifs of numerous developmental and nutrient responsive transcription factors that display disparate expression patterns between different root tissues (primary root apex, elongation zone, and lateral root apex). Suggesting that epigenetic shifts during growth on LP results in targeted gene expression in a tissue-specific manner that optimizes the RSA for improved P uptake.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to low P, epigenetic and transcriptional changes stimulate lateral root growth in Sorghum bicolor BTx623, increasing the root surface area for enhanced “mining” of P from the soil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445633" rel="alternate" title="Sorghum Root Epigenetic Landscape During Limiting Phosphorus Conditions (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>