<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.494250+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445036</id><title>RNA silencing by CRISPR in plants does not require Cas13 (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.494627+00:00</updated><author><name>VK Sharma</name></author><author><name>S Marla</name></author><author><name>WG Zheng</name></author><author><name>D Mishra</name></author><author><name>J Huang</name></author><author><name>W Zhang</name></author><author><name>GP Morris</name></author><author><name>DE Cook</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA-targeting CRISPR-Cas can provide potential advantages over DNA editing, such as avoiding pleiotropic effects of genome editing, providing precise spatiotemporal regulation and expanded function including anti-viral immunity. Here, we report the use of CRISPR-Cas13 in plants to reduce both viral and endogenous RNA. Unexpectedly, we discovered that crRNA designed to guide Cas13 could, in the absence of the Cas13 protein, cause substantial reduction in RNA levels as well. We demonstrate Cas13-independent guide-induced gene silencing (GIGS) in three plant species, including stable transgenic &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/italic&gt;. We determined that GIGS utilizes endogenous RNAi machinery despite the fact that crRNA are unlike canonical triggers of RNAi such as miRNA, hairpins or long double-stranded RNA. These results suggest that GIGS offers a novel and flexible approach to RNA reduction with potential benefits over existing technologies for crop improvement. Our results demonstrate that GIGS is active across a range of plant species, evidence similar to recent findings in an insect system, which suggests that GIGS is potentially active across many eukaryotes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.20.445036" rel="alternate" title="RNA silencing by CRISPR in plants does not require Cas13 (47 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445339</id><title>Positive Selection and Heat-Response Transcriptomes Reveal Adaptive Features of the Arabidopsis Desert Relative, Anastatica hierochuntica (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-24T05:58:18.497107+00:00</updated><author><name>Gil Eshel</name></author><author><name>Nick Duppen</name></author><author><name>Guannan Wang</name></author><author><name>Dong-Ha Oh</name></author><author><name>Yana Kazachkova</name></author><author><name>Pawel Herzyk</name></author><author><name>Anna Amtmann</name></author><author><name>Michal Gordon</name></author><author><name>Vered Chalifa-Caspi</name></author><author><name>Michelle Arland Oscar</name></author><author><name>Shirli Bar-David</name></author><author><name>Amy Marshall-Colon</name></author><author><name>Maheshi Dassanayake</name></author><author><name>Simon Barak</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Extremophytes have evolved genetic adaptations for tolerance to abiotic stresses characteristic of their extreme environments. Comparative molecular analyses of &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; with its halophytic Brassicaceae relatives have revealed that the halophytes exist in a pre-adapted, stress-ready state. We generated a reference transcriptome of the heat-tolerant &lt;italic&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; desert relative, &lt;italic&gt;Anastatica hierochuntica&lt;/italic&gt; (True Rose of Jericho) and used two approaches to identify adaptations that could facilitate an extremophyte lifestyle: (i) We identified common positively selected extremophyte genes that target stomatal opening, nutrient acquisition, and UV-B induced DNA repair. In &lt;italic&gt;A. hierochuntica&lt;/italic&gt;, we identified genes consistent with a photoperiod-insensitive, early-flowering phenotype that could be advantageous in the desert environment; (ii) Using RNA-seq analysis, we demonstrate that &lt;italic&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;A. hierochuntica&lt;/italic&gt; transcriptomes exhibit similar transcriptional adjustment in response to heat, and that the &lt;italic&gt;A. hierochuntica&lt;/italic&gt; transcriptome does not exist in a heat stress-ready state, unlike its halophytic relatives. Furthermore, the &lt;italic&gt;A. hierochuntica&lt;/italic&gt; global transcriptome as well as orthologs belonging to specific functional groups, display a lower basal expression but higher heat-induced expression than in &lt;italic&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/italic&gt;. We suggest that the increased reactiveness of the &lt;italic&gt;A. hierochuntica&lt;/italic&gt; transcriptome in response to heat stress is related to specific conditions native to a desert environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.23.445339" rel="alternate" title="Positive Selection and Heat-Response Transcriptomes Reveal Adaptive Features of the Arabidopsis Desert Relative, Anastatica hierochuntica (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>