<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.465271+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473005</id><title>Bacterial Outer Membrane Vesicles Induce a Transcriptional Shift in Arabidopsis Towards Immune System Activation Leading to Suppression of Pathogen Growth in Planta (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.465765+00:00</updated><author><name>Laura Chalupowicz</name></author><author><name>Gideon Mordukhovich</name></author><author><name>Nofar Assoline</name></author><author><name>Leron Katsir</name></author><author><name>Noa Sela</name></author><author><name>Ofir Bahar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gram negative bacteria form spherical blebs on their cell periphery, which later dissociate and released into the surrounding environment. Previous studies have shown that these nano scale structures, derived primarily from the bacterial outer membrane and are termed outer membrane vesicles (OMVs), induce typical immune outputs in both mammals and plants. On the other hand, these same structures have been shown to promote infection and disease. To better understand the broad transcriptional change plants undergo following exposure to OMVs, we treated &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; (Arabidopsis) seedlings with OMVs purified from the Gram-negative plant pathogenic bacterium &lt;italic&gt;Xanthomonas campestris&lt;/italic&gt; pv. &lt;italic&gt;campestris&lt;/italic&gt; and performed RNA-seq analysis on OMV- and mock-treated samples at 2, 6 and 24 h post challenge. We found that the most pronounced transcriptional shift occurred in the first two time points, as was reflected by both the number of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) and the average fold change. Gene ontology enrichment analysis revealed that OMVs induce a major transcriptional shift in Arabidopsis towards immune system activation, upregulating a multitude of immune-related pathways including a variety of immune receptors and transcriptional factors. Comparing Arabidopsis response to OMVs and to single purified elicitors, revealed that while OMVs induce a similar suite of genes and pathways as single elicitors, some differential pathways activated by OMVs were detected including response to drug and apoptosis, which may indicate exposure to toxic compounds via OMV. To examine whether the observed transcriptional shift in Arabidopsis leads to an effective immune response, plants were pretreated with OMVs and then inoculated with a bacterial pathogen. OMV-mediated priming led to a significant reduction in bacterial titer in inoculated leaves two days following inoculation. Mutations in the elongation factor receptor (EFR), flagellin receptor (FLS2), or the brassinosteroid-insensitive 1–associated kinase (BAK1) receptor, did not significantly affect OMV-priming. All together these results show that OMV induce a broad transcriptional shift in Arabidopsis leading to upregulation of multiple immune pathways, and that this transcriptional change is reflected in the ability to better resist bacterial infection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473005" rel="alternate" title="Bacterial Outer Membrane Vesicles Induce a Transcriptional Shift in Arabidopsis Towards Immune System Activation Leading to Suppression of Pathogen Growth in Planta (9 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473855</id><title>Photosynthetic light harvesting and thylakoid organization in a CRISPR/Cas9 Arabidopsis thaliana LHCB1 knockout mutant. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.466049+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamed Sattari Vayghan</name></author><author><name>Wojciech J Nawrocki</name></author><author><name>Christo Schiphorst</name></author><author><name>Dimitri Tolleter</name></author><author><name>Hu Chen</name></author><author><name>Veronique Douet</name></author><author><name>Gaetan Glauser</name></author><author><name>Giovanni Finazzi</name></author><author><name>Roberta Croce</name></author><author><name>Emilie Wientjes</name></author><author><name>Fiamma Longoni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Light absorbed by chlorophylls of photosystem II and I drives oxygenic photosynthesis. Light-harvesting complexes increase the absorption cross-section of these photosystems. Furthermore, these complexes play a central role in photoprotection by dissipating the excess of absorbed light energy in an inducible and regulated fashion. In higher plants, the main light-harvesting complex is the trimeric LHCII. In this work, we used CRISPR/Cas9 to knockout the five genes encoding LHCB1, which is the major component of the trimeric LHCII. In absence of LHCB1 the accumulation of the other LHCII isoforms was only slightly increased, thereby resulting in chlorophyll loss leading to a pale green phenotype and growth delay. Photosystem II absorption cross-section was smaller while photosystem I absorption cross-section was unaffected. This altered the chlorophyll repartition between the two photosystems, favoring photosystem I excitation. The equilibrium of the photosynthetic electron transport was partially maintained by a lower photosystem I over photosystem II reaction center ratio and by the dephosphorylation of LHCII and photosystem II. Loss of LHCB1 altered the thylakoid structure, with less membrane layers per grana stack and reduced grana width. Stable LHCB1 knock out lines allow characterizing the role of this protein in light harvesting and acclimation and pave the way for future in vivo mutational analyses of LHCII.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473855" rel="alternate" title="Photosynthetic light harvesting and thylakoid organization in a CRISPR/Cas9 Arabidopsis thaliana LHCB1 knockout mutant. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473296</id><title>ROOT PENETRATION INDEX 3, a major quantitative trait locus (QTL) associated with root system penetrability in Arabidopsis. (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.466319+00:00</updated><author><name>Elohim Bello Bello</name></author><author><name>Thelma Y. Rico Cambron</name></author><author><name>Ruben Rellan Alvarez</name></author><author><name>Luis Rafael Herrera-Estrella</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Soil mechanical impedance precludes root penetration, confining root system development to shallow soil horizons where mobile nutrients are scarce. Using a two-phase-agar system, we characterized Arabidopsis thaliana responses to low and high mechanical impedance at three root penetration stages. We found that seedlings whose roots fail to penetrate agar barriers show drastic changes in shoot and root morphology, while those capable of penetrating have only minor morphological effects. The assessment of 21 Arabidopsis accessions revealed that primary root penetrability (PRP) varies widely among accessions. To search for quantitative trait loci (QTLs) associated to root system penetrability, we evaluated a recombinant inbred population (RIL) derived from Landsberg erecta (Ler-0, with a high PRP) and Shahdara (Sha, with a low PRP) accessions. QTL analysis revealed a major-effect QTL localized in chromosome 3 (q-RPI3), which accounted for 29.98% (LOD = 8.82) of the total phenotypic variation. Employing an introgression line (IL-321), with a homozygous q-RPI3 region from Sha in the Ler-0 genetic background, we demonstrated that q-RPI3 plays a crucial role in root penetrability. This multiscale study revels new insights into root plasticity during the penetration process in hard agar layers, natural variation and genetic architecture behind primary root penetrability in Arabidopsis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473296" rel="alternate" title="ROOT PENETRATION INDEX 3, a major quantitative trait locus (QTL) associated with root system penetrability in Arabidopsis. (4 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>