<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.767476+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450226</id><title>Single-cell RNA-sequencing of Nicotiana attenuata petal cells reveals the entire biosynthetic pathway of a floral scent (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.767918+00:00</updated><author><name>Moonyoung Kang</name></author><author><name>Yuri Choi</name></author><author><name>Hyeonjin Kim</name></author><author><name>Sang-Gyu Kim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High-throughput single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) identifies distinct cell populations based on cell-to-cell heterogeneity in gene expression. By examining the distribution of the density of gene expression profiles, the metabolic features of each cell population can be observed. Here, we employ the scRNA-seq technique to reveal the entire biosynthetic pathway of a flower volatile. The corolla (petals) of the wild tobacco &lt;italic&gt;Nicotiana attenuata&lt;/italic&gt; emits a bouquet of scents that are composed mainly of benzylacetone (BA), a rare floral volatile. Protoplasts from the &lt;italic&gt;N. attenuata&lt;/italic&gt; corolla were isolated at three different time points, and the transcript levels of &amp;gt;16,000 genes were analyzed in 3,756 single cells. We performed unsupervised clustering analysis to determine which cell clusters were involved in BA biosynthesis. The biosynthetic pathway of BA was uncovered by analyzing gene co-expression in scRNA-seq datasets and by silencing candidate genes in the corolla. In conclusion, the high-resolution spatiotemporal atlas of gene expression provided by scRNA-seq reveals the molecular features underlying cell-type-specific metabolism in a plant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450226" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell RNA-sequencing of Nicotiana attenuata petal cells reveals the entire biosynthetic pathway of a floral scent (19 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.27.450062</id><title>Herbivore feeding behavior validates optimal defense theory for specialized metabolites within plants (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.768168+00:00</updated><author><name>Pascal Hunziker</name></author><author><name>Sophie Konstanze Lambertz</name></author><author><name>Konrad Weber</name></author><author><name>Christoph Crocoll</name></author><author><name>Barbara Ann Halkier</name></author><author><name>Alexander Schulz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Numerous plants protect themselves from attackers using specialized metabolites. The biosynthesis of these deterrent, often toxic metabolites is costly, as their synthesis diverts energy and resources on account of growth and development. How plants diversify investments into growth and defense is explained by the optimal defense theory. The central prediction of the optimal defense theory is that plants maximize growth and defense by concentrating specialized metabolites in tissues that are decisive for fitness. To date, supporting physiological evidence merely relies on the correlation between plant metabolite distribution and animal feeding preference. Here, we use glucosinolates as a model to examine the effect of changes in chemical defense distribution on actual feeding behavior. Taking advantage of the uniform glucosinolate distribution in transporter mutants, we show that high glucosinolate accumulation in tissues important to fitness protects them by guiding larvae of a generalist herbivore to feed on other tissues. Moreover, we show that mature leaves of &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; supply young leaves with glucosinolates to optimize defense against herbivores. Our study provides physiological evidence for the central hypothesis of the optimal defense theory and sheds light on the importance of integrating glucosinolate biosynthesis and transport for optimizing plant defense.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.27.450062" rel="alternate" title="Herbivore feeding behavior validates optimal defense theory for specialized metabolites within plants (9 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>