<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv plant-biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.758561+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453699</id><title>Supra-physiological levels of gibberellins/DELLAs modify the root cell size/number and the root architecture in root tips of A. thaliana seedlings. Connections to the root hair patterning and abundance (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.758826+00:00</updated><author><name>Iva McCarthy-Suárez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;A previous study (McCarthy-Suárez, 2021) showed that growing &lt;italic&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; seedlings for 5 days under excessive levels of gibberellins (GAs)/DELLAs altered the arrangement, shape and frequency of root hairs in root tips. Because no changes in the distribution or number of root hairs occurred when the gai-1 (gibberellin-insensitive-1) DELLA was over-expressed at the root epidermis, it was concluded that the GAs/DELLAs might regulate the root hair patterning and abundance in &lt;italic&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; seedlings by acting from the root sub-epidermal tissues. In the present study, microscopy analyses showed that excessive levels of GAs/DELLAs also modified the size and number of root tip cells in &lt;italic&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; seedlings. While excessive DELLAs shortened and widened the root epidermal, cortical, endodermal and pericycle cells, excessive GAs, excepting the epidermal cells, generally narrowed them. However, no changes of root cell size occurred when gai-1 was over-expressed at the root epidermis. In addition, high levels of DELLAs often induced extra cells at the root epidermis, cortex, endodermis and pericycle, whereas high levels of GAs sometimes induced extra cells at the root cortex and pericycle. On the other hand, excessive levels of DELLAs enhanced the outgrowth of lateral roots in root tips, unlike excessive levels of GAs. Thus, the results of this study suggest that supra-physiological levels of GAs/DELLAs might modify the size/number of root tip cells by acting from the root sub-epidermal tissues. This, in turn, might impact on the patterning and abundance of root hairs and on the root architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453699" rel="alternate" title="Supra-physiological levels of gibberellins/DELLAs modify the root cell size/number and the root architecture in root tips of A. thaliana seedlings. Connections to the root hair patterning and abundance (9 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453319</id><title>Pectin remodeling belongs to a homeostatic system and triggers transcriptomic and hormonal modulations (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.758999+00:00</updated><author><name>François Jobert</name></author><author><name>Stéphanie Guénin</name></author><author><name>Aline Voxeur</name></author><author><name>Kieran J. D. Lee</name></author><author><name>Sophie Bouton</name></author><author><name>Fabien Sénéchal</name></author><author><name>Ludivine Hocq</name></author><author><name>Gaëlle Mongelard</name></author><author><name>Hervé Demailly</name></author><author><name>Petra Amakorová</name></author><author><name>Miroslav Strnad</name></author><author><name>Samantha Vernhettes</name></author><author><name>Gregory Mouille</name></author><author><name>Serge Pilard</name></author><author><name>J. Paul Knox</name></author><author><name>Ondřej Novák</name></author><author><name>Jérôme Pelloux</name></author><author><name>Laurent Gutierrez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pectins occur in primary cell walls and consist of multiblock co-polymers among which homogalacturonan (HG) is the simplest and most abundant form. Methylesterification patterns of HG are tuned by pectin methylesterases (PMEs), the activities of which are controlled by specific inhibitors (PMEIs). By impacting cell wall mechanical properties, PME-mediated regulation of HG methylesterification plays a major role in several developmental processes, including seed germination and dark-grown hypocotyl elongation. Arabidopsis &lt;italic&gt;PME36&lt;/italic&gt; is preferentially expressed during the late stage of seed development and, using the knock-out mutant &lt;italic&gt;pme36-1&lt;/italic&gt;, we show here that PME36 is required to implement the characteristic pattern of de-methylesterified pectin in the mature seed. Surprisingly, while this pattern is strongly impaired in &lt;italic&gt;pme36-1&lt;/italic&gt; mature seed, no phenotypical effect is observed in the mutant during seed germination and dark-grown hypocotyl elongation, suggesting the existence of a compensatory mechanism overcoming the defect in pectin de-methylesterification. By analyzing hormone contents and gene expression, a strong, dynamic, and long-lasting physiological disorder is revealed in the mutant. These results suggest the existence of complex connections between pectin remodeling, transcriptomic regulations and hormonal homeostasis, modulating several physiological parameters to ensure the maintenance of a normal seed-to-seedling developmental program in &lt;italic&gt;pme36-1&lt;/italic&gt;. Considered for a long time as an end-point passive effector mainly involved in modification of cell wall mechanics, the role of pectin methylesterification needs to be reconsidered as a modulator acting upstream of diverse regulatory pathways involved in plant development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.22.453319" rel="alternate" title="Pectin remodeling belongs to a homeostatic system and triggers transcriptomic and hormonal modulations (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453727</id><title>Miniature inverted-repeat transposable elements drive rapid microRNA diversification in angiosperms (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T06:56:54.759257+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhonglong Guo</name></author><author><name>Zheng Kuang</name></author><author><name>Yihan Tao</name></author><author><name>Haotian Wang</name></author><author><name>Miaomiao Wan</name></author><author><name>Chen Hao</name></author><author><name>Fei Shen</name></author><author><name>Xiaozeng Yang</name></author><author><name>Lei Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are rapidly evolving endogenous small RNAs programing organism function and behavior. Although models for miRNA origination have been proposed based on sporadic cases, the genomic mechanisms driving swift diversification of the miRNA repertoires in plants remain elusive. Here, by comprehensively analyzing 20 phylogenetically representative plant species, we identified miniature inverted-repeat transposable elements (MITEs) as the predominant genomic sources for de novo miRNAs in angiosperms. Our data illustrated a transposition-transcription process whereby properly sized MITEs transposed into active genic regions could be converted into new miRNAs, termed MITE-miRNAs, in as few as 20 generations. We showed that this molecular domestication mechanism leads to a possible evolutionary arms race between the MITEs and the host genomes that rapidly and continuously changes the miRNA repertoires. We found that the MITE-miRNAs are selected for targeting genes associated with plant adaptation and habitat expansion, thereby constituting a genomic innovation potentially underlying angiosperm megadiversity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453727" rel="alternate" title="Miniature inverted-repeat transposable elements drive rapid microRNA diversification in angiosperms (6 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>