<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular plant biology preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.257163+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/plant-biology/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457556</id><title>Interactions between a mechanosensitive channel and cell wall integrity signaling influence pollen germination in Arabidopsis thaliana (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-30T06:18:32.257420+00:00</updated><author><name>Yanbing Wang</name></author><author><name>Joshua Coomey</name></author><author><name>Kari Miller</name></author><author><name>Gregory S. Jensen</name></author><author><name>Elizabeth S. Haswell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cells employ multiple systems to maintain cellular integrity, including mechanosensitive (MS) ion channels and the cell wall integrity (CWI) pathway. Here, we use pollen as a model system to ask how these different mechanisms are interconnected at the cellular level. MscS-Like (MSL)8 is an MS channel required to protect &lt;italic&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/italic&gt; pollen from osmotic challenges during &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; rehydration, germination and tube growth. New CRISPR/Cas9 and artificial microRNA-generated &lt;italic&gt;msl8&lt;/italic&gt; alleles produced unexpected pollen phenotypes, including the ability to germinate a tube after bursting, dramatic defects in cell wall structure and disorganized callose deposition at the germination site. We document complex genetic interactions between &lt;italic&gt;MSL8&lt;/italic&gt; and two previously established components of the CWI pathway, &lt;italic&gt;MARIS&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;ANXUR1/2&lt;/italic&gt;. Overexpression of &lt;italic&gt;MARIS&lt;sup&gt;R240C&lt;/sup&gt;-FP&lt;/italic&gt; suppressed the bursting, germination, and callose deposition phenotypes of &lt;italic&gt;msl8&lt;/italic&gt; mutant pollen. Null &lt;italic&gt;msl8&lt;/italic&gt; alleles suppressed the internalized callose structures observed in &lt;italic&gt;MARIS&lt;sup&gt;R240C&lt;/sup&gt;-FP&lt;/italic&gt; lines. Similarly, &lt;italic&gt;MSL8-YFP&lt;/italic&gt; overexpression suppressed bursting in the &lt;italic&gt;anxur1/2&lt;/italic&gt; mutant background, while &lt;italic&gt;anxur1/2&lt;/italic&gt; alleles reduced the strong rings of callose around ungerminated pollen grains in &lt;italic&gt;MSL8-YFP&lt;/italic&gt; over-expressors. These data show that MS ion channels modulate callose deposition in pollen and provides evidence that cell wall and membrane surveillance systems coordinate in a complex manner to maintain cell integrity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457556" rel="alternate" title="Interactions between a mechanosensitive channel and cell wall integrity signaling influence pollen germination in Arabidopsis thaliana (7 tweets)"/><category term="Plant Biology"/><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>