<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.239195+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.466958</id><title>amica: an interactive and user-friendly web-platform for the analysis of proteomics data (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.239604+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Didusch</name></author><author><name>Moritz Madern</name></author><author><name>Markus Hartl</name></author><author><name>Manuela Baccarini</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantitative proteomics has become an increasingly prominent tool in the study of life sciences. A substantial hurdle for many biologists are, however, the intricacies involved in the associated high troughput data analysis. In order to facilitate this task for users with little background knowledge in proteomics, we have developed amica, a freely available open-source web-based software that accepts proteomic input files from different sources and provides quality control, differential expression, biological network and over-representation analysis on the basis of minimal user input. Scientists can use amica interactively to compare proteins across multiple groups, create customized output graphics, and ultimately export the results in a tab-separated format that can be shared with collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and Implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code for the application, input data and documentation can be accessed online at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/tbaccata/amica"&gt;https://github.com/tbaccata/amica&lt;/ext-link&gt; and is also incorporated in the web application. A freely available version of amica is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioapps.maxperutzlabs.ac.at/app/amica"&gt;https://bioapps.maxperutzlabs.ac.at/app/amica&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;sebastian.didusch@univie.ac.at&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.466958" rel="alternate" title="amica: an interactive and user-friendly web-platform for the analysis of proteomics data (25 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469797</id><title>Using AnnoTree to get more assignments, faster, in DIAMOND+MEGAN microbiome analysis (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.239785+00:00</updated><author><name>Anupam Gautam</name></author><author><name>Hendrik Felderhoff</name></author><author><name>Caner Bağci</name></author><author><name>Daniel H. Huson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In microbiome analysis, one main approach is to align metagenomic sequencing reads against a protein-reference database such as NCBI-nr, and then to perform taxonomic and functional binning based on the alignments. This approach is embodied, for example, in the standard DIAMOND+MEGAN analysis pipeline, which first aligns reads against NCBI-nr using DIAMOND and then performs taxonomic and functional binning using MEGAN. Here we propose the use of the AnnoTree protein database, rather than NCBI-nr, in such alignment-based analyses to determine the prokaryotic content of metagenomic samples. We demonstrate a 2-fold speedup over the usage of the prokaryotic part of NCBI-nr, and increased assignment rates, in particular, assigning twice as many reads to KEGG. In addition to binning to the NCBI taxonomy, MEGAN now also bins to the GTDB taxonomy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;IMPORTANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NCBI-nr database is not explicitly designed for the purpose of microbiome analysis and its increasing size makes its unwieldy and computationally expensive for this purpose. The AnnoTree protein database is only one quarter the size of the full NCBI-nr database and is explicitly designed for metagenomic analysis, and so should be supported by alignment-based pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469797" rel="alternate" title="Using AnnoTree to get more assignments, faster, in DIAMOND+MEGAN microbiome analysis (21 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469703</id><title>PerSVade: Personalized Structural Variation detection in your species of interest (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.239918+00:00</updated><author><name>Miquel Àngel Schikora-Tamarit</name></author><author><name>Toni Gabaldón</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural variants (SVs) like translocations, deletions, and other rearrangements underlie genetic and phenotypic variation. SVs are often overlooked due to difficult detection from short-read sequencing. Most algorithms yield low recall on humans, but the performance in other organisms is unclear. Similarly, despite remarkable differences across species’ genomes, most approaches use parameters optimized for humans. To overcome this and enable species-tailored approaches, we developed perSVade (personalized Structural Variation Detection), a pipeline that identifies SVs in a way that is optimized for any input sample. Starting from short reads, perSVade uses simulations on the reference genome to choose the best SV calling parameters. The output includes the optimally-called SVs and the accuracy, useful to assess the confidence in the results. In addition, perSVade can call small variants and copy-number variations. In summary, perSVade automatically identifies several types of genomic variation from short reads using sample-optimized parameters. We validated that perSVade increases the SV calling accuracy on simulated variants for six diverse eukaryotes, and on datasets of validated human variants. Importantly, we found no universal set of “optimal” parameters, which underscores the need for species-specific parameter optimization. PerSVade will improve our understanding about the role of SVs in non-human organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469703" rel="alternate" title="PerSVade: Personalized Structural Variation detection in your species of interest (21 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469568</id><title>A flexible workflow for building spectral libraries from narrow window data independent acquisition mass spectrometry data (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240037+00:00</updated><author><name>Lilian R. Heil</name></author><author><name>William E. Fondrie</name></author><author><name>Christopher D. McGann</name></author><author><name>Alexander J. Federation</name></author><author><name>William S. Noble</name></author><author><name>Michael J. MacCoss</name></author><author><name>Uri Keich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advances in library-based methods for peptide detection from data independent acquisition (DIA) mass spectrometry have made it possible to detect and quantify tens of thousands of peptides in a single mass spectrometry run. However, many of these methods rely on a comprehensive, high quality spectral library containing information about the expected retention time and fragmentation patterns of peptides in the sample. Empirical spectral libraries are often generated through data-dependent acquisition and may suffer from biases as a result. Spectral libraries can be generated &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; but these models are not trained to handle all possible post-translational modifications. Here, we propose a false discovery rate controlled spectrum-centric search workflow to generate spectral libraries directly from gas-phase fractionated DIA tandem mass spectrometry data. We demonstrate that this strategy is able to detect phosphorylated peptides and can be used to generate a spectral library for accurate peptide detection and quantitation in wide window DIA data. We compare the results of this search workflow to other library-free approaches and demonstrate that our search is competitive in terms of accuracy and sensitivity. These results demonstrate that the proposed workflow has the capacity to generate spectral libraries while avoiding the limitations of other methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469568" rel="alternate" title="A flexible workflow for building spectral libraries from narrow window data independent acquisition mass spectrometry data (17 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469628</id><title>IReNA: integrated regulatory network analysis of single-cell transcriptomes (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240181+00:00</updated><author><name>Junyao Jiang</name></author><author><name>Seth Blackshaw</name></author><author><name>Jiang Qian</name></author><author><name>Jie Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) is widely used to profile gene expression, few methods are available to infer gene regulatory networks using scRNA-seq data. Here, we developed and extended IReNA (Integrated Regulatory Network Analysis) to perform regulatory network analysis using scRNA-seq profiles. Four features are developed for IReNA. First, regulatory networks are divided into different modules which represent distinct biological functions. Second, transcription factors significantly regulating each gene module can be identified. Third, regulatory relationships among modules can be inferred. Fourth, IReNA can integrate ATAC-seq data into regulatory network analysis. If ATAC-seq data is available, both transcription factor footprints and binding motifs are used to refine regulatory relationships among co-expressed genes. Using public datasets, we showed that integrated network analysis of scRNA-seq data with ATAC-seq data identified a higher fraction of known regulators than scRNA-seq data alone. Moreover, IReNA provided a better performance of network analysis than currently available methods. Beyond the reconstruction of regulatory networks, IReNA can modularize regulatory networks, and identify key regulators and significant regulatory relationships for modules, facilitating the systems-level understanding of biological regulatory mechanisms. The R package IReNA is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jiang-junyao/IReNA"&gt;https://github.com/jiang-junyao/IReNA&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Key points&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="order"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have developed IReNA, a new method for reconstructing regulatory networks using either scRNA-seq and ATAC-seq data or scRNA-seq data alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;IReNA can establish modular regulatory networks to identify key regulatory factors and statistically significant regulatory relationships among modules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through analyzing three public scRNA-seq datasets, IReNA shows better performance on identifying known regulators than Rcistarget, the most widely used alternative method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469628" rel="alternate" title="IReNA: integrated regulatory network analysis of single-cell transcriptomes (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469509</id><title>A computationally efficient clustering linear combination approach to jointly analyze multiple phenotypes for GWAS (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240305+00:00</updated><author><name>Meida Wang</name></author><author><name>Shuanglin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Qiuying Sha</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There has been an increasing interest in joint analysis of multiple phenotypes in genome-wide association studies (GWAS) because jointly analyzing multiple phenotypes may increase statistical power to detect genetic variants associated with complex diseases or traits. Recently, many statistical methods have been developed for joint analysis of multiple phenotypes in genetic association studies, including the Clustering Linear Combination (CLC) method. The CLC method works particularly well with phenotypes that have natural groupings, but due to the unknown number of clusters for a given data, the final test statistic of CLC method is the minimum p-value among all p-values of the CLC test statistics obtained from each possible number of clusters. Therefore, a simulation procedure must be used to evaluate the p-value of the final test statistic. This makes the CLC method computationally demanding. We develop a new method called computationally efficient CLC (ceCLC) to test the association between multiple phenotypes and a genetic variant. Instead of using the minimum p-value as the test statistic in the CLC method, ceCLC uses the Cauchy combination test to combine all p-values of the CLC test statistics obtained from each possible number of clusters. The test statistic of ceCLC approximately follows a standard Cauchy distribution, so the p-value can be obtained from the cumulative density function without the need for the simulation procedure. Through extensive simulation studies and application on the COPDGene data, the results demonstrate that the type I error rates of ceCLC are effectively controlled in different simulation settings and ceCLC either outperforms all other methods or has statistical power that is very close to the most powerful method with which it has been compared.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469509" rel="alternate" title="A computationally efficient clustering linear combination approach to jointly analyze multiple phenotypes for GWAS (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469984</id><title>DeepSpot: a deep neural network for RNA spot enhancement in smFISH microscopy images (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240422+00:00</updated><author><name>Emmanuel Bouilhol</name></author><author><name>Edgar Lefevre</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Dartigues</name></author><author><name>Robyn Brackin</name></author><author><name>Anca Flavia Savulescu</name></author><author><name>Macha Nikolski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Detection of RNA spots in single molecule FISH microscopy images remains a difficult task especially when applied to large volumes of data. The small size of RNA spots combined with high noise level of images often requires a manual adaptation of the spot detection thresholds for each image. In this work we introduce DeepSpot, a Deep Learning based tool specifically designed to enhance RNA spots which enables spot detection without need to resort to image per image parameter tuning. We show how our method can enable the downstream accurate detection of spots. The architecture of DeepSpot is inspired by small object detection approaches. It incorporates dilated convolutions into a module specifically designed for the Context Aggregation for Small Object (CASO) and uses Residual Convolutions to propagate this information along the network. This enables DeepSpot to enhance all RNA spots to the same intensity and thus circumvents the need for parameter tuning. We evaluated how easily spots can be detected in images enhanced by our method, by training DeepSpot on 20 simulated and 1 experimental datasets, and have shown that more than 97% accuracy is achieved. Moreover, comparison with alternative deep learning approaches for mRNA spot detection (deepBlink) indicated that DeepSpot allows more precise mRNA detection. In addition, we generated smFISH images from mouse fibroblasts in a wound healing assay to evaluate whether DeepSpot enhancement can enable seamless mRNA spot detection and thus streamline studies of localized mRNA expression in cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469984" rel="alternate" title="DeepSpot: a deep neural network for RNA spot enhancement in smFISH microscopy images (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470093</id><title>Paleozoic Protein Fossils Illuminate the Evolution of Vertebrate Genomes and Transposable Elements (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240555+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin C Frith</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genomes hold a treasure trove of protein fossils: fragments of formerly protein-coding DNA, which mainly come from transposable elements (TEs) or host genes. These fossils reveal ancient evolution of TEs and genomes, and many fossils have been exapted to perform diverse functions important for the host's fitness. However, old and highly-degraded fossils are hard to identify, and standard methods (e.g. BLAST) are not optimized for this task. Here, a recently optimized method is used to find protein fossils in vertebrate genomes. It finds Paleozoic fossils predating the amphibian/amniote divergence from most major TE categories, including virus-related Polinton and Gypsy elements. It finds 10 fossils in the human genome (8 from TEs and 2 from host genes) that predate the last common ancestor of all jawed vertebrates, probably from the Ordovician period. It also finds types of transposon and retrotransposon not found in human before. These fossils have extreme sequence conservation, indicating exaptation: some have evidence of gene-regulatory function, and they tend to lie nearest to developmental genes. Some ancient fossils suggest "genome tectonics", where two fragments of one TE have drifted apart by up to megabases, possibly explaining gene deserts and large introns. This paints a picture of great TE diversity in our aquatic ancestors, with patchy TE inheritance by later vertebrates, producing new genes and regulatory elements on the way. Host-gene fossils too have contributed anciently-conserved DNA segments. This paves the way to further studies of ancient protein fossils.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470093" rel="alternate" title="Paleozoic Protein Fossils Illuminate the Evolution of Vertebrate Genomes and Transposable Elements (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469543</id><title>ME-ACP: Multi-view Neural Networks with Ensemble Model for Identification of Anticancer Peptides (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240660+00:00</updated><author><name>Guanwen Feng</name></author><author><name>Hang Yao</name></author><author><name>Chaoneng Li</name></author><author><name>Ruyi Liu</name></author><author><name>Rungen Huang</name></author><author><name>Xiaopeng Fan</name></author><author><name>Ruiquan Ge</name></author><author><name>Qiguang Miao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer remains one of the most threatening diseases, which kills millions of lives every year. As a promising perspective for cancer treatments, anticancer peptides (ACPs) overcome a lot of disadvantages of traditional treatments. However, it is time-consuming and expensive to identify ACPs through conventional experiments. Hence, it is urgent and necessary to develop highly effective approaches to accurately identify ACPs in large amounts of protein sequences. In this work, we proposed a novel and effective method named ME-ACP which employed multi-view neural networks with ensemble model to identify ACPs. Firstly, we employed residue level and peptide level features preliminarily with ensemble models based on lightGBMs. Then, the outputs of lightGBM classifiers were fed into a hybrid deep neural network (HDNN) to identify ACPs. The experiments on independent test datasets demonstrated that ME-ACP achieved competitive performance on common evaluation metrics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469543" rel="alternate" title="ME-ACP: Multi-view Neural Networks with Ensemble Model for Identification of Anticancer Peptides (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469574</id><title>Correlations from structure and phylogeny combine constructively in the inference of protein partners from sequences (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240806+00:00</updated><author><name>Andonis Gerardos</name></author><author><name>Nicola Dietler</name></author><author><name>Anne-Florence Bitbol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Inferring protein-protein interactions from sequences is an important task in computational biology. Recent methods based on Direct Coupling Analysis (DCA) or Mutual Information (MI) allow to find interaction partners among paralogs of two protein families. Does successful inference mainly rely on correlations from structural contacts or from phylogeny, or both? Do these two types of signal combine constructively or hinder each other? To address these questions, we generate and analyze synthetic data produced using a minimal model that allows us to control the amounts of structural constraints and phylogeny. We show that correlations from these two sources combine constructively to increase the performance of partner inference by DCA or MI. Furthermore, signal from phylogeny can rescue partner inference when signal from contacts becomes less informative, including in the realistic case where inter-protein contacts are restricted to a small subset of sites. We also demonstrate that DCA-inferred couplings between non-contact pairs of sites improve partner inference in the presence of strong phylogeny, while deteriorating it otherwise. Moreover, restricting to non-contact pairs of sites preserves inference performance in the presence of strong phylogeny. In a natural dataset, as well as in realistic synthetic data based on it, we find that non-contact pairs of sites contribute positively to partner inference performance, and that restricting to them preserves performance, evidencing an important role of phylogeny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In protein sequence data, the amino acid usages at different sites of a protein or of two interacting proteins can be correlated because of functional constraints. For instance, the need to maintain physico-chemical complementarity among two sites that are in contact in the three-dimensional structure of a protein complex causes such correlations. However, correlations can also arise due to shared evolutionary history, even in the absence of any functional constraint. While these phylogenetic correlations are known to obscure the inference of structural contacts, we show, using controlled synthetic data, that correlations from structure and phylogeny combine constructively to allow the inference of protein partners from sequences. We also show that pairs of amino acids that are not in contact in the structure have a major impact on partner inference in a natural dataset and in realistic synthetic ones. These findings explain the success of methods based on pairwise maximum-entropy models or on information theory at predicting protein partners from sequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469574" rel="alternate" title="Correlations from structure and phylogeny combine constructively in the inference of protein partners from sequences (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469506</id><title>NGSpop: A desktop software that supports population studies by identifying sequence variations from next-generation sequencing data (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.240923+00:00</updated><author><name>Dong-Jun Lee</name></author><author><name>Taesoo Kwon</name></author><author><name>Hye-Jin Lee</name></author><author><name>Yun-Ho Oh</name></author><author><name>Jin-Hyun Kim</name></author><author><name>Tae-Ho Lee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Next-generation sequencing (NGS) is widely used in all areas of genetic research, such as for genetic disease diagnosis and breeding, and it can produce massive amounts of data. The identification of sequence variants is an important step when processing large NGS datasets; however, currently, the process is complicated, repetitive, and requires concentration, which can be taxing on the researcher. Therefore, to support researchers who are not familiar with bioinformatics in identifying sequence variations regularly from large datasets, we have developed a fully automated desktop software, NGSpop. NGSpop includes functionalities for all the variant calling and visualization procedures used when processing NGS data, such as quality control, mapping, filtering details, and variant calling. In the variant calling step, the user can select the GATK or DeepVariant algorithm for variant calling. These algorithms can be executed using pre-set pipelines and options or customized with the user-specified options. NGSpop is implemented using JavaFX (version 1.8) and can thus be run on Unix like operating systems such as Ubuntu Linux (version 16.04, 18.0.4). Although there are several pipelines and visualization tools available for NGS data analysis, most integrated environments do not support batch processes; thus, variant detection cannot be automated for population-level studies. The NGSpop software, developed in this study, has an easy-to-use interface and helps in rapid analysis of multiple NGS data from population studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469506" rel="alternate" title="NGSpop: A desktop software that supports population studies by identifying sequence variations from next-generation sequencing data (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469423</id><title>Conserved recombination patterns across coronavirus subgenera (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241055+00:00</updated><author><name>Arné de Klerk</name></author><author><name>Phillip Swanepoel</name></author><author><name>Rentia Lourens</name></author><author><name>Mpumelelo Zondo</name></author><author><name>Isaac Abodunran</name></author><author><name>Spyros Lytras</name></author><author><name>Oscar A MacLean</name></author><author><name>David Robertson</name></author><author><name>Sergei L Kosakovsky Pond</name></author><author><name>Jordan D Zehr</name></author><author><name>Venkatesh Kumar</name></author><author><name>Michael J. Stanhope</name></author><author><name>Gordon Harkins</name></author><author><name>Ben Murrell</name></author><author><name>Darren P Martin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recombination contributes to the genetic diversity found in coronaviruses and is known to be a prominent mechanism whereby they evolve. It is apparent, both from controlled experiments and in genome sequences sampled from nature, that patterns of recombination in coronaviruses are non-random and that this is likely attributable to a combination of sequence features that favour the occurrence of recombination breakpoints at specific genomic sites, and selection disfavouring the survival of recombinants within which favourable intra-genome interactions have been disrupted. Here we leverage available whole-genome sequence data for six coronavirus subgenera to identify specific patterns of recombination that are conserved between multiple subgenera and then identify the likely factors that underlie these conserved patterns. Specifically, we confirm the non-randomness of recombination breakpoints across all six tested coronavirus subgenera, locate conserved recombination hot- and cold-spots, and determine that the locations of transcriptional regulatory sequences are likely major determinants of conserved recombination breakpoint hot-spot locations. We find that while the locations of recombination breakpoints are not uniformly associated with degrees of nucleotide sequence conservation, they display significant tendencies in multiple coronavirus subgenera to occur in low guanine-cytosine content genome regions, in non-coding regions, at the edges of genes, and at sites within the Spike gene that are predicted to be minimally disruptive of Spike protein folding. While it is apparent that sequence features such as transcriptional regulatory sequences are likely major determinants of where the template-switching events that yield recombination breakpoints most commonly occur, it is evident that selection against misfolded recombinant proteins also strongly impacts observable recombination breakpoint distributions in coronavirus genomes sampled from nature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.21.469423" rel="alternate" title="Conserved recombination patterns across coronavirus subgenera (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470242</id><title>Rethinking protein drug design with highly accurate structure prediction of anti-CRISPR proteins (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241244+00:00</updated><author><name>Ho-min Park</name></author><author><name>Yunseol Park</name></author><author><name>Joris Vankerschaver</name></author><author><name>Arnout Van Messem</name></author><author><name>Wesley De Neve</name></author><author><name>Hyunjin Shim</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein therapeutics play an important role in controlling the functions and activities of disease-causing proteins in modern medicine. Despite protein therapeutics having several advantages over traditional small-molecule therapeutics, further development has been hindered by drug complexity and delivery issues. However, recent progress in deep learning-based protein structure prediction approaches such as AlphaFold opens new opportunities to exploit the complexity of these macro-biomolecules for highly-specialised design to inhibit, regulate or even manipulate specific disease-causing proteins. Anti-CRISPR proteins are small proteins from bacteriophages that counter-defend against the prokaryotic adaptive immunity of CRISPR-Cas systems. They are unique examples of natural protein therapeutics that have been optimized by the host-parasite evolutionary arms race to inhibit a wide variety of host proteins. Here, we show that these Anti-CRISPR proteins display diverse inhibition mechanisms through accurate structural prediction and functional analysis. We find that these phage-derived proteins are extremely distinct in structure, some of which have no homologues in the current protein structure domain. Furthermore, we find a novel family of Anti-CRISPR proteins which are structurally homologous to the recently-discovered mechanism of manipulating host proteins through enzymatic activity, rather than through direct inference. Using highly accurate structure prediction, we present a wide variety of protein-manipulating strategies of anti-CRISPR proteins for future protein drug design.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470242" rel="alternate" title="Rethinking protein drug design with highly accurate structure prediction of anti-CRISPR proteins (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470262</id><title>Optimizing multiplexed imaging experimental design through tissue spatial segregation estimation (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241378+00:00</updated><author><name>Pierre Bost</name></author><author><name>Daniel Schulz</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Engler</name></author><author><name>Clive Wasserfall</name></author><author><name>Bernd Bodenmiller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in multiplexed imaging methods allow simultaneous detection of dozens of proteins or RNAs enabling deep spatial characterization of both healthy and tumor tissues. Parameters for design of optimal sequencing-based experiments have been established, but such parameters are lacking for multiplex imaging studies. Here, using a spatial transcriptomic atlas of healthy and tumor human tissues, we developed a new statistical framework that determines the number of fields of view necessary to accurately identify all cell types that are part of the tissue. Using this strategy on imaging mass cytometry data, we identified a measurement of tissue spatial segregation that enables optimal experimental design and that is technology invariant. This strategy will enable significantly improved design of multiplexed imaging studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.28.470262" rel="alternate" title="Optimizing multiplexed imaging experimental design through tissue spatial segregation estimation (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469039</id><title>Fuzzy set intersection based paired-end short-read alignment (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241507+00:00</updated><author><name>William J. Bolosky</name></author><author><name>Arun Subramaniyan</name></author><author><name>Matei Zaharia</name></author><author><name>Ravi Pandya</name></author><author><name>Taylor Sittler</name></author><author><name>David Patterson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Much genomic data comes in the form of paired-end reads: two reads that represent genetic material with a small gap between. We present a new algorithm for aligning both reads in a pair simultaneously by fuzzily intersecting the sets of candidate alignment locations for each read. This algorithm is often much faster and produces alignments that result in variant calls having roughly the same concordance as the best competing aligners.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469039" rel="alternate" title="Fuzzy set intersection based paired-end short-read alignment (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469579</id><title>Identification of biological processes and signaling pathways for the knockout of REV-ERB in mouse brain (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241640+00:00</updated><author><name>Jing Li</name></author><author><name>Wei Wang</name></author><author><name>Hanming Gu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;REV-ERB is an orphan nuclear receptor that is widely expressed in the brain and inhibits transcriptional activities. A variety of genes affect the activity and expression of REV-ERB. In this study, our objective is to identify significant signaling pathways and biological processes in the knockout of the REV-ERB mouse brain. The GSE152919 dataset was originally created by using the Illumina HiSeq 4000 (Mus musculus). The KEGG and GO analyses suggested that biological processes “PPAR signaling”, “Hippo signaling”, and “Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM)” are mostly affected in the knockout of REV-ERB. Furthermore, we identified a number of genes according to the PPI network including NPAS2, CRY2, BMAL1, and CRY1 which were involved in the lack of REV-ERB in the brain. Therefore, our study provides further insights into the study of circadian clocks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469579" rel="alternate" title="Identification of biological processes and signaling pathways for the knockout of REV-ERB in mouse brain (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470059</id><title>Single-cell generalized trend model (scGTM): a flexible and interpretable model of gene expression trend along cell pseudotime (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241757+00:00</updated><author><name>Elvis Han Cui</name></author><author><name>Weng Kee Wong</name></author><author><name>Dongyuan Song</name></author><author><name>Jingyi Jessica Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Modeling single-cell gene expression trends along cell pseudotime is a crucial analysis for exploring biological processes. Most existing methods rely on nonparametric regression models for their flexibility; however, nonparametric models often provide trends too complex to interpret. Other existing methods use interpretable but restrictive models. Since model interpretability and flexibility are both indispensable for understanding biological processes, the single-cell field needs a model that improves the interpretability and largely maintains the flexibility of nonparametric regression models. Here we propose the single-cell generalized trend model (scGTM) for capturing a gene's expression trend, which may be monotone, hill-shaped, or valley-shaped, along cell pseudotime. The scGTM has three advantages: (1) it can capture non-monotonic trends that are still easy to interpret, (2) its parameters are biologically interpretable and trend informative, and (3) it can flexibly accommodate common distributions for modeling gene expression counts. To tackle the complex optimization problems, we use the particle swarm optimization algorithm to find the constrained maximum likelihood estimates for the scGTM parameters. As an application, we analyze several single-cell gene expression data sets using the scGTM and show that it can capture interpretable gene expression trends along cell pseudotime and reveal molecular insights underlying the biological processes. We also provide an open-access Python package for fitting the scGTM at https://github. com/ElvisCuiHan/scGTM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.470059" rel="alternate" title="Single-cell generalized trend model (scGTM): a flexible and interpretable model of gene expression trend along cell pseudotime (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470104</id><title>Proteomic Characterization of Serum Small Extracellular Vesicles in Human Breast Cancer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.241878+00:00</updated><author><name>Ganfei Xu</name></author><author><name>Weiyi Huang</name></author><author><name>Shaoqian Du</name></author><author><name>Minjing Huang</name></author><author><name>Jiacheng Lyu</name></author><author><name>Fei Zhou</name></author><author><name>Rongxuan Zhu</name></author><author><name>Yuan Cao</name></author><author><name>Jingxuan Xv</name></author><author><name>Ning Li</name></author><author><name>Guoying Yu</name></author><author><name>Binghua Jiang</name></author><author><name>Olivier Gires</name></author><author><name>Lei Zhou</name></author><author><name>Hongwei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Chen Ding</name></author><author><name>Hongxia Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There is a lack of comprehensive understanding of breast cancer (BC) specific sEVs characteristics and composition on BC unique proteomic information from human samples. Here, we interrogated the proteomic landscape of sEVs in 167 serum samples from patients with BC, benign mammary disease (BD) and from healthy donors (HD). The analysis provides a comprehensive landscape of serum sEVs with totally 9,589 proteins identified, considerably expanding the panel of sEVs markers. Of note, serum BC-sEVs protein signatures were distinct from those of BD and HD, representing stage- and molecular subtype-specific patterns. We constructed specific sEVs protein identifiers that could serve as a liquid biopsy tool for diagnosis and classification of BC from benign mammary disease, molecular subtypes, as well as assessment of lymph node metastasis. We also identified 11 potential survival biomarkers for distant metastasis. This work may provide reference value for the accurate diagnosis and monitoring of BC progression using serum sEVs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.26.470104" rel="alternate" title="Proteomic Characterization of Serum Small Extracellular Vesicles in Human Breast Cancer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469692</id><title>The DOMINO web-server for active module identification analysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.242075+00:00</updated><author><name>Hagai Levi</name></author><author><name>Nima Rahmanian</name></author><author><name>Ran Elkon</name></author><author><name>Ron Shamir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Active module identification (AMI) is an essential step in many omics analyses. Such algorithms receive a gene network and a gene activity profile as input and report subnetworks that show significant over-representation of accrued activity signal (“active modules”). Such modules can point out key molecular processes in the analyzed biological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recently introduced a novel AMI algorithm called DOMINO, and demonstrated that it detects active modules that capture biological signals with markedly improved rate of empirical validation. Here, we provide an online server that executes DOMINO, making it more accessible and user-friendly. To help the interpretation of solutions, the server provides GO enrichment analysis, module visualizations, and accessible output formats for customized downstream analysis. It also enables running DOMINO with various gene identifiers of different organisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The server is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://domino.cs.tau.ac.il"&gt;http://domino.cs.tau.ac.il&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Its codebase is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Shamir-Lab"&gt;https://github.com/Shamir-Lab&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.25.469692" rel="alternate" title="The DOMINO web-server for active module identification analysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469529</id><title>Simulation of aerosol dispersion during medical examinations (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.242199+00:00</updated><author><name>Sebastian Falk</name></author><author><name>Sarina K Mueller</name></author><author><name>Stefan Kniesburges</name></author><author><name>Michael Döllinger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The main route of transmission of the SARS-CoV2 virus has been shown to be airborne. The objective of this study is to analyze the aerosol dispersion and potential exposure to medical staff within a typical medical examination room during classical airway procedures. The multiphase simulation of the aerosol particles in the airflow is based on a Lagrangian-Eulerian approach. All simulation cases with surgical mask show partially but significantly reduced maxi-mum dispersion distances of the aerosol particles compared to the cases without surgical mask. The simulations have shown that medical examiner are exposed to large amount of aerosol particles, especially during procedures such as laryngoscopy where the examiner’s head is directly in front of the the patient’s face. However, exposure can be drastically reduced if the patient wears a mask which is possible for the most of the procedures studied, such as otoscopy, sonography, or anamnesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469529" rel="alternate" title="Simulation of aerosol dispersion during medical examinations (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469497</id><title>Fine-grained, Nonlinear Image Registration of Live Cell Movies Reveals Spatiotemporal Organization of Diffuse Molecular Processes (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.242320+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuexia Jiang</name></author><author><name>Tadamoto Isogai</name></author><author><name>Joseph Chi</name></author><author><name>Gaudenz Danuser</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present an application of non-linear Image registration that allows spatiotemporal analysis of extremely noisy and diffuse molecular processes across the entire cell. To produce meaningful local tracking of the spatially coherent portion of diffuse protein dynamics, we improved upon existing non-linear image registration to compensate for cell movement and deformation. The registration relies on a subcellular fiducial marker, a cell motion mask, and a topological regularization that enforces diffeomorphism on the registration without significant loss of granularity. We demonstrate the potential of this approach in conjunction with stochastic time-series analysis through the discovery of distinct zones of coherent Profillin dynamics in symmetry-breaking U2OS cells. Further analysis of the resulting Profilin dynamics revealed strong relationships with the underlying actin organization. This study thus provides a framework for extracting functional interactions between cell morphodynamics, protein distributions, and signaling in cells undergoing continuous shape changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;By adapting optical flow based nonlinear image registration we created a method specific for live cell movies that preserves the dynamics of a signal of interest by remapping using a separate measurable subcellular location fiducial. This is an extension as well on our lab’s previously published method of cell edge-based referencing of subcellular locations that was incapable of extracting interpretable subcellular time series more than a few microns away from the cell edge. We showed that our method overcomes this key limitation and allows sampling of subcellular time series from every subcellular location through our discovery of organized profilin dynamics in moving cell and that these profilin dynamics are related to actin dynamics due to their ability to bind growing actin structures likely through actin polymerizing factors. Most importantly, our method is applicable to discovering subcellular organization and coordination in a widely used form of live cell microscopy data that hitherto has been largely limited to anecdotal analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.22.469497" rel="alternate" title="Fine-grained, Nonlinear Image Registration of Live Cell Movies Reveals Spatiotemporal Organization of Diffuse Molecular Processes (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469730</id><title>Identification of biological processes and signaling pathways in the stretched nucleus pulposus cells (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.242441+00:00</updated><author><name>Min Zhang</name></author><author><name>Jing Wang</name></author><author><name>Hanming Gu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Low back pain is mostly caused by disc degeneration, which is due to the alterations in the osmotic pressure of nucleus pulposus cells. However, the knowledge about the mechanism and therapies for disc degeneration is not fully understood. Here, our objective is to identify significantly changed genes and biological processes in the stretched nucleus pulposus cells. The GSE175710 dataset was originally produced by using the Illumina HiSeq 4000 (Rattus norvegicus). The KEGG and GO analyses indicated that “MAPK signaling”, “TNF signaling”, “IL17 signaling”, and the “NF-κB signaling pathway” are mostly affected in the stretched nucleus pulposus cells. Moreover, we identified several genes according to the PPI network such as Mmp9, Cxcl12, Col1a1, and Col3a1 in the stretched nucleus pulposus cells. Thus, our study provides further insights into the study of disc deterioration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469730" rel="alternate" title="Identification of biological processes and signaling pathways in the stretched nucleus pulposus cells (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469777</id><title>Propagation of seminal toxins through binary expression gene drives can suppress polyandrous populations (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-29T11:32:15.242555+00:00</updated><author><name>Juan Hurtado</name></author><author><name>Santiago Revale</name></author><author><name>Luciano M Matzkin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene drives can be highly effective in controlling a target population by disrupting a female fertility gene. To spread across a population, these drives require that disrupted alleles be largely recessive so as not to impose too high of a fitness penalty. We argue that this restriction may be relaxed by using a double gene drive design to spread a split binary expression system. One drive carries a dominant lethal/toxic effector alone and the other a transactivator factor, without which the effector will not act. Only after the drives reach sufficiently high frequencies would individuals have the chance to inherit both system components and the effector be expressed. We explore through mathematical modeling the potential of this design to spread dominant lethal/toxic alleles and suppress populations. We show that this system could be implemented to spread engineered seminal proteins designed to kill females, making it highly effective against polyandrous populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.23.469777" rel="alternate" title="Propagation of seminal toxins through binary expression gene drives can suppress polyandrous populations (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>