<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.790698+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463725</id><title>Mutagenesis-visualization: analysis of site saturation mutagenesis datasets in Python (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.791116+00:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hidalgo</name></author><author><name>Sage Templeton</name></author><author><name>Che Olavaria Gallegos</name></author><author><name>Joanne Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Site saturation mutagenesis (SSM) experiments have been transformative in our study of protein function. Despite the rich data generated from such experiments, current tools for processing, analyzing, and visualizing the data offer only a limited set of static plots that are difficult to customize. Furthermore, usage of the tools requires extensive experience and programming. This slows the research process for those in the biological field who are unfamiliar with programming. Here, we introduce mutagenesis-visualization, a Python API for the creation of publication quality figures for SSM datasets which requires no prior Python or statistics experience. The plots can be rendered as native matplotlib objects (easy to stylize) or as Plotly objects (interactive graphs). Additionally, the software offers the possibility to visualize the datasets on Pymol. Availability and implementation: The software can be installed from PyPI or GitHub using the pip package manager and is compatible with Python ≥ 3.8. The documentation can be found at readthedocs and the source code can be found on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463725" rel="alternate" title="Mutagenesis-visualization: analysis of site saturation mutagenesis datasets in Python (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.462574</id><title>Deep learning-based tumor microenvironment segmentation is predictive of tumor mutations and patient survival in non-small-cell lung cancer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T09:54:27.791598+00:00</updated><author><name>Łukasz Rączkowski</name></author><author><name>Iwona Paśnik</name></author><author><name>Michał Kukiełka</name></author><author><name>Marcin Nicoś</name></author><author><name>Magdalena A Budzinska</name></author><author><name>Tomasz Kucharczyk</name></author><author><name>Justyna Szumiło</name></author><author><name>Paweł Krawczyk</name></author><author><name>Nicola Crosetto</name></author><author><name>Ewa Szczurek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that tumor microenvironment (TME) and gene mutations are the main determinants of progression of the deadliest cancer in the world - lung cancer - their interrelations are not well understood. Digital pathology data provide a unique insight into the spatial composition of the TME. Here, we generated 23,199 image patches from 55 hematoxylin-and-eosin (H&amp;amp;E)-stained lung cancer tissue sections and annotated them into 9 different tissue classes. Using this dataset, we trained a deep neural network and used it to segment 467 lung cancer H&amp;amp;E images downloaded from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) database. We used the segmented images to compute human interpretable features reflecting the heterogeneous composition of the TME, and successfully utilized them to predict patient survival (c-index 0.723) and cancer gene mutations (largest AUC 73.5% for PDGFRB). Our approach can be generalized to different cancer types to inform precision medicine strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.462574" rel="alternate" title="Deep learning-based tumor microenvironment segmentation is predictive of tumor mutations and patient survival in non-small-cell lung cancer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>