<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in bioinformatics posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.037986+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.03.442417</id><title>Open issues for protein function assignment in Haloferax volcanii and other halophilic archaea (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.043966+00:00</updated><author><name>Friedhelm Pfeiffer</name></author><author><name>Mike Dyall-Smith</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annotation ambiguities and annotation errors are a general challenge in genomics. While a reliable protein function assignment can be obtained by experimental characterization, this is expensive and time-consuming, and the number of such Gold Standard Proteins (GSP) with experimental support remains very low compared to proteins annotated by sequence homology, usually through automated pipelines. Even a GSP may give a misleading assignment when used as a reference: the homolog may be close enough to support isofunctionality, but the substrate of the GSP is absent from the species being annotated. In such cases the enzymes cannot be isofunctional. Here, we examine a variety of such issues in halophilic archaea (class Halobacteria), with a strong focus on the model haloarchaeon &lt;italic&gt;Haloferax volcanii&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annotated proteins of &lt;italic&gt;Hfx. volcanii&lt;/italic&gt; were identified for which public databases tend to assign a function that is probably incorrect. In some cases, an alternative, probably correct, function can be predicted or inferred from the available evidence but this has not been adopted by public databases because experimental validation is lacking. In other cases, a probably invalid specific function is predicted by homology, and while there is evidence that this assigned function is unlikely, the true function remains elusive. We list 50 of those cases, each with detailed background information so that a conclusion about the most likely biological function can be drawn. For reasons of brevity and comprehension, only key aspects are listed in the main text, with detailed information being provided in a corresponding section of the Supplementary Material.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compiling, describing and summarizing these open annotation issues and functional predictions will benefit the scientific community in the general effort to improve the evaluation of protein function assignments and more thoroughly detail them. By highlighting the gaps and likely annotation errors currently in the databases, we hope this study will provide a framework for experimentalists to sytematically confirm (or disprove) our function predictions or to uncover yet unexpected functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442567</id><title>Biological mechanisms of aging predict age-related disease multimorbidities in patients (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-10T05:46:11.042624+00:00</updated><author><name>Helen C Fraser</name></author><author><name>Valerie Kuan</name></author><author><name>Ronja Johnen</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Zwierzyna</name></author><author><name>Aroon D Hingorani</name></author><author><name>Andreas Beyer</name></author><author><name>Linda Partridge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic, environmental and pharmacological interventions into the aging process can confer resistance to a multiple age-related diseases in laboratory animals, including rhesus monkeys. These findings imply that mechanisms of aging might contribute to patterns of multimorbidity in humans, and hence could be targeted to prevent multiple conditions simultaneously. To address this question, we text mined 917,645 literature abstracts followed by manual curation, and found strong, non-random associations between age-related diseases and aging mechanisms, confirmed by gene set enrichment analysis of GWAS data. Integration of these associations with clinical data from 3.01 million patients showed that age-related diseases associated with each of five aging mechanisms were more likely than chance to be present together in patients. Genetic evidence revealed that innate and adaptive immunity, the intrinsic apoptotic signalling pathway and activity of the ERK1/2 pathway played a significant role across multiple aging mechanisms and multiple, diverse age-related diseases. Mechanisms of aging therefore contribute to multiple age-related diseases and to patterns of human age-related multimorbidity, and could potentially be targeted to prevent more than one age-related condition in the same patient.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>