<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.033241+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462485</id><title>Repurposing CAR targets in solid tumors via a pan-cancer single-cell transcriptome analysis (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.033673+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanna Madan</name></author><author><name>Alejandro A. Schäffer</name></author><author><name>Eytan Ruppin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cell therapy is a powerful and promising tool for unleashing lasting antitumor immunity, which is currently studied in numerous blood and solid cancers. Here, mining single cell transcriptomics datasets of solid tumors, we survey many existing CAR targets, aiming to new solid tumor types in which these targets are differentially expressed in tumor cells and not on non-tumor cells within the tumor microenvironment, thus providing new repurposing opportunities. Quite surprisingly, we find that many existing solid cancer CAR targets have a better discriminatory power in uncharted cancer types than in the ones they have been developed or being tested for. Furthermore, we show that several existing liquid cancer CAR targets may also hold promise in specific solid tumors. Taken together, this analysis uncovers a large potential of repurposing current CARs that is currently yet untapped.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462485" rel="alternate" title="Repurposing CAR targets in solid tumors via a pan-cancer single-cell transcriptome analysis (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462364</id><title>Multi-omics and deep learning provide a multifaceted view of cancer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.034009+00:00</updated><author><name>Bora Uyar</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Ronen</name></author><author><name>Vedran Franke</name></author><author><name>Gaetano Gargiulo</name></author><author><name>Altuna Akalin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer is a complex disease with a large financial and healthcare burden on society. One hallmark of the disease is the uncontrolled growth and proliferation of malignant cells. Unlike Mendelian diseases which may be explained by a few genomic loci, a deeper molecular and mechanistic understanding of the development of cancer is needed. Such an endeavor requires the integration of tens of thousands of molecular features across multiple layers of information encoded in the cells. In practical terms, this implies integration of multi omics information from the genome, transcriptome, epigenome, proteome, metabolome, and even micro-environmental factors such as the microbiome. Finding mechanistic insights and biomarkers in such a high dimensional space is a challenging task. Therefore, efficient machine learning techniques are needed to reduce the dimensionality of the data while simultaneously discovering complex but meaningful biomarkers. These markers then can lead to testable hypotheses in research and clinical applications. In this study, we applied advanced deep learning methods to uncover multi-omic fingerprints that are associated with a wide range of clinical and molecular features of tumor samples. Using these fingerprints, we can accurately classify different cancer types, and their subtypes. Non-linear multi-omic fingerprints can uncover clinical features associated with patient survival and response to treatment, ranging from chemotherapy to immunotherapy. In addition, multi-omic fingerprints may be deconvoluted into a meaningful subset of genes and genomic alterations to support clinically relevant decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="462364v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462364" rel="alternate" title="Multi-omics and deep learning provide a multifaceted view of cancer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462262</id><title>Open Imputation Server provides secure Imputation services with provable genomic privacy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.034285+00:00</updated><author><name>Arif O. Harmanci</name></author><author><name>Miran Kim</name></author><author><name>Su Wang</name></author><author><name>Wentao Li</name></author><author><name>Yongsoo Song</name></author><author><name>Kristin E. Lauter</name></author><author><name>Xiaoqian Jiang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As DNA sequencing data is available for personal use, genomic privacy is becoming a major challenge. Nevertheless, high-throughput genomic data analysis outsourcing is performed using pipelines that tend to overlook these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a client-server-based outsourcing framework for genotype imputation, an important step in genomic data analyses. Genotype data is encrypted by the client and encrypted data are used by the server that never observes the data in plain. Cloud-based framework can benefit from virtually unlimited computational resources while providing provable confidentiality. We demonstrate server’s utility from several aspects using genotype dataset from the 1000 Genomes datasets. First, we benchmark the accuracy of common variant imputation in comparison to BEAGLE, a state-of-the-art imputation method. We also provide the detailed time requirements of the server to showcase scaling of time usage in different steps of imputation. We also present a simple correlation metric that can be used to estimate imputation accuracy using only the reference panels. This is important for filtering the variants in downstream analyses. As a further demonstration and a different use case, we performed a simulated genomewide association study (GWAS) using imputed and known genotypes and highlight potential utility of the server for association studies. Overall, our study present multiple lines of evidence for usability of secure imputation service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Server is publicly available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.secureomics.org/OpenImpute"&gt;https://www.secureomics.org/OpenImpute&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Users can anonymously test and use imputation server without registration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;Arif.O.Harmanci@uth.tmc.edu&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462262" rel="alternate" title="Open Imputation Server provides secure Imputation services with provable genomic privacy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462291</id><title>easyfm: An easy software suite for file manipulation of Next Generation Sequencing data on desktops (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.034568+00:00</updated><author><name>Hyungtaek Jung</name></author><author><name>Brendan Jeon</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ortiz-Barrientos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Storing and manipulating Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) file formats is an essential but difficult task in biological data analysis. The &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;bold&gt;easy f&lt;/bold&gt;ile &lt;bold&gt;m&lt;/bold&gt;anipulation) toolkit (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm"&gt;https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm&lt;/ext-link&gt;) makes manipulating commonly used NGS files more accessible to biologists. It enables them to perform end-to-end reproducible data analyses using a free standalone desktop application (available on Windows, Mac and Linux). Unlike existing tools (e.g. Galaxy), the Graphical User Interface (GUI)-based &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; is not dependent on any high-performance computing (HPC) system and can be operated without an internet connection. This specific benefit allow &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; to seamlessly integrate visual and interactive representations of NGS files, supporting a wider scope of bioinformatics applications in the life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The analysis and manipulation of NGS data for understanding biological phenomena is an increasingly important aspect in the life sciences. Yet, most methods for analysing, storing and manipulating NGS data require complex command-line tools in HPC or web-based servers and have not yet been implemented in comprehensive, easy-to-use software. This is a major hurdle preventing more general application in the field of NGS data analysis and file manipulation. Here we present &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt;, a free standalone Graphical User Interface (GUI) software with Python support that can be used to facilitate the rapid discovery of target sequences (or user’s interest) in NGS datasets for novice users. For user-friendliness and convenience, &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; was developed with four work modules and a secondary GUI window (herein secondary window), covering different aspects of NGS data analysis (mainly focusing on FASTA files), including post-processing, filtering, format conversion, generating results, real-time log, and help. In combination with the executable tools (BLAST+ and BLAT) and Python, &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; allows the user to set analysis parameters, select/extract regions of interest, examine the input and output results, and convert to a wide range of file formats. To help augment the functionality of existing web-based and command-line tools, &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt;, a self-contained program, comes with extensive documentation (hosted at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm"&gt;https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm&lt;/ext-link&gt;) including a comprehensive step-by-step guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462291" rel="alternate" title="easyfm: An easy software suite for file manipulation of Next Generation Sequencing data on desktops (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462289</id><title>Computational design of peptide therapeutics: how useful are sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors? (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T06:39:44.036942+00:00</updated><author><name>François Charih</name></author><author><name>Kyle K. Biggar</name></author><author><name>James R. Green</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Engineering peptides to achieve a desired therapeutic effect through the inhibition of a specific target activity or protein interaction is a non-trivial task. Few of the existing &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; peptide design algorithms generate target-specific peptides. Instead, many methods produce peptides that achieve a desired effect through an unknown mechanism. In contrast with resource-intensive high-throughput experiments, &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; screening is a cost-effective alternative that can prune the space of candidates when engineering target-specific peptides. Using a set of FDA-approved peptides we curated specifically for this task, we assess the applicability of several sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors as a screening tool within the context of peptide therapeutic engineering. We show that similarity-based protein-protein interaction predictors are more suitable for this purpose than the current state-of-the-art deep learning methods. We also show that this approach is mostly useful when designing new peptides against targets for which naturally-occurring interactors are already known, and that deploying it for &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; peptide engineering tasks may require gathering additional target-specific training data. Taken together, this work offers evidence that supports the use of similarity-based protein-protein interaction predictors for peptide therapeutic engineering, especially peptide analogs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peptides are short chains of amino acids that represent an alternative to small molecule drugs to inhibit enzymatic activity or protein-protein interactions. Designing small peptides to target a protein specifically is challenging, though a number of computational approaches do exist. These methods must to evaluate the quality of a peptide in terms of its ability to bind specifically to a target protein, which can be done &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; with sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors. It isn’t clear, however, how suitable the different types of predictors are for the task of predicting interactions between peptides and proteins. Herein, we apply state-of-the-art protein-protein interaction predictors to a set of FDA-approved peptide therapeutics to determine how the different protein-protein interaction predictors compare for the task of assessing peptide quality, and to determine under which circumstances these methods may be successful. Our results show that similarity-based predictors outperform deep learning methods, and that these methods may be more suitable for peptide analog engineering than for the design of peptide therapeutics &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462289" rel="alternate" title="Computational design of peptide therapeutics: how useful are sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors? (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>