<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.792144+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467651</id><title>Block aligner: fast and flexible pairwise sequence alignment with SIMD-accelerated adaptive blocks (87 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.792663+00:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Liu</name></author><author><name>Martin Steinegger</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Smith-Waterman-Gotoh alignment algorithm is the most popular method for comparing biological sequences. Recently, Single Instruction Multiple Data methods have been used to speed up alignment. However, these algorithms have limitations like being optimized for specific scoring schemes, cannot handle large gaps, or require quadratic time computation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a new algorithm called block aligner for aligning nucleotide and protein sequences. It greedily shifts and grows a block of computed scores to span large gaps within the aligned sequences. This greedy approach is able to only compute a fraction of the DP matrix. In exchange for these features, there is no guarantee that the computed scores are accurate compared to full DP. However, in our experiments, we show that block aligner performs accurately on various realistic datasets, and it is up to 9 times faster than the popular Farrar’s algorithm for protein global alignments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our algorithm has applications in computing global alignments and &lt;italic&gt;X&lt;/italic&gt;-drop alignments on proteins and long reads. It is available as a Rust library at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Daniel-Liu-c0deb0t/block-aligner"&gt;https://github.com/Daniel-Liu-c0deb0t/block-aligner&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467651" rel="alternate" title="Block aligner: fast and flexible pairwise sequence alignment with SIMD-accelerated adaptive blocks (87 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467498</id><title>Accelerating in-silico saturation mutagenesis using compressed sensing (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.792935+00:00</updated><author><name>Jacob Schreiber</name></author><author><name>Surag Nair</name></author><author><name>Akshay Balsubramani</name></author><author><name>Anshul Kundaje</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In-silico saturation mutagenesis (ISM) is a popular approach in computational genomics for calculating feature attributions on biological sequences that proceeds by systematically perturbing each position in a sequence and recording the difference in model output. However, this method can be slow because systematically perturbing each position requires performing a number of forward passes proportional to the length of the sequence being examined. In this work, we propose a modification of ISM that leverages the principles of compressed sensing to require only a constant number of forward passes, regardless of sequence length, when applied to models that contain operations with a limited receptive field, such as convolutions. Our method, named Yuzu, can reduce the time that ISM spends in convolution operations by several orders of magnitude and, consequently, Yuzu can speed up ISM on several commonly used architectures in genomics by over an order of magnitude. Notably, we found that Yuzu provides speedups that increase with the complexity of the convolution operation and the length of the sequence being analyzed, suggesting that Yuzu provides large benefits in realistic settings. We have made this tool available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kundajelab/yuzu"&gt;https://github.com/kundajelab/yuzu&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467498" rel="alternate" title="Accelerating in-silico saturation mutagenesis using compressed sensing (40 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467820</id><title>scDeepHash: An automatic cell type annotation and cell retrieval method for large-scale scRNA-seq datasets using neural network-based hashing (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.793156+00:00</updated><author><name>Shihao Ma</name></author><author><name>Yanyi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Bohao Wang</name></author><author><name>Zian Hu</name></author><author><name>Jingwei Zhang</name></author><author><name>Bo Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA-sequencing technologies measure transcriptomic expressions, which quantifies cell-to-cell heterogeneity at an unprecedented resolution. As these technologies become more readily available, the number of scRNA-seq datasets increases drastically. Prior works have demonstrated that bias-free, holistic single-cell profiling infrastructures are essential to the emerging automatic cell-type annotation methods. We propose scDeepHash, a scalable scRNA-seq analytic tool that employs content-based deep hashing to index single-cell gene expressions. scDeepHash allows for fast and accurate automated cell-type annotation and similar-cell retrieval. We also demonstrated the performance of scDeepHash by benchmarking it against current state of the art methods across multiple public scRNA-seq datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467820" rel="alternate" title="scDeepHash: An automatic cell type annotation and cell retrieval method for large-scale scRNA-seq datasets using neural network-based hashing (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467937</id><title>Improving Neural Networks for Genotype-Phenotype Prediction Using Published Summary Statistics (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.793667+00:00</updated><author><name>Tianyu Cui</name></author><author><name>Khaoula El Mekkaoui</name></author><author><name>Aki Havulinna</name></author><author><name>Pekka Marttinen</name></author><author><name>Samuel Kaski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Phenotype prediction is a necessity in numerous applications in genetics. However, when the size of the individual-level data of the cohort of interest is small, statistical learning algorithms, from linear regression to neural networks, usually fail due to insufficient data. Fortunately, summary statistics from genome-wide association studies (GWAS) on other large cohorts are often publicly available. In this work, we propose a new regularization method, namely, &lt;italic&gt;main effect prior (MEP)&lt;/italic&gt;, for making use of GWAS summary statistics from external datasets. The main effect prior is generally applicable for machine learning algorithms, such as neural networks and linear regression. With simulation and real-world experiments, we show empirically that MEP improves the prediction performance on both homogeneous and heterogeneous datasets. Moreover, deep neural networks with MEP outperform standard baselines even when the training set is small.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467937" rel="alternate" title="Improving Neural Networks for Genotype-Phenotype Prediction Using Published Summary Statistics (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467260</id><title>Predicting Relative Protein Abundance via Sequence-Based Information (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.793930+00:00</updated><author><name>Gregory M. Parkes</name></author><author><name>Robert M. Ewing</name></author><author><name>Mahesan Niranjan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the complex interactions between transcriptome and proteome is essential in uncovering cellular mechanisms both in health and disease contexts. The limited correlations between corresponding transcript and protein abundance suggest that regulatory processes tightly govern information flow surrounding transcription and translation, and beyond. In this study we adopt an approach which expands the feature scope that models the human proteome: we develop machine learning models that incorporate sequence-derived features (SDFs), sometimes in conjunction with corresponding mRNA levels. We develop a large resource of sequence-derived features which cover a significant proportion of the H. sapiens proteome, demonstrate which of these features are significant in prediction on multiple cell lines, and suggest insights into which biological processes can be explained using these features. We reveal that (a) SDFs are significantly better at protein abundance prediction across multiple cell lines both in steady-state and dynamic contexts, (b) that SDFs can cover the domain of translation with relative efficiency but struggle with cell-line specific pathways and (c) provide a resource which can be plugged into many subsequent protein-centric analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467260" rel="alternate" title="Predicting Relative Protein Abundance via Sequence-Based Information (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467510</id><title>SECEDO: SNV-based subclone detection using ultra-low coverage single-cell DNA sequencing (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.794069+00:00</updated><author><name>Hana Rozhoňová</name></author><author><name>Daniel Danciu</name></author><author><name>Stefan Stark</name></author><author><name>Gunnar Rätsch</name></author><author><name>André Kahles</name></author><author><name>Kjong-Van Lehmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recently developed single-cell DNA sequencing technologies enable whole-genome, amplification-free sequencing of thousands of cells at the cost of ultra-low coverage of the sequenced data (&amp;lt; 0.05x per cell), which mostly limits their usage to the identification of copy number alterations (CNAs) in multi-megabase segments. Aside from CNA-based subclone detection, single-nucleotide variant (SNV)-based subclone detection may contribute to a more comprehensive view on intra-tumor heterogeneity. Due to the low coverage of the data, the identification of SNVs is only possible when superimposing the sequenced genomes of hundreds of genetically similar cells. Here we present &lt;underline&gt;S&lt;/underline&gt;ingl&lt;underline&gt;e Ce&lt;/underline&gt;ll &lt;underline&gt;D&lt;/underline&gt;ata Tum&lt;underline&gt;o&lt;/underline&gt;r Clusterer (SECEDO, lat. ‘to separate’), a new method to cluster tumor cells based solely on SNVs, inferred on ultra-low coverage single-cell DNA sequencing data. The core aspects of the method are an efficient Bayesian filtering of relevant loci and the exploitation of read overlaps and phasing information. We applied SECEDO to a synthetic dataset simulating 7,250 cells and eight tumor subclones from a single patient, and were able to accurately reconstruct the clonal composition, detecting 92.11% of the somatic SNVs, with the smallest clusters representing only 6.9% of the total population. When applied to four real single-cell sequencing datasets from a breast cancer patient, SECEDO was able to recover the major clonal composition in each dataset at the original sequencing depth of 0.03x per cell, an 8-fold improvement relative to the state of the art. Variant calling on the resulting clusters recovered more than twice as many SNVs with double the allelic ratio compared to calling on all cells together, demonstrating the utility of SECEDO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SECEDO is implemented in C++ and is publicly available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ratschlab/secedo"&gt;https://github.com/ratschlab/secedo&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467510" rel="alternate" title="SECEDO: SNV-based subclone detection using ultra-low coverage single-cell DNA sequencing (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467781</id><title>AWGAN: A Powerful Batch Correction Model for scRNA-seq Data (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.794217+00:00</updated><author><name>Tianyu Liu</name></author><author><name>Yuge Wang</name></author><author><name>Hongyu Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the advancement of technology, we can generate and access large-scale, high dimensional and diverse genomics data, especially through single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq). However, integrative downstream analysis from multiple scRNA-seq datasets remains challenging due to batch effects. In this paper, we focus on scRNA-seq data integration and propose a new deep learning framework based on Wasserstein Generative Adversarial Network (WGAN) combined with an attention mechanism to reduce the differences among batches. We also discuss the limitations of the existing methods and demonstrate the advantages of our new model from both theoretical and practical aspects, advocating the use of deep learning in genomics research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.08.467781" rel="alternate" title="AWGAN: A Powerful Batch Correction Model for scRNA-seq Data (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468415</id><title>Optimization algorithm for omic data subspace clustering (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.794401+00:00</updated><author><name>Madalina Ciortan</name></author><author><name>Matthieu Defrance</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Subspace clustering identifies multiple feature subspaces embedded in a dataset together with the underlying sample clusters. When applied to omic data, subspace clustering is a challenging task, as additional problems have to be addressed: the curse of dimensionality, the imperfect data quality and cluster separation, the presence of multiple subspaces representative of divergent views of the dataset, and the lack of consensus on the best clustering method. First, we propose a computational method discover to perform subspace clustering on tabular high dimensional data by maximizing the internal clustering score (i.e. cluster compactness) of feature subspaces. Our algorithm can be used in both unsupervised and semi-supervised settings. Secondly, by applying our method to a large set of omic datasets (i.e. microarray, bulk RNA-seq, scRNA-seq), we show that the subspace corresponding to the provided ground truth annotations is rarely the most compact one, as assumed by the methods maximizing the internal quality of clusters. Our results highlight the difficulty of fully validating subspace clusters (justified by the lack of feature annotations). Tested on identifying the ground-truth subspace, our method compared favorably with competing techniques on all datasets. Finally, we propose a suite of techniques to interpret the clustering results biologically in the absence of annotations. We demonstrate that subspace clustering can provide biologically meaningful sample-wise and feature-wise information, typically missed by traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.12.468415" rel="alternate" title="Optimization algorithm for omic data subspace clustering (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468111</id><title>Genome-wide alignment-free phylogenetic distance estimation under a no strand-bias model (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.794626+00:00</updated><author><name>Metin Balaban</name></author><author><name>Nishat Anjum Bristy</name></author><author><name>Ahnaf Faisal</name></author><author><name>Md Shamsuzzoha Bayzid</name></author><author><name>Siavash Mirarab</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While aligning sequences has been the dominant approach for determining homology prior to phylogenetic inference, alignment-free methods have much appeal in terms of simplifying the process of inference, especially when analyzing genome-wide data. Furthermore, alignment-free methods present the only option for some emerging forms of data such as genome skims, which cannot be assembled. Despite the appeal, alignment-free methods have not been competitive with alignment-based methods in terms of accuracy. One limitation of alignment-free methods is that they typically rely on simplified models of sequence evolution such as Jukes-Cantor. It is possible to compute pairwise distances under more complex models by computing frequencies of base substitutions provided that these quantities can be estimated in the alignment-free setting. A particular limitation is that for many forms of genome-wide data, which arguably present the best use case for alignment-free methods, the strand of DNA sequences is unknown. Under such conditions, the so-called no-strand bias models are the most complex models that can be used. Here, we show how to calculate distances under a no-strain bias restriction of the General Time Reversible (GTR) model called TK4 without relying on alignments. The method relies on replacing letters in the input sequences, and subsequent computation of Jaccard indices between k-mer sets. For the method to work on large genomes, we also need to compute the number of k-mer mismatches after replacement due to random chance. We show in simulation that these alignment-free distances can be highly accurate when genomes evolve under the assumed models, and we examine the effectiveness of the method on real genomic data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.10.468111" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide alignment-free phylogenetic distance estimation under a no strand-bias model (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467922</id><title>Toeholder: a Software for Automated Design and In Silico Validation of Toehold Riboswitches (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-15T10:41:14.794984+00:00</updated><author><name>Angel F. Cisneros</name></author><author><name>François D. Rouleau</name></author><author><name>Carla Bautista</name></author><author><name>Pascale Lemieux</name></author><author><name>Nathan Dumont-Leblond</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Synthetic biology aims to engineer biological circuits, which often involve gene expression. A particularly promising group of regulatory elements are riboswitches because of their versatility with respect to their targets, but early synthetic designs were not as attractive because of a reduced dynamic range with respect to protein regulators. Only recently, the creation of toehold switches helped overcome this obstacle by also providing an unprecedented degree of orthogonality. However, a lack of automated design and optimization tools prevents the widespread and effective use of toehold switches in high-throughput experiments. To address this, we developed Toeholder, a comprehensive open-source software for toehold design and &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; benchmarking. Toeholder takes into consideration sequence constraints as well as data derived from molecular dynamics simulations of a toehold switch. We describe the software and its &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; validation results, as well as its potential applications and impacts on the management and design of toehold switches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.11.09.467922" rel="alternate" title="Toeholder: a Software for Automated Design and In Silico Validation of Toehold Riboswitches (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>