<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.418714+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471629</id><title>Image-based representation of massive spatial transcriptomics datasets (84 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419018+00:00</updated><author><name>Stephan Preibisch</name></author><author><name>Nikos Karaiskos</name></author><author><name>Nikolaus Rajewsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present STIM, an imaging-based computational framework for exploring, visualizing, and processing high-throughput spatial sequencing datasets. STIM is built on the powerful ImgLib2, N5 and BigDataViewer (BDV) frameworks enabling transfer of computer vision techniques to datasets with irregular measurement-spacing and arbitrary spatial resolution, such as spatial transcriptomics data generated by multiplexed targeted hybridization or spatial sequencing technologies. We illustrate STIM’s capabilities by representing, visualizing, and automatically registering publicly available spatial sequencing data from 14 serial sections of mouse brain tissue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471629" rel="alternate" title="Image-based representation of massive spatial transcriptomics datasets (84 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471401</id><title>MIRA: Joint regulatory modeling of multimodal expression and chromatin accessibility in single cells (67 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419222+00:00</updated><author><name>Allen W. Lynch</name></author><author><name>Christina V. Theodoris</name></author><author><name>Henry Long</name></author><author><name>Myles Brown</name></author><author><name>X. Shirley Liu</name></author><author><name>Clifford A. Meyer</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rigorously comparing gene expression and chromatin accessibility in the same single cells could illuminate the logic of how coupling or decoupling of these mechanisms regulates fate commitment. Here, we present MIRA: Probabilistic Multimodal Models for Integrated Regulatory Analysis, a comprehensive methodology that systematically contrasts transcription and accessibility to infer the regulatory circuitry driving cells along developmental trajectories. MIRA leverages joint topic modeling of cell states and regulatory potential modeling of individual gene loci. MIRA thereby represents cell states in an efficient and interpretable latent space, infers high fidelity lineage trees, determines key regulators of fate decisions at branch points, and exposes the variable influence of local accessibility on transcription at distinct loci. Applied to epidermal maintenance differentiation and embryonic brain development from two different multimodal platforms, MIRA revealed that early developmental genes were tightly regulated by local chromatin landscape whereas terminal fate genes were titrated without requiring extensive chromatin remodeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471401" rel="alternate" title="MIRA: Joint regulatory modeling of multimodal expression and chromatin accessibility in single cells (67 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471237</id><title>“A novel paradigm for optimal mass feature peak picking in large scale LC-MS datasets using the ‘isopair’: isoLock, autoCredential and anovAlign” (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419364+00:00</updated><author><name>Allen Hubbard</name></author><author><name>Louis Connelly</name></author><author><name>Shrikaar Kambhampati</name></author><author><name>Brad Evans</name></author><author><name>Ivan Baxter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Untargeted metabolomics enables direct quantification of metabolites without apriori knowledge of their identity. Liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS), a popular method to implement untargeted metabolomics, identifies metabolites via combined mass/charge (m/z) and retention time as mass features. Improvements in the sensitivity of mass spectrometers has increased the complexity of data produced, leading to computational obstacles. One outstanding challenge is calling metabolite mass feature peaks rapidly and accurately in large LC-MS datasets (dozens to thousands of samples) in the presence of measurement and other noise. While existing algorithms are useful, they have limitations that become pronounced at scale and lead to false positive metabolite predictions as well as signal dropouts. To overcome some of these shortcomings, biochemists have developed hybrid computational and carbon labeling techniques, such as credentialing. Credentialing can validate metabolite signals, but is laborious and its applicability is limited. We have developed a suite of three computational tools to overcome the challenges of unreliable algorithms and inefficient validation protocols: isolock, autoCredential and anovAlign. Isolock uses isopairs, or metabolite-istopologue pairs, to calculate and correct for mass drift noise across LC-MS runs. autoCredential leverages statistical features of LC-MS data to amplify naturally present 13C isotopologues and validate metabolites through isopairs. This obviates the need to artificially introduce carbon labeling. anovAlign, an anova-derived algorithm, is used to align retention time windows across samples to accurately delineate retention time windows for mass features. Using a large published clinical dataset as well as a plant dataset with biological replicates across time, genotype and treatment, we demonstrate that this suite of tools is more sensitive and reproducible than both an open source metabolomics pipelines, XCMS, and the commercial software progenesis QI. This software suite opens a new era for enhanced accuracy and increased throughput for untargeted metabolomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471237" rel="alternate" title="“A novel paradigm for optimal mass feature peak picking in large scale LC-MS datasets using the ‘isopair’: isoLock, autoCredential and anovAlign” (28 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471436</id><title>CMash: fast, multi-resolution estimation of k-mer-based Jaccard and containment indices (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419494+00:00</updated><author><name>Shaopeng Liu</name></author><author><name>David Koslicki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;K&lt;/italic&gt;-mer based methods are used ubiquitously in the field of computational biology. However, determining the optimal value of &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt; for a specific application often remains heuristic. Simply reconstructing a new &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer set with another &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer size is computationally expensive, especially in metagenomic analysis where data sets are large. Here, we introduce a hashing-based technique that leverages a kind of bottom-&lt;italic&gt;m&lt;/italic&gt; sketch as well as a &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer ternary search tree (KTST) to obtain &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer based similarity estimates for a range of &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt; values. By truncating &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mers stored in a pre-built KTST with a large &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt; = &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;max&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; value, we can simultaneously obtain &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer based estimates for all &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt; values up to &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;italic&gt;max&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;. This truncation approach circumvents the reconstruction of new &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-mer sets when changing &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt; values, making analysis more time and space-efficient. For example, we show that when using a KTST to estimate the containment index between a RefSeq-based microbial reference database and simulated metagenome data for 10 values of &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;, the running time is close to 10x faster compared to a classic MinHash approach while using less than one-fifth the space to store the data structure. A python implementation of this method, CMash, is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dkoslicki/CMash"&gt;https://github.com/dkoslicki/CMash&lt;/ext-link&gt;. The reproduction of all experiments presented herein can be accessed via &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/KoslickiLab/CMASH-reproducibles"&gt;https://github.com/KoslickiLab/CMASH-reproducibles&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471436" rel="alternate" title="CMash: fast, multi-resolution estimation of k-mer-based Jaccard and containment indices (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471115</id><title>TRAWLING: a Transcriptome Reference Aware of spLIciNG events (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419606+00:00</updated><author><name>Noemi Di Nanni</name></author><author><name>Alejandro Reyes</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ho</name></author><author><name>Robert Ihry</name></author><author><name>Audrey Kauffmann</name></author><author><name>Eric Y. Durand</name></author><author><name>Antoine de Weck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative splicing is critical for human gene expression regulation and plays an important role in multiple human diseases. In this context, RNA sequencing has emerged as powerful approach to detect alternative splicing events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In parallel, fast alignment-free methods have emerged as a viable alternative to quantify gene and transcript level abundance from RNAseq data. However, the ability to detect differential splicing events is dependent on the annotation of the transcript reference provided by the user.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we introduce a new reference transcriptome aware of splicing events, TRAWLING, which simplifies the detection of aberrant splicing events in a fast and simple way. In addition, we evaluate the performances and the benefits of aligning transcriptome data to TRAWLING using three different RNA sequencing datasets: whole transcriptome sequencing, single cell RNA sequencing and Digital RNA with pertUrbation of Genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Collectively, our comprehensive evaluation underlines the value of using TRAWLING in transcriptomic data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Novartis/TRAWLING"&gt;https://github.com/Novartis/TRAWLING&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.471115" rel="alternate" title="TRAWLING: a Transcriptome Reference Aware of spLIciNG events (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471323</id><title>LEXAS: a web application for life science experiment search and suggestion (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419744+00:00</updated><author><name>Kei K Ito</name></author><author><name>Yoshimasa Tsuruoka</name></author><author><name>Daiju Kitagawa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In cellular biology, researchers design wet experiments by reading the relevant articles and considering the described experiments and results. Today, researchers spend a long time exploring the literature in order to plan experiments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To accelerate experiment planning, we have developed a web application named LEXAS (Life-science EXperiment seArch and Suggestion). LEXAS curates the description of biomedical experiments and suggests the experiments on genes that could be performed next. To develop LEXAS, we first retrieved the descriptions of experiments from full-text biomedical articles archived in PubMed Central. Using these retrieved experiments and biomedical knowledgebases and databases, we trained a machine learning model that suggests the next experiments. This model can suggest not only reasonable genes but also novel genes as targets for the next experiment as long as they share some critical features with the gene of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;LEXAS is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://lexas.f.u-tokyo.ac.jp/"&gt;https://lexas.f.u-tokyo.ac.jp/&lt;/ext-link&gt; and provides users with two interfaces: search and suggestion. The search interface allows users to find a comprehensive list of experiment descriptions, and the suggestion interface allows users to find a list of genes that could be analyzed along with possible experiment methods. The source code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lexas-f-utokyo/lexas"&gt;https://github.com/lexas-f-utokyo/lexas&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;ito-delightfully-kei@g.ecc.u-tokyo.ac.jp&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471323" rel="alternate" title="LEXAS: a web application for life science experiment search and suggestion (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471476</id><title>A method to build extended sequence context models of point mutations and indels (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.419859+00:00</updated><author><name>Jörn Bethune</name></author><author><name>April Kleppe</name></author><author><name>Søren Besenbacher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The mutation rate of a specific position in the human genome depends on the sequence context surrounding it. Modeling the mutation rate by estimating a rate for each possible k-mer, however, only works for small values of k since the data becomes too sparse for larger values of k. Here we propose a new method that solves this problem by grouping similar k-mers using IUPAC patterns. We refer to the method as k-mer pattern partition and have implemented it in a software package called kmerPaPa. We use a large set of human &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; mutations to show that this new method leads to improved prediction of mutation rates and makes it possible to create models using wider sequence contexts than previous studies. Revealing that for some mutation types, the mutation rate of a position is significantly affected by nucleotides that are up to four base pairs away. As the first method of its kind, it does not only predict rates for point mutations but also indels. We have additionally created a software package called Genovo that, given a k-mer pattern partition model, predicts the expected number of synonymous, missense, and other functional mutation types for each gene. Using this software, we show that the created mutation rate models increase the statistical power to detect genes containing disease-causing variants and to identify genes under strong constraint, e.g. haploinsufficient genes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.471476" rel="alternate" title="A method to build extended sequence context models of point mutations and indels (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471549</id><title>DALI (Diversity AnaLysis Interface): a novel tool for the integrated analysis of multimodal single cell RNAseq data and immune receptor profiling (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420006+00:00</updated><author><name>Kevin Verstaen</name></author><author><name>Inés Lammens</name></author><author><name>Jana Roels</name></author><author><name>Yvan Saeys</name></author><author><name>Bart N Lambrecht</name></author><author><name>Niels Vandamme</name></author><author><name>Stijn Vanhee</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA sequencing is instrumental to unravel the cellular and transcriptomic heterogeneity of T and B cells in health and disease. Recent technological advances add additional layers of information allowing researchers to simultaneously explore the transcriptomic, surface protein and immune receptor diversity during adaptive immune responses. The increasing data complexicity poses a burden on the workload for bioinformaticians, who are often not familiar with the specificities and biology of immune receptor profiling. The wet-lab modalities and sequencing capabilities currently have outpaced bioinformatics solutions, which forms an ever-increasing barrier for many biologists to analyze their datasets. Here, we present DALI (Diversity AnaLysis Interface), a software package to identify and analyze T cell and B cell receptor diversity in high-throughput single-cell sequencing data. DALI aims to support bioinformaticians with a functional toolbox, allowing seamless integration of multimodel scRNAseq and immune receptor profiling data. The R-based package builds further on workflows using the Seurat package and other existing tools for BCR/TCR analyses. In addition, DALI is designed to engage immunologists having limited coding experience with their data, using a browser-based interactive graphical user interface. The implementation of DALI can effectively lead to a two-way communication between wet-lab scientists and bioinformaticians to advance the analysis of complex datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.07.471549" rel="alternate" title="DALI (Diversity AnaLysis Interface): a novel tool for the integrated analysis of multimodal single cell RNAseq data and immune receptor profiling (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471338</id><title>PIPP: Improving peptide identity propagation using neural networks (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420143+00:00</updated><author><name>Soroor Hediyeh-zadeh</name></author><author><name>Jarryd Martin</name></author><author><name>Melissa J. Davis</name></author><author><name>Andrew I. Webb</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Peptide identity propagation (PIP) can substantially reduce missing values in label-free mass spectrometry quantification by transferring peptides identified by tandem mass (MS/MS) spectra in one run to experimentally related runs where the peptides are not identified by MS/MS. The existing frameworks for matching identifications between runs perform peak tracing and propagation based on similarity of precursor features using only a limited number of dimensions available in MS1 data. These approaches do not produce accompanying confidence estimates and hence cannot filter probable false positive identity transfers. We introduce an embedding based PIP that uses a higher dimensional representation of MS1 measurements that is optimized to capture peptide identities using deep neural networks. We developed a propagation framework that works entirely on MaxQuant results. Current PIP workflows typically perform propagation mainly using two feature dimensions, and rely on deterministic tolerances for identification transfer. Our framework overcomes both these limitations while additionally assigning probabilities to each transferred identity. The proposed embedding approach enables quantification of the empirical false discovery rate (FDR) for peptide identification, while also increasing depth of coverage through coembedding the runs from the experiment with experimental libraries. In published datasets with technical and biological variability, we demonstrate that our method reduces missing values in MaxQuant results, maintains high quantification precision and accuracy, and low false transfer rate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.05.471338" rel="alternate" title="PIPP: Improving peptide identity propagation using neural networks (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471788</id><title>Efficient pre-processing of Single-cell ATAC-seq data (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420262+00:00</updated><author><name>Fan Gao</name></author><author><name>Lior Pachter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The primary tool currently used to pre-process 10X Chromium single-cell ATAC-seq data is Cell Ranger, which can take very long to run on standard datasets. To facilitate rapid pre-processing that enables reproducible workflows, we present a suite of tools called scATAK for pre-processing single-cell ATAC-seq data that is 18 times faster than Cell Ranger on human samples, and that uses 33% less RAM when 8 CPU threads are used. Our tool can also calculate chromatin interaction potential matrices, and generate open chromatin signals and interaction traces for cell groups. We demonstrate the utility of scATAK in an exploration of the chromatin regulatory landscape of a healthy adult human brain and show that it can reveal cell-type-specific features. 
scATAK is available at https://pachterlab.github.io/scATAK/.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471788" rel="alternate" title="Efficient pre-processing of Single-cell ATAC-seq data (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471986</id><title>Whole genome resequencing and comparative genome analysis of three Puccinia striiformis f. sp. tritici pathotypes prevalent in India (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420370+00:00</updated><author><name>Inderjit Singh Yadav</name></author><author><name>S. C. Bhardwaj</name></author><author><name>Jaspal Kaur</name></author><author><name>Deepak Singla</name></author><author><name>Satinder Kaur</name></author><author><name>Harmandeep Kaur</name></author><author><name>Nidhi Rawat</name></author><author><name>Vijay Kumar Tiwari</name></author><author><name>Diane Saunders</name></author><author><name>Cristobal Uauy</name></author><author><name>Parveen Chhuneja</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Stripe rust disease of wheat, caused by  Puccinia striiformis  f. sp.  tritici,  (  Pst  ) is one of the most serious diseases of wheat worldwide. In India, virulent stripe rust races have been constantly evolving in the North-Western Plains Zone leading to the failure of some of the most widely grown resistant varieties in the region. With the goal of studying the recent evolution of virulent races in this region, we conducted whole-genome sequencing of three prevalent Indian  Pst  pathotypes Pst46S119, Pst78S84 and Pst110S119. We assembled 58.62, 58.33 and 55.78 Mb of Pst110S119, Pst46S119 and Pst78S84 genome, respectively. Pathotypes were found to be highly heterozygous. Comparative phylogenetic analysis indicated the recent evolution of pathotypes Pst110S119 and Pst78S84 from Pst46S119. Pathogenicity-related genes classes (CAZyme, proteases, effectors, and secretome proteins) were identified and found to be under positive selection. Higher rate of gene family expansion was also observed in the three pathotypes. A strong association between the effector genes and transposable elements may be the source of the rapid evolution of these strains. Phylogenetic analysis differentiated the Indian races in this study from other known US, European, African and Asian races. Diagnostic markers developed for the identification of different Pst pathotypes will help tracking of yellow rust at farmers’ field and strategizing resistance gene deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.471986" rel="alternate" title="Whole genome resequencing and comparative genome analysis of three Puccinia striiformis f. sp. tritici pathotypes prevalent in India (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471786</id><title>Induced fit with replica exchange improves protein complex structure prediction (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420659+00:00</updated><author><name>Ameya Harmalkar</name></author><author><name>Sai Pooja Mahajan</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey J. Gray</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the progress in prediction of protein complexes over the last decade, recent blind protein complex structure prediction challenges revealed limited success rates (less than 20% models with DockQ score &amp;gt; 0.4) on targets that exhibit significant conformational change upon binding. To overcome limitations in capturing backbone motions, we developed a new, aggressive sampling method that incorporates temperature replica exchange Monte Carlo (T-REMC) and conformational sampling techniques within docking protocols in Rosetta.  Our method, ReplicaDock 2.0, mimics induced-fit mechanism of protein binding to sample backbone motions across putative interface residues on-the-fly, thereby recapitulating binding-partner induced conformational changes. Furthermore, ReplicaDock 2.0 clocks in at 150-500 CPU hours per target (protein-size dependent); a runtime that is significantly faster than Molecular Dynamics based approaches. For a benchmark set of 88 proteins with moderate to high flexibility (unbound-to-bound iRMSD over 1.2 Angstroms), ReplicaDock 2.0 successfully docks 61% of moderately flexible complexes and 35% of highly flexible complexes. Additionally, we demonstrate that by biasing backbone sampling particularly towards residues comprising flexible loops or hinge domains, highly flexible targets can be predicted to under 2 angstrom accuracy. This indicates that additional gains are possible when mobile protein segments are known.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.08.471786" rel="alternate" title="Induced fit with replica exchange improves protein complex structure prediction (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471213</id><title>Metabolic profiling of serum for osteoarthritis biomarkers (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420799+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziqian Xiao</name></author><author><name>Zhenyang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shanbin Huang</name></author><author><name>Jerome Rumdon Lon</name></author><author><name>Shuilin Xie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Osteoarthritis is a prevalent aging disease in the world, and in recent years it has shown a trend toward younger age, which is becoming a major health problem in the world and seriously endangers the health of the elderly. However, the etiology and pathogenesis of osteoarthritis are still unclear, causing great trouble for treatment. To screen out potential biomarkers that could be used as identification of osteoarthritis and explore the pathogenesis of osteoarthritis, we performed untargeted metabolomics analysis of nine New Zealand rabbit serum samples by LC-MS / MS, including three normal serum samples (control group) and six osteoarthritis serum samples (case group). Finally 44 differential metabolites were identified, and the ROC analysis results indicated that a total of 36 differential metabolites could be used as potential biomarkers. Further metabolic pathway enrichment analysis was performed on these differential metabolites, and we found that a total of 17 metabolic pathways were affected, which may provide directions for the study of osteoarthritis mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.04.471213" rel="alternate" title="Metabolic profiling of serum for osteoarthritis biomarkers (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470936</id><title>TargetGeneReg 2.0: a comprehensive web-atlas for p53, p63, and cell cycle-dependent gene regulation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-13T10:09:22.420933+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fischer</name></author><author><name>Konstantin Riege</name></author><author><name>Robert Schwarz</name></author><author><name>James A. DeCaprio</name></author><author><name>Steve Hoffmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, our web-atlas at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.TargetGeneReg.org"&gt;www.TargetGeneReg.org&lt;/ext-link&gt; has enabled many researchers to uncover new biological insights and to identify novel regulatory mechanisms that affect p53 and the cell cycle – signaling pathways that are frequently dysregulated in diseases like cancer. Here, we provide a substantial upgrade of the database that comprises an extension to include non-coding genes and the transcription factors ΔNp63 and RFX7. TargetGeneReg 2.0 combines gene expression profiling and transcription factor DNA binding data to determine, for each gene, the response to p53, ΔNp63, and cell cycle signaling. It can be used to dissect common, cell type, and treatment-specific effects, identify the most promising candidates, and validate findings. We demonstrate the increased power and more intuitive layout of the resource using realistic examples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.06.470936" rel="alternate" title="TargetGeneReg 2.0: a comprehensive web-atlas for p53, p63, and cell cycle-dependent gene regulation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>