<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.201009+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465371</id><title>Real-Time Structure Search and Structure Classification for AlphaFold Protein Models (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.201809+00:00</updated><author><name>Tunde Aderinwale</name></author><author><name>Vijay Bharadwaj</name></author><author><name>Charles Christoffer</name></author><author><name>Genki Terashi</name></author><author><name>Zicong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Rhashidedin Jahandideh</name></author><author><name>Yuki Kagaya</name></author><author><name>Daisuke Kihara</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;AlphaFold2 showed a substantial improvement in the accuracy of protein structure prediction. Following the release of the software, whole-proteome protein structure predictions by AlphaFold2 for 21 organisms were made publicly available. Here, we developed the infrastructure, 3D-AF-Surfer, to enable real-time structure-based search for the AlphaFold2 models by combining molecular surface representation with 3D Zernike descriptors and deep neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.21.465371" rel="alternate" title="Real-Time Structure Search and Structure Classification for AlphaFold Protein Models (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465087</id><title>A Network-based Deep Learning Framework Catalyzes GWAS and Multi-Omics Findings to Biology and Drug Repurposing for Alzheimer’s Disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.202219+00:00</updated><author><name>Jielin Xu</name></author><author><name>Yuan Hou</name></author><author><name>Yadi Zhou</name></author><author><name>Ming Hu</name></author><author><name>Feixiong Cheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Human genome sequencing studies have identified numerous loci associated with complex diseases, including Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Translating human genetic findings (i.e., genome-wide association studies [GWAS]) to pathobiology and therapeutic discovery, however, remains a major challenge. To address this critical problem, we present a &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;net&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;work &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;t&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;opology-based deep learning framework to identify disease-&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;a&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;ssociated &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;g&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;enes (NETTAG). NETTAG is capable of integrating multigenomics data along with the protein-protein interactome to infer putative risk genes and drug targets impacted by GWAS loci. Specifically, we leverage non-coding GWAS loci effects on expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs), histone-QTLs, and transcription factor binding-QTLs, enhancers and CpG islands, promoter regions, open chromatin, and promoter flanking regions. The key premises of NETTAG are that the disease risk genes exhibit distinct functional characteristics compared to non-risk genes and therefore can be distinguished by their aggregated genomic features under the human protein interactome. Applying NETTAG to the latest AD GWAS data, we identified 156 putative AD-risk genes (i.e., &lt;italic&gt;APOE&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;BIN1&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;GSK3B&lt;/italic&gt;, &lt;italic&gt;MARK4&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;PICALM&lt;/italic&gt;). We showed that predicted risk genes are: 1) significantly enriched in AD-related pathobiological pathways, 2) more likely to be differentially expressed regarding transcriptome and proteome of AD brains, and 3) enriched in druggable targets with approved medicines (i.e., choline and ibudilast). In summary, our findings suggest that understanding of human pathobiology and therapeutic development could benefit from a network-based deep learning methodology that utilizes GWAS findings under the multimodal genomic analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465087" rel="alternate" title="A Network-based Deep Learning Framework Catalyzes GWAS and Multi-Omics Findings to Biology and Drug Repurposing for Alzheimer’s Disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465108</id><title>hyperTRIBER: a flexible R package for the analysis of differential RNA editing (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-25T09:53:04.202434+00:00</updated><author><name>Sarah Rennie</name></author><author><name>Daniel Heidar Magnusson</name></author><author><name>Robin Andersson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA editing by ADAR (adenosine deaminase acting on RNA) is gaining an increased interest in the field of post-transcriptional regulation. Fused to an RNA-binding protein (RBP) of interest, the catalytic activity of ADAR results in A-to-I RNA edits, whose identification will determine RBP-bound RNA transcripts. However, the computational tools available for their identification and differential RNA editing statistical analysis are limited or too specialised for general-purpose usage. Here we present &lt;monospace&gt;hyperTRIBER&lt;/monospace&gt;, a flexible suite of tools, wrapped into a convenient R package, for the detection of differential RNA editing. &lt;monospace&gt;hyperTRIBER&lt;/monospace&gt; is applicable to complex scenarios and experimental designs, and provides a robust statistical framework allowing for the control for coverage of reads at a given base, the total expression level and other co-variates. We demonstrate the capabilities of our approach on HyperTRIBE RNA-seq data for the detection of bound RNAs by the &lt;italic&gt;N6&lt;/italic&gt;-methyladenosine (m&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;A) reader protein ECT2 in Arabidopsis roots. We show that &lt;monospace&gt;hyperTRIBER&lt;/monospace&gt; finds edits with a high statistical power, even where editing proportions and RNA transcript expression levels are low, together demonstrating its usability and versatility for analysing differential RNA editing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.20.465108" rel="alternate" title="hyperTRIBER: a flexible R package for the analysis of differential RNA editing (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>