<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.815193+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.464465</id><title>Polypolish: short-read polishing of long-read bacterial genome assemblies (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.815636+00:00</updated><author><name>Ryan R Wick</name></author><author><name>Kathryn E Holt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Long-read-only bacterial genome assemblies usually contain residual errors, most commonly homopolymer-length errors. Short-read polishing tools can use short reads to fix these errors, but most rely on short-read alignment which is unreliable in repeat regions. Errors in such regions are therefore challenging to fix and often remain after short-read polishing. Here we introduce Polypolish, a new short-read polisher which uses all-per-read alignments to repair errors in repeat sequences that other polishers cannot. In benchmarking tests using both simulated and real reads, we find that Polypolish performs well, and the best results are achieved by using Polypolish in combination with other short-read polishers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.14.464465" rel="alternate" title="Polypolish: short-read polishing of long-read bacterial genome assemblies (42 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.15.464546</id><title>Airpart: Interpretable statistical models for analyzing allelic imbalance in single-cell datasets (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.816066+00:00</updated><author><name>Wancen Mu</name></author><author><name>Hirak Sarkar</name></author><author><name>Avi Srivastava</name></author><author><name>Kwangbom Choi</name></author><author><name>Rob Patro</name></author><author><name>Michael I Love</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivation: Allelic expression analysis aids in detection of cis-regulatory mechanisms of genetic variation which produce allelic imbalance (AI) in heterozygotes. Measuring AI in bulk data lacking time or spatial resolution has the limitation that cell-type-specific (CTS), spatial-, or time-dependent AI signals may be dampened or not detected. Results: We introduce a statistical method airpart for identifying differential CTS AI from single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) data, or other spatially- or time-resolved datasets. airpart outputs discrete partitions of data, pointing to groups of genes and cells under common mechanisms of cis-genetic regulation. In order to account for low counts in single-cell data, our method uses a Generalized Fused Lasso with Binomial likelihood for partitioning groups of cells by AI signal, and a hierarchical Bayesian model for AI statistical inference. In simulation, airpart accurately detected partitions of cell types by their AI and had lower RMSE of allelic ratio estimates than existing methods. In real data, airpart identified differential AI patterns across cell states and could be used to define trends of AI signal over spatial or time axes. Availability: The airpart package is available as a R/Bioconductor package at https://bioconductor.org/packages/airpart.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.15.464546" rel="alternate" title="Airpart: Interpretable statistical models for analyzing allelic imbalance in single-cell datasets (32 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464028</id><title>HORmon: automated annotation of human centromeres (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.816419+00:00</updated><author><name>Olga Kunyavskaya</name></author><author><name>Tatiana Dvorkina</name></author><author><name>Andrey V. Bzikadze</name></author><author><name>Ivan A. Alexandrov</name></author><author><name>Pavel A. Pevzner</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in long-read sequencing opened a possibility to address the long-standing questions about the architecture and evolution of human centromeres. They also emphasized the need for centromere annotation (partitioning human centromeres into monomers and higher-order repeats (HORs)). Even though there was a half-century-long series of semi-manual studies of centromere architecture, a rigorous centromere annotation algorithm is still lacking. Moreover, an automated centromere annotation is a prerequisite for studies of genetic diseases associated with centromeres, and evolutionary studies of centromeres across multiple species. Although the monomer decomposition (transforming a centromere into a monocentromere written in the monomer alphabet) and the HOR decomposition (representing a monocentromere in the alphabet of HORs) are currently viewed as two separate problems, we demonstrate that they should be integrated into a single framework in such a way that HOR (monomer) inference affects monomer (HOR) inference. We thus developed the HORmon algorithm that integrates the monomer/HOR inference and automatically generates the human monomers/HORs that are largely consistent with the previous semi-manual inference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.12.464028" rel="alternate" title="HORmon: automated annotation of human centromeres (17 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.459411</id><title>GEOexplorer: an R/Bioconductor package for gene expression analysis and visualisation (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.816768+00:00</updated><author><name>Guy P Hunt</name></author><author><name>Rafael Henkin</name></author><author><name>Fabrizio Smeraldi</name></author><author><name>Michael R Barnes</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past three decades there have been numerous molecular biology developments that have led to an explosion in the number of gene expression studies being performed. Many of these gene expression studies publish their data to the public database GEO, making them freely available. By analysing gene expression datasets, researchers can identify genes that are differentially expressed between two groups. This can provide insights that lead to the development of new tests and treatments for diseases. Despite the wide availability of gene expression datasets, analysing them is difficult for several reasons. These reasons include the fact that most methods for performing gene expression analysis require programming proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed the GEOexplorer software package to overcome several of the difficulties in performing gene expression analysis. GEOexplorer was therefore developed as a web application, that can perform interactive and reproducible microarray gene expression analysis, while producing a wealth of interactive visualisations to facilitate result exploration. GEOexplorer is implemented in R using the Shiny framework and is fully integrated with the existing core structures of the Bioconductor project. Users can perform the essential steps of exploratory data analysis and differential gene expression analysis intuitively and generate a broad spectrum of publication ready outputs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GEOexplorer is distributed as an R package in the Bioconductor project (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioconductor.org/packages/GEOexplorer/"&gt;http://bioconductor.org/packages/GEOexplorer/&lt;/ext-link&gt;). GEOexplorer provides a solution for performing interactive and reproducible analyses of microarray gene expression data, empowering life scientists to perform exploratory data analysis and differential gene expression analysis on GEO microarray datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.06.459411" rel="alternate" title="GEOexplorer: an R/Bioconductor package for gene expression analysis and visualisation (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463729</id><title>Deep Learning Genome-wide Linkage Association Study for Wheat Fusarium Head Blight Resistance Genes Discovery (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.817092+00:00</updated><author><name>Wayne Xu</name></author><author><name>Andriy Bilichak</name></author><author><name>Raman Dhariwal</name></author><author><name>Maria A. Henriquez</name></author><author><name>Harpinder Randhawa</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Fusarium&lt;/italic&gt; head blight (FHB) is one of the most devastating diseases of wheat worldwide and artificial intelligence can assist with understanding resistance to the disease. Considering different sample populations, marker types, reference maps, and statistical methods, we developed a Deep Learning Genome-wide Linkage Association Study (dpGLAS) of FHB resistance in wheat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dpGLAS was first applied to two bi-parental population datasets in which the cultivar AC Barrie was a common parent for FHB resistance. Eight candidate gene markers were discovered in the one AC Barrie population and 10 in the other associated with FHB resistance. Eight of these markers were also supported by the conventional QTL mapping. Most of these candidate marker genes were found associated with the Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) and Abscisic acid (ABA) axes. These ROS and ABA pathways were further supported by RNA-seq transcriptome data of FHB resistant cv. AAC Tenacious, a parent of the third bi-parental population. In this dataset, the ROS-centered Panther protein families were significantly enriched in those genes that had most different response to FHB when compared the resistance Tenacious and the susceptible Roblin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study developed the framework of dpGLAS and identified candidate genes for FHB resistance in the Canadian spring wheat cultivars AC Barrie and AAC Tenacious.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.11.463729" rel="alternate" title="Deep Learning Genome-wide Linkage Association Study for Wheat Fusarium Head Blight Resistance Genes Discovery (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.15.464501</id><title>Identification of binding interaction between Curcumin derivative and PERK13 Proline rich receptor like protein kinase protein using In silico docking techniques – to help plants tackle salt water (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-18T08:35:20.817442+00:00</updated><author><name>Prakash Angadipuram Vaithyanathan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Arabidopsis thaliana, mouse ear cress or thale cress are small flowering plants included in the cruciferae family. They comprise of various characteristics such as diploid genetics, small genome size, rapid growth cycle, and relatively low repetitive DNA content, making it a perfect model for plant genome projects. Objective: The aim of this present Insilico research study is to carry out molecular drug docking studies between PERK13  Proline rich receptor like protein kinase and De O Acetylated Curcumin Di Galactose or digalactosylated curcumin, a derivative of curcumin. PERK13 protein is considered to play a significant role in helping plants tackle salinity levels in water. Methods: In this study, protein modelling tools and servers are used to model the 3D structure and the same is validated using Protein structure validation tools. Automated drug docking servers were used to dock the modelled protein with the chemical compound to analyse the electrostatic (H bond) interaction between PERK13 and De O Acetylated Curcumin Di Galactose, a better water soluble compound than curcumin. The docked structure was visualized using an advanced molecular visualization tool. Results and Discussion: The overall results obtained from this study on De O Acetylated Curcumin Di Galactose and PERK13 protein shows that De O Acetylated Curcumin Di Galactose, directly binds with the active site and other potentially binding regions of PERK13. Hence, it is concluded that De O Acetylated Curcumin Di Galactose could potentially play a vital role in future research related to the problem of helping the plants tackle increased saline levels in water. Keywords: A. thaliana, De O Acetylated Curcumin Di Galactose, Drug Docking, Insilico, PERK13, Protein Modelling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.15.464501" rel="alternate" title="Identification of binding interaction between Curcumin derivative and PERK13 Proline rich receptor like protein kinase protein using In silico docking techniques – to help plants tackle salt water (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>