<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.106752+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470769</id><title>No part gets left behind: Tiled nanopore sequencing of whole ASFV genomes stitched together using Lilo (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.107239+00:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Warr</name></author><author><name>Caitlin Newman</name></author><author><name>Nicky Craig</name></author><author><name>Ingrida Vendele</name></author><author><name>Rizalee Pilare</name></author><author><name>Lilet Cariazo Cruz</name></author><author><name>Twinkle Galase Barangan</name></author><author><name>Reildrin G Morales</name></author><author><name>Tanja I Opriessnig</name></author><author><name>Virginia Venturina</name></author><author><name>Milagros R Mananggit</name></author><author><name>Samantha Lycett</name></author><author><name>Clarissa Yvonne J Domingo</name></author><author><name>Christine Tait-Burkard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;African Swine Fever virus (ASFV) is the causative agent of a deadly, panzootic disease, infecting wild and domesticated suid populations. Contained for a long time to the African continent, an outbreak of a particularly infectious variant in Georgia in 2007 initiated the spread of the virus around the globe, severely impacting pork production and local economies. The virus is highly contagious and has a mortality of up to 100% in domestic pigs. It is critical to track the spread of the virus, detect variants associated with pathology, and implement biosecurity measures in the most effective way to limit its spread. Due to its size and other limitations, the 170-190kbp large DNA virus has not been well sequenced with fewer than 200 genome sequences available in public repositories. Here we present an efficient, low-cost method of sequencing ASFV at scale. The method uses tiled PCR amplification of the virus to achieve greater coverage, multiplexability and accuracy on a portable sequencer than achievable using shotgun sequencing. We also present Lilo, a pipeline for assembling tiled amplicon data from viral or microbial genomes without relying on polishing against a reference, allowing for structural variation and hypervariable region assembly other methods fail on. The resulting ASFV genomes are near complete, lacking only parts of the highly repetitive 3'- and 5'-telomeric regions, and have a high level of accuracy. Our results will allow sequencing of ASFV at optimal efficiency and high throughput to monitor and act on the spread of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470769" rel="alternate" title="No part gets left behind: Tiled nanopore sequencing of whole ASFV genomes stitched together using Lilo (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470966</id><title>U-CIE [/juː 'siː/]: Color encoding of high-dimensional data (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.107649+00:00</updated><author><name>Mikaela Koutrouli</name></author><author><name>John H. Morris</name></author><author><name>Lars Juhl Jensen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;U-CIE is a visualization method that encodes arbitrary high-dimensional data as colors using a combination of dimensionality reduction and the CIELAB color space to retain the original structure to the extent possible. We illustrate its broad applicability by visualizing single-cell data on a protein network and metagenomic data on a world map and on scatter plots. U-CIE is available as a web resource at https://u-cie.jensenlab.org/ and as an R package.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.470966" rel="alternate" title="U-CIE [/juː 'siː/]: Color encoding of high-dimensional data (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470739</id><title>Rapid, Reference-Free Human Genotype Imputation with Denoising Autoencoders (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.108333+00:00</updated><author><name>Raquel Dias</name></author><author><name>Doug Evans</name></author><author><name>Shang-Fu Chen</name></author><author><name>Kai-Yu Chen</name></author><author><name>Leslie Chan</name></author><author><name>Ali Torkamani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genotype imputation is a foundational tool for population genetics. Standard statistical imputation approaches rely on the co-location of large whole-genome sequencing-based reference panels, powerful computing environments, and potentially sensitive genetic study data. This results in computational resource and privacy-risk barriers to access to cutting-edge imputation techniques. Moreover, the accuracy of current statistical approaches is known to degrade in regions of low and complex linkage disequilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artificial neural network-based imputation approaches may overcome these limitations by encoding complex genotype relationships in easily portable inference models. Here we demonstrate an autoencoder-based approach for genotype imputation, using a large, commonly-used reference panel, and spanning the entirety of human chromosome 22. Our autoencoder-based genotype imputation strategy achieved superior imputation accuracy across the allele-frequency spectrum and across genomes of diverse ancestry, while delivering at least 4-fold faster inference run time relative to standard imputation tools.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470739" rel="alternate" title="Rapid, Reference-Free Human Genotype Imputation with Denoising Autoencoders (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.471022</id><title>Comprehensive mapping of the alternative polyadenylation site usage and its dynamics at single cell resolution (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.108784+00:00</updated><author><name>Junliang Wang</name></author><author><name>Wei Chen</name></author><author><name>Wenhong Hou</name></author><author><name>Ni Hong</name></author><author><name>Hanbing Zhong</name></author><author><name>Ting Ni</name></author><author><name>Yuanming Qi</name></author><author><name>Wenfei Jin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative polyadenylation (APA) plays an important role in post-transcriptional gene regulation such as transcript stability and translation efficiency. However, our knowledge about APA dynamics at single cell level is largely unexplored. Here we developed single cell polyadenylation sequencing (scPolyA-seq), a strand-specific approach for sequencing 3' end of transcripts, to investigate the landscape of APA at single cell level. By analyzing several cell lines, we found many genes using multiple polyA sites in bulk data are prone to use only one polyA site in each single cell. Interestingly, cell cycle was significantly enriched in genes showing high variation of polyA site usages. We further identified 414 genes showing polyA site usage switch after cell synchronization. Genes showing cell cycle associated polyA site usage switch were grouped into 6 clusters, with cell phase specific functional categories enriched in each cluster. Furthermore, scPolyA-seq could facilitate study of APA in various biological processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.02.471022" rel="alternate" title="Comprehensive mapping of the alternative polyadenylation site usage and its dynamics at single cell resolution (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.470940</id><title>Transcriptional shift and metabolic adaptations during Leishmania quiescence using stationary-phase and drug pressure as models (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.109531+00:00</updated><author><name>Marlene Jara</name></author><author><name>Michael Barrett</name></author><author><name>Ilse Maes</name></author><author><name>Clement Regnault</name></author><author><name>Hideo Imamura</name></author><author><name>Malgorzata Anna Domagalska</name></author><author><name>Jean Claude Dujardin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microorganisms can adopt a quiescent physiological condition which acts as a survival strategy under unfavourable conditions. Quiescent cells are characterized by slow or non-proliferation and deep down-regulation of processes related to biosynthesis. Although quiescence has been described mostly in bacteria, this survival skill is widespread, including in eukaryotic microorganisms. In Leishmania, a digenetic parasitic protozoan that causes a major infectious disease, quiescence has been demonstrated, but molecular and metabolic features enabling its maintenance are unknown. Here we quantified the transcriptome and metabolome of Leishmania promastigotes and amastigotes where quiescence was induced in vitro either through drug pressure or by stationary phase. Quiescent cells have a global and coordinated reduction in overall transcription, with levels dropping to as low as 0.4% of those in proliferating cells. However, a subset of transcripts did not follow this trend and were relatively upregulated in quiescent populations, including those encoding membrane components such as amastins and GP63 or processes like autophagy. The metabolome followed a similar trend of overall downregulation albeit to a lesser magnitude than the transcriptome. Noteworthy, among the commonly upregulated metabolites were those involved in carbon sources as an alternative to glucose. This first integrated two omics layers affords novel insights into cell regulation and shows commonly modulated features across stimuli and stages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.03.470940" rel="alternate" title="Transcriptional shift and metabolic adaptations during Leishmania quiescence using stationary-phase and drug pressure as models (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470731</id><title>Protein structure dynamic prediction: a Machine Learning/Molecular Dynamic approach to investigate the protein conformational sampling (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-06T09:31:49.111451+00:00</updated><author><name>Martina Audagnotto</name></author><author><name>Werngard Czechtizky</name></author><author><name>Leonardo De Maria</name></author><author><name>Helena Käck</name></author><author><name>Garegin Papoian</name></author><author><name>Lars Tornberg</name></author><author><name>Christian Tyrchan</name></author><author><name>Johan Ulander</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Proteins exist in several different conformations. These structural changes are often associated with fluctuations at the residue level. Recent findings show that co-evolutionary analysis coupled with machine- learning techniques improves the precision by providing quantitative distance predictions between pairs of residues. The predicted statistical distance distribution from Multi Sequence Analysis (MSA) reveals the presence of different local maxima suggesting the flexibility of key residue pairs. Here we investigate the ability of the residue-residue distance prediction to provide insights into the protein conformational ensemble. We combine deep learning approaches with mechanistic modeling to a set of proteins that experimentally showed conformational changes. The predicted protein models were filtered based on energy scores, RMSD clustering, and the centroids selected as the lowest energy structure per cluster. The models were compared to the experimental-Molecular Dynamics (MD) relaxed structure by analyzing the backbone residue torsional distribution and the sidechain orientations. Our pipeline not only allows us to retrieve the global experimental folding but also the experimental structural dynamics. We show the potential correlation between the experimental structure dynamics and the predicted model ensemble demonstrating the susceptibility of the current state-of-the-art methods in protein folding and dynamics prediction and pointing out the areas of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.01.470731" rel="alternate" title="Protein structure dynamic prediction: a Machine Learning/Molecular Dynamic approach to investigate the protein conformational sampling (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>