<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.820842+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448848</id><title>LongStitch: High-quality genome assembly correction and scaffolding using long reads (30 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-21T07:09:23.821245+00:00</updated><author><name>Lauren Coombe</name></author><author><name>Janet X Li</name></author><author><name>Theodora Lo</name></author><author><name>Johnathan Wong</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Nikolic</name></author><author><name>René L Warren</name></author><author><name>Inanc Birol</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generating high-quality &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; genome assemblies is foundational to the genomics study of model and non-model organisms. In recent years, long-read sequencing has greatly benefited genome assembly and scaffolding, a process by which assembled sequences are ordered and oriented through the use of long-range information. Long reads are better able to span repetitive genomic regions compared to short reads, and thus have tremendous utility for resolving problematic regions and helping generate more complete draft assemblies. Here, we present LongStitch, a scalable pipeline that corrects and scaffolds draft genome assemblies exclusively using long reads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;LongStitch incorporates multiple tools developed by our group and runs in up to three stages, which includes initial assembly correction (Tigmint-long), followed by two incremental scaffolding stages (ntLink and ARKS-long). Tigmint-long and ARKS-long are misassembly correction and scaffolding utilities, respectively, previously developed for linked reads, that we adapted for long reads. Here, we describe the LongStitch pipeline and introduce our new long-read scaffolder, ntLink, which utilizes lightweight minimizer mappings to join contigs. LongStitch was tested on short and long-read assemblies of three different human individuals using corresponding nanopore long-read data, and improves the contiguity of each assembly from 2.0-fold up to 304.6-fold (as measured by NGA50 length). Furthermore, LongStitch generates more contiguous and correct assemblies compared to state-of-the-art long-read scaffolder LRScaf in most tests, and consistently runs in under five hours using less than 23GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to its effectiveness and efficiency in improving draft assemblies using long reads, we expect LongStitch to benefit a wide variety of &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; genome assembly projects. The LongStitch pipeline is freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/bcgsc/longstitch"&gt;https://github.com/bcgsc/longstitch&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.17.448848" rel="alternate" title="LongStitch: High-quality genome assembly correction and scaffolding using long reads (30 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>