<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>BioRxiv preprints in bioinformatics posted in the last week with at least 5 tweets</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.453733+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.03.442417</id><title>Open issues for protein function assignment in Haloferax volcanii and other halophilic archaea (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.455773+00:00</updated><author><name>Friedhelm Pfeiffer</name></author><author><name>Mike Dyall-Smith</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annotation ambiguities and annotation errors are a general challenge in genomics. While a reliable protein function assignment can be obtained by experimental characterization, this is expensive and time-consuming, and the number of such Gold Standard Proteins (GSP) with experimental support remains very low compared to proteins annotated by sequence homology, usually through automated pipelines. Even a GSP may give a misleading assignment when used as a reference: the homolog may be close enough to support isofunctionality, but the substrate of the GSP is absent from the species being annotated. In such cases the enzymes cannot be isofunctional. Here, we examine a variety of such issues in halophilic archaea (class Halobacteria), with a strong focus on the model haloarchaeon &lt;italic&gt;Haloferax volcanii&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annotated proteins of &lt;italic&gt;Hfx. volcanii&lt;/italic&gt; were identified for which public databases tend to assign a function that is probably incorrect. In some cases, an alternative, probably correct, function can be predicted or inferred from the available evidence but this has not been adopted by public databases because experimental validation is lacking. In other cases, a probably invalid specific function is predicted by homology, and while there is evidence that this assigned function is unlikely, the true function remains elusive. We list 50 of those cases, each with detailed background information so that a conclusion about the most likely biological function can be drawn. For reasons of brevity and comprehension, only key aspects are listed in the main text, with detailed information being provided in a corresponding section of the Supplementary Material.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compiling, describing and summarizing these open annotation issues and functional predictions will benefit the scientific community in the general effort to improve the evaluation of protein function assignments and more thoroughly detail them. By highlighting the gaps and likely annotation errors currently in the databases, we hope this study will provide a framework for experimentalists to sytematically confirm (or disprove) our function predictions or to uncover yet unexpected functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.424421</id><title>q-mer analysis: a generalized method for analyzing RNA-Seq data (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.455583+00:00</updated><author><name>Tatsuma Shoji</name></author><author><name>Sato Yoshiharu</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNA-Seq data are usually summarized just by counting the number of reads aligned to each gene. However, this count-based method ignores the alignment information: where each read was mapped in the gene. This is very problematic because the alignment information retains the information regarding the second or third structure of mRNA, or protein-mRNA interaction including ribosomal distribution over mRNAs, which potentially reflects the sample conditions that we need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Method&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;To include the alignment information, we introduced “q-mer analysis”, a generalized method for analyzing RNA-Seq data. The q-mer analysis summarizes the RNA-Seq data using the “q-mer vector”: the ratio of 4&lt;sup&gt;q&lt;/sup&gt; kinds of q-length oligomer in the alignment data. Note that, by increasing the q value, q-mer analysis can produce the vector with a higher dimension than the one from the count-based method. This “dimensionality increment” is the key point to describe the sample conditions more accurately than the count-based method does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We first determined the appropriate q value in &lt;italic&gt;H. sapiens&lt;/italic&gt; by investigating how sparse each q-mer vector is using the publically available RNA-Seq dataset taken from 17 healthy or 19 cocaine-addicted cases (GEO accession number: GSE99349) as an example. As a result, q-mer vectors with q ≦ 9 had no zero elements, indicating at least q=9 is required to summarize the RNA-Seq data in &lt;italic&gt;H. sapiens&lt;/italic&gt;. The 4&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; = 262,144 is approximately 10 times larger than the number of genes in &lt;italic&gt;H. sapiens&lt;/italic&gt; (20,022 genes). Next, to examine the ability of q-mer analysis to describe the sample conditions especially with q &amp;gt; 9, we prepared the “q-mer matrix” by aligning the 36 q-mer vectors. Then, we decomposed the matrix using the principal component analysis (PCA) and (PC1, PC2) of each case was plotted onto a two-dimensional plane. As a result, the q-mer matrix with q ≧ 13 with PCA were successfully linearly distinguished cocaine-addicted cases from the healthy control cases on the plane while the matrix derived from the count-based method failed to separate, indicating the q-mer analysis describes the sample conditions more accurately than the count-based method does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduced q-mer analysis, a new method for analyzing RNA-Seq data, and demonstrated q-mer analysis can describe the sample conditions more accurately than the count-based methods does. The combination of RNA-Seq experiment and q-mer analysis will be the promising strong tool when describing the samples conditions or diseases in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.04.442567</id><title>Biological mechanisms of aging predict age-related disease multimorbidities in patients (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.455327+00:00</updated><author><name>Helen C Fraser</name></author><author><name>Valerie Kuan</name></author><author><name>Ronja Johnen</name></author><author><name>Magdalena Zwierzyna</name></author><author><name>Aroon D Hingorani</name></author><author><name>Andreas Beyer</name></author><author><name>Linda Partridge</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genetic, environmental and pharmacological interventions into the aging process can confer resistance to a multiple age-related diseases in laboratory animals, including rhesus monkeys. These findings imply that mechanisms of aging might contribute to patterns of multimorbidity in humans, and hence could be targeted to prevent multiple conditions simultaneously. To address this question, we text mined 917,645 literature abstracts followed by manual curation, and found strong, non-random associations between age-related diseases and aging mechanisms, confirmed by gene set enrichment analysis of GWAS data. Integration of these associations with clinical data from 3.01 million patients showed that age-related diseases associated with each of five aging mechanisms were more likely than chance to be present together in patients. Genetic evidence revealed that innate and adaptive immunity, the intrinsic apoptotic signalling pathway and activity of the ERK1/2 pathway played a significant role across multiple aging mechanisms and multiple, diverse age-related diseases. Mechanisms of aging therefore contribute to multiple age-related diseases and to patterns of human age-related multimorbidity, and could potentially be targeted to prevent more than one age-related condition in the same patient.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.02.442318</id><title>Inferring species compositions of complex fungal communities from long- and short-read sequence data (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.455136+00:00</updated><author><name>Yiheng Hu</name></author><author><name>Laszlo Irinyi</name></author><author><name>Minh Thuy Vi Hoang</name></author><author><name>Tavish Eenjes</name></author><author><name>Abigail Graetz</name></author><author><name>Eric Stone</name></author><author><name>Wieland Meyer</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Schwessinger</name></author><author><name>John P. Rathjen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The kingdom fungi is crucial for life on earth and is highly diverse. Yet fungi are challenging to characterize. They can be difficult to culture and may be morphologically indistinct in culture. They can have complex genomes of over 1 Gb in size and are still underrepresented in whole genome sequence databases. Overall their description and analysis lags far behind other microbes such as bacteria. At the same time, classification of species via high throughput sequencing without prior purification is increasingly becoming the norm for pathogen detection, microbiome studies, and environmental monitoring. However, standardized procedures for characterizing unknown fungi from complex sequencing data have not yet been established.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We compared different metagenomics sequencing and analysis strategies for the identification of fungal species. Using two fungal mock communities of 44 phylogenetically diverse species, we compared species classification and community composition analysis pipelines using shotgun metagenomics and amplicon sequencing data generated from both short and long read sequencing technologies. We show that regardless of the sequencing methodology used, the highest accuracy of species identification was achieved by sequence alignment against a fungi-specific database. During the assessment of classification algorithms, we found that applying cut-offs to the query coverage of each read or contig significantly improved the classification accuracy and community composition analysis without significant data loss.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, our study expands the toolkit for identifying fungi by improving sequence-based fungal classification, and provides a practical guide for the design of metagenomics analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.442219</id><title>DeepLIIF: Deep Learning-Inferred Multiplex ImmunoFluorescence for IHC Quantification (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.454934+00:00</updated><author><name>Parmida Ghahremani</name></author><author><name>Yanyun Li</name></author><author><name>Arie Kaufman</name></author><author><name>Rami Vanguri</name></author><author><name>Noah Greenwald</name></author><author><name>Michael Angelo</name></author><author><name>Travis J. Hollmann</name></author><author><name>Saad Nadeem</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reporting biomarkers assessed by routine immunohistochemical (IHC) staining of tissue is broadly used in diagnostic pathology laboratories for patient care. To date, clinical reporting is predominantly qualitative or semi-quantitative. By creating a multitask deep learning framework referred to as DeepLIIF, we are presenting a single step solution to nuclear segmentation and quantitative single-cell IHC scoring. Leveraging a unique &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; dataset of co-registered IHC and multiplex immunoflourescence (mpIF) data generated from the same tissue section, we simultaneously segment and translate low-cost and prevalent IHC slides to more expensive-yet-informative mpIF images. Moreover, a nuclear-pore marker, LAP2beta, is co-registered to improve cell segmentation and protein expression quantification on IHC slides. By formulating the IHC quantification as cell instance segmentation/classification rather than cell detection problem, we show that our model trained on clean IHC Ki67 data can generalize to more noisy and artifact-ridden images as well as other nuclear and non-nuclear markers such as CD3, CD8, BCL2, BCL6, MYC, MUM1, CD10 and TP53. We thoroughly evaluate our method on publicly available bench-mark datasets as well as against pathologists’ semi-quantitative scoring. The code, trained models, and the resultant embeddings for all the datasets used in this paper will be released via GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.01.442281</id><title>RNA splicing programs define tissue compartments and cell types at single cell resolution (40 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-09T14:38:49.454677+00:00</updated><author><name>Julia Eve Olivieri</name></author><author><name>Roozbeh Dehghannasiri</name></author><author><name>Peter Wang</name></author><author><name>SoRi Jang</name></author><author><name>Antoine de Morree</name></author><author><name>Serena Y. Tan</name></author><author><name>Jingsi Ming</name></author><author><name>Angela Ruohao Wu</name></author><author><name>Tabula Sapiens Consortium</name></author><author><name>Stephen R. Quake</name></author><author><name>Mark A. Krasnow</name></author><author><name>Julia Salzman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;More than 95% of human genes are alternatively spliced. Yet, the extent splicing is regulated at single-cell resolution has remained controversial due to both available data and methods to interpret it. We apply the SpliZ, a new statistical approach that is agnostic to transcript annotation, to detect cell-type-specific regulated splicing in &amp;gt; 110K carefully annotated single cells from 12 human tissues. Using 10x data for discovery, 9.1% of genes with computable SpliZ scores are cell-type specifically spliced. These results are validated with RNA FISH, single cell PCR, and in high throughput with Smart-seq2. Regulated splicing is found in ubiquitously expressed genes such as actin light chain subunit &lt;italic&gt;MYL6&lt;/italic&gt; and ribosomal protein &lt;italic&gt;RPS24&lt;/italic&gt;, which has an epithelial-specific microexon. 13% of the statistically most variable splice sites in cell-type specifically regulated genes are also most variable in mouse lemur or mouse. SpliZ analysis further reveals 170 genes with regulated splicing during sperm development using, 10 of which are conserved in mouse and mouse lemur. The statistical properties of the SpliZ allow model-based identification of subpopulations within otherwise indistinguishable cells based on gene expression, illustrated by subpopulations of classical monocytes with stereotyped splicing, including an un-annotated exon, in &lt;italic&gt;SAT1&lt;/italic&gt;, a Diamine acetyltransferase. Together, this unsupervised and annotation-free analysis of differential splicing in ultra high throughput droplet-based sequencing of human cells across multiple organs establishes splicing is regulated cell-type-specifically independent of gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>