<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.005251+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461077</id><title>ProteInfer: deep networks for protein functional inference (53 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.006085+00:00</updated><author><name>Theo Sanderson</name></author><author><name>Maxwell L. Bileschi</name></author><author><name>David Belanger</name></author><author><name>Lucy J. Colwell</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Predicting the function of a protein from its amino acid sequence is a long-standing challenge in bioinformatics. Traditional approaches use sequence alignment to compare a query sequence either to thousands of models of protein families or to large databases of individual protein sequences. Here we instead employ deep convolutional neural networks to directly predict a variety of protein functions – EC numbers and GO terms – directly from an unaligned amino acid sequence. This approach provides precise predictions which complement alignment-based methods, and the computational efficiency of a single neural network permits novel and lightweight software interfaces, which we demonstrate with an in-browser graphical interface for protein function prediction in which all computation is performed on the user’s personal computer with no data uploaded to remote servers. Moreover, these models place full-length amino acid sequences into a generalised functional space, facilitating downstream analysis and interpretation. To read the interactive version of this paper, please visit &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://google-research.github.io/proteinfer/"&gt;https://google-research.github.io/proteinfer/&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="461077v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;p&gt;QR code for the interactive version of this preprint at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://google-research.github.io/proteinfer/"&gt;https://google-research.github.io/proteinfer/&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461077" rel="alternate" title="ProteInfer: deep networks for protein functional inference (53 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461790</id><title>Cross-species cell-type assignment of single-cell RNA-seq by a heterogeneous graph neural network (45 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.007136+00:00</updated><author><name>Xingyan Liu</name></author><author><name>Qunlun Shen</name></author><author><name>Shihua Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cross-species comparative analyses of single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) data allow us to explore, at single-cell resolution, the origins of cellular diversity and the evolutionary mechanisms that shape cellular form and function. Here, we aimed to utilize a heterogeneous graph neural network to learn aligned and interpretable cell and gene embeddings for cross-species &lt;bold&gt;c&lt;/bold&gt;ell type &lt;bold&gt;a&lt;/bold&gt;ssignment and gene &lt;bold&gt;m&lt;/bold&gt;odule &lt;bold&gt;e&lt;/bold&gt;xtraction (CAME) from scRNA-seq data. A systematic evaluation study on 649 pairs of cross-species datasets showed that CAME outperformed six benchmarking methods in terms of cell-type assignment and model robustness to insufficiency and inconsistency of sequencing depths. Comparative analyses of the major types of human and mouse brains by CAME revealed shared cell type-specific functions in homologous gene modules. Alignment of the trajectories of human and macaque spermatogenesis by CAME revealed conservative gene expression dynamics during spermatogenesis between humans and macaques. Owing to the utilization of non-one-to-one homologous gene mappings, CAME made a significant improvement on cell-type characterization cross zebrafish and other species. Overall, CAME can not only make an effective cross-species assignment of cell types on scRNA-seq data but also reveal evolutionary conservative and divergent features between species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461790" rel="alternate" title="Cross-species cell-type assignment of single-cell RNA-seq by a heterogeneous graph neural network (45 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461825</id><title>A neural network-based method for exhaustive cell label assignment using single cell RNA-seq data (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.007447+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziyi Li</name></author><author><name>Hao Feng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The fast-advancing single cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) technology enables researchers to study the transcriptome of heterogeneous tissues at a single cell level. The initial important step of analyzing scRNA-seq data is usually to accurately annotate cells. The traditional approach of annotating cell types based on unsupervised clustering and marker genes is time-consuming and laborious. Taking advantage of the numerous existing scRNA-seq databases, many supervised label assignment methods have been developed. One feature that many label assignment methods shares is to label cells with low confidence as “unassigned.” These unassigned cells can be the result of assignment difficulties due to highly similar cell types or caused by the presence of unknown cell types. However, when unknown cell types are not expected, existing methods still label a considerable number of cells as unassigned, which is not desirable. In this work, we develop a neural network-based cell annotation method called NeuCA (Neural network-based Cell Annotation) for scRNA-seq data obtained from well-studied tissues. NeuCA can utilize the hierarchical structure information of the cell types to improve the annotation accuracy, which is especially helpful when data contain closely correlated cell types. We show that NeuCA can achieve more accurate cell annotation results compared with existing methods. Additionally, the applications on eight real datasets show that NeuCA has stable performance for intra- and inter-study annotation, as well as cross-condition annotation. NeuCA is freely available as an R/Bioconductor package at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/NeuCA"&gt;https://bioconductor.org/packages/NeuCA&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461825" rel="alternate" title="A neural network-based method for exhaustive cell label assignment using single cell RNA-seq data (35 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461597</id><title>Polygenic enrichment distinguishes disease associations of individual cells in single-cell RNA-seq data (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.007718+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Jinye Zhang</name></author><author><name>Kangcheng Hou</name></author><author><name>Kushal K. Dey</name></author><author><name>Karthik A. Jagadeesh</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Weinand</name></author><author><name>Saori Sakaue</name></author><author><name>Aris Taychameekiatchai</name></author><author><name>Poorvi Rao</name></author><author><name>Angela Oliveira Pisco</name></author><author><name>James Zou</name></author><author><name>Bruce Wang</name></author><author><name>Michael Gandal</name></author><author><name>Soumya Raychaudhuri</name></author><author><name>Bogdan Pasaniuc</name></author><author><name>Alkes L. Price</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene expression at the individual cell-level resolution, as quantified by single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq), can provide unique insights into the pathology and cellular origin of diseases and complex traits. Here, we introduce single-cell Disease Relevance Score (&lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt;), an approach that links scRNA-seq with polygenic risk of disease at individual cell resolution; &lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt; identifies individual cells that show excess expression levels for genes in a disease-specific gene set constructed from GWAS data. We determined via simulations that &lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt; is well-calibrated and powerful in identifying individual cells associated to disease. We applied &lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt; to GWAS data from 74 diseases and complex traits (average &lt;italic&gt;N&lt;/italic&gt; =341K) in conjunction with 16 scRNA-seq data sets spanning 1.3 million cells from 31 tissues and organs. At the cell type level, &lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt; broadly recapitulated known links between classical cell types and disease, and also produced novel biologically plausible findings. At the individual cell level, &lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt; identified subpopulations of disease-associated cells that are not captured by existing cell type labels, including subpopulations of CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells associated with inflammatory bowel disease, partially characterized by their effector-like states; subpopulations of hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons associated with schizophrenia, partially characterized by their spatial location at the proximal part of the hippocampal CA1 region; and subpopulations of hepatocytes associated with triglyceride levels, partially characterized by their higher ploidy levels. At the gene level, we determined that genes whose expression across individual cells was correlated with the &lt;monospace&gt;scDRS&lt;/monospace&gt; score (thus reflecting co-expression with GWAS disease genes) were strongly enriched for gold-standard drug target and Mendelian disease genes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461597" rel="alternate" title="Polygenic enrichment distinguishes disease associations of individual cells in single-cell RNA-seq data (28 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461295</id><title>pChem: a modification-centric assessment tool for the performance of chemoproteomic probes (15 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.020511+00:00</updated><author><name>Ji-Xiang He</name></author><author><name>Zheng-Cong Fei</name></author><author><name>Ling Fu</name></author><author><name>Cai-Ping Tian</name></author><author><name>Fu-Chu He</name></author><author><name>Si-Min He</name></author><author><name>Hao Chi</name></author><author><name>Jing Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We report a modification-centric, blind-search tool termed &lt;underline&gt;pChem&lt;/underline&gt; to provide a streamlined pipeline for unbiased assessing of the performance of chemoproteomic probes. The pipeline starts with an experimental setting for isotopically coding probe-derived modifications that can be automatically recognized, accurately calculated and precisely localized by pChem with neither prior knowledge nor manual inspection. Further, pChem exports on-demand reports by scoring the profiling efficiency, modification-homogeneity and proteome-wide residue selectivity of a tested probe. The performance and robustness of pChem were benchmarked by applying it to various bioorthogonal probes, including 15 activity-based protein profiling (ABPP) probes and 3 metabolic labeling probes. Together, pChem is a user-friendly computational tool for probe developers, even those with no experience in informatics, and aims to facilitate the development and optimization of probes for the ever-growing field of chemoproteomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461295" rel="alternate" title="pChem: a modification-centric assessment tool for the performance of chemoproteomic probes (15 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461581</id><title>SCONCE: A method for profiling Copy Number Alterations in Cancer Evolution using Single Cell Whole Genome Sequencing (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.021803+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandra Hui</name></author><author><name>Rasmus Nielsen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Copy number alterations are a significant driver in cancer growth and development, but remain poorly characterized on the single cell level. Although genome evolution in cancer cells is Markovian through evolutionary time, copy number alterations are not Markovian along the genome. However, existing methods call copy number profiles with Hidden Markov Models or change point detection algorithms based on changes in observed read depth, corrected by genome content, and do not account for the stochastic evolutionary process. We present a theoretical framework to use tumor evolutionary history to accurately call copy number alterations in a principled manner. In order to model the tumor evolutionary process and account for technical noise from low coverage single cell whole genome sequencing data, we developed SCONCE, a method based on a Hidden Markov Model to analyze read depth data from tumor cells using matched normal cells as negative controls. Using a combination of public datasets and simulations, we show SCONCE accurately decodes copy number profiles, with broader implications for understanding tumor evolution. SCONCE is implemented in C++11 and is freely available from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/NielsenBerkeleyLab/sconce"&gt;https://github.com/NielsenBerkeleyLab/sconce&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461581" rel="alternate" title="SCONCE: A method for profiling Copy Number Alterations in Cancer Evolution using Single Cell Whole Genome Sequencing (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461587</id><title>JaponicusDB: Rapid deployment of a model organism database for an emerging model species (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.024183+00:00</updated><author><name>Kim M. Rutherford</name></author><author><name>Midori A. Harris</name></author><author><name>Snezhana Oliferenko</name></author><author><name>Valerie Wood</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The fission yeast &lt;italic&gt;Schizosaccharomyces japonicus&lt;/italic&gt; has recently emerged as a powerful system for studying the evolution of essential cellular processes, drawing on similarities as well as key differences between &lt;italic&gt;S. japonicus&lt;/italic&gt; and the related, well-established model &lt;italic&gt;Schizosaccharomyces pombe&lt;/italic&gt;. We have deployed the open-source, modular code and tools originally developed for PomBase, the &lt;italic&gt;S. pombe&lt;/italic&gt; model organism database (MOD), to create JaponicusDB (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.japonicusdb.org"&gt;www.japonicusdb.org&lt;/ext-link&gt;), a new MOD dedicated to &lt;italic&gt;S. japonicus&lt;/italic&gt;. By providing a central resource with ready access to a growing body of experimental data, ontology-based curation, seamless browsing and querying, and the ability to integrate new data with existing knowledge, JaponicusDB supports fission yeast biologists to a far greater extent than any other source of &lt;italic&gt;S. japonicus&lt;/italic&gt; data. JaponicusDB thus enables &lt;italic&gt;S. japonicus&lt;/italic&gt; researchers to realise the full potential of studying a newly emerging model species, and illustrates the widely applicable power and utility of harnessing reusable PomBase code to build a comprehensive, community-maintainable repository of species-relevant knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461587" rel="alternate" title="JaponicusDB: Rapid deployment of a model organism database for an emerging model species (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461130</id><title>GBSmode: a pipeline for haplotype-aware analysis of genotyping-by-sequencing data (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.032114+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Yates</name></author><author><name>Bruno Studer</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;2&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;A&lt;sc&gt;bstract&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;label&gt;2.1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;B&lt;sc&gt;ackground&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genotyping-by-sequencing (GBS) has revolutionised molecular genetic analysis. It enables simultaneous genotyping of thousands of DNA markers in the genome of any species. In contrast to whole-genome shotgun sequencing, GBS exploits a restriction enzyme to reduce genome complexity and directs the sequencing to begin at fixed digestion sites. However, currently used tools for the analysis of GBS data, such as SAMtools, often neglect the fundamental technical differences between GBS and shotgun sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;label&gt;2.2&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;R&lt;sc&gt;esults&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present GBSmode, a dedicated pipeline to call DNA sequence variants using whole-read information from GBS data. It removes false positives by incorporating biological features such as the ploidy level and the number of possible alleles in the population under investigation. Comparison of GBSmode with SAMtools in an F2 population of rice (&lt;italic&gt;Oryza sativa&lt;/italic&gt; L.) showed both identified a similar number of polymorphisms (13,449 and 14,445, respectively) with a high overlap (8,143). However, differences were found in the number of read misalignments (8.0% and 14.3% for GBSmode and SAMtools, respectively) and genotyping errors (5.0% and 8.3% for GBSmode and SAMtools, respectively). Further tests in a bi-parental F1 population of cassava (&lt;italic&gt;Manihot esculenta&lt;/italic&gt; Crantz) showed GBSmode found 31,489 polymorphic loci, whereas the number was higher with SAMtools (43,860). However, this difference was mainly attributable to GBSmode rejecting 11,695 loci that were biologically not possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;label&gt;2.3&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;C&lt;sc&gt;onclusions&lt;/sc&gt;&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study shows that GBSmode is a versatile tool for the analysis of GBS data. Moreover, GBSmode was able to reduce genotyping errors arising from read misalignments by combining haplotype data with biological information. Whilst other tools may find more markers, GBSmode is designed for accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461130" rel="alternate" title="GBSmode: a pipeline for haplotype-aware analysis of genotyping-by-sequencing data (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462485</id><title>Repurposing CAR targets in solid tumors via a pan-cancer single-cell transcriptome analysis (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.032463+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanna Madan</name></author><author><name>Alejandro A. Schäffer</name></author><author><name>Eytan Ruppin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cell therapy is a powerful and promising tool for unleashing lasting antitumor immunity, which is currently studied in numerous blood and solid cancers. Here, mining single cell transcriptomics datasets of solid tumors, we survey many existing CAR targets, aiming to new solid tumor types in which these targets are differentially expressed in tumor cells and not on non-tumor cells within the tumor microenvironment, thus providing new repurposing opportunities. Quite surprisingly, we find that many existing solid cancer CAR targets have a better discriminatory power in uncharted cancer types than in the ones they have been developed or being tested for. Furthermore, we show that several existing liquid cancer CAR targets may also hold promise in specific solid tumors. Taken together, this analysis uncovers a large potential of repurposing current CARs that is currently yet untapped.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462485" rel="alternate" title="Repurposing CAR targets in solid tumors via a pan-cancer single-cell transcriptome analysis (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461229</id><title>A waveform-independent measure of recurrent neural activity (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.032808+00:00</updated><author><name>Immo Weber</name></author><author><name>Carina R. Oehrn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Rhythmic neural activity, so called oscillations, play a key role for neural information transmission, processing and storage. Neural oscillations in distinct frequency bands are central to physiological brain function and alterations thereof have been associated with several neurological and psychiatric disorders. The most common methods to analyse neural oscillations, e.g. short-term Fourier transform or wavelet analysis, assume that measured neural activity is composed of a series of symmetric prototypical waveforms, e.g. sinusoids. However, usually the models generating the signal, including waveform shapes of experimentally measured neural activity are unknown. Decomposing asymmetric waveforms of nonlinear origin using these classic methods may result in spurious harmonics visible in the estimated frequency spectra. Here, we introduce a new method for capturing rhythmic brain activity based on recurrences of similar states in phase-space. This method allows for a time-resolved estimation of amplitude fluctuations of recurrent activity irrespective of or specific to waveform-shapes. The algorithm is derived from the well-established field of recurrence analysis, which has rarely been adopted in neuroscience. In this paper, we show its advantages and limitations in comparison to short-time Fourier transform and wavelet convolution using periodic signals of different waveform shapes. Further, we demonstrate its application using experimental data, i.e. intracranial electrophysiological recordings from the human motor cortex of one epilepsy patient.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461229" rel="alternate" title="A waveform-independent measure of recurrent neural activity (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461277</id><title>Differential Network Analysis of Longitudinal Gene Expression in Response to Perturbations (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.033289+00:00</updated><author><name>Shuyue Xue</name></author><author><name>Lavida R.K. Rogers</name></author><author><name>Minzhang Zheng</name></author><author><name>Jin He</name></author><author><name>Carlo Piermarocchi</name></author><author><name>George I. Mias</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Understanding changes in gene expression under the effects of a perturbation is a key goal of systems biology. A powerful approach to address this goal uses gene networks and describes the perturbation’s effects as a rewiring of each gene’s connections. This approach is known as differential network (DN) analysis. Here, we used DNs to analyze RNA-sequencing time series datasets, focusing on expression changes: (i) In the saliva of a human subject after vaccination with a pneumococcal vaccine (PPSV23), and (ii) in B cells treated &lt;italic&gt;ex vivo&lt;/italic&gt; with a monoclonal antibody drug (Rituximab). Using network community detection, we revealed the collective behavior of clusters of genes, and detected communities of genes based on their longitudinal behavior, and corresponding pathway activations. We identified biological pathways consistent with the mechanism of action of the vaccine and with Rituximab’s targets. The approach may be useful in drug development by providing an effective analysis of expressing changes in response to a drug.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461277" rel="alternate" title="Differential Network Analysis of Longitudinal Gene Expression in Response to Perturbations (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461910</id><title>AlphaFold2: A role for disordered protein prediction? (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.037206+00:00</updated><author><name>Carter J. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Wing-Yiu Choy</name></author><author><name>Mikko Karttunen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of AlphaFold2 was a paradigm-shift in the structural biology community; herein we assess the ability of AlphaFold2 to predict disordered regions against traditional sequence-based disorder predictors. We find that a näive use of Dictionary of Secondary Structure of Proteins (DSSP) to separate ordered from disordered regions leads to a dramatic overestimation in disorder content, and that the Predicted Aligned Error (PAE) provides a much more rigorous metric. In addition, we show that even when used for disorder prediction, conventional predictors can outperform the PAE in disorder identification, and note an interesting relationship between the PAE and secondary structure that may explain our observations and hints at a broader application of the PAE to IDP dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461910" rel="alternate" title="AlphaFold2: A role for disordered protein prediction? (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.459925</id><title>Revisiting the Use of Structural Similarity Index in Hi-C (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.037549+00:00</updated><author><name>Hanjun Lee</name></author><author><name>Bruce Blumberg</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Lawrence</name></author><author><name>Toshi Shioda</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Identification of dynamic changes in chromatin conformation is a fundamental task in genetics. In 2020, Galan et al.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; presented CHESS (Comparison of Hi-C Experiments using Structural Similarity), a novel computational algorithm designed for systematic identification of structural differences in chromatin-contact maps. Using CHESS, the same group recently reported that chromatin organization is largely maintained across tissues during dorsoventral patterning of fruit fly embryos despite tissue-specific chromatin states and gene expression&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. However, here we show that the primary outputs of CHESS–namely, the structural similarity index (SSIM) profiles–are nearly identical regardless of the input matrices, even when query and reference reads were shuffled to destroy any significant differences. This issue stems from the dominance of the regional counting noise arising from stochastic sampling in chromatin-contact maps, reflecting a fundamentally incorrect assumption of the CHESS algorithm. Therefore, biological interpretation of SSIM profiles generated by CHESS requires considerable caution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.459925" rel="alternate" title="Revisiting the Use of Structural Similarity Index in Hi-C (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461359</id><title>Identification of Bacteriophages Using Deep Representation Model with Pre-training (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.037783+00:00</updated><author><name>Zeheng Bai</name></author><author><name>Yao-zhong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Satoru Miyano</name></author><author><name>Rui Yamaguchi</name></author><author><name>Satoshi Uematsu</name></author><author><name>Seiya Imoto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bacteriophages/Phages are viruses that infect and replicate within bacteria and archaea. Antibiotic resistance is one of the biggest threats to global health. The therapeutic use of bacteriophages provides another potential solution for solving antibiotic resistance. To develop phage therapies, the identification of phages from metagenome sequences is the fundamental step. Currently, several methods have been developed for identifying phages. These methods can be categorized into two types: database-based methods and alignmentfree methods. The database-based approach, such as VIBRANT, utilizes existing databases and compares sequence similarity between candidates and those in the databases. The alignment-free method, such as Seeker and DeepVirFinder, uses deep learning models to directly predict phages based on nucleotide sequences. Both approaches have their advantages and disadvantages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, we propose using a deep representation learning model with pre-training to integrate the database-based and non-alignment-based methods (we call it INHERIT). The pre-training is used as an alternative way for acquiring knowledge representations from existing databases, while the BERT-style deep learning framework retains the advantage of alignment-free methods. We compared the proposed method with VIBRANT and Seeker on a third-party benchmark dataset. Our experiments show that INHERIT achieves better performance than the database-based approach and the alignment-free method, with the best F1-score of 0.9868. Meanwhile, we demonstrated that using pre-trained models helps to improve the non-alignment deep learning model further.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.25.461359" rel="alternate" title="Identification of Bacteriophages Using Deep Representation Model with Pre-training (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461312</id><title>Optimised multiplex amplicon sequencing for mutation identification using the MinION nanopore sequencer (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.043426+00:00</updated><author><name>Whitney Whitford</name></author><author><name>Victoria Hawkins</name></author><author><name>Kriebashne Moodley</name></author><author><name>Matthew J. Grant</name></author><author><name>Klaus Lehnert</name></author><author><name>Russell G. Snell</name></author><author><name>Jessie C. Jacobsen</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Objective&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rapid, cost-effective identification of genetic variants in small candiate genomic regions remains a challenge, particularly for less well equipped or lower throughput laboratories. Application of Oxford Nanopore Technologies’ MinION sequencer has the potential to fulfil this requirement. We have developed a multiplexing assay which pools PCR amplicons for MinION sequencing to enable sequencing of multiple templates from multiple individuals which could be applied to gene-targeted diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A combined strategy of barcoding and sample pooling was developed for simultaneous multiplex MinION sequencing of 100 PCR amplicons, spanning 30 loci in DNA isolated from 82 neurodevelopmental cases and family members. The target regions were chosen for further interegation because a potentially disease-causative variants had been identified in affected individuals by Illumina exome sequencing. The pooled MinION sequences were deconvoluted by aligning to custom references using the guppy aligner software.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our multiplexing approach produced interpretable and expected sequence from 29 of the 30 targeted genetic loci. The sequence variant which was not correctly resolved in the MinION sequence was adjacent to a five nucleotide homopolymer. It is already known that homopolymers present a resolution problem with the MinION approach. Interstingly despite equimolar quantities of PCR amplicon pooled for sequencing, significant variation in the depth of coverage (139x – 21,499x; mean = 9,050, std err = 538.21) was observed. We observed independent relationships between depth of coverage and target length, and depth of coverage and GC content. These relationships demonstrate biases of the MinION sequencer for longer templates and those with lower GC content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate an efficient approach for variant discovery or confirmation from short DNA templates using the MinION sequencing device. With less than 140x depth of coverage required for accurate genotyping, the methodology described here allows for rapid highly multiplexed targeted sequencing of large numbers of samples in a minimally equipped laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461312" rel="alternate" title="Optimised multiplex amplicon sequencing for mutation identification using the MinION nanopore sequencer (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462040</id><title>Machine learning modeling of protein-intrinsic features predicts tractability of targeted protein degradation (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.044150+00:00</updated><author><name>Wubing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Shourya S. Roy Burman</name></author><author><name>Jiaye Chen</name></author><author><name>Katherine A. Donovan</name></author><author><name>Yang Cao</name></author><author><name>Boning Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zexian Zeng</name></author><author><name>Yi Zhang</name></author><author><name>Dian Li</name></author><author><name>Eric S. Fischer</name></author><author><name>Collin Tokheim</name></author><author><name>X. Shirley Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Targeted protein degradation (TPD) has rapidly emerged as a therapeutic modality to eliminate previously undruggable proteins by repurposing the cell’s endogenous protein degradation machinery. However, the susceptibility of proteins for targeting by TPD approaches, termed “degradability”, is largely unknown. Recent systematic studies to map the degradable kinome have shown differences in degradation between kinases with similar drug-target engagement, suggesting yet unknown factors influencing degradability. We therefore developed a machine learning model, MAPD (Model-based Analysis of Protein Degradability), to predict degradability from protein features that encompass post-translational modifications, protein stability, protein expression and protein-protein interactions. MAPD shows accurate performance in predicting kinases that are degradable by TPD compounds (auPRC=0.759) and is likely generalizable to independent non-kinase proteins. We found five features with statistical significance to achieve optimal prediction, with ubiquitination potential being the most predictive. By structural modeling, we found that E2-accessible ubiquitination sites, but not lysine residues in general, are particularly associated with kinase degradability. Finally, we extended MAPD predictions to the entire proteome to find 964 disease-causing proteins, including 278 cancer genes, that may be tractable to TPD drug development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462040" rel="alternate" title="Machine learning modeling of protein-intrinsic features predicts tractability of targeted protein degradation (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461746</id><title>Bakdrive: Identifying the Minimum Set of Bacterial Driver Species across Multiple Microbial Communities (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.044521+00:00</updated><author><name>Qi Wang</name></author><author><name>Michael Nute</name></author><author><name>Todd Treangen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interactions among microbes within microbial communities have been shown to play crucial roles in human health. In spite of recent progress, low-level knowledge of bacteria driving microbial interactions within microbiomes remains unknown, limiting our ability to fully understand and control microbial communities. In this study, we present a novel approach for identifying driver species within microbiomes. Bakdrive infers ecological networks of given metagenomic sequencing samples and identifies minimum sets of driver species using control theory. Bakdrive has three key innovations in this space: (i) it leverages inherent information from metagenomic sequencing samples to identify driver species, (ii) it explicitly takes host-specific variation into consideration, and (iii) it does not require a known ecological network. In extensive simulated data, we demonstrate identifying driver species identified from healthy donor samples and introducing them to the disease samples, we can restore the gut microbiome in recurrent &lt;italic&gt;Clostridioides difficile&lt;/italic&gt; infection patients to a healthy state. We also applied Bakdrive to two real datasets, rCDI and Crohn’s disease patients, uncovering driver species consistent with previous work. In summary, Bakdrive provides a novel approach for teasing apart microbial interactions. Bakdrive is open-source and available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gitlab.com/treangenlab/bakdrive"&gt;https://gitlab.com/treangenlab/bakdrive&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461746" rel="alternate" title="Bakdrive: Identifying the Minimum Set of Bacterial Driver Species across Multiple Microbial Communities (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461527</id><title>BionetBF: A Novel Bloom Filter for Faster Membership Identification of Paired Biological Network Data (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.044761+00:00</updated><author><name>Sabuzima Nayak</name></author><author><name>Ripon Patgiri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological network represents the interaction or relationship between the biological entities such as proteins and genes of a biological process. A biological network with thousands of millions of vertices makes its processing complex and challenging. In this article, we have proposed a novel Bloom Filter for biological networks, called BionetBF, to provide fast membership identification of the biological network edges or paired biological data. BionetBF is capable of executing millions of operations within a second on datasets having millions of paired biological data while occupying tiny amount of main memory. We have conducted rigorous experiments to prove the performance of BionetBF with large datasets. The experiment is conducted using 12 generated datasets and three biological network datasets. BionetBF demonstrates higher performance while maintaining a 0.001 false positive probability. BionetBF is also compared with other filters: Cuckoo Filter and Libbloom, where BionetBF proves its supremacy by exhibiting higher performance with a smaller sized memory compared with large sized filters of Cuckoo Filter and Libbloom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461527" rel="alternate" title="BionetBF: A Novel Bloom Filter for Faster Membership Identification of Paired Biological Network Data (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460993</id><title>deCS: A tool for systematic cell type annotations of single-cell RNA sequencing data among human tissues (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.044984+00:00</updated><author><name>Guangsheng Pei</name></author><author><name>Fangfang Yan</name></author><author><name>Lukas M. Simon</name></author><author><name>Yulin Dai</name></author><author><name>Peilin Jia</name></author><author><name>Zhongming Zhao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) is revolutionizing the study of complex and dynamic cellular mechanisms. However, cell-type annotation remains a main challenge as it largely relies on manual curation, which is cumbersome and less accurate. The increasing number of scRNA-seq data sets, as well as numerous published genetic studies, motivated us to build a comprehensive human cell type reference atlas. Here, we present &lt;italic&gt;deCS&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;underline&gt;de&lt;/underline&gt;coding &lt;underline&gt;C&lt;/underline&gt;ell type-&lt;underline&gt;S&lt;/underline&gt;pecificity), an automatic cell type annotation method based on a comprehensive collection of human cell type expression profiles or a list of marker genes. We applied &lt;italic&gt;deCS&lt;/italic&gt; to single-cell data sets from various tissue types, and systematically evaluated the annotation accuracy under various conditions, including reference panels, sequencing depth and feature selection. Our results demonstrated that expanding the references is critical for improving annotation accuracy. Compared to the existing state-of-the-art annotation tools, &lt;italic&gt;deCS&lt;/italic&gt; significantly reduced computation time while increased accuracy. &lt;italic&gt;deCS&lt;/italic&gt; can be integrated into the standard scRNA-seq analytical pipeline to enhance cell type annotation. Finally, we demonstrated the broad utility of &lt;italic&gt;deCS&lt;/italic&gt; to identify trait-cell type associations in 51 human complex traits, providing deeper insight into the cellular mechanisms of disease pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.19.460993" rel="alternate" title="deCS: A tool for systematic cell type annotations of single-cell RNA sequencing data among human tissues (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462364</id><title>Multi-omics and deep learning provide a multifaceted view of cancer (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.045240+00:00</updated><author><name>Bora Uyar</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Ronen</name></author><author><name>Vedran Franke</name></author><author><name>Gaetano Gargiulo</name></author><author><name>Altuna Akalin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer is a complex disease with a large financial and healthcare burden on society. One hallmark of the disease is the uncontrolled growth and proliferation of malignant cells. Unlike Mendelian diseases which may be explained by a few genomic loci, a deeper molecular and mechanistic understanding of the development of cancer is needed. Such an endeavor requires the integration of tens of thousands of molecular features across multiple layers of information encoded in the cells. In practical terms, this implies integration of multi omics information from the genome, transcriptome, epigenome, proteome, metabolome, and even micro-environmental factors such as the microbiome. Finding mechanistic insights and biomarkers in such a high dimensional space is a challenging task. Therefore, efficient machine learning techniques are needed to reduce the dimensionality of the data while simultaneously discovering complex but meaningful biomarkers. These markers then can lead to testable hypotheses in research and clinical applications. In this study, we applied advanced deep learning methods to uncover multi-omic fingerprints that are associated with a wide range of clinical and molecular features of tumor samples. Using these fingerprints, we can accurately classify different cancer types, and their subtypes. Non-linear multi-omic fingerprints can uncover clinical features associated with patient survival and response to treatment, ranging from chemotherapy to immunotherapy. In addition, multi-omic fingerprints may be deconvoluted into a meaningful subset of genes and genomic alterations to support clinically relevant decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="462364v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462364" rel="alternate" title="Multi-omics and deep learning provide a multifaceted view of cancer (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461475</id><title>Protein sequence profile prediction using ProtAlbert transformer (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.053473+00:00</updated><author><name>Armin Behjati</name></author><author><name>Fatemeh Zare-Mirakabad</name></author><author><name>Seyed Shahriar Arab</name></author><author><name>Abbas Nowzari-Dalini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein sequences can be viewed as a language; therefore, we benefit from using the models initially developed for natural languages such as transformers. ProtAlbert is one of the best pre-trained transformers on protein sequences, and its efficiency enables us to run the model on longer sequences with less computation power while having similar performance with the other pre-trained transformers. This paper includes two main parts: transformer analysis and profile prediction. In the first part, we propose five algorithms to assess the attention heads in different layers of ProtAlbert for five protein characteristics, nearest-neighbor interactions, type of amino acids, biochemical and biophysical properties of amino acids, protein secondary structure, and protein tertiary structure. These algorithms are performed on 55 proteins extracted from CASP13 and three case study proteins whose sequences, experimental tertiary structures, and HSSP profiles are available. This assessment shows that although the model is only pre-trained on protein sequences, attention heads in the layers of ProtAlbert are representative of some protein family characteristics. This conclusion leads to the second part of our work. We propose an algorithm called PA_SPP for protein sequence profile prediction by pre-trained ProtAlbert using masked-language modeling. PA_SPP algorithm can help the researchers to predict an HSSP profile while there are no similar sequences to a query sequence in the database for making the HSSP profile.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461475" rel="alternate" title="Protein sequence profile prediction using ProtAlbert transformer (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461731</id><title>Double reduction estimation and equilibrium tests in natural autopolyploid populations (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.053934+00:00</updated><author><name>David Gerard</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many bioinformatics pipelines include tests for equilibrium. Tests for diploids are well studied and widely available, but extending these approaches to autopolyploids is hampered by the presence of double reduction, the co-migration of sister chromatid segments into the same gamete during meiosis. Though a hindrance for equilibrium tests, double reduction rates are quantities of interest in their own right, as they provide insights about the meiotic behavior of autopolyploid organisms. Here, we develop procedures to (i) test for equilibrium while accounting for double reduction, and (ii) estimate double reduction given equilibrium. To do so, we take two approaches: a likelihood approach, and a novel &lt;italic&gt;U&lt;/italic&gt;-statistic minimization approach that we show generalizes the classical equilibrium &lt;italic&gt;χ&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; test in diploids. For small sample sizes and uncertain genotypes, we further develop a bootstrap procedure based on our &lt;italic&gt;U&lt;/italic&gt;-statistic to test for equilibrium. Finally, we highlight the difficulty in distinguishing between random mating and equilibrium in tetraploids at biallelic loci. Our methods are implemented in the hwep R package on GitHub &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dcgerard/hwep"&gt;https://github.com/dcgerard/hwep&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461731" rel="alternate" title="Double reduction estimation and equilibrium tests in natural autopolyploid populations (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462283</id><title>In silico screening of TMPRSS2 SNPs that affect its binding with SARS-CoV2 spike protein and directly involved in the interaction affinity changes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.054184+00:00</updated><author><name>Fatma Nouira</name></author><author><name>Manel Hamdi</name></author><author><name>Alaeddine Redissi</name></author><author><name>Soumaya Kouidhi</name></author><author><name>Cherine Charfeddine</name></author><author><name>Meriem M’saad</name></author><author><name>Ameur Cherif</name></author><author><name>Sabri Messaoudi</name></author><author><name>Sarah Aldulaijan</name></author><author><name>Noureddine Raouafi</name></author><author><name>Adnene Dhouib</name></author><author><name>Amor Mosbah</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we used in silico analysis to shed light on the possible interaction between TMPRSS2 and SARS-CoV2 spike (S) protein by examining the role of TMPRSS2 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in relation with susceptibility and inter-individual variability of SARS-CoV2 infection. First, we used molecular docking of human TMPRSS2 protein to predict the binding site of TMPRSS2, especially the TMPRSS2 link loops, in order to assess the effect TMPRSS2 SNPs. The latter lead to missense variants on the interaction between TMPRSS2 and SARS-CoV2 S protein. In a second step, we further refine our analysis by performing a structure-function analysis of the complexes using PyMol software, and finally by MD simulations to validate the as-obtained results. Our findings show that 17 SNPs among the 692 natural TMPRSS2 coding variants are in positions to influence the binding of TMPRSS2 with the viral S protein. All of them give more important interaction energy as assessed by docking. Among the 17 SNPs, four missense variants E389A, K392Q, T393S and Q438E lead to “directly increasing” the interaction affinity and 2 missense variants R470I and Y416C cause it “directly decreasing”. The R470I and Y416C present in African and American population, respectively. While the other 4 SNP variants (E389A; K392Q; T393S and Q438E) are present only in the European population, which could link the viral infection susceptibility to demographic, geographic and genetic factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462283" rel="alternate" title="In silico screening of TMPRSS2 SNPs that affect its binding with SARS-CoV2 spike protein and directly involved in the interaction affinity changes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461564</id><title>Dirichlet variational autoencoders for de novo motif discovery from accessible chromatin (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.054467+00:00</updated><author><name>Meghana Kshirsagar</name></author><author><name>Han Yuan</name></author><author><name>Juan Lavista Ferres</name></author><author><name>Christina Leslie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Determining the cell type-specific and genome-wide binding locations of transcription factors (TFs) is an important step towards decoding gene regulatory programs. Profiling by the assay for transposase-accessible chromatin using sequencing (ATAC-seq) reveals open chromatin sites that are potential binding sites for TFs but does not identify which TFs occupy a given site. We present a novel unsupervised deep learning approach called BindVAE, based on Dirichlet variational autoencoders, for jointly decoding multiple TF binding signals from open chromatin regions. Our approach automatically learns distinct groups of kmer patterns that correspond to cell type-specific &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; binding signals. Latent factors found by BindVAE generally map to TFs that are expressed in the input cell type. BindVAE finds different TF binding sites in different cell types and can learn composite patterns for TFs involved in co-operative binding. BindVAE therefore provides a novel unsupervised approach to deconvolve the complex TF binding signals in chromatin accessible sites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461564" rel="alternate" title="Dirichlet variational autoencoders for de novo motif discovery from accessible chromatin (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461089</id><title>Deriving time-concordant event cascades from gene expression data: A case study for Drug-Induced Liver Injury (DILI) (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.054706+00:00</updated><author><name>Anika Liu</name></author><author><name>Namshik Han</name></author><author><name>Jordi Munoz-Muriedas</name></author><author><name>Andreas Bender</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adverse event pathogenesis is often a complex process which compromises multiple events ranging from the molecular to the phenotypic level. Adverse Outcome Pathways (AOPs) aim to formalize this as temporal sequences of events, in which event relationships should be supported by causal evidence according to the tailored Bradford-Hill criteria. One of the criteria is whether events are consistently observed in a certain temporal order and, in this work, we study this time concordance between gene expression- and histopathology-derived events as data-driven means to generate hypotheses on potentially causal mechanisms. As a case study, we analysed liver data from repeat-dose studies in rats from the TG-GATEs database which comprises measurements across eight timepoints, ranging from 3 hours to 4 weeks post-treatment. We identified time concordant pathway- and transcription factor (TF)-level events preceding adverse histopathology, which serves as surrogate readout for Drug-Induced Liver Injury (DILI). Among known events in DILI, we found some to change strongly before adverse histopathology, e.g. fatty acid beta oxidation, while others were more confident, e.g. bile acid recycling, or frequent, e.g. ATF4-mediated stress response, further characterizing their mechanistic roles. Moreover, we used the temporal order of TF expression and regulon activity to separate induced TFs, such as Cebpa, from post-transcriptionally activated ones, e.g. Srebf2, and subsequently combined this with known functional interactions (TF-target or protein-protein) to derive detailed gene-regulatory mechanisms, such as Hnf4a-dependent Cebpa expression. We additionally evaluate which time concordant events show sustained or increasing activation over time, as this time dependence is favourable for biomarker development, and identify pathways indicating dyslipidaemia, and a decrease in Hnf1a and Hnf4a indicating deteriorating liver function. At the same, time also potentially novel events are identified such as Sox13 which shows a more significant time dependence and -concordance than many known TFs in liver injury. Overall, we demonstrate how time-resolved transcriptomics can derive and support mechanistic hypotheses by quantifying time concordance and how this can be combined with prior causal knowledge, with the aim of both understanding mechanisms of toxicity, as well as potential applications to the AOP framework. We make our results available in the form of a Shiny app (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/anikaliu/DILICascades_App"&gt;https://github.com/anikaliu/DILICascades_App&lt;/ext-link&gt;), which allows users to query events of interest in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;One key challenge in statistical analysis is to infer causation instead of correlation, in particular in case of observational data. The conserved temporal order of events, their time concordance, is thereby one potential source of evidence and consequentially time-series data is particularly suited to study causal mechanisms. In this study, we present an automatable framework to quantify and characterize time concordance across a large set of time-series, and we apply this concept to gene-expression- and histopathology-derived events derived from the TG-GATEs &lt;italic&gt;in vivo&lt;/italic&gt; liver data as a case study. We were able to recover known events involved in the pathogenesis of Drug-Induced Liver Injury (DILI), and identify potentially novel pathway and transcription factors (TFs) which precede adverse histopathology. As complementary sources of evidence for causality, we additionally show how time concordance and prior knowledge on plausible interactions between TFs can be combined to derive causal hypotheses on the TFs’ mode of regulation and interaction partners. Overall, the results derived in our case study can serve as valuable hypothesis-free starting points for the development of Adverse Outcome Pathways for DILI, and demonstrate that our approach provides a novel angle to prioritize mechanistically relevant events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461089" rel="alternate" title="Deriving time-concordant event cascades from gene expression data: A case study for Drug-Induced Liver Injury (DILI) (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461074</id><title>Single Object Profiles Regression Analysis (SOPRA): A novel method for analyzing high content cell-based screens (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.054956+00:00</updated><author><name>Rajendra Kumar Gurumurthy</name></author><author><name>Klaus-Peter Pleissner</name></author><author><name>Cindrilla Chumduri</name></author><author><name>Thomas F. Meyer</name></author><author><name>André P. Mäurer</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;High content screening (HCS) experiments generate complex data from multiple object features for each cell within a treated population. Usually these data are analyzed by using population-averaged values of the features of interest, increasing the amount of false positives and the need for intensive follow-up validation. Therefore, there is a strong need for novel approaches with reproducible hit prediction by identifying significantly altered cell populations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we describe SOPRA, a workflow for analyzing image-based HCS data based on regression analysis of non-averaged object features from cell populations, which can be run on hundreds of samples using different cell features. Following plate-wise normalization the values are counted within predetermined binning intervals, generating unique frequency distribution profiles (histograms) for each population, which are then normalized to control populations. Statistically significant differences are identified using a regression model approach. Significantly changed profiles can be used to generate a heatmap from which altered cell populations with similar phenotypes are identified, enabling detection of siRNAs and compounds with the same ‘on-target’ profile, reducing the number of false positive hits. A screen for cell cycle progression was used to validate the workflow, which identified statistically significant changes induced by siRNA-mediated gene perturbations and chemical inhibitors of different cell cycle stages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461074" rel="alternate" title="Single Object Profiles Regression Analysis (SOPRA): A novel method for analyzing high content cell-based screens (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461211</id><title>PharmacoDB 2.0 : Improving scalability and transparency of in vitro pharmacogenomics analysis (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.056188+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikta Feizi</name></author><author><name>Sisira Kadambat Nair</name></author><author><name>Petr Smirnov</name></author><author><name>Gangesh Beri</name></author><author><name>Christopher Eeles</name></author><author><name>Parinaz Nasr Esfahani</name></author><author><name>Minoru Nakano</name></author><author><name>Denis Tkachuk</name></author><author><name>Anthony Mammoliti</name></author><author><name>Evgeniya Gorobets</name></author><author><name>Arvind Singh Mer</name></author><author><name>Eva Lin</name></author><author><name>Yihong Yu</name></author><author><name>Scott Martin</name></author><author><name>Marc Hafner</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Haibe-Kains</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cancer pharmacogenomics studies provide valuable insights into disease progression and associations between genomic features and drug response. PharmacoDB integrates multiple cancer pharmacogenomics datasets profiling approved and investigational drugs across cell lines from diverse tissue types. The web-application enables users to efficiently navigate across datasets, view and compare drug dose-response data for a specific drug-cell line pair. In the new version of PharmacoDB (version 2.0, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pharmacodb.ca/"&gt;https://pharmacodb.ca/&lt;/ext-link&gt;), we present: (&lt;italic&gt;i&lt;/italic&gt;) new datasets such as NCI-60, the Profiling Relative Inhibition Simultaneously in Mixtures (PRISM) dataset, as well as updated data from the Genomics of Drug Sensitivity in Cancer (GDSC) and the Genentech Cell Line Screening Initiative (gCSI); (&lt;italic&gt;ii&lt;/italic&gt;) implementation of FAIR data pipelines using ORCESTRA and PharmacoDI; (&lt;italic&gt;iii&lt;/italic&gt;) enhancements to drug response analysis such as tissue distribution of dose-response metrics and biomarker analysis; (&lt;italic&gt;iv&lt;/italic&gt;) improved connectivity to drug and cell line databases in the community. The web interface has been rewritten using a modern technology stack to ensure scalability and standardization to accommodate growing pharmacogenomics datasets. PharmacoDB 2.0 is a valuable tool for mining pharmacogenomics datasets, comparing and assessing drug response phenotypes of cancer models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;PharmacoDB 2.0 includes new and updated large pharmacogenomic datasets. The data processing for PharmacoDB is made fully reproducible through the use of the ORCESTRA platform and automated data ingestion pipelines&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new release contains enriched annotations for drugs and cell lines via connectivity to external databases, as well as new analytical methods for tissue-specific and pan-cancer biomarker discovery&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new version of PharmacoDB incorporates a scalable and reproducible framework that can accelerate the implementation of analytical pipelines including machine learning/AI for biomarker discovery in the future&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461211" rel="alternate" title="PharmacoDB 2.0 : Improving scalability and transparency of in vitro pharmacogenomics analysis (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461522</id><title>Energy efficient convolutional neural networks for arrhythmia detection (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.057029+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikoletta Katsaouni</name></author><author><name>Florian Aul</name></author><author><name>Lukas Krischker</name></author><author><name>Sascha Schmalhofer</name></author><author><name>Lars Hedrich</name></author><author><name>Marcel H. Schulz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Electrocardiograms (ECG) record the heart activity and are the most common and reliable method to detect cardiac arrhythmias, such as atrial fibrillation (AFib). Lately, many commercially available devices such as smartwatches are offering ECG monitoring. Therefore, there is increasing demand for designing deep learning models with the perspective to be physically implemented on these small portable devices with limited energy supply. In this paper, a workflow for the design of small, energy-efficient recurrent convolutional neural network (RCNN) architecture for AFib detection is proposed. However, the approach can be well generalized to every type of long time series. In contrast to previous studies, that demand thousands of additional network neurons and millions of extra model parameters, the logical steps for the generation of a CNN with only 114 trainable parameters are described. The model consists of a small segmented CNN in combination with an optimal energy classifier. The architectural decisions are made by using the energy consumption as a metric in an equally important way as the accuracy. The optimisation steps are focused on the software which can be embedded afterwards on a physical chip. Finally, a comparison with some previous relevant studies suggests that the widely used huge CNNs for similar tasks are mostly redundant and unessentially computationally expensive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461522" rel="alternate" title="Energy efficient convolutional neural networks for arrhythmia detection (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461072</id><title>DeNovoCNN: A deep learning approach to de novo variant calling in next generation sequencing data (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.057341+00:00</updated><author><name>Gelana Khazeeva</name></author><author><name>Karolis Sablauskas</name></author><author><name>Bart van der Sanden</name></author><author><name>Wouter Steyaert</name></author><author><name>Michael Kwint</name></author><author><name>Dmitrijs Rots</name></author><author><name>Max Hinne</name></author><author><name>Marcel van Gerven</name></author><author><name>Helger Yntema</name></author><author><name>Lisenka Vissers</name></author><author><name>Christian Gilissen</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;De novo&lt;/italic&gt; mutations (DNMs) are an important cause of genetic disorders. The accurate identification of DNMs from sequencing data is therefore fundamental to rare disease research and diagnostics. Unfortunately, identifying reliable DNMs remains a major challenge due to sequence errors, uneven coverage, and mapping artifacts. Here, we developed a deep convolutional neural network (CNN) DNM caller (DeNovoCNN), that encodes alignment of sequence reads for a trio as 160×164 resolution images. DeNovoCNN was trained on DNMs of whole exome sequencing (WES) of 2003 trios achieving on average 99.2% recall and 93.8% precision. We find that DeNovoCNN has increased recall/sensitivity and precision compared to existing &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; calling approaches (GATK, DeNovoGear, Samtools) based on the Genome in a Bottle reference dataset. Sanger validations of DNMs called in both exome and genome datasets confirm that DeNovoCNN outperforms existing methods. Most importantly, we show that DeNovoCNN is robust against different exome sequencing and analyses approaches, thereby allowing it to be applied on other datasets. DeNovoCNN is freely available and can be run on existing alignment (BAM/CRAM) and variant calling (VCF) files from WES and WGS without a need for variant recalling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461072" rel="alternate" title="DeNovoCNN: A deep learning approach to de novo variant calling in next generation sequencing data (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461055</id><title>Detection of m6A from direct RNA sequencing using a Multiple Instance Learning framework (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.057677+00:00</updated><author><name>Christopher Hendra</name></author><author><name>Ploy N. Pratanwanich</name></author><author><name>Yuk Kei Wan</name></author><author><name>W.S. Sho Goh</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Thiery</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Göke</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;RNA modifications such as m6A methylation form an additional layer of complexity in the transcriptome. Nanopore direct RNA sequencing captures this information in the raw current signal for each RNA molecule, enabling the detection of RNA modifications using supervised machine learning. However, experimental approaches provide only site-level training data, whereas the modification status for each single RNA molecule is missing. Here we present m6Anet, a neural network-based method that leverages the Multiple Instance Learning framework to specifically handle missing read-level modification labels in site-level training data. m6Anet outperforms existing computational methods, shows similar accuracy as experimental approaches, and generalises to different cell lines with almost identical accuracy. We demonstrate that m6Anet captures the underlying read-level stoichiometry that can be used to approximate differences in modification rates. m6Anet achieves this without retraining model parameters, enabling the transcriptome-wide identification and quantification of m6A from a single run of direct RNA sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Code Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source code for m6Anet is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/GoekeLab/m6anet"&gt;https://github.com/GoekeLab/m6anet&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Installation instructions and online documentation is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://m6anet.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;https://m6anet.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461055" rel="alternate" title="Detection of m6A from direct RNA sequencing using a Multiple Instance Learning framework (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461437</id><title>Nonparametric Interrogation of Transcriptional Regulation in Single-Cell RNA and Chromatin Accessibility Multiomic Data (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.058023+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuriko Harigaya</name></author><author><name>Zhaojun Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hongpan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Chongzhi Zang</name></author><author><name>Nancy R Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yuchao Jiang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Epigenetic control of gene expression is highly cell-type- and context-specific. Yet, despite its complexity, gene regulatory logic can be broken down into modular components consisting of a transcription factor (TF) activating or repressing the expression of a target gene through its binding to a &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory region. Recent advances in joint profiling of transcription and chromatin accessibility with single-cell resolution offer unprecedented opportunities to interrogate such regulatory logic. Here, we propose a nonparametric approach, TRIPOD, to detect and characterize three-way relationships between a TF, its target gene, and the accessibility of the TF’s binding site, using single-cell RNA and ATAC multiomic data. We apply TRIPOD to interrogate cell-type-specific regulatory logic in peripheral blood mononuclear cells and contrast our results to detections from enhancer databases, &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-eQTL studies, ChIP-seq experiments, and TF knockdown/knockout studies. We then apply TRIPOD to mouse embryonic brain data during neurogenesis and gliogenesis and identified known and novel putative regulatory relationships, validated by ChIP-seq and PLAC-seq. Finally, we demonstrate TRIPOD on SHARE-seq data of differentiating mouse hair follicle cells and identify lineage-specific regulation supported by histone marks for gene activation and super-enhancer annotations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461437" rel="alternate" title="Nonparametric Interrogation of Transcriptional Regulation in Single-Cell RNA and Chromatin Accessibility Multiomic Data (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461882</id><title>Using causality and correlation analysis to decipher microbial interactions in activated sludge (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.058865+00:00</updated><author><name>Weiwei Cai</name></author><author><name>Xiangyu Han</name></author><author><name>Hong Yao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Network theory is widely used to understand microbial interactions in activated sludge and numerous other artificial and natural environments. However, when using correlation-based methods, it is not possible to identify the directionality of interactions within microbiota. Based on the classic Granger test of sequencing-based time-series data, a new Microbial Causal Correlation Network (MCCN) was constructed with distributed ecological interaction on the directed, associated links. As a result of applying MCCN to a time series of activated sludge data, we found that the hub species OTU56, classified as belonging the genus &lt;italic&gt;Nitrospira&lt;/italic&gt;, was responsible for completing nitrification in activated sludge, and mainly interacted with &lt;italic&gt;Proteobacteria&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Bacteroidetes&lt;/italic&gt; in the form of amensal and commensal relationships, respectively. Phylogenetic tree suggested a mutualistic relationship between Nitrospira and denitrifiers. &lt;italic&gt;Zoogloea&lt;/italic&gt; displayed the highest &lt;italic&gt;ncf&lt;/italic&gt; value within the classified OTUs of the MCCN, indicating that it could be a foundation for activated sludge through forming the characteristic cell aggregate matrices into which other organisms embed during floc formation. Overall, the introduction of causality analysis greatly expands the ability of a network to shed a light on understanding the interactions between members of a microbial community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461882" rel="alternate" title="Using causality and correlation analysis to decipher microbial interactions in activated sludge (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461544</id><title>Expert-integrated automated machine learning uncovers hemodynamic predictors in spinal cord injury (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.059171+00:00</updated><author><name>Austin Chou</name></author><author><name>Abel Torres-Espin</name></author><author><name>Nikos Kyritsis</name></author><author><name>J. Russell Huie</name></author><author><name>Sarah Khatry</name></author><author><name>Jeremy Funk</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Hay</name></author><author><name>Andrew Lofgreen</name></author><author><name>Rajiv Shah</name></author><author><name>Chandler McCann</name></author><author><name>Lisa U Pascual</name></author><author><name>Edilberto Amorim</name></author><author><name>Philip R Weinstein</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey T Manley</name></author><author><name>Sanjay S Dhall</name></author><author><name>Jonathan Z Pan</name></author><author><name>Jacqueline C Bresnahan</name></author><author><name>Michael S Beattie</name></author><author><name>William D Whetstone</name></author><author><name>Adam R Ferguson</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Automated machine learning (AutoML) is positioned to democratize artificial intelligence (AI) by reducing the amount of human input and ML expertise needed to create prediction models. However, successful translation of ML in biomedicine requires moving beyond optimizing only for prediction accuracy and towards discovering reproducible clinical and biological inferences. Here, we present a model-agnostic framework to reinforce AutoML using strategies and tools of explainable and reproducible AI, including novel metrics for performance precision and feature instability. The framework enables clinicians to interpret AutoML-generated models for clinical and biological verifiability and consequently integrate domain expertise during model development. We applied the framework towards spinal cord injury prognostication and identified a detrimental relationship between intraoperative hypertension and patient outcome. Furthermore, our analysis captured evolving clinical practices such as faster time-to-surgery and blood pressure management that affected clinical model validation. Altogether, we illustrate how augmenting AutoML for inferential reproducibility empowers biomedical discovery and builds trust in AI processes towards effective clinical integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.461544" rel="alternate" title="Expert-integrated automated machine learning uncovers hemodynamic predictors in spinal cord injury (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.460959</id><title>OnePetri: accelerating common bacteriophage Petri dish assays with computer vision (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.060670+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael Shamash</name></author><author><name>Corinne F. Maurice</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Introduction&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bacteriophage plaque enumeration is a critical step in a wide array of protocols. The current gold standard for plaque enumeration on Petri dishes is through manual counting. This approach is time-intensive, has low-throughput, is limited to Petri dishes which have a countable number of plaques, and can have variable results upon recount due to human error.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present OnePetri, a collection of trained machine learning models and open-source mobile application for the rapid enumeration of bacteriophage plaques on circular Petri dishes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;When compared against the current gold standard of manual counting, OnePetri was significantly faster, with minimal error. Compared against two other similar tools, Plaque Size Tool and CFU.AI, OnePetri had higher plaque recall and reduced detection times on most test images.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The OnePetri application can rapidly enumerate phage plaques on circular Petri dishes with high precision and recall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.460959" rel="alternate" title="OnePetri: accelerating common bacteriophage Petri dish assays with computer vision (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461345</id><title>Identification of active modules in interaction networks using node2vec network embedding (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.061054+00:00</updated><author><name>Claude Pasquier</name></author><author><name>Vincent Guerlais</name></author><author><name>Denis Pallez</name></author><author><name>Raphaël Rapetti-Mauss</name></author><author><name>Olivier Soriani</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The identification of condition-specific gene sets from transcriptomic experiments is important to reveal regulatory and signaling mechanisms associated with a given cellular response. Statistical approaches using only expression data allow the identification of genes whose expression is most altered between different conditions. However, a phenotype is rarely a direct consequence of the activity of a single gene, but rather reflects the interplay of several genes to carry out certain molecular processes. Many methods have been proposed to analyze the activity of genes in light of our knowledge of their molecular interactions. However, existing methods have many limitations that make them of limited use to biologists: they detect modules that are too large, too small, or they require the users to specify a priori the size of the modules they are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose AMINE (Active Module Identification through Network Embedding), an efficient method for the identification of active modules. Experiments carried out on artificial data sets show that the results obtained are more reliable than many available methods. Moreover, the size of the modules to be identified is not a fixed parameter of the method and does not need to be specified; rather, it adjusts according to the size of the modules to be found. The applications carried out on real datasets show that the method enables to find important genes already highlighted by approaches solely based on gene variations, but also to identify new groups of genes of high interest. In addition, AMINE method can be used as a web service on your own data (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://amine.i3s.unice.fr"&gt;http://amine.i3s.unice.fr&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461345" rel="alternate" title="Identification of active modules in interaction networks using node2vec network embedding (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461335</id><title>Automated 3D reconstruction of the fetal thorax in the standard atlas space from motion-corrupted MRI stacks for 21-36 weeks GA range (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.061354+00:00</updated><author><name>Alena Uus</name></author><author><name>Irina Grigorescu</name></author><author><name>Milou P.M. van Poppel</name></author><author><name>Johannes K. Steinweg</name></author><author><name>Thomas A. Roberts</name></author><author><name>Mary A. Rutherford</name></author><author><name>Joseph V. Hajnal</name></author><author><name>David F.A. Lloyd</name></author><author><name>Kuberan Pushparajah</name></author><author><name>Maria Deprez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Slice-to-volume registration (SVR) methods allow reconstruction of high-resolution 3D images from multiple motion-corrupted stacks. SVR-based pipelines have been increasingly used for motion correction for fetal MRI since they allow more informed and detailed diagnosis of brain and body anomalies including congenital heart defects (Lloyd et al., 2019). Recently, fully automated rigid SVR reconstruction of the fetal brain in the atlas space was achieved in (Salehi et al., 2019) that used segmentation and pose estimation convolutional neural networks (CNNs). However, these CNN-based methods have not yet been applied to the fetal body region. Meanwhile, the existing rigid and deformable SVR (DSVR) solutions (Uus et al., 2020) for the fetal trunk region are limited by the requirement of manual input as well the narrow capture range of the classical gradient descent based registration methods that cannot resolve severe fetal motion frequently occurring at the early gestational age (GA). Furthermore, in our experience, the conventional 2D slice-wise CNN-based brain masking solutions are reportedly prone to errors that require manual corrections when applied on a wide range of acquisition protocols or abnormal cases in clinical setting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, we propose a fully automated pipeline for reconstruction of the fetal thorax region for 21-36 weeks GA range MRI datasets. It includes 3D CNN-based intra-uterine localisation of the fetal trunk and landmark-guided pose estimation steps that allow automated DSVR reconstruction in the standard radiological space irrespective of the fetal body position or the regional stack coverage. The additional step for generation of the common template space and rejection of outliers provides the means for automated exclusion of stacks affected by low image quality or extreme motion. The pipeline was evaluated on a series of experiments including fetal MRI datasets and simulated rotation motion. Furthermore, we performed a qualitative assessment of the image reconstruction quality in terms of the definition of vascular structures on 100 early (median 23.14 weeks) and late (median 31.79 weeks) GA group MRI datasets covering 21 to 36 weeks GA range.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461335" rel="alternate" title="Automated 3D reconstruction of the fetal thorax in the standard atlas space from motion-corrupted MRI stacks for 21-36 weeks GA range (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461375</id><title>Literature-Based Discovery beyond the ABC paradigm: a contrastive approach (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.061802+00:00</updated><author><name>Erwan Moreau</name></author><author><name>Orla Hardiman</name></author><author><name>Mark Heverin</name></author><author><name>Declan O’Sullivan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Literature-Based Discovery (LBD) aims to help researchers to identify relations between concepts which are worthy of further investigation by text-mining the biomedical literature. The vast majority of the LBD research follows the ABC model: a relation (A,C) is a candidate for discovery if there is some intermediate concept B which is related to both A and C. The ABC model has been successful in applications where the search space is strongly constrained, but there is limited evidence about its usefulness when applied in a broader context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through a case study of 8 recent discoveries related to neurodegenerative diseases (NDs), we show the limitations of the ABC model in an open-ended context. The study emphasizes the impact of the choice of source data and extraction method on the resulting knowledge base: different “views” of the biomedical literature offer different levels of accuracy and coverage. We propose a novel contrastive approach which leverages these differences between “views” in order to target relations between concepts of interest. We explore various parameters and demonstrate the relevance of our approach through quantitative evaluation on the 8 target discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source data used in this article are publicly available. The different parts of the software used to process the data are published under open-source license and provided with detailed instructions. The main code for this paper is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/erwanm/lbd-contrast"&gt;https://github.com/erwanm/lbd-contrast&lt;/ext-link&gt; (required dependencies are detailed in the documentation). A prototype of the system is also provided as an online exploration tool at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brainmend.adaptcentre.ie/"&gt;brainmend.adaptcentre.ie&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.22.461375" rel="alternate" title="Literature-Based Discovery beyond the ABC paradigm: a contrastive approach (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461460</id><title>Biclique extension as an effective approach to predict novel interaction partners in metabolic compound-protein interaction networks (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.062060+00:00</updated><author><name>Sandra Thieme</name></author><author><name>Dirk Walther</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metabolic networks are complex systems of connected chemical reactions with physical interactions between metabolites and proteins playing a critical role for both metabolic conversion and regulation. In this study, we aimed to predict previously unknown compound-protein interactions (CPI) by transferring the concept of biclique extension, which was developed in the context of drug-target interaction prediction and that is based on the rationale that interactions that readily extend an existing biclique are real, to metabolic CPI networks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed and tested a workflow to predict CPIs based on the concept of extending existing bicliques and applied it to &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; and human using their respective known CPI network as input. Depending on the chosen biclique size, for the &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt; network we reached a sensitivity of 39% with an associated precision of 59%. For the larger human CPI network, a sensitivity of 78% with a false-positive rate of less than 5% and an associated precision of 75% was obtained. At more stringent settings, a precision as high as 95% was attainable at the expense of a lowered recall. Prediction performance significantly exceeded that obtained using randomized networks as input. Predicted novel interactions were tested for biomolecular function involvement, with TCA-cycle and ribosomal processes found associated with particularly pronounced statistical significance. As we demonstrate, our approach holds great potential to increase efficiency of experimental testing of CPIs and can readily be transferred to other species of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The R code and datasets are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/SandraThieme/BiPredict"&gt;https://github.com/SandraThieme/BiPredict&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461460" rel="alternate" title="Biclique extension as an effective approach to predict novel interaction partners in metabolic compound-protein interaction networks (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462262</id><title>Open Imputation Server provides secure Imputation services with provable genomic privacy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.065064+00:00</updated><author><name>Arif O. Harmanci</name></author><author><name>Miran Kim</name></author><author><name>Su Wang</name></author><author><name>Wentao Li</name></author><author><name>Yongsoo Song</name></author><author><name>Kristin E. Lauter</name></author><author><name>Xiaoqian Jiang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As DNA sequencing data is available for personal use, genomic privacy is becoming a major challenge. Nevertheless, high-throughput genomic data analysis outsourcing is performed using pipelines that tend to overlook these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a client-server-based outsourcing framework for genotype imputation, an important step in genomic data analyses. Genotype data is encrypted by the client and encrypted data are used by the server that never observes the data in plain. Cloud-based framework can benefit from virtually unlimited computational resources while providing provable confidentiality. We demonstrate server’s utility from several aspects using genotype dataset from the 1000 Genomes datasets. First, we benchmark the accuracy of common variant imputation in comparison to BEAGLE, a state-of-the-art imputation method. We also provide the detailed time requirements of the server to showcase scaling of time usage in different steps of imputation. We also present a simple correlation metric that can be used to estimate imputation accuracy using only the reference panels. This is important for filtering the variants in downstream analyses. As a further demonstration and a different use case, we performed a simulated genomewide association study (GWAS) using imputed and known genotypes and highlight potential utility of the server for association studies. Overall, our study present multiple lines of evidence for usability of secure imputation service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Server is publicly available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.secureomics.org/OpenImpute"&gt;https://www.secureomics.org/OpenImpute&lt;/ext-link&gt;. Users can anonymously test and use imputation server without registration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;Arif.O.Harmanci@uth.tmc.edu&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.30.462262" rel="alternate" title="Open Imputation Server provides secure Imputation services with provable genomic privacy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461161</id><title>rsRNASP: A residue-separation-based statistical potential for RNA 3D structure evaluation (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.065407+00:00</updated><author><name>Ya-Lan Tan</name></author><author><name>Xunxun Wang</name></author><author><name>Ya-Zhou Shi</name></author><author><name>Wenbing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhi-Jie Tan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Knowledge-based statistical potentials have been shown to be rather effective in protein 3-dimensional (3D) structure evaluation and prediction. Recently, several statistical potentials have been developed for RNA 3D structure evaluation, while their performances are either still at low level for the test datasets from structure prediction models or dependent on the “black-box” process through neural networks. In this work, we have developed an all-atom distance-dependent statistical potential based on residue separation for RNA 3D structure evaluation, namely rsRNASP, which is composed of short- and long-ranged potentials distinguished by residue separation. The extensive examinations against available RNA test datasets show that, rsRNASP has apparently higher performance than the existing statistical potentials for the realistic test datasets with large RNAs from structure prediction models including the newly released RNA-Puzzles dataset, and is comparable to the existing top statistical potentials for the test datasets with small RNAs or near-native decoys. Additionally, rsRNASP is also superior to RNA3DCNN, a recently developed scoring function through 3D convolutional neural networks. rsRNASP and the relevant databases are available at website &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Tan-group/rsRNASP"&gt;https://github.com/Tan-group/rsRNASP&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;SIGNIFICANCE&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;RNAs play crucial roles in catalyzing biochemical reactions and regulating gene expression, and the biological functions of RNAs are generally coupled to their structures. Complementary to experiments, developing computational models to predict RNA 3D structures can be very helpful for understanding RNA biology functions. For a computational model, a reliable energy function is essentially important either for guiding conformational folding or for structure evaluation. For this purpose, we developed a residue-separation-based distance-dependent statistical potential, named rsRNASP which distinguishes the short- and long-ranged interactions, for RNA 3D structure evaluation. Our rsRNASP were examined against extensive test sets and shows overall superior performance over existing top traditional statistical potentials and a recently developed scoring function through 3D convolutional neural networks, especially for realistic test set from various computational structure prediction models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.20.461161" rel="alternate" title="rsRNASP: A residue-separation-based statistical potential for RNA 3D structure evaluation (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461307</id><title>Single shot detector application for image disease localization (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.065923+00:00</updated><author><name>Rushikesh Chopade</name></author><author><name>Aditya Stanam</name></author><author><name>Shrikant Pawar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bounding box algorithms are useful in localization of image patterns. Recently, utilization of convolutional neural networks on X-ray images has proven a promising disease prediction technique. However, pattern localization over prediction has always been a challenging task with inconsistent coordinates, sizes, resolution and capture positions of an image. Several model architectures like Fast R-CNN, Faster R-CNN, Histogram of Oriented Gradients (HOG), You only look once (YOLO), Region-based Convolutional Neural Networks (R-CNN), Region-based Fully Convolutional Networks (R-FCN), Single Shot Detector (SSD), etc. are used for object detection and localization in modern-day computer vision applications. SSD and region-based detectors like Fast R-CNN or Faster R-CNN are very similar in design and implementation, but SSD have shown to work efficiently with larger frames per second (FPS) and lower resolution images. In this article, we present a unique approach of SSD with a VGG-16 network as a backbone for feature detection of bounding box algorithm to predict the location of an anomaly within chest X-ray image.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461307" rel="alternate" title="Single shot detector application for image disease localization (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462084</id><title>PlasmidHostFinder: Prediction of plasmid hosts using random forest (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.066189+00:00</updated><author><name>Derya Aytan-Aktug</name></author><author><name>Philip TLC Clausen</name></author><author><name>Judit Szarvas</name></author><author><name>Patrick Munk</name></author><author><name>Saria Otani</name></author><author><name>Marcus Nguyen</name></author><author><name>James J Davis</name></author><author><name>Ole Lund</name></author><author><name>Frank M Aarestrup</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Plasmids play a major role facilitating the spread of antimicrobial resistance between bacteria. Understanding the host range and dissemination trajectories of plasmids is critical for surveillance and prevention of antimicrobial resistance. Identification of plasmid host ranges could be improved using automated pattern detection methods, compared to homology-based methods due to the diversity and genetic plasticity of plasmids. In this study, we developed a method for predicting the host range of plasmids based on the random forest machine learning method. We trained the models with 8,519 plasmids from 359 different bacterial species per taxonomic level, where the models achieved 0.662 and 0.867 Matthews correlation coefficients at the species and order levels, respectively. Our results suggest that despite the diverse nature and genetic plasticity of plasmids, our random forest model can accurately distinguish between plasmid hosts. This tool can be used online through Center for Genomic Epidemiology (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/PlasmidHostFinder/"&gt;https://cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/PlasmidHostFinder/&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Importance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance is a global health threat to humans and animals causing high mortality and morbidity, and effectively ending decades of success in fighting against bacterial infections. Plasmids confer extra genetic capabilities to the host organisms through accessory genes, which can encode antimicrobial resistance and virulence factors. In addition to lateral inheritance, plasmids can be transferred horizontally between bacterial taxa. Therefore, detecting the host range of plasmids is crucial for understanding and predicting the dissemination trajectories of extrachromosomal genes and bacterial evolution, as well as for taking effective counter measures against antimicrobial resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.27.462084" rel="alternate" title="PlasmidHostFinder: Prediction of plasmid hosts using random forest (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462353</id><title>SHAPR - An AI approach to predict 3D cell shapes from 2D microscopic images (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.066618+00:00</updated><author><name>Dominik Jens Elias Waibel</name></author><author><name>Niklas Kiermeyer</name></author><author><name>Scott Atwell</name></author><author><name>Ario Sadafi</name></author><author><name>Matthias Meier</name></author><author><name>Carsten Marr</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reconstruction of shapes, forms, and sizes of three-dimensional (3D) objects from two-dimensional (2D) information is one of the most complex functions of the human brain. It also poses an algorithmic challenge and at present is a widely studied subject in computer vision. We here focus on the single cell level and present a neural network-based SHApe PRediction autoencoder SHAPR that accurately reconstructs 3D cellular and nuclear shapes from 2D microscopic images and may have great potential for application in the biomedical sciences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462353" rel="alternate" title="SHAPR - An AI approach to predict 3D cell shapes from 2D microscopic images (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461176</id><title>The genes controlling normal function of citrate and spermine secretion is lost in aggressive prostate cancer and prostate model systems (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.067596+00:00</updated><author><name>Morten Beck Rye</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Krossa</name></author><author><name>Martina Hall</name></author><author><name>Casper van Mourik</name></author><author><name>Tone F. Bathen</name></author><author><name>Finn Drabløs</name></author><author><name>May-Britt Tessem</name></author><author><name>Helena Bertilsson</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretion of the metabolites citrate and spermine into prostate lumen is a unique hallmark for normal prostate epithelial cells. However, the identity of the genes controlling citrate and spermine secretion remains mostly unknown despite their obvious relevance for progression to aggressive prostate cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Materials &amp;amp; Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we have correlated simultaneous measurement of citrate/spermine and transcriptomics data. We have refined these gene correlations in 12 prostate cancer cohorts containing 2915 tissue samples to create a novel gene signature of 150 genes connected with citrate and spermine secretion. We further explored the signature in public data, interrogating over 18 000 samples from various tissues and model systems, including 3826 samples from prostate and prostate cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In prostate cancer, the expression of this gene signature is gradually lost in tissue from normal epithelial cells through PIN, low grade (Gleason &amp;lt;= 7), high grade cancer (Gleason &amp;gt;= 8) and metastatic lesions. The accuracy of the signature is validated by its unique enrichment in prostate compared to other tissues, and its strong enrichment in epithelial tissue compartments compared to stroma. Several zinc-binding proteins that are not previously investigated in the prostate are present in the gene signature, suggesting new mechanisms for controlling zinc homeostasis in citrate/spermine secretion. However, the absence of the gene signature in all common prostate normal and cancer cell-lines, as well as prostate organoids, underlines the challenge to study the role of these genes during prostate cancer progression in model systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A large collection of transcriptomics data integrated with metabolomics identifies the genes related to citrate and spermine secretion in the prostate, and show that the expression of these genes gradually decreases on the path towards aggressive prostate cancer. In addition, the study questions the relevance of currently available model systems to study metabolism in prostate cancer development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461176" rel="alternate" title="The genes controlling normal function of citrate and spermine secretion is lost in aggressive prostate cancer and prostate model systems (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461194</id><title>Identification and quantification of chimeric sequencing reads in a highly multiplexed RAD-seq protocol (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.067843+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Luisa Martin Cerezo</name></author><author><name>Rohan Raval</name></author><author><name>Bernardo de Haro Reyes</name></author><author><name>Marek Kucka</name></author><author><name>Frank Yingguang Chan</name></author><author><name>Jarosław Bryk</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Highly multiplexed approaches have become a common practice in genomic studies. They have improved the cost-effectiveness of genotyping hundreds of individuals by using combinatorially-barcoded adapters. These strategies, however, can potentially misassign reads to incorrect samples. Here we used a modified quaddRAD protocol to analyse the occurrence of index hopping and PCR chimeras in a series of experiments with up to a 100 multiplexed samples per sequencing lane (total n = 639). We created two types of sequencing libraries: four libraries of Type A, where PCR reactions were run on individual samples before multiplexing, and three libraries of Type B, where PCRs were run on pooled samples. We used fixed pairs of inner barcodes to identify chimeric reads. Type B libraries show a higher percentage of misassigned reads (1.15%) compared to Type A libraries (0.65%). We also quantify the commonly undetectable chimeric sequences that occur whenever multiplexed groups of samples with different outer barcodes are sequenced together on a single flow cell. Our results suggest that these types of chimeric sequences represent up to 1.56% and 1.29% of reads in Type A and B libraries, respectively. We review the source of such errors, provide recommendations for developing highly-multiplexed RAD-seq protocols and analysing the resulting data to minimise the generation of chimeric sequences, allow their quantification, and provide finer control over the number of PCR cycles necessary to generate enough input DNA for library preparation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461194" rel="alternate" title="Identification and quantification of chimeric sequencing reads in a highly multiplexed RAD-seq protocol (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462289</id><title>Computational design of peptide therapeutics: how useful are sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors? (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.068031+00:00</updated><author><name>François Charih</name></author><author><name>Kyle K. Biggar</name></author><author><name>James R. Green</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Engineering peptides to achieve a desired therapeutic effect through the inhibition of a specific target activity or protein interaction is a non-trivial task. Few of the existing &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; peptide design algorithms generate target-specific peptides. Instead, many methods produce peptides that achieve a desired effect through an unknown mechanism. In contrast with resource-intensive high-throughput experiments, &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; screening is a cost-effective alternative that can prune the space of candidates when engineering target-specific peptides. Using a set of FDA-approved peptides we curated specifically for this task, we assess the applicability of several sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors as a screening tool within the context of peptide therapeutic engineering. We show that similarity-based protein-protein interaction predictors are more suitable for this purpose than the current state-of-the-art deep learning methods. We also show that this approach is mostly useful when designing new peptides against targets for which naturally-occurring interactors are already known, and that deploying it for &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; peptide engineering tasks may require gathering additional target-specific training data. Taken together, this work offers evidence that supports the use of similarity-based protein-protein interaction predictors for peptide therapeutic engineering, especially peptide analogs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peptides are short chains of amino acids that represent an alternative to small molecule drugs to inhibit enzymatic activity or protein-protein interactions. Designing small peptides to target a protein specifically is challenging, though a number of computational approaches do exist. These methods must to evaluate the quality of a peptide in terms of its ability to bind specifically to a target protein, which can be done &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; with sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors. It isn’t clear, however, how suitable the different types of predictors are for the task of predicting interactions between peptides and proteins. Herein, we apply state-of-the-art protein-protein interaction predictors to a set of FDA-approved peptide therapeutics to determine how the different protein-protein interaction predictors compare for the task of assessing peptide quality, and to determine under which circumstances these methods may be successful. Our results show that similarity-based predictors outperform deep learning methods, and that these methods may be more suitable for peptide analog engineering than for the design of peptide therapeutics &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462289" rel="alternate" title="Computational design of peptide therapeutics: how useful are sequence-based protein-protein interaction predictors? (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461238</id><title>piRNAdb: A piwi-interacting RNA database (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.068204+00:00</updated><author><name>Ricardo Piuco</name></author><author><name>Pedro A. F. Galante</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Found in several metazoan species, piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs) regulate the expression of a wide variety of transposable elements and genes associated with cellular development, differentiation, and growth. Despite their importance, piRNAs are not well known and are still underexplored. To facilitate piRNA research, a comprehensive and easy-to-use piRNA database is still needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we present piRNAdb, an integrative and user-friendly database designed to encompass several aspects of piRNAs. We selected piRNAs from four reliable human RNA-sequencing datasets to start our database. After data processing, we displayed these sequences, their genomic location, clustering information, putative targets on known genes and transposable elements, as well as direct links to other databases. In this first release, piRNAdb catalogues 27,329 piRNAs, as well as 23,380 genes that are putative targets and 47,060 associated gene ontology terms, both of which are organized and linked to each respective piRNA. Finally, to improve information exchange and increase the confidence of sequences, a feedback system is provided to users of piRNAdb.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of new features to facilitate piRNA analyses, data visualization, and integration is the major pillar of piRNAdb. Our main goal was to make this database an easy interface between the data and the user. We believe that this web tool achieves this objective by providing a streamlined and well-organized data repository for piRNAs and that it will be extremely useful to those already studying piRNAs and to the broader community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;piRNAdb is available freely and is compatible with smartphones and tablets: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pirnadb.org/"&gt;https://www.pirnadb.org/&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.21.461238" rel="alternate" title="piRNAdb: A piwi-interacting RNA database (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462291</id><title>easyfm: An easy software suite for file manipulation of Next Generation Sequencing data on desktops (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.068347+00:00</updated><author><name>Hyungtaek Jung</name></author><author><name>Brendan Jeon</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ortiz-Barrientos</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Storing and manipulating Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) file formats is an essential but difficult task in biological data analysis. The &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; (&lt;bold&gt;easy f&lt;/bold&gt;ile &lt;bold&gt;m&lt;/bold&gt;anipulation) toolkit (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm"&gt;https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm&lt;/ext-link&gt;) makes manipulating commonly used NGS files more accessible to biologists. It enables them to perform end-to-end reproducible data analyses using a free standalone desktop application (available on Windows, Mac and Linux). Unlike existing tools (e.g. Galaxy), the Graphical User Interface (GUI)-based &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; is not dependent on any high-performance computing (HPC) system and can be operated without an internet connection. This specific benefit allow &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; to seamlessly integrate visual and interactive representations of NGS files, supporting a wider scope of bioinformatics applications in the life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The analysis and manipulation of NGS data for understanding biological phenomena is an increasingly important aspect in the life sciences. Yet, most methods for analysing, storing and manipulating NGS data require complex command-line tools in HPC or web-based servers and have not yet been implemented in comprehensive, easy-to-use software. This is a major hurdle preventing more general application in the field of NGS data analysis and file manipulation. Here we present &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt;, a free standalone Graphical User Interface (GUI) software with Python support that can be used to facilitate the rapid discovery of target sequences (or user’s interest) in NGS datasets for novice users. For user-friendliness and convenience, &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; was developed with four work modules and a secondary GUI window (herein secondary window), covering different aspects of NGS data analysis (mainly focusing on FASTA files), including post-processing, filtering, format conversion, generating results, real-time log, and help. In combination with the executable tools (BLAST+ and BLAT) and Python, &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt; allows the user to set analysis parameters, select/extract regions of interest, examine the input and output results, and convert to a wide range of file formats. To help augment the functionality of existing web-based and command-line tools, &lt;italic&gt;easyfm&lt;/italic&gt;, a self-contained program, comes with extensive documentation (hosted at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm"&gt;https://github.com/TaekAndBrendan/easyfm&lt;/ext-link&gt;) including a comprehensive step-by-step guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.29.462291" rel="alternate" title="easyfm: An easy software suite for file manipulation of Next Generation Sequencing data on desktops (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461713</id><title>Deep-learning based retinal fluid segmentation in optical coherence tomography images using a cascade of ENets (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.068494+00:00</updated><author><name>Sophie Loizillon</name></author><author><name>Cédric Meurée</name></author><author><name>Camille Breuil</name></author><author><name>Timothée Faucon</name></author><author><name>Arnaud Lambert</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Optical coherence tomography (OCT) is a non-invasive, painless and reproducible examination which allows ophthalmologists to visualize retinal layers. This imaging modality is useful to detect diseases such as diabetic macular edema (DME) or age related macular degeneration (AMD), which are associated with fluid accumulations. In this paper, a cascade of deep convolutional neural networks is proposed using ENets for the segmentation of fluid accumulations in OCT B-Scans. After denoising the B-Scans, a first ENet extracts the region of interest (ROI) between the inner limiting membrane (ILM) and the Bruch’s membrane (BM), whereas the second ENet segments the fluid in the ROI. A random forest classifier was applied on the segmented fluid regions to reject false positive. Our framework was trained on three different datasets with several diseases such as diabetic retinopathy (DR) and AMD. Our method achieves an average Dice Score for fluid segmentation of 0.80, 0.83 and 0.83 on the UMN DME, UMN AMD and Kermany datasets respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.24.461713" rel="alternate" title="Deep-learning based retinal fluid segmentation in optical coherence tomography images using a cascade of ENets (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461860</id><title>Amino Acid Composition and Charge Based Prediction of Antisepsis Peptides by Random Forest Machine Learning Algorithm (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.068696+00:00</updated><author><name>Aayushi Rathore</name></author><author><name>Anu Saini</name></author><author><name>Navjot Kaur</name></author><author><name>Aparna Singh</name></author><author><name>Ojasvi Dutta</name></author><author><name>Mrinal Bamhotra</name></author><author><name>Avneet Saini</name></author><author><name>Sandeep Saini</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sepsis is a severe infectious disease with high mortality, and it occurs when chemicals released in the bloodstream to fight an infection trigger inflammation throughout the body and it can cause a cascade of changes that damage multiple organ systems, leading them to fail, even resulting in death. In order to reduce the possibility of sepsis or infection antiseptics are used and process is known as antisepsis. Antiseptic peptides (ASPs) show properties similar to antigram-negative peptides, antigram-positive peptides and many more. Machine learning algorithms are useful in screening and identification of therapeutic peptides and thus provide initial filters or built confidence before using time consuming and laborious experimental approaches. In this study, various machine learning algorithms like Support Vector Machine (SVM), Random Forest (RF), K-Nearest Neighbour (KNN) and Logistic Regression (LR) were evaluated for prediction of ASPs. Moreover, the characteristics physicochemical features of ASPs were also explored to use them in machine learning. Both manual and automatic feature selection methodology was employed to achieve best performance of machine learning algorithms. A 5-fold cross validation and independent data set validation proved RF as the best model for prediction of ASPs. Our RF model showed an accuracy of 97%, Matthew’s Correlation Coefficient (MCC) of 0.93, which are indication of a robust and good model. To our knowledge this is the first attempt to build a machine learning classifier for prediction of ASPs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.26.461860" rel="alternate" title="Amino Acid Composition and Charge Based Prediction of Antisepsis Peptides by Random Forest Machine Learning Algorithm (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461592</id><title>Batch effects removal for microbiome data via conditional quantile regression (ConQuR) (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-07T08:46:55.068956+00:00</updated><author><name>Wodan Ling</name></author><author><name>Ni Zhao</name></author><author><name>Anju Lulla</name></author><author><name>Anna M. Plantinga</name></author><author><name>Weijia Fu</name></author><author><name>Angela Zhang</name></author><author><name>Hongjiao Liu</name></author><author><name>Zhigang Li</name></author><author><name>Jun Chen</name></author><author><name>Timothy Randolph</name></author><author><name>Wei Li A. Koay</name></author><author><name>James R. White</name></author><author><name>Lenore J. Launer</name></author><author><name>Anthony A. Fodor</name></author><author><name>Katie A. Meyer</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Wu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Batch effects in microbiome data arise from differential processing of specimens and can lead to spurious findings and obscure true signals. Most existing strategies for mitigating batch effects rely on approaches designed for genomic analysis, failing to address the zero-inflated and over-dispersed microbiome data. Strategies tailored for microbiome data are restricted to association testing, failing to allow other analytic goals such as visualization. We develop the Conditional Quantile Regression (ConQuR) approach to remove microbiome batch effects using a two-part quantile regression model. It is a fundamental advancement in the field because it is the first comprehensive method that accommodates the complex distributions of microbial read counts, and it generates batch-removed zero-inflated read counts that can be used in and benefit all usual subsequent analyses. We apply ConQuR to real microbiome data sets and demonstrate its state-of-the-art performance in removing batch effects while preserving or even amplifying the signals of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.23.461592" rel="alternate" title="Batch effects removal for microbiome data via conditional quantile regression (ConQuR) (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>