<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.205466+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472164</id><title>EraSOR: Erase Sample Overlap in polygenic score analyses (37 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.206037+00:00</updated><author><name>Shing Wan Choi</name></author><author><name>Timothy Shin Heng Mak</name></author><author><name>Clive J. Hoggart</name></author><author><name>Paul F. O’Reilly</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polygenic risk score (PRS) analyses are now routinely applied in biomedical research, with great hope that they will aid in our understanding of disease aetiology and contribute to personalized medicine. The continued growth of multi-cohort genome-wide association studies (GWASs) and large-scale biobank projects has provided researchers with a wealth of GWAS summary statistics and individual-level data suitable for performing PRS analyses. However, as the size of these studies increase, the risk of inter-cohort sample overlap and close relatedness increases. Ideally sample overlap would be identified and removed directly, but this is typically not possible due to privacy laws or consent agreements. This sample overlap, whether known or not, is a major problem in PRS analyses because it can lead to inflation of type 1 error and, thus, erroneous conclusions in published work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, for the first time, we report the scale of the sample overlap problem for PRS analyses by generating known sample overlap across sub-samples of the UK Biobank data, which we then use to produce GWAS and target data to mimic the effects of inter-cohort sample overlap. We demonstrate that inter-cohort overlap results in a significant and often substantial inflation in the observed PRS-trait association, coefficient of determination (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) and false-positive rate. This inflation can be high even when the absolute number of overlapping individuals is small if this makes up a notable fraction of the target sample. We develop and introduce EraSOR (&lt;underline&gt;Era&lt;/underline&gt;se &lt;underline&gt;S&lt;/underline&gt;ample &lt;underline&gt;O&lt;/underline&gt;verlap and &lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;elatedness), a software for adjusting inflation in PRS prediction and association statistics in the presence of sample overlap or close relatedness between the GWAS and target samples. A key component of the EraSOR approach is inference of the degree of sample overlap from the intercept of a bivariate LD score regression applied to the GWAS and target data, making it powered in settings where both have sample sizes over 1,000 individuals. Through extensive benchmarking using UK Biobank and HapGen2 simulated genotype-phenotype data, we demonstrate that PRSs calculated using EraSOR-adjusted GWAS summary statistics are robust to inter-cohort overlap in a wide range of realistic scenarios and are even robust to high levels of residual genetic and environmental stratification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of all PRS analyses for which sample overlap cannot be definitively ruled out should be considered with caution given high type 1 error observed in the presence of even low overlap between base and target cohorts. Given the strong performance of EraSOR in eliminating inflation caused by sample overlap in PRS studies with large (&amp;gt;5k) target samples, we recommend that EraSOR be used in all future such PRS studies to mitigate the potential effects of inter-cohort overlap and close relatedness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.10.472164" rel="alternate" title="EraSOR: Erase Sample Overlap in polygenic score analyses (37 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473018</id><title>vRhyme enables binning of viral genomes from metagenomes (28 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.206470+00:00</updated><author><name>Kristopher Kieft</name></author><author><name>Alyssa Adams</name></author><author><name>Rauf Salamzade</name></author><author><name>Lindsay Kalan</name></author><author><name>Karthik Anantharaman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome binning has been essential for characterization of bacteria, archaea, and even eukaryotes from metagenomes. Yet, no approach exists for viruses. We developed vRhyme, a fast and precise software for construction of viral metagenome-assembled genomes (vMAGs). vRhyme utilizes single- or multi-sample coverage effect size comparisons between scaffolds and employs supervised machine learning to identity nucleotide feature similarities, which are compiled into iterations of weighted networks and refined bins. Using simulated viromes, we displayed superior performance of vRhyme compared to available binning tools in constructing more complete and uncontaminated vMAGs. When applied to 10,601 viral scaffolds from human skin, vRhyme advanced our understanding of resident viruses, highlighted by identification of a Herelleviridae vMAG comprised of 22 scaffolds, and another vMAG encoding a nitrate reductase metabolic gene, representing near-complete genomes post-binning. vRhyme will enable a convention of binning uncultivated viral genomes and has the potential to transform metagenome-based viral ecology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473018" rel="alternate" title="vRhyme enables binning of viral genomes from metagenomes (28 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.471754</id><title>Namco: A microbiome explorer (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.207632+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Dietrich</name></author><author><name>Monica Steffi Matchado</name></author><author><name>Maximilian Zwiebel</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Ölke</name></author><author><name>Michael Lauber</name></author><author><name>Ilias Lagkouvardos</name></author><author><name>Jan Baumbach</name></author><author><name>Dirk Haller</name></author><author><name>Beate Brandl</name></author><author><name>Thomas Skurk</name></author><author><name>Hans Hauner</name></author><author><name>Sandra Reitmeier</name></author><author><name>Markus List</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: 16S rRNA gene profiling is currently the most widely used technique in microbiome research and allows for studying microbial diversity, taxonomic profiling, phylogenetics, functional and network analysis. While a plethora of tools have been developed for the analysis of 16S rRNA gene data, only few platforms offer a user-friendly interface and none comprehensively cover the whole analysis pipeline from raw data processing down to complex analysis. Results: We introduce Namco, an R shiny application that offers a streamlined interface and serves as a one-stop solution for microbiome analysis. We demonstrate Namco's capabilities by studying the association between rich fibre diet and the gut microbiota composition. Namco helped to prove the hypothesis that butyrate-producing bacteria are prompted by fibre-enriched intervention. Conclusion: Namco provides a broad range of features from raw data processing and basic statistics down to machine learning and network analysis, thus covering complex data analysis tasks that are not comprehensively covered elsewhere. Namco is freely available at https://exbio.wzw.tum.de/namco/.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.471754" rel="alternate" title="Namco: A microbiome explorer (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472751</id><title>Polymorphism-aware estimation of species trees and evolutionary forces from genomic sequences with RevBayes (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.207922+00:00</updated><author><name>Rui Borges</name></author><author><name>Bastien Boussau</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Hoehna</name></author><author><name>Ricardo J Pereira</name></author><author><name>Carolin Kosiol</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The availability of population genomic data through new sequencing technologies gives unprecedented opportunities for estimating important evolutionary forces such as genetic drift, selection, and mutation biases across organisms. Yet, analytical methods that can handle polymorphisms jointly with sequence divergence across species are rare and not easily accessible to empiricists. We implemented polymorphism-aware phylogenetic models (PoMos), an alternative approach for species tree estimation, in the Bayesian phylogenetic software RevBayes. PoMos naturally account for incomplete lineage sorting, which is known to cause difficulties for phylogenetic inference in species radiations, and scale well with genome-wide data. Simultaneously, PoMos can estimate mutation and selection biases. We have applied our methods to resolve the complex phylogenetic relationships of a young radiation of Chorthippus grasshoppers, based on coding sequences. In addition to establishing a well-supported species tree, we found a mutation bias favoring AT alleles and selection bias promoting the fixation of GC alleles, the latter consistent with GC-biased gene conversion. The selection bias is two orders of magnitude lower than genetic drift, validating the critical role of nearly neutral evolutionary processes in species radiation. PoMos offer a wide range of models to reconstruct phylogenies and can be easily combined with existing models in RevBayes - e.g., relaxed clock and divergence time estimation - offering new insights into the evolutionary processes underlying molecular evolution and, ultimately, species diversification.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.15.472751" rel="alternate" title="Polymorphism-aware estimation of species trees and evolutionary forces from genomic sequences with RevBayes (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472999</id><title>3D-Strudel - a novel model-dependent map-feature validation method for high-resolution cryo-EM structures (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.208092+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrei Istrate</name></author><author><name>Zhe Wang</name></author><author><name>Garib N Murshudov</name></author><author><name>Ardan Patwardhan</name></author><author><name>Gerard J Kleywegt</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent technological advances in electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM) have led to significant improvements in the resolution of many single-particle reconstructions and a sharp increase in the number of entries released in the Electron Microscopy Data Bank (EMDB) every year, which in turn has opened new possibilities for data mining. Here we present a resolution-dependent library of rotamer-specific amino-acid map motifs mined from entries in the EMDB archive with reported resolution between 2.0 and 4.0A. We further describe 3D-Strudel, a method for map/model validation based on these libraries. 3D-Strudel calculates linear correlation coefficients between the map values of a map-motif from the library and the experimental map values around a target residue. We also present "Strudel Score", a plug-in for ChimeraX, as a user-friendly tool for visualisation of 3D-Strudel validation results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.472999" rel="alternate" title="3D-Strudel - a novel model-dependent map-feature validation method for high-resolution cryo-EM structures (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472307</id><title>Scalable batch-correction approach for integrating large-scale single-cell transcriptomes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.208253+00:00</updated><author><name>Xilin Shen</name></author><author><name>Hongru Shen</name></author><author><name>Dan Wu</name></author><author><name>Mengyao Feng</name></author><author><name>Jiani Hu</name></author><author><name>Jilei Liu</name></author><author><name>Yichen Yang</name></author><author><name>Meng Yang</name></author><author><name>Yang Li</name></author><author><name>Lei Shi</name></author><author><name>Kexin Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiangchun Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Integration of the evolving large-scale single-cell transcriptomes requires scalable batch-correction approaches. Here we propose a simple batch-correction method that is scalable for integrating super large-scale single-cell transcriptomes from diverse sources. The core idea of the method is encoding batch information of each cell as a trainable parameter and added to its expression profile; subsequently, a contrastive learning approach is used to learn feature representation of the additive expression profile. We demonstrate the scalability of the proposed method by integrating 18 million cells obtained from the Human Cell Atlas. Our benchmark comparisons with current state-of-the-art single-cell integration methods demonstrated that our method could achieve comparable data alignment and cluster preservation. Our study would facilitate the integration of super large-scale single-cell transcriptomes. The source code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/xilinshen/Fugue"&gt;https://github.com/xilinshen/Fugue&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472307" rel="alternate" title="Scalable batch-correction approach for integrating large-scale single-cell transcriptomes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472366</id><title>Modeling of microRNA-derived disease network repurposes methotrexate for the prevention and therapy of abdominal aortic aneurysm in mice (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.208493+00:00</updated><author><name>Yicong Shen</name></author><author><name>Yuanxu Gao</name></author><author><name>Jiangcheng Shi</name></author><author><name>Zhou Huang</name></author><author><name>Rongbo Dai</name></author><author><name>Yi Fu</name></author><author><name>Yuan Zhou</name></author><author><name>Wei Kong</name></author><author><name>Qinghua Cui</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) is a highly lethal vascular disease characterized by permanent dilatation of the abdominal aorta. The main purpose of the current study is to search for noninvasive medical therapies for abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA), for which there is currently no effective drug therapy. Network medicine represents a cutting-edge technology, as analysis and modeling of disease networks can provide critical clues regarding the etiology of specific diseases and which therapeutics may be effective. Here, we proposed a novel algorithm to quantify disease relations based on a large accumulated microRNA-disease association dataset and then built a disease network that covered 15 disease classes and included 304 diseases. Analysis revealed a number of patterns for these diseases; for example, diseases tended to be clustered and coherent in the network. Surprisingly, we found that AAA showed the strongest similarity with rheumatoid arthritis and systemic lupus erythematosus, both of which are autoimmune diseases, suggesting that AAA could be one type of autoimmune disease in etiology. Based on this observation, we further hypothesized that drugs for autoimmune disease could be repurposed for the prevention and therapy of AAA. Finally, animal experiments confirmed that methotrexate, a drug for autoimmune disease, was able to prevent the formation and inhibit the development of AAA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472366" rel="alternate" title="Modeling of microRNA-derived disease network repurposes methotrexate for the prevention and therapy of abdominal aortic aneurysm in mice (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.472408</id><title>Fully Automatic Cell Segmentation with Fourier Descriptors (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.208789+00:00</updated><author><name>Dominik Hirling</name></author><author><name>Peter Horvath</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell segmentation is a fundamental problem in biology for which convolutional neural networks yield the best results nowadays. In this paper, we present HarmonicNet, a network, which is a modification of the popular StarDist and SplineDist architectures. While StarDist and SplineDist describe an object by the lengths of equiangular rays and control points respectively, our network utilizes Fourier descriptors, predicting a coefficient vector for every pixel on the image, which implicitly define the resulting segmentation. We evaluate our model on three different datasets, and show that Fourier descriptors can achieve a high level of accuracy with a small number of coefficients. HarmonicNet is also capable of accurately segmenting objects that are not star-shaped, a case where StarDist performs suboptimally according to our experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.472408" rel="alternate" title="Fully Automatic Cell Segmentation with Fourier Descriptors (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472204</id><title>Black chromatin is indispensable for accurate simulations of Drosophila melanogaster chromatin structure (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.208958+00:00</updated><author><name>Irina Tuszynska</name></author><author><name>Pawel Bednarz</name></author><author><name>Bartek Wilczynski</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The interphase chromatin structure is extremely complex, precise and dynamic. Experimental methods can only show the frequency of interaction of the various parts of the chromatin. Therefore, it is extremely important to develop theoretical methods to predict the chromatin structure. In this publication, we describe the necessary factors for the effective modeling of the chromatin structure in &lt;italic&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/italic&gt;. We also compared Monte Carlo with Molecular Dynamic methods. We showed that incorporating black, non-reactive chromatin is necessary for successfully prediction of chromatin structure, while the loop extrusion model or using Hi-C data as input are not essential for the basic structure reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="472204v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472204" rel="alternate" title="Black chromatin is indispensable for accurate simulations of Drosophila melanogaster chromatin structure (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473069</id><title>Enhancer RNA-based modeling of adverse events and objective responses of immunotherapy (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.209229+00:00</updated><author><name>Mengbiao Guo</name></author><author><name>Zhiya Lu</name></author><author><name>Yuanyan Xiong</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICI) targeting PD-1/PD-L1 or CTLA-4 are emerging and effective immunotherapy strategies. However, ICI treated patients present heterogeneous responses and adverse events, thus demanding effective ways to assess benefit over risk before treatment. Here, by integrating pan-cancer clinical and molecular data, we tried to predict immune-related adverse events (irAEs, risk) and objective response rates (ORRs, benefit) based on enhancer RNAs (eRNAs) expression among patients receiving anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapy. We built two effective regression models, explaining 71% variance (R=0.84) of irAEs with three eRNAs and 79% (R=0.89) of ORRs with five eRNAs. Interestingly, target genes of irAE-related enhancers, including upstream regulators of MYC, were involved in metabolism, inflammation, and immune activation, while ORR-related enhancers target PAK2 and DLG1 which directly participate in T cell activation. Our study provides references for the identification of immunotherapy-related biomarkers and potential therapeutic targets during immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.16.473069" rel="alternate" title="Enhancer RNA-based modeling of adverse events and objective responses of immunotherapy (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472455</id><title>Identifying Protein Features and Pathways Responsible for Toxicity using Machine learning, CANDO, and Tox21 datasets: Implications for Predictive Toxicology (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.209372+00:00</updated><author><name>Lama Moukheiber</name></author><author><name>William Mangione</name></author><author><name>Saeed Maleki</name></author><author><name>Zackary Falls</name></author><author><name>Mingchen Gao</name></author><author><name>Ram Samudrala</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Humans are exposed to numerous compounds daily, some of which have adverse effects on health. Computational approaches for modeling toxicological data in conjunction with machine learning algorithms have gained popularity over the last few years. Machine learning methods have been used to predict toxicity-related biological activities using chemical structure descriptors. However, proteomic features have not been fully investigated. In this study, we construct a computational model using machine learning for selecting the most important proteins representing features in predicting the toxicity of the compounds in the Tox21 dataset using the multiscale Computational Analysis of Novel Drug Opportunities (CANDO) platform for therapeutic discovery. Tox21 is a highly imbalanced dataset consisting of twelve in-vitro assays, seven from the nuclear receptor (NR) signaling pathway and five from the stress response (SR) pathway, for more than 10,000 compounds. For our computational model, we employed a random forest (RF) with the combination of Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE) and Edited Nearest Neighbor (ENN) method, aka SMOTE+ENN, which is resampling method to balance the activity class distribution. Within the NR and SR pathways, the activity of the aryl hydrocarbon receptor (NR-AhR), toxicity mediating transcription factor, and microchondrial membrane potential (SR-MMP) were two of the top-performing twelve toxicity endpoints with AUROCs of 0.90 and 0.92, respectively. The top extracted features for evaluating compound toxicity were passed into enrichment analysis to highlight the implicated biological pathways and proteins. We validated our enrichment results for the activity of the AhR using a thorough literature search. Our case study showed that the selected enriched pathways and proteins from our computational pipeline are not only correlated with NR-AhR toxicity but also form a cascading upstream/downstream arrangement. Our work elucidates significant relationships between protein and compound interactions computed using CANDO and the associated biological pathways to which the proteins belong, with twelve toxicity endpoints. This novel study uses machine learning not only to predict and understand toxicity but also elucidates therapeutic mechanisms at a proteomic level for a variety of toxicity endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.13.472455" rel="alternate" title="Identifying Protein Features and Pathways Responsible for Toxicity using Machine learning, CANDO, and Tox21 datasets: Implications for Predictive Toxicology (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.11.472233</id><title>Video-Based Deep Learning to Detect Dyssynergic Defecation with 3D High-Definition Anorectal Manometry (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.209527+00:00</updated><author><name>Joshua J. Levy</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Navas</name></author><author><name>Joan A. Chandra</name></author><author><name>Brock C. Christensen</name></author><author><name>Louis J. Vaickus</name></author><author><name>Michael Curley</name></author><author><name>William D. Chey</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Baker</name></author><author><name>Eric D. Shah</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;BACKGROUND AND AIMS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluation for dyssynergia is the most common reason that gastroenterologists refer patients for anorectal manometry, because dyssynergia is amenable to biofeedback by physical therapists. High-definition anorectal manometry (3D-HDAM) is a promising technology to evaluate anorectal physiology, but adoption remains limited by its sheer complexity. We developed a 3D-HDAM deep learning algorithm to evaluate for dyssynergia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;METHODS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spatial-temporal data were extracted from consecutive 3D-HDAM studies performed between 2018-2020 at a tertiary institution. The technical procedure and gold standard definition of dyssynergia were based on the London consensus, adapted to the needs of 3D-HDAM technology. Three machine learning models were generated: (1) traditional machine learning informed by conventional anorectal function metrics, (2) deep learning, and (3) a hybrid approach. Diagnostic accuracy was evaluated using bootstrap sampling to calculate area-under-the-curve (AUC). To evaluate overfitting, models were validated by adding 502 simulated defecation maneuvers with diagnostic ambiguity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;RESULTS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;302 3D-HDAM studies representing 1,208 simulated defecation maneuvers were included (average age 55.2 years; 80.5% women). The deep learning model had comparable diagnostic accuracy (AUC=0.91 [95% confidence interval 0.89-0.93]) to traditional (AUC=0.93[0.92-0.95]) and hybrid (AUC=0.96[0.94-0.97]) predictive models in training cohorts. However, the deep learning model handled ambiguous tests more cautiously than other models; the deep learning model was more likely to designate an ambiguous test as inconclusive (odds ratio=4.21[2.78-6.38]) versus traditional/hybrid approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;CONCLUSIONS&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;By considering complex spatial-temporal information beyond conventional anorectal function metrics, deep learning on 3D-HDAM technology may enable gastroenterologists to reliably identify and manage dyssynergia in broader practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.11.472233" rel="alternate" title="Video-Based Deep Learning to Detect Dyssynergic Defecation with 3D High-Definition Anorectal Manometry (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472268</id><title>Contrastive Cycle Adversarial Autoencoders for Single-cell Multi-omics Alignment and Integration (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-20T08:42:20.209693+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuesong Wang</name></author><author><name>Zhihang Hu</name></author><author><name>Tingyang Yu</name></author><author><name>Ruijie Wang</name></author><author><name>Yumeng Wei</name></author><author><name>Juan Shu</name></author><author><name>Jianzhu Ma</name></author><author><name>Yu Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Muilti-modality data are ubiquitous in biology, especially that we have entered the multi-omics era, when we can measure the same biological object (cell) from different aspects (omics) to provide a more comprehensive insight into the cellular system. When dealing with such multi-omics data, the first step is to determine the correspondence among different modalities. In other words, we should match data from different spaces corresponding to the same object. This problem is particularly challenging in the single-cell multi-omics scenario because such data are very sparse with extremely high dimensions. Secondly, matched single-cell multi-omics data are rare and hard to collect. Furthermore, due to the limitations of the experimental environment, the data are usually highly noisy. To promote the single-cell multi-omics research, we overcome the above challenges, proposing a novel framework to align and integrate single-cell RNA-seq data and single-cell ATAC-seq data. Our approach can efficiently map the above data with high sparsity and noise from different spaces to a low-dimensional manifold in a unified space, making the downstream alignment and integration straightforward. Compared with the other state-of-the-art methods, our method performs better in both simulated and real single-cell data. The proposed method is helpful for the single-cell multi-omics research. The improvement for integration on the simulated data is significant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.12.472268" rel="alternate" title="Contrastive Cycle Adversarial Autoencoders for Single-cell Multi-omics Alignment and Integration (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>