<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.370175+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473622</id><title>From mass spectral features to molecules in molecular networks: a novel workflow for untargeted metabolomics (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.370874+00:00</updated><author><name>Damien Olivier-Jimenez</name></author><author><name>Zakaria Bouchouireb</name></author><author><name>Simon Ollivier</name></author><author><name>Julia Mocquard</name></author><author><name>Pierre-Marie Allard</name></author><author><name>Guillaume Bernadat</name></author><author><name>Marylène Chollet-Krugler</name></author><author><name>David Rondeau</name></author><author><name>Joël Boustie</name></author><author><name>Justin J.J. van der Hooft</name></author><author><name>Jean-Luc Wolfender</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In the context of untargeted metabolomics, molecular networking is a popular and efficient tool which organizes and simplifies mass spectrometry fragmentation data (LC-MS/MS), by clustering ions based on a cosine similarity score. However, the nature of the ion species is rarely taken into account, causing redundancy as a single compound may be present in different forms throughout the network. Taking advantage of the presence of such redundant ions, we developed a new method named MolNotator. Using the different ion species produced by a molecule during ionization (adducts, dimers, trimers, in-source fragments), a predicted molecule node (or neutral node) is created by triangulation, and ultimately computing the associated molecule’s calculated mass. These neutral nodes provide researchers with several advantages. Firstly, each molecule is then represented in its ionization context, connected to all produced ions and indirectly to some coeluted compounds, thereby also highlighting unexpected widely present adduct species. Secondly, the predicted neutrals serve as anchors to merge the complementary positive and negative ionization modes into a single network. Lastly, the dereplication is improved by the use of all available ions connected to the neutral nodes, and the computed molecular masses can be used for exact mass dereplication. MolNotator is available as a Python library and was validated using the lichen database spectra acquired on an Orbitrap, computing neutral molecules for &amp;gt;90% of the 156 molecules in the dataset. By focusing on actual molecules instead of ions, &lt;italic&gt;MolNotator&lt;/italic&gt; greatly facilitates the selection of molecules of interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract Figure&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="473622v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.21.473622" rel="alternate" title="From mass spectral features to molecules in molecular networks: a novel workflow for untargeted metabolomics (33 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473496</id><title>Boosting annotation in nutrimetabolomics by Feature-Based Molecular Networking: analytical and computational strategies applied to human urine samples from an untargeted LC-MS/MS based bilberry-blueberry intervention study (17 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.371532+00:00</updated><author><name>Lapo Renai</name></author><author><name>Marynka Ulaszewska</name></author><author><name>Fulvio Mattivi</name></author><author><name>Riccardo Bartoletti</name></author><author><name>Massimo Del Bubba</name></author><author><name>Justin J. J. van der Hooft</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Urine represents a challenging metabolite mixture to decipher. Yet, it contains valuable information on dietary intake patterns as typically investigated using randomized, single-blinded, intervention studies. This research demonstrates how the use of Feature-Based Molecular Networking in combination with public spectral libraries, further expanded with an “In-house” library of metabolite spectra, improved the non-trivial annotation of metabolites occurring in human urine samples following bilberry and blueberry intake. Following this approach, 65 berry-related and human endogenous metabolites were annotated, increasing the annotation coverage by 72% compared to conventional annotation approaches. Furthermore, the structures of 15 additional metabolites were hypothesized by spectral analysis. Then, by leveraging the MzMine quantitative information, several molecular families of phase II (e.g., glucuronidated phenolics) and phase I (e.g., phenylpropionic acid and hydroxybenzoic acid molecular scaffolds) metabolism were identified by correlation analysis of postprandial kinetics, and the dietary impact of endogenous and exogenous metabolites following bilberry-blueberry intake was estimated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473496" rel="alternate" title="Boosting annotation in nutrimetabolomics by Feature-Based Molecular Networking: analytical and computational strategies applied to human urine samples from an untargeted LC-MS/MS based bilberry-blueberry intervention study (17 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473169</id><title>The BioImage Archive - home of life-sciences microscopy data (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.372144+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Hartley</name></author><author><name>Gerard Kleywegt</name></author><author><name>Ardan Patwardhan</name></author><author><name>Ugis Sarkans</name></author><author><name>Jason R. Swedlow</name></author><author><name>Alvis Brazma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the importance of data resources in genomics and structural biology, until now there has been no central archive for biological data for all imaging modalities. The BioImage Archive is a new data resource at the European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI) designed to fill this gap. It accepts bioimaging data associated with publication in any format, from any imaging modality at any scale, as well as reference datasets. The BioImage Archive will improve reproducibility of published studies that derive results from image data. In addition, providing reference datasets to the scientific community reduces duplication of effort and allows downstream analysis to focus on a consistent set of data. The BioImage Archive will also help to generate new insights through reuse of existing data to answer new biological questions, or provision of training, testing and benchmarking data for image analysis tool development. The Archive is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/bioimage-archive/"&gt;https://www.ebi.ac.uk/bioimage-archive/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BioImage Archive is a new archival data resource at the European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BioImage Archive aims to accept all biological imaging data associated with peer-reviewed publications using microscopy that probe biological structure, mechanism and dynamics, as well as other important datasets that can serve as a reference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BioImage Archive aims to maximise the use of valuable microscopy data, to improve reproducibility of published results that rely on image data, and to facilitate development of both novel biological insights from existing data and new image analysis methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BioImage Archive anchors an ecosystem of related databases, supporting those resources with storage infrastructure, linkage and indexing across databases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Across this ecosystem, the BioImage Archive already stores and provides access to over one petabyte of image data from many different imaging modalities and biological domains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Future development of the BioImage Archive will support the fast-emerging next generation file formats (NGFFs) for bioimaging data, providing access mechanisms tailored toward unlocking the power of modern AI-based image-analysis approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473169" rel="alternate" title="The BioImage Archive - home of life-sciences microscopy data (13 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473966</id><title>Baltica: integrated splice junction usage analysis (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.372748+00:00</updated><author><name>Thiago Britto-Borges</name></author><author><name>Volker Boehm</name></author><author><name>Niels H Gehring</name></author><author><name>Christoph Dieterich</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alternative splicing is a tightly regulated co- and post-transcriptional process contributing to the transcriptome diversity observed in eukaryotes. Several methods for detecting differential junction usage (DJU) from RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) datasets exist. Yet, efforts to integrate the results from DJU methods are lacking. Here, we present Baltica, a framework that provides workflows for quality control, de novo transcriptome assembly with StringTie2, and currently 4 DJU methods: rMATS, JunctionSeq, Majiq, and LeafCutter. Baltica puts the results from different DJU methods into context by integrating the results at the junction level. We present Baltica using 2 datasets, one containing known artificial transcripts (SIRVs) and the second dataset of paired Illumina and Oxford Nanopore Technologies RNA-seq. The data integration allows the user to compare the performance of the tools and reveals that JunctionSeq outperforms the other methods, in terms of F1 score, for both datasets. Finally, we demonstrate for the first time that meta-classifiers trained on scores of multiple methods outperform classifiers trained on scores of a single method, emphasizing the application of our data integration approach for differential splicing identification. Baltica is available at https://github.com/dieterich-lab/Baltica under MIT license.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.23.473966" rel="alternate" title="Baltica: integrated splice junction usage analysis (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473403</id><title>Towards mechanistic models of mutational effects: Deep Learning on Alzheimer's Aβ peptide (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.373261+00:00</updated><author><name>Bo Wang</name></author><author><name>Eric R Gamazon</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer's Disease (AD) is a debilitating form of dementia with a high prevalence in the global population and a large burden on the community and health care systems. AD's complex pathobiology consists of extracellular β-amyloid deposition and intracellular hyperphosphorylated tau. Comprehensive mutational analyses can generate a wealth of knowledge about protein properties and enable crucial insights into molecular mechanisms of disease. Deep Mutational Scanning (DMS) has enabled multiplexed measurement of mutational effects on protein properties, including kinematics and self-organization, with unprecedented resolution. However, potential bottlenecks of DMS characterization include experimental design, data quality, and the depth of mutational coverage. Here, we apply Deep Learning to comprehensively model the mutational effect of the AD-associated peptide Aβ&lt;sub&gt;42&lt;/sub&gt; on aggregation-related biochemical traits from DMS measurements. Among tested neural network architectures, Convolutional Neural Networks (ConvNets) and Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN) are found to be the most cost-effective models with robust high performance even under insufficiently-sampled DMS studies. While sequence features are essential for satisfactory prediction from neural networks, geometric-structural features further enhance the prediction performance. Notably, we demonstrate how mechanistic insights into phenotype may be extracted from the neural networks themselves suitably designed. This methodological benefit is particularly relevant for biochemical systems displaying a strong coupling between structure and phenotype such as the conformation of Aβ&lt;sub&gt;42&lt;/sub&gt; aggregate and nucleation, as shown here using a Graph Convolutional Neural Network (GCN) developed from the protein atomic structure input. In addition to accurate imputation of missing values (which here ranged up to 55% of all phenotype values at key residues), the mutationally-defined nucleation phenotype generated from a GCN shows improved resolution for identifying known disease-causing mutations relative to the original DMS phenotype. Our study suggests that neural network derived sequence-phenotype mapping can be exploited not only to provide direct support for protein engineering or genome editing but also to facilitate therapeutic design with the gained perspectives from biological modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473403" rel="alternate" title="Towards mechanistic models of mutational effects: Deep Learning on Alzheimer's Aβ peptide (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473612</id><title>Transmission dynamics and control of Sporotrichosis in domestic felines (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.373591+00:00</updated><author><name>Aurélio A Araújo</name></author><author><name>Cláudia Codeço</name></author><author><name>Dayvison F S Freitas</name></author><author><name>Priscila M de Macedo</name></author><author><name>Sandro A Pereira</name></author><author><name>Isabella D F Gremião</name></author><author><name>Flávio C. Coelho</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Sporotrichosis&lt;/italic&gt; is a subcutaneous mycosis with a global distribution, also known as “rose gardener’s disease”. Brazil is experiencing a rapid spread of the zoonotic transmission of of &lt;italic&gt;Sporothrix brasiliensis&lt;/italic&gt;, the main etiological agent of this disease in this country, affecting domestic felines. Cost-effective interventions need to be developed to control this emergent public health problem. To allow for the comparison of alternative control strategies, we propose in this paper, a mathematical model representing the transmission of &lt;italic&gt;S. brasiliensis&lt;/italic&gt; among cats, stratified by age and sex. Analytical properties of the model are derived and simulations show possible strategies for reducing the endemic levels of the disease in the cat population, with a positive impact on human health. The scenarios included mass treatment of infected cats and mass implementation of contact reduction practices, such as neutering. The results indicate that mass treatment can reduce substantially the disease prevalence, and this effect is potentialized when combined with neutering or other contact-reduction interventions. On the other hand, contact-reduction methods alone are not sufficient to reduce prevalence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sporotrichosis, as a neglected tropical mycosis, has in domestic cats a very important reservoir for Sporothrix sp., its pathogen. Infected cats can easily transmit the fungus to other cats and also to humans by means of scratching and biting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we propose a mathematical model incorporating all forms of transmission of Sporothrix within a cat population, taking into account age and sex-related behavioral differences which can affect the transmission dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The model also includes a treated compartment, which facilitates the exploration of pharmacological interventions to reduce the prevalence of the disease. We derive the next-generation matrix for the model, which allows the calculation of the disease’s basic reproduction number under different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the model, we explore different control scenarios involving treatment of the disease, but also the contribution of neutering of cats to the reduction of transmission through changes induced by neutering, of the cat’s social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473612" rel="alternate" title="Transmission dynamics and control of Sporotrichosis in domestic felines (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473339</id><title>MOPower: an R-shiny application for the simulation and power calculation of multi-omics studies (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.373853+00:00</updated><author><name>Hamzah Syed</name></author><author><name>Georg W Otto</name></author><author><name>Daniel Kelberman</name></author><author><name>Chiara Bacchelli</name></author><author><name>Philip L Beales</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-omics studies are increasingly used to help understand the underlying mechanisms of clinical phenotypes, integrating information from the genome, transcriptome, epigenome, metabolome, proteome and microbiome. This integration of data is of particular use in rare disease studies where the sample sizes are often relatively small. Methods development for multi-omics studies is in its early stages due to the complexity of the different individual data types. There is a need for software to perform data simulation and power calculation for multi-omics studies to test these different methodologies and help calculate sample size before the initiation of a study. This software, in turn, will optimise the success of a study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interactive R shiny application MOPower described below simulates data based on three different omics using statistical distributions. It calculates the power to detect an association with the phenotype through analysis of n number of replicates using a variety of the latest multi-omics analysis models and packages. The simulation study confirms the efficiency of the software when handling thousands of simulations over ten different sample sizes. The average time elapsed for a power calculation run between integration models was approximately 500 seconds. Additionally, for the given study design model, power varied with the increase in the number of features affecting each method differently. For example, using MOFA had an increase in power to detect an association when the study sample size equally matched the number of features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MOPower addresses the need for flexible and user-friendly software that undertakes power calculations for multi-omics studies. MOPower offers users a wide variety of integration methods to test and full customisation of omics features to cover a range of study designs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473339" rel="alternate" title="MOPower: an R-shiny application for the simulation and power calculation of multi-omics studies (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473524</id><title>Informeasure: an R/Bioconductor package to quantify nonlinear dependence between variables in biological networks from an information theory perspective (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.374190+00:00</updated><author><name>Chu Pan</name></author><author><name>Limei Jing</name></author><author><name>Jiawei Luo</name></author><author><name>Xiangxiang Zeng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Using information measures to infer biological regulatory networks can observe nonlinear relationship between variables, but it is computationally challenging and there is currently no convenient tool available. We here describe an information theory R package named Informeasure that devotes to quantifying nonlinear dependence between variables in biological regulatory networks from an information theory perspective. This package compiles most of the information measures currently available: mutual information, conditional mutual information, interaction information, partial information decomposition and part mutual information. The first estimator is used to infer bivariate networks while the last four estimators are dedicated to analysis of trivariate networks. The base installation of this turn-key package allows users to approach these information measures out of the box. Informeasure is implemented in R program and is available as an R/Bioconductor package at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/Informeasure"&gt;https://bioconductor.org/packages/Informeasure&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473524" rel="alternate" title="Informeasure: an R/Bioconductor package to quantify nonlinear dependence between variables in biological networks from an information theory perspective (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473334</id><title>A Parameter-free Deep Embedded Clustering Method for Single-cell RNA-seq Data (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.374695+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuansong Zeng</name></author><author><name>Zhuoyi Wei</name></author><author><name>Fengqi Zhong</name></author><author><name>Zixiang Pan</name></author><author><name>Yutong Lu</name></author><author><name>Yuedong Yang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Clustering analysis is widely utilized in single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) data to discover cell heterogeneity and cell states. While many clustering methods have been developed for scRNA-seq analysis, most of these methods require to provide the number of clusters. However, it is not easy to know the exact number of cell types in advance, and experienced determination is not always reliable. Here, we have developed ADClust, an &lt;bold&gt;a&lt;/bold&gt;utomatic &lt;bold&gt;d&lt;/bold&gt;eep embedding &lt;bold&gt;clust&lt;/bold&gt;ering method for scRNA-seq data, which can accurately cluster cells without requiring a predefined number of clusters. Specifically, ADClust first obtains low-dimensional representation through pre-trained autoencoder, and uses the representations to cluster cells into initial micro-clusters. The clusters are then compared in between by a statistical test, and similar micro-clusters are merged into larger clusters. According to the clustering, cell representations are updated so that each cell will be pulled toward centres of its assigned cluster and similar clusters, while cells are separated to keep distances between clusters. This is accomplished through jointly optimizing the carefully designed clustering and autoencoder loss functions. This merging process continues until convergence. ADClust was tested on eleven real scRNA-seq datasets, and shown to outperform existing methods in terms of both clustering performance and the accuracy on the number of the determined clusters. More importantly, our model provides high speed and scalability for large datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473334" rel="alternate" title="A Parameter-free Deep Embedded Clustering Method for Single-cell RNA-seq Data (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473414</id><title>Therapeutic potential of methylxanthine drug on alpha synuclein protein in Parkinson’s disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.375014+00:00</updated><author><name>Nishant Kumar Rana</name></author><author><name>Neha Srivastava</name></author><author><name>Bhupendra Kumar</name></author><author><name>Abhishek Pathak</name></author><author><name>Vijay Nath Mishra</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parkinson’s disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder after Alzheimer. It exists in sporadic (90 to 95%) and familial (5 to 10%) form. Its pathogenesis is due to oxidative stress, glutamate excitotoxicity, protein aggregation, neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration. There is currently no cure for this disease. The protein-protein interaction and gene ontology/functional enrichment analysis have been performed to find out the prominent interactor protein and shared common biological pathways, especially PD pathway. Further &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; docking analysis was performed on target protein to investigate the prominent drug molecule for PD. Through computational molecular virtual screening of small molecules from selected twelve natural compounds, and among these compounds methylxanthine was shown to be prominent inhibitor to SNCA protein that ultimately prevent PD. The interaction of methylxanthine compound with the target protein SNCA suggested that, it interacted with prominent binding site with good docking score and might be involved in blocking the binding of neuroinducing substances like: 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine (MPTP) to SNCA protein. Thus methylxanthine compounds can be explored as promising drugs for the prevention of Parkinson’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473414" rel="alternate" title="Therapeutic potential of methylxanthine drug on alpha synuclein protein in Parkinson’s disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473242</id><title>Gene regulation network inference using k-nearest neighbor-based mutual information estimation-Revisiting an old DREAM (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.375221+00:00</updated><author><name>Lior I. Shachaf</name></author><author><name>Elijah Roberts</name></author><author><name>Patrick Cahan</name></author><author><name>Jie Xiao</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cell exhibits a variety of responses to internal and external cues. These responses are possible, in part, due to the presence of an elaborate gene regulatory network (GRN) in every single cell. In the past twenty years, many groups worked on reconstructing the topological structure of GRNs from large-scale gene expression data using a variety of inference algorithms. Insights gained about participating players in GRNs may ultimately lead to therapeutic benefits. Mutual information (MI) is a widely used metric within this inference/reconstruction pipeline as it can detect any correlation (linear and non-linear) between any number of variables (&lt;italic&gt;n&lt;/italic&gt;-dimensions). However, the use of MI with continuous data (for example, normalized fluorescence intensity measurement of gene expression levels) is sensitive to data size, correlation strength and underlying distributions, and often requires laborious and, at times, &lt;italic&gt;ad hoc&lt;/italic&gt; optimization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, we first show that estimating MI of a bi- and tri-variate Gaussian distribution using &lt;italic&gt;k&lt;/italic&gt;-nearest neighbor (kNN) MI estimation results in significant error reduction as compared to commonly used methods based on fixed binning. Second, we demonstrate that implementing the MI-based kNN Kraskov-Stoögbauer-Grassberger (KSG) algorithm leads to a significant improvement in GRN reconstruction for popular inference algorithms, such as Context Likelihood of Relatedness (CLR). Finally, through extensive &lt;italic&gt;in-silico&lt;/italic&gt; benchmarking we show that a new inference algorithm CMIA (Conditional Mutual Information Augmentation), inspired by CLR, in combination with the KSG-MI estimator, outperforms commonly used methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using three canonical datasets containing 15 synthetic networks, the newly developed method for GRN reconstruction - which combines CMIA, and the KSG-MI estimator - achieves an improvement of 20-35% in precision-recall measures over the current gold standard in the field. This new method will enable researchers to discover new gene interactions or choose gene candidates for experimental validations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473242" rel="alternate" title="Gene regulation network inference using k-nearest neighbor-based mutual information estimation-Revisiting an old DREAM (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473392</id><title>Scellseg: a style-aware cell instance segmentation tool with pre-training and contrastive fine-tuning (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.375470+00:00</updated><author><name>Dejin Xun</name></author><author><name>Deheng Chen</name></author><author><name>Yitian Zhou</name></author><author><name>Volker M. Lauschke</name></author><author><name>Rui Wang</name></author><author><name>Yi Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Deep learning-based cell segmentation is increasingly utilized in cell biology and molecular pathology, due to massive accumulation of diverse large-scale datasets and excellent performance in cell representation. However, the development of specialized algorithms has long been hampered by a paucity of annotated training data, whereas the performance of generalist algorithm was limited without experiment-specific calibration. Here, we present a deep learning-based tool called Scellseg consisted of novel pre-trained network architecture and contrastive fine-tuning strategy. In comparison to four commonly used algorithms, Scellseg outperformed in average precision on three diverse datasets with no need for dataset-specific configuration. Interestingly, we found that eight images are sufficient for model tuning to achieve satisfied performance based on a shot data scale experiment. We also developed a graphical user interface integrated with functions of annotation, fine-tuning and inference, that allows biologists to easily specialize their own segmentation model and analyze data at the single-cell level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.19.473392" rel="alternate" title="Scellseg: a style-aware cell instance segmentation tool with pre-training and contrastive fine-tuning (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473021</id><title>The ground truth of the Data-Iceberg: Correct Meta-data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.375801+00:00</updated><author><name>Aylin Caliskan</name></author><author><name>Seema Dangwal</name></author><author><name>Thomas Dandekar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological molecular data such as sequence information increase so rapidly that detailed metadata, describing the process and conditions of data collection as well as proper labelling and typing of the data become ever more important to avoid mistakes and erroneous labeling. Starting from a striking example of wrong labelling of patient data recently published in Nature, we advocate measures to improve software metadata and controls in a timely manner to not rapidly loose quality in the ever-growing data flood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.17.473021" rel="alternate" title="The ground truth of the Data-Iceberg: Correct Meta-data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473925</id><title>Bridging functional annotation gaps in non-model plant genes with AlphaFold, DeepFRI and small molecule docking (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.376075+00:00</updated><author><name>Georgie Stephan</name></author><author><name>Benjamin Dugdale</name></author><author><name>Pradeep Deo</name></author><author><name>Rob Harding</name></author><author><name>James Dale</name></author><author><name>Paul Visendi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Functional annotation assigns descriptive biological meaning to genetic sequences. Limited availability of manually curated or experimentally validated plant genes from a diverse range of taxa poses a significant challenge for functional annotation in non-model organisms. Accurate computational approaches are required. We argue that recent breakthroughs in deep learning have the potential to not only narrow the functional annotation gap between non-model and model plant organisms, but also annotate and reveal novel functions even for genes with no homologs in public databases. Results: Deep learning models were applied to functionally annotate a set of previously published differentially expressed genes. Predicted protein structures and functional annotations were generated using the AlphaFold protein structure and DeepFRI protein language inference models respectively. The resulting structures and functional annotations were validated using small molecule docking experiments. DeepFRI and AlphaFold models not only correctly annotated differentially expressed genes, but also revealed detailed mechanisms involving protein-protein interactions. Conclusions: Deep learning models are capable of inferring novel functions and achieving high accuracy in functional annotation. Their increased use in plant research will result in major improvements in annotations for non-model plants that are underrepresented in genome databases. We illustrate how integrating protein structure prediction, functional residue prediction, and small molecule docking can infer plausible protein-protein interactions and yield additional mechanistic insights. This approach will aid in the selection of candidate genes for further study from differential expression studies that generate large gene lists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.22.473925" rel="alternate" title="Bridging functional annotation gaps in non-model plant genes with AlphaFold, DeepFRI and small molecule docking (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473456</id><title>TreeKnit: Inferring Ancestral Reassortment Graphs of influenza viruses (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.376297+00:00</updated><author><name>Pierre Barrat-Charlaix</name></author><author><name>Timothy G. Vaughan</name></author><author><name>Richard A. Neher</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;When two influenza viruses co-infect the same cell, they can exchange genome segments in a process known as reassortment. Reassortment is an important source of genetic diversity and is known to have been involved in the emergence of most pandemic influenza strains. However, because of the difficulty in identifying reassortments events from viral sequence data, little is known about its role in the evolution of the seasonal influenza viruses. Here we introduce TreeKnit, a method that infers ancestral reassortment graphs (ARG) from two segment trees. It is based on topological differences between trees, and proceeds in a greedy fashion by finding regions that are compatible in the two trees. Using simulated genealogies with reassortments, we show that TreeKnit performs well in a wide range of settings and that it is as accurate as a more principled bayesian method, while being orders of magnitude faster. Finally, we show that it is possible to use the inferred ARG to better resolve segment trees and to construct more informative visualizations of reassortments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473456" rel="alternate" title="TreeKnit: Inferring Ancestral Reassortment Graphs of influenza viruses (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473413</id><title>Integrated view and comparative analysis of baseline protein expression in mouse and rat tissues (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.376474+00:00</updated><author><name>Shengbo Wang</name></author><author><name>David García-Seisdedos</name></author><author><name>Ananth Prakash</name></author><author><name>Deepti Jaiswal Kundu</name></author><author><name>Andrew Collins</name></author><author><name>Nancy George</name></author><author><name>Silvie Fexova</name></author><author><name>Pablo Moreno</name></author><author><name>Irene Papatheodorou</name></author><author><name>Andrew R. Jones</name></author><author><name>Juan Antonio Vizcaíno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The increasingly large amount of public proteomics data enables, among other applications, the combined analyses of datasets to create comparative protein expression maps covering different organisms and different biological conditions. Here we have reanalysed public proteomics datasets from mouse and rat tissues (14 and 9 datasets, respectively), to assess baseline protein abundance. Overall, the aggregated dataset contains 23 individual datasets, which have a total of 211 samples coming from 34 different tissues across 14 organs, comprising 9 mouse and 3 rat strains, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We compared protein expression between the different organs, including the distribution of proteins across them. We also performed gene ontology and pathway enrichment analyses to identify organ-specific enriched biological processes and pathways. As a key point we carried out a comparative analysis of protein expression between mouse, rat and human tissues. We observed a high level of correlation of protein expression among orthologs between all three species in brain, kidney, heart and liver samples. Finally, it should be noted that protein expression results have been integrated into the resource Expression Atlas for widespread dissemination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have reanalysed 23 baseline public proteomics datasets stored in the PRIDE database belonging to various mouse and rat tissues and organs. Overall, the aggregated dataset contained 211 samples, coming from 34 different tissues across 14 organs, comprising 9 mouse and 3 rat strains, respectively. We analysed the distribution of protein expression across organs in both species. Then we performed gene ontology and pathway enrichment analyses to identify organ-specific enriched biological processes and pathways. We also carried out a comparative analysis of baseline protein expression between mouse, rat and human tissues, observing a high level of expression correlation among orthologs in all three species, in brain, kidney, heart and liver samples. To disseminate these findings, we have integrated the protein expression results into the resource Expression Atlas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473413" rel="alternate" title="Integrated view and comparative analysis of baseline protein expression in mouse and rat tissues (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473422</id><title>Identification of upstream transcription factor binding sites in orthologous genes using mixed Student’s t-test statistics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.376729+00:00</updated><author><name>Tinghua Huang</name></author><author><name>Hong Xiao</name></author><author><name>Qi Tian</name></author><author><name>Zhen He</name></author><author><name>Cheng Yuan</name></author><author><name>Zezhao Lin</name></author><author><name>Xuejun Gao</name></author><author><name>Min Yao</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcription factor (TF) regulates the transcription of DNA to messenger RNA by binding to upstream sequence motifs. Identifying the locations of known motifs in whole genomes is computationally intensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methodology/Principal Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study presents a computational tool, named “Grit”, for screening TF-binding sites (TFBS) by coordinating transcription factors to their promoter sequences in orthologous genes. This tool employs a newly developed mixed Student’s &lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;-test statistical method that detects high-scoring conserved and non-conserved binding sites among species. The program performs sequence scanning at a rate of 3.2 Mb/s on a quad-core Amazon server and has been benchmarked by the well-established ChIP-Seq datasets, putting Grit amongst the top-ranked TFBS predictors. It marginally outperforms the well-known transcription factor motif scanning tools, Pscan (4.8%) and FIMO (17.8%), in analyzing well-documented ChIP-Atlas human genome Chip-Seq datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grit is a good alternative to current available motif scanning tools and is publicly available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thua45.cn/grit"&gt;http://www.thua45.cn/grit&lt;/ext-link&gt; under an academic free license.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Locating transcription factor-binding (TF-binding) site in the genome and identification their function is fundamental in understanding various biological processes. Improve the performance of the prediction tools is important because accurate TF-binding site prediction can save cost and time for wet-lab experiments. Also, genome wide TF-binding site prediction can provide new insights for transcriptome regulation in system biology perspective. This study developed a new TF-binding site prediction tool based on mixed Student’s &lt;italic&gt;t&lt;/italic&gt;-test statistical method. The tool is amongst the top-ranked TF-binding site predictors, as such, it can help the researchers in TF-binding site identification and transcriptional regulation mechanism interpretation of genes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473422" rel="alternate" title="Identification of upstream transcription factor binding sites in orthologous genes using mixed Student’s t-test statistics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473520</id><title>Explore synergistic and competitive miRNA regulation mechanisms in the miRNA-mRNA regulatory network from the information decomposition perspective (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.376948+00:00</updated><author><name>Chu Pan</name></author><author><name>Jing Jiang</name></author><author><name>Limei Jing</name></author><author><name>Wangqing Chen</name></author><author><name>Yi Yang</name></author><author><name>Ying Liu</name></author><author><name>Jiawei Luo</name></author><author><name>Xiangxiang Zeng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Since multiple microRNAs can target 3’ untranslated regions of the same mRNA transcript, it is likely that these endogenous microRNAs may form synergistic alliances, or compete for the same mRNA harbouring overlapping binding site matches. Synergistic and competitive microRNA regulation is an intriguing yet poorly elucidated mechanism. We here introduce a computational method based on the multivariate information measurement to quantify such implicit interaction effects between microRNAs. Our informatics method of integrating sequence and expression data is designed to establish the functional correlation between microRNAs. To demonstrate our method, we exploited TargetScan and The Cancer Genome Atlas data. As a result, we indeed observed that the microRNA pair with neighbouring binding site(s) on the mRNA is likely to trigger synergistic events, while the microRNA pair with overlapping binding site(s) on the mRNA is likely to cause competitive events, provided that the pair of microRNAs has a high functional similarity and the corresponding triplet presents a positive/negative ‘synergy-redundancy’ score.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.473520" rel="alternate" title="Explore synergistic and competitive miRNA regulation mechanisms in the miRNA-mRNA regulatory network from the information decomposition perspective (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472904</id><title>Inductive inference of novel protein-molecule interactions using Heterogeneous Graph Transformer (HGT) AutoEncoder (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-12-27T09:09:39.377164+00:00</updated><author><name>Alberto Arrigoni</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protein-molecule interactions are promoted by the physicochemical characteristics of the actors involved, but structural information alone does not capture expression patterns, localization and pharmacokinetics. In this work we propose an integrative strategy for protein-molecule interaction discovery that combines different layers of information through the use of convolutional operators on graph, and frame the problem as missing link prediction task on an heterogeneous graph constituted by three node types: 1) molecules 2) proteins 3) diseases. Physicochemical information of the actors are encoded using shallow embedding techniques (SeqVec, Mol2Vec, Doc2Vec respectively) and are supplied as feature vectors to a Graph AutoEncoer (GAE) that uses a Heterogeneous Graph Transformer (HGT) in the encoder module. We show in this work that HGT Autoencoder can be used to accurately recapitulate the proteinmolecule interactions set and propose novel relationships in inductive settings that are grounded in biological and functional information extracted from the graph.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.20.472904" rel="alternate" title="Inductive inference of novel protein-molecule interactions using Heterogeneous Graph Transformer (HGT) AutoEncoder (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>