<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.606622+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447890</id><title>Shape-restrained modelling of protein-small molecule complexes with HADDOCK (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.606983+00:00</updated><author><name>Panagiotis I. Koukos</name></author><author><name>Manon Réau</name></author><author><name>Alexandre M. J. J. Bonvin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Small molecule docking remains one of the most valuable computational techniques for the structure prediction of protein-small molecule complexes. It allows us to study the interactions between compounds and the protein receptors they target at atomic detail, in a timely and efficient manner. Here we present a new protocol in HADDOCK, our integrative modelling platform, which incorporates homology information for both receptor and compounds. It makes use of HADDOCK’s unique ability to integrate information in the simulation to drive it toward conformations which agree with the provided data. The focal point is the use of shape restraints derived from homologous compounds bound to the target receptors. We have developed two protocols: In the first, the shape is composed of fake atom beads based on the position of the heavy atoms of the homologous template compound, whereas in the second the shape is additionally annotated with pharmacophore data, for some or all beads. For both protocols, ambiguous distance restraints are subsequently defined between those beads and the heavy atoms of the ligand to be docked. We have benchmarked the performance of these protocols with a fully unbound version of the widely used DUD-E dataset. In this unbound docking scenario, our template/shape-based docking protocol reaches an overall success rate of 81% on 99 complexes, which is close to the best results reported for bound docking on the DUD-E dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Table of contents graphic&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="float" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="447890v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447890" rel="alternate" title="Shape-restrained modelling of protein-small molecule complexes with HADDOCK (13 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447808</id><title>CANT-HYD: A curated database of phylogeny-derived Hidden Markov Models for annotation of marker genes involved in hydrocarbon degradation (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-14T06:58:24.607373+00:00</updated><author><name>Varada Khot</name></author><author><name>Jackie Zorz</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Gittins</name></author><author><name>Anirban Chakraborty</name></author><author><name>Emma Bell</name></author><author><name>María A. Bautista</name></author><author><name>Alexandre J. Paquette</name></author><author><name>Alyse K. Hawley</name></author><author><name>Breda Novotnik</name></author><author><name>Casey R. J. Hubert</name></author><author><name>Marc Strous</name></author><author><name>Srijak Bhatnagar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Discovery of microbial hydrocarbon degradation pathways has traditionally relied on laboratory isolation and characterization of microorganisms. Although many metabolic pathways for hydrocarbon degradation have been discovered, the absence of tools dedicated to their annotation makes it difficult to identify the relevant genes and predict the hydrocarbon degradation potential of microbial genomes and metagenomes. Furthermore, sequence homology between hydrocarbon degradation genes and genes with other functions often results in misannotation. A tool that systematically identifies hydrocarbon metabolic potential is therefore needed. We present the Calgary approach to ANnoTating HYDrocarbon degradation genes (CANT-HYD), a database containing HMMs of 37 marker genes involved in anaerobic and aerobic degradation pathways of aliphatic and aromatic hydrocarbons. Using this database, we show that hydrocarbon metabolic potential is widespread in the tree of life and identify understudied or overlooked hydrocarbon degradation potential in many phyla. We also demonstrate scalability by analyzing large metagenomic datasets for the prediction of hydrocarbon utilization in diverse environments. To the best of our knowledge, CANT-HYD is the first comprehensive tool for robust and accurate identification of marker genes associated with aerobic and anaerobic hydrocarbon degradation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447808" rel="alternate" title="CANT-HYD: A curated database of phylogeny-derived Hidden Markov Models for annotation of marker genes involved in hydrocarbon degradation (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>