<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.373396+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466024</id><title>Tree-based Correlation Screen and Visualization for Exploring Phenotype-Cell Type Association in Multiple Sample Single-Cell RNA-Sequencing Experiments (24 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.373897+00:00</updated><author><name>Boyang Zhang</name></author><author><name>Zhicheng Ji</name></author><author><name>Hongkai Ji</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA-seq experiments with multiple samples are increasingly used to discover cell types and their molecular features that may influence sample phenotype (e.g. disease). However, analyzing and visualizing the complex cell type-phenotype association remains nontrivial. TreeCorTreat is an open source R package that tackles this problem by using a tree-based correlation screen to analyze and visualize the association between phenotype and transcriptomic features and cell types at multiple cell type resolution levels. With TreeCorTreat, one can conveniently explore and compare different feature types, phenotypic traits, analysis protocols and datasets, and evaluate the impacts of potential confounders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.27.466024" rel="alternate" title="Tree-based Correlation Screen and Visualization for Exploring Phenotype-Cell Type Association in Multiple Sample Single-Cell RNA-Sequencing Experiments (24 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466333</id><title>Deciphering the species-level structure of topologically associating domains (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.374229+00:00</updated><author><name>Rohit Singh</name></author><author><name>Bonnie Berger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chromosome conformation capture technologies such as Hi-C have revealed a rich hierarchical structure of chromatin, with topologically associating domains (TADs) as a key organizational unit, but experimentally reported TAD architectures, currently determined separately for each cell type, are lacking for many cell/tissue types. A solution to address this issue is to integrate existing epigenetic data across cells and tissue types to develop a species-level consensus map relating genes to TADs. Here, we introduce the TAD Map, a bag-of-genes representation that we use to infer, or "impute", TAD architectures for those cells/tissues with limited Hi-C experimental data. The TAD Map enables a systematic analysis of gene coexpression induced by chromatin structure. By overlaying transcriptional data from hundreds of bulk and single-cell assays onto the TAD Map, we assess gene coexpression in TADs and find that expressed genes cluster into fewer TADs than would be expected by chance, and show that time-course and RNA velocity studies further reveal this clustering to be strongest in the early stages of cell differentiation; it is also strong in tumor cells. We provide a probabilistic model to summarize any scRNA-seq transcriptome in terms of its TAD activation profile, which we term a TAD signature, and demonstrate its value for cell type inference, cell fate prediction, and multimodal synthesis. More broadly, our work indicates that the TAD Map's comprehensive, quantitative integration of chromatin structure and scRNA-seq data should play a key role in epigenetic and transcriptomic analyses.

Software availability: https://tadmap.csail.mit.edu&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466333" rel="alternate" title="Deciphering the species-level structure of topologically associating domains (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466072</id><title>Alu-mediated weak CEBPA binding and slow B cell transdifferentiation in human (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.374471+00:00</updated><author><name>Ramil Nurtdinov</name></author><author><name>Maria Sanz</name></author><author><name>Amaya Abad</name></author><author><name>Alexandre Esteban</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Ullrich</name></author><author><name>Carme Arnan</name></author><author><name>Rory Johnson</name></author><author><name>Silvia Perez-Lluch</name></author><author><name>Roderic Guigo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Many developmental and differentiation processes take substantially longer in human than in mouse. To investigate the molecular mechanisms underlying this phenomenon, here we have specifically focused on the transdifferentiation from B cells to macrophages. The process is triggered by exactly the same molecular mechanism -- the induction by the transcription factor (TF) CEBPA -- but takes three days in mouse and seven in human. In mouse, the speed of this process is known to be associated with Myc expression. We found that in this species, CEBPA binds strongly to the Myc promoter, efficiently down-regulating Myc. In human, in contrast, CEBPA does not bind this promoter, and MYC is indirectly and more slowly down-regulated. Attenuation of CEBPA binding is not specific to the MYC promoter, but a general trait of the human genome across multiple biological conditions. We traced back weak CEBPA binding to the primate-specific Alu repeat expansion. Many Alu repeats carry strong CEBPA binding motifs, which sequester CEBPA, and attenuate CEBPA binding genome-wide. We observed similar CEBPA and MYC dynamics in natural processes regulated by CEBPA, suggesting that CEBPA attenuation could underlie the longer duration in human processes controlled by this factor. Our work highlights the highly complex mode in which biological information is encoded in genome sequences, evolutionarily connecting, in an unexpected way, lineage-specific transposable element expansions to species-specific changes in developmental tempos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466072" rel="alternate" title="Alu-mediated weak CEBPA binding and slow B cell transdifferentiation in human (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465513</id><title>Cloud-enabled Fiji for reproducible, integrated and modular image processing (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.374776+00:00</updated><author><name>Ling-Hong Hung</name></author><author><name>Evan Straw</name></author><author><name>Shishir Reddy</name></author><author><name>Zachary Colburn</name></author><author><name>Ka Yee Yeung</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biomedical image analyses can require many steps processing different types of data. Analysis of increasingly large data sets often exceeds the capacity of local computational resources. We present an easy-to-use and modular cloud platform that allows biomedical researchers to reproducibly execute and share complex analytical workflows to process large image datasets. The workflows and the platform are encapsulated in software containers to ensure reproducibility and facilitate installation of even the most complicated workflows. The platform is both graphical and interactive allowing users to use the viewer of their choice to adjust the image pre-processing and analysis steps to iteratively improve the final results. We demonstrate the utility of our platform via two use cases in focal adhesion and 3D imaging analyses. In particular, our focal adhesion workflow demonstrates integration of Fiji with Jupyter Notebooks. Our 3D imaging use case applies Fiji/BigStitcher to big datasets on the cloud. The accessibility and modularity of the cloud platform democratizes the application and development of complex image analysis workflows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.22.465513" rel="alternate" title="Cloud-enabled Fiji for reproducible, integrated and modular image processing (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465589</id><title>UHRF1, NSUN2, and NEIL1 were Detected as Clinical Biomarker Candidates in Prostate Adenocarcinoma with Potential Roles in Disease Pathogenesis (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.376928+00:00</updated><author><name>Buse Nur Kahyaoğulları</name></author><author><name>Turan Demircan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Prostate cancer (PCa) is the most commonly diagnosed cancer in men. Expanding evidence suggests a significant association between cancer progression and RNA modifications. However, our knowledge of the link between m5C and hm5C pathways with PCa is limited. Therefore, we aimed to explore the diagnostic and prognostic values of m5C and hm5C regulators in PCa. In this study, genetic alterations in m5C and hm5C regulators were identified using publicly available databases. Differentially expressed genes in these pathways between tumor and nontumor samples, correlation among m5C and hm5C pathway members, and prognostic value of the regulators were evaluated. Furthermore, enrichment of gene ontology (GO) terms and KEGG pathways was carried out. Obtained results unveiled the mRNA level differences as the key genetic alterations for m5C and hm5C regulators between tumor and nontumor samples. &lt;italic&gt;UHRF1, TET3,&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;NEIL1&lt;/italic&gt; were significantly upregulated in tumor samples compared to nontumor ones, whereas &lt;italic&gt;EGR1&lt;/italic&gt; was significantly downregulated. &lt;italic&gt;UHRF1, DNMT1, NSUN2, NSUN4, C1orf77, C3orf37, WDR77, NEIL1&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;TDG&lt;/italic&gt; genes were identified as candidate prognostic markers of overall survival. The upregulated genes in patient samples with genetic alterations in m5C and hm5C pathways enriched cell cycle-related processes. In summary, our findings suggest that the m5C and hm5C regulators might play a role in PRAD development by activation of proliferation, and the &lt;italic&gt;UHRF1, NSUN2&lt;/italic&gt;, and &lt;italic&gt;NEIL1&lt;/italic&gt; genes have the potential to be utilized as clinical biomarkers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.23.465589" rel="alternate" title="UHRF1, NSUN2, and NEIL1 were Detected as Clinical Biomarker Candidates in Prostate Adenocarcinoma with Potential Roles in Disease Pathogenesis (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465734</id><title>MACA: Marker-based automatic cell-type annotation for single cell expression data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.377214+00:00</updated><author><name>Yang Xu</name></author><author><name>Simon J. Baumgart</name></author><author><name>Christian Stegmann</name></author><author><name>Sikander Hayat</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accurately identifying cell-types is a critical step in single-cell sequencing analyses. Here, we present marker-based automatic cell-type annotation (MACA), a new tool for annotating single-cell transcriptomics datasets. We developed MACA by testing 4 cell-type scoring methods with 2 public cell-marker databases as reference in 6 single-cell studies. MACA compares favorably to 4 existing marker-based cell-type annotation methods in terms of accuracy and speed. We show that MACA can annotate a large single-nuclei RNA-seq study in minutes on human hearts with ~ 290k cells. MACA scales easily to large datasets and can broadly help experts to annotate cell types in single-cell transcriptomics datasets, and we envision MACA provides a new opportunity for integration and standardization of cell-type annotation across multiple datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;MACA is written in python and released under GNU General Public License v3.0. The source code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ImXman/MACA"&gt;https://github.com/ImXman/MACA&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yang Xu (&lt;email&gt;yxu71@vols.utk.edu&lt;/email&gt;), Sikander Hayat (&lt;email&gt;hayat221@gmail.com&lt;/email&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.25.465734" rel="alternate" title="MACA: Marker-based automatic cell-type annotation for single cell expression data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466272</id><title>Computational Fontan Analysis: Preserving accuracy while expediting workflow (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.377418+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiaolong Liu</name></author><author><name>Seda Aslan</name></author><author><name>Byeol Kim</name></author><author><name>Linnea Warburton</name></author><author><name>Derrick Jackson</name></author><author><name>Abir Muhuri</name></author><author><name>Akshay Subramanian</name></author><author><name>Paige Mass</name></author><author><name>Vincent Cleveland</name></author><author><name>Yue-Hin Loke</name></author><author><name>Narutoshi Hibino</name></author><author><name>Laura Olivieri</name></author><author><name>Axel Krieger</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Post-operative outcomes of the Fontan operation have been linked to graft shape after implantation. Computational fluid dynamics (CFD) simulations are used to explore different surgical options. The objective of this study is to perform a systematic in vitro validation for investigating the accuracy and efficiency of CFD simulation to predict Fontan hemodynamics. Methods: CFD simulations were performed to measure indexed power loss (iPL) and hepatic flow distribution (HFD) in 10 patient-specific Fontan models, with varying mesh and numerical solvers. The results were compared with a novel in vitro flow loop setup with 3D printed Fontan models. A high-resolution differential pressure sensor was used to measure the pressure drop for validating iPL predictions. Microparticles with particle filtering system were used to measure HFD. The computational time was measured for a representative Fontan model with different mesh sizes and numerical solvers. Results: When compared to in vitro setup, variations in CFD mesh sizes had significant effect on HFD (p = 0.0002) but no significant impact on iPL (p = 0.069). Numerical solvers had no significant impact in both iPL (p = 0.50) and HFD (P = 0.55). A transient solver with 0.5 mm mesh size requires computational time 100 times more than a steady solver with 2.5 mm mesh size to generate similar results. Conclusions: The predictive value of CFD for Fontan planning can be validated against an in vitro flow loop. The prediction accuracy can be affected by the mesh size, model shape complexity and flow competition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466272" rel="alternate" title="Computational Fontan Analysis: Preserving accuracy while expediting workflow (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466332</id><title>Causal Haplotype Block Identification in Plant Genome-Wide Association Studies (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-11-01T10:59:12.377650+00:00</updated><author><name>Xing Wu</name></author><author><name>Wei Jiang</name></author><author><name>Christopher Fragoso</name></author><author><name>Jing Huang</name></author><author><name>Geyu Zhou</name></author><author><name>Hong-yu Zhao</name></author><author><name>Stephen Dellaporta</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome wide association studies (GWAS) can play an essential role in understanding genetic basis of complex traits in plants and animals. Conventional SNP-based linear mixed models (LMM) used in many GWAS that marginally test single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have successfully identified many loci with major and minor effects. In plants, the relatively small population size in GWAS and the high genetic diversity found many plant species can impede mapping efforts on complex traits. Here we present a novel haplotype-based trait fine-mapping framework, HapFM, to supplement current GWAS methods. HapFM uses genotype data to partition the genome into haplotype blocks, identifies haplotype clusters within each block, and then performs genome-wide haplotype fine-mapping to infer the causal haplotype blocks of trait. We benchmarked HapFM, GEMMA, BSLMM, and GMMAT in both simulation and real plant GWAS datasets. HapFM consistently resulted in higher mapping power than the other GWAS methods in simulations with high polygenicity. Moreover, it resulted in higher mapping resolution, especially in regions of high LD, by identifying small causal blocks in the larger haplotype block. In the Arabidopsis flowering time (FT10) datasets, HapFM identified four novel loci compared to GEMMA results, and its average mapping interval of HapFM was 9.6 times smaller than that of GEMMA. In conclusion, HapFM is tailored for plant GWAS to result in high mapping power on complex traits and improved mapping resolution to facilitate crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.28.466332" rel="alternate" title="Causal Haplotype Block Identification in Plant Genome-Wide Association Studies (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>