<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.583018+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443517</id><title>Multi-resolution deconvolution of spatial transcriptomics data reveals continuous patterns of inflammation (67 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.583490+00:00</updated><author><name>Romain Lopez</name></author><author><name>Baoguo Li</name></author><author><name>Hadas Keren-Shaul</name></author><author><name>Pierre Boyeau</name></author><author><name>Merav Kedmi</name></author><author><name>David Pilzer</name></author><author><name>Adam Jelinski</name></author><author><name>Eyal David</name></author><author><name>Allon Wagner</name></author><author><name>Yoseph Addad</name></author><author><name>Michael I. Jordan</name></author><author><name>Ido Amit</name></author><author><name>Nir Yosef</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The function of mammalian cells is largely influenced by their tissue microenvironment. Advances in spatial transcriptomics open the way for studying these important determinants of cellular function by enabling a transcriptome-wide evaluation of gene expression &lt;italic&gt;in situ&lt;/italic&gt;. A critical limitation of the current technologies, however, is that their resolution is limited to niches (spots) of sizes well beyond that of a single cell, thus providing measurements for cell aggregates which may mask critical interactions between neighboring cells of different types. While joint analysis with single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) can be leveraged to alleviate this problem, current analyses are limited to a discrete view of cell type proportion inside every spot. This limitation becomes critical in the common case where, even within a cell type, there is a continuum of cell states that cannot be clearly demarcated but reflects important differences in the way cells function and interact with their surroundings. To address this, we developed Deconvolution of Spatial Transcriptomics profiles using Variational Inference (DestVI), a probabilistic method for multi-resolution analysis for spatial transcriptomics that explicitly models continuous variation within cell types. Using simulations, we demonstrate that DestVI is capable of providing higher resolution compared to the existing methods and that it can estimate gene expression by every cell type inside every spot. We then introduce an automated pipeline that uses DestVI for analysis of single tissue slices and comparison between tissues. We apply this pipeline to study the immune crosstalk within lymph nodes to infection and explore the spatial organization of a mouse tumor model. In both cases, we demonstrate that DestVI can provide a high resolution and accurate spatial characterization of the cellular organization of these tissues, and that it is capable of identifying important cell-type-specific changes in gene expression - between different tissue regions or between conditions. DestVI is available as an open-source software package in the scvi-tools codebase (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scvi-tools.org"&gt;https://scvi-tools.org&lt;/ext-link&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443517" rel="alternate" title="Multi-resolution deconvolution of spatial transcriptomics data reveals continuous patterns of inflammation (67 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443525</id><title>Systematic tissue annotations of –omics samples by modeling unstructured metadata (65 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.584045+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathaniel T. Hawkins</name></author><author><name>Marc Maldaver</name></author><author><name>Anna Yannakopoulos</name></author><author><name>Lindsay A. Guare</name></author><author><name>Arjun Krishnan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;There are currently &amp;gt;1.3 million human –omics samples that are publicly available. However, this valuable resource remains acutely underused because discovering samples, say from a particular tissue of interest, from this ever-growing data collection is still a significant challenge. The major impediment is that sample attributes such as tissue/cell-type of origin are routinely described using non-standard, varied terminologies written in unstructured natural language. Here, we propose a natural-language-processing-based machine learning approach (NLP-ML) to infer tissue and cell-type annotations for –omics samples based only on their free-text metadata. NLP-ML works by creating numerical representations of sample text descriptions and using these representations as features in a supervised learning classifier that predicts tissue/cell-type terms in a structured ontology. Our approach significantly and substantially outperforms an advanced text annotation method (MetaSRA) that uses graph-based reasoning and a baseline method (TAGGER) that annotates text based on exact string matching. Model similarities between related tissues demonstrate that NLP-ML models capture biologically-meaningful signals in text, as does the ability of these models to classify tissue-associated biological processes and diseases based on their descriptions alone. NLP-ML models are nearly as accurate as models based on gene-expression profiles in predicting sample tissue annotations but have the distinct capability to classify samples irrespective of the –omics experiment type based on their text metadata. Python NLP-ML prediction code and trained tissue models are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/krishnanlab/txt2onto"&gt;https://github.com/krishnanlab/txt2onto&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443525" rel="alternate" title="Systematic tissue annotations of –omics samples by modeling unstructured metadata (65 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443685</id><title>A clusterability measure for single-cell transcriptomics reveals phenotypic subpopulations (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.584474+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Mircea</name></author><author><name>Mazène Hochane</name></author><author><name>Xueying Fan</name></author><author><name>Susana M. Chuva de Sousa Lopes</name></author><author><name>Diego Garlaschelli</name></author><author><name>Stefan Semrau</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability to discover new cell populations by unsupervised clustering of single-cell transcriptomics data has revolutionized biology. Currently, there is no principled way to decide, whether a cluster of cells contains meaningful subpopulations that should be further resolved. Here we present SIGMA, a clusterability measure derived from random matrix theory, that can be used to identify cell clusters with non-random sub-structure, testably leading to the discovery of previously overlooked phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443685" rel="alternate" title="A clusterability measure for single-cell transcriptomics reveals phenotypic subpopulations (23 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443585</id><title>OVarFlow: a resource optimized GATK 4 based Open source Variant calling workFlow (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.584826+00:00</updated><author><name>Jochen Bathke</name></author><author><name>Gesine Lühken</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next generation sequencing technologies are opening new doors to researchers. One application is the direct discovery of sequence variants that are causative for a phenotypic trait or a disease. The detection of an organisms alterations from a reference genome is know as variant calling, a computational task involving a complex chain of software applications. One key player in the field is the Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK). The GATK Best Practices are commonly referred recipe for variant calling on human sequencing data. Still the fact the Best Practices are highly specialized on human sequencing data and are permanently evolving is often ignored. Reproducibility is thereby aggravated, leading to continuous reinvention of pretended GATK Best Practice workflows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present an automatized variant calling workflow, for the detection of SNPs and indels, that is broadly applicable for model as well as non-model diploid organisms. It is derived from the GATK Best Practice workflow for “Germline short variant discovery”, without being focused on human sequencing data. The workflow has been highly optimized to achieve parallelized data evaluation and also maximize performance of individual applications to shorten overall analysis time. Optimized Java garbage collection and heap size settings for the GATK applications SortSam, MarkDuplicates, HaplotypeCaller and GatherVcfs were determined by thorough benchmarking. In doing so, runtimes of an example data evaluation could be reduced from 67 h to less than 35 h.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The demand for standardized variant calling workflows is proportionally growing with the dropping costs of next generation sequencing methods. Our workflow perfectly fits into this niche, offering automatization, reproducibility and documentation of the variant calling process. Moreover resource usage is lowered to a minimum. Thereby variant calling projects should become more standardized, reducing the barrier further for smaller institutions or groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443585" rel="alternate" title="OVarFlow: a resource optimized GATK 4 based Open source Variant calling workFlow (18 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443497</id><title>LYRUS: A Machine Learning Model for Predicting the Pathogenicity of Missense Variants (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.585117+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiaying Lai</name></author><author><name>Jordan Yang</name></author><author><name>Ece D. Gamsiz Uzun</name></author><author><name>Brenda M. Rubenstein</name></author><author><name>Indra Neil Sarkar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single amino acid variations (SAVs) are a primary contributor to variations in the human genome. Identifying pathogenic SAVs can aid in the diagnosis and understanding of the genetic architecture of complex diseases, such as cancer. Most approaches for predicting the functional effects or pathogenicity of SAVs rely on either sequence or structural information. Nevertheless, previous analyses have shown that methods that depend on only sequence or structural information may have limited accuracy. Recently, researchers have attempted to increase the accuracy of their predictions by incorporating protein dynamics into pathogenicity predictions. This study presents &amp;lt; Lai Yang Rubenstein Uzun Sarkar &amp;gt; (LYRUS), a machine learning method that uses an XGBoost classifier selected by TPOT to predict the pathogenicity of SAVs. LYRUS incorporates five sequence-based features, six structure-based features, and four dynamics-based features. Uniquely, LYRUS includes a newly-proposed sequence co-evolution feature called variation number. LYRUS’s performance was evaluated using a dataset that contains 4,363 protein structures corresponding to 20,307 SAVs based on human genetic variant data from the ClinVar database. Based on our dataset, the LYRUS classifier has a higher accuracy, specificity, F-measure, and Matthews correlation coefficient (MCC) than alternative methods including PolyPhen2, PROVEAN, SIFT, Rhapsody, EVMutation, MutationAssessor, SuSPect, FATHMM, and MVP. Variation numbers used within LYRUS differ greatly between pathogenic and neutral SAVs, and have a high feature weight in the XGBoost classifier employed by this method. Applications of the method to PTEN and TP53 further corroborate LYRUS’s strong performance. LYRUS is freely available and the source code can be found at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jiaying2508/LYRUS"&gt;https://github.com/jiaying2508/LYRUS&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.10.443497" rel="alternate" title="LYRUS: A Machine Learning Model for Predicting the Pathogenicity of Missense Variants (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443665</id><title>A graphical, interactive and GPU-enabled workflow to process long-read sequencing data (13 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.585336+00:00</updated><author><name>Shishir Reddy</name></author><author><name>Ling-Hong Hung</name></author><author><name>Olga Sala-Torra</name></author><author><name>Jerald Radich</name></author><author><name>Cecilia CS Yeung</name></author><author><name>Ka Yee Yeung</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present a graphical cloud-enabled workflow for fast, interactive analysis of nanopore sequencing data using GPUs. Users customize parameters, monitor execution and visualize results through an accessible graphical interface. To facilitate reproducible deployment, we use Docker containers and provide an Amazon Machine Image (AMI) with all software and drivers pre-installed for GPU computing on the cloud. We observe a 34x speedup and a 109x reduction in costs for the rate-limiting basecalling step in the analysis of blood cancer cell line data. The graphical interface and greatly simplified deployment facilitate the adoption of GPUs for rapid, cost-effective analysis of long-read sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443665" rel="alternate" title="A graphical, interactive and GPU-enabled workflow to process long-read sequencing data (13 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.443910</id><title>riboviz 2: A flexible and robust ribosome profiling data analysis and visualization workflow (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.585562+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexander L Cope</name></author><author><name>Felicity Anderson</name></author><author><name>John Favate</name></author><author><name>Michael Jackson</name></author><author><name>Amanda Mok</name></author><author><name>Anna Kurowska</name></author><author><name>Emma MacKenzie</name></author><author><name>Vikram Shivakumar</name></author><author><name>Peter Tilton</name></author><author><name>Sophie M Winterbourne</name></author><author><name>Siyin Xue</name></author><author><name>Kostas Kavoussanakis</name></author><author><name>Liana F Lareau</name></author><author><name>Premal Shah</name></author><author><name>Edward WJ Wallace</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivation: Ribosome profiling, or Ribo-seq, is the state of the art method for quantifying protein synthesis in living cells. Computational analysis of Ribo-seq data remains challenging due to the complexity of the procedure, as well as variations introduced for specific organisms or specialized analyses. Many bioinformatic pipelines have been developed, but these pipelines have key limitations in terms of functionality or usability.
Results: We present riboviz 2, an updated riboviz package, for the comprehensive transcript-centric analysis and visualization of Ribo-seq data. riboviz 2 includes an analysis workflow built on the Nextflow workflow management system, combining freely available software with custom code. The package is extensively documented and provides example configuration files for organisms spanning the domains of life. riboviz 2 is distinguished by clear separation of concerns between annotation and analysis: prior to a run, the user chooses a transcriptome in FASTA format, paired with annotation for the CDS locations in GFF3 format. The user is empowered to choose the relevant transcriptome for their biological question, or to run alternative analyses that address distinct questions. riboviz 2 has been extensively tested on various library preparation strategies, including multiplexed samples. riboviz 2 is flexible and uses open, documented file formats, allowing users to integrate new analyses with the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.14.443910" rel="alternate" title="riboviz 2: A flexible and robust ribosome profiling data analysis and visualization workflow (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443668</id><title>Comparison of Approaches to Transcriptomic Analysis in Multi-Sampled Tumors (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.585946+00:00</updated><author><name>Anson T. Ku</name></author><author><name>Scott Wilkinson</name></author><author><name>Adam G. Sowalsky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Intratumoral heterogeneity is a well-documented feature of human cancers associated with outcome and treatment resistance. However, a heterogeneous tumor transcriptome contributes an unknown level of variability to analyses of differentially expressed genes that may contribute to phenotypes of interest, including treatment response. Although current clinical practice and the vast majority of research studies use a single sample from each patient, decreasing costs in sequencing technologies and computing costs have made repeated-measures analyses increasingly economical. Repeatedly sampling the same tumor increases the statistical power of differentially expressed gene analysis that is indispensable towards downstream analysis and also increases ones understanding of within-tumor variance that may affect conclusions. Here, we compared five different methods for analyzing gene expression profiles derived from repeated sampling of human prostate tumors in two separate cohorts of patients. We also benchmarked the sensitivity of generalized linear models to linear mixed models for identifying differentially expressed genes contributing to relevant prostate cancer pathways based on a ground truth model.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.443668" rel="alternate" title="Comparison of Approaches to Transcriptomic Analysis in Multi-Sampled Tumors (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443769</id><title>A de novo protein structure prediction by iterative partition sampling, topology adjustment, and residue-level distance deviation optimization (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-18T05:45:25.586396+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Liu</name></author><author><name>Kai-Long Zhao</name></author><author><name>Guang-Xing He</name></author><author><name>Liu-Jing Wang</name></author><author><name>Xiao-Gen Zhou</name></author><author><name>Gui-Jun Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the great progress of deep learning-based inter-residue contact/distance prediction, the discrete space formed by fragment assembly cannot satisfy the distance constraint well. Thus, the optimal solution of the continuous space may not be achieved. Designing an effective closed-loop continuous dihedral angle optimization strategy that complements the discrete fragment assembly is crucial to improve the performance of the distance-assisted fragment assembly method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this article, we proposed a de novo protein structure prediction method called IPTDFold based on closed-loop iterative partition sampling, topology adjustment and residue-level distance deviation optimization. First, local dihedral angle crossover and mutation operators are designed to explore the conformational space extensively and achieve information exchange between the conformations in the population. Then, the dihedral angle rotation model of loop region with partial inter-residue distance constraints is constructed, and the rotation angle satisfying the constraints is obtained by differential evolution algorithm, so as to adjust the spatial position relationship between the secondary structures. Lastly, the residue distance deviation is evaluated according to the difference between the conformation and the predicted distance, and the dihedral angle of the residue is optimized with biased probability. The final model is generated by iterating the above three steps. IPTDFold is tested on 462 benchmark proteins, 24 FM targets of CASP13, and 20 FM targets of CASP14. Results show that IPTDFold is significantly superior to the distance-assisted fragment assembly method Rosetta_D (Rosetta with distance). In particular, the prediction accuracy of IPTDFold does not decrease as the length of the protein increases. When using the same &lt;italic&gt;FastRelax&lt;/italic&gt; protocol, the prediction accuracy of IPTDFold is significantly superior to that of trRosetta without orientation constraints, and is equivalent to that of the full version of trRosetta.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source code and executable are freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/iobio-zjut/IPTDFold"&gt;https://github.com/iobio-zjut/IPTDFold&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;zgj@zjut.edu.cn&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.12.443769" rel="alternate" title="A de novo protein structure prediction by iterative partition sampling, topology adjustment, and residue-level distance deviation optimization (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>