<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.905759+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457057</id><title>MultiVI: deep generative model for the integration of multi-modal data (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.906177+00:00</updated><author><name>Tal Ashuach</name></author><author><name>Mariano I Gabitto</name></author><author><name>Michael I Jordan</name></author><author><name>Nir Yosef</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The ability to jointly profile the transcriptional and chromatin landscape of single-cells has emerged as a powerful technique to identify cellular populations and shed light on their regulation of gene expression. Current computational methods analyze jointly profiled (paired) or individual data modalities (unpaired), but do not offer a principled method to analyze both paired and unpaired samples jointly. Here we present MultiVI, a probabilistic framework that leverages deep neural networks to jointly analyze scRNA, scATAC and multiomic (scRNA + scATAC) data. MultiVI creates an informative low-dimensional latent space that accurately reflects both chromatin and transcriptional properties of the cells even when one of the modalities is missing. MultiVI accounts for technical effects in both scRNA and scATAC-seq while correcting for batch effects in both data modalities. We use public datasets to demonstrate that MultiVI is stable, easy to use, and outperforms current approaches for the joint analysis of paired and unpaired data. MultiVI is available as an open source package, implemented in the scvi-tools framework: https://docs.scvi-tools.org&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.20.457057" rel="alternate" title="MultiVI: deep generative model for the integration of multi-modal data (42 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456499</id><title>scFlow: A Scalable and Reproducible Analysis Pipeline for Single-Cell RNA Sequencing Data (36 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.906531+00:00</updated><author><name>Combiz Khozoie</name></author><author><name>Nurun Fancy</name></author><author><name>Mahdi M. Marjaneh</name></author><author><name>Alan E. Murphy</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Matthews</name></author><author><name>Nathan Skene</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advances in single-cell RNA-sequencing technology over the last decade have enabled exponential increases in throughput: datasets with over a million cells are becoming commonplace. The burgeoning scale of data generation, combined with the proliferation of alternative analysis methods, led us to develop the scFlow toolkit and the nf-core/scflow pipeline for reproducible, efficient, and scalable analyses of single-cell and single-nuclei RNA-sequencing data. The scFlow toolkit provides a higher level of abstraction on top of popular single-cell packages within an R ecosystem, while the nf-core/scflow Nextflow pipeline is built within the nf-core framework to enable compute infrastructure-independent deployment across all institutions and research facilities. Here we present our flexible pipeline, which leverages the advantages of containerization and the potential of Cloud computing for easy orchestration and scaling of the analysis of large case/control datasets by even non-expert users. We demonstrate the functionality of the analysis pipeline from sparse-matrix quality control through to insight discovery with examples of analysis of four recently published public datasets and describe the extensibility of scFlow as a modular, open-source tool for single-cell and single nuclei bioinformatic analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456499" rel="alternate" title="scFlow: A Scalable and Reproducible Analysis Pipeline for Single-Cell RNA Sequencing Data (36 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456500</id><title>SeqDistK: a Novel Tool for Alignment-free Phylogenetic Analysis (18 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.906980+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuemei Liu</name></author><author><name>Wen Li</name></author><author><name>Guanda Huang</name></author><author><name>Tianlai Huang</name></author><author><name>Qingang Xiong</name></author><author><name>Wen Chen</name></author><author><name>Li C. Xia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Algorithms for constructing phylogenetic trees are fundamental to study the evolution of viruses, bacteria, and other microbes. Established multiple alignment-based algorithms are inefficient for large scale metagenomic sequence data because of their high requirement of inter-sequence correlation and high computational complexity. In this paper, we present SeqDistK, a novel tool for alignment-free phylogenetic analysis. SeqDistK computes the dissimilarity matrix for phylogenetic analysis, incorporating seven k-mer based dissimilarity measures, namely d2, d2S, d2star, Euclidean, Manhattan, CVTree, and Chebyshev. Based on these dissimilarities, SeqDistK constructs phylogenetic tree using the Unweighted Pair Group Method with Arithmetic Mean algorithm. Using a golden standard dataset of 16S rRNA and its associated phylogenetic tree, we compared SeqDistK to Muscle – a multi sequence aligner. We found SeqDistK was not only 38 times faster than Muscle in computational efficiency but also more accurate. SeqDistK achieved the smallest symmetric difference between the inferred and ground truth trees with a range between 13 to 18, while that of Muscle was 62. When measures d2, d2star, d2S, Euclidean, and k-mer size k=5 were used, SeqDistK consistently inferred phylogenetic tree almost identical to the ground truth tree. We also performed clustering of 16S rRNA sequences using SeqDistK and found the clustering was highly consistent with known biological taxonomy. Among all the measures, d2S (k=5, M=2) showed the best accuracy as it correctly clustered and classified all sample sequences. In summary, SeqDistK is a novel, fast and accurate alignment-free tool for large-scale phylogenetic analysis. SeqDistK software is freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/htczero/SeqDistK"&gt;https://github.com/htczero/SeqDistK&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.16.456500" rel="alternate" title="SeqDistK: a Novel Tool for Alignment-free Phylogenetic Analysis (18 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456871</id><title>RRNPP_detector: a tool to detect RRNPP quorum sensing systems in chromosomes, plasmids and phages of gram-positive bacteria (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.907338+00:00</updated><author><name>Charles Bernard</name></author><author><name>Yanyan Li</name></author><author><name>Eric Bapteste</name></author><author><name>Philippe Lopez</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gram-positive bacteria (e.g. Firmicutes) and their mobile genetic elements (plasmids, bacteriophages) encode peptide-based quorum sensing systems (QSSs) that regulate behavioral transitions in a density-dependent manner. In their simplest form, termed “RRNPP”, these QSSs are composed of two adjacent genes: a communication propeptide and its cognate intracellular receptor. Despite the prime importance of RRNPP QSSs in the regulation of key biological pathways such as virulence, sporulation or biofilm formation in bacteria, conjugation in plasmids or lysogeny in temperate bacteriophages, no tools exist to predict their presence in target genomes/mobilomes. Here, we introduce RRNPP_detector, a software to predict RRNPP QSSs in chromosomes, plasmids and bacteriophages of gram-positive bacteria, available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/TeamAIRE/RRNPP_detector"&gt;https://github.com/TeamAIRE/RRNPP_detector&lt;/ext-link&gt;. RRNPP_detector does not rely on homology searches but on a signature of multiple criteria, which are common between distinct families of experimentally-validated RRNPP QSSs. Because this signature is generic while specific to the canonical mechanism of RRNPP quorum sensing, it enables the discovery of novel RRNPP QSSs and thus of novel “languages” of biocommunication. Applying RRNPP_detector against complete genomes of viruses and Firmicutes available on the NCBI, we report a potential 7.5-fold expansion of RRNPP QSS diversity, alternative secretion-modes for certain candidate QSS propeptides, ‘bilingual’ bacteriophages and plasmids, as well as predicted chromosomal and plasmidic Biosynthetic-Gene-Clusters regulated by QSSs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.18.456871" rel="alternate" title="RRNPP_detector: a tool to detect RRNPP quorum sensing systems in chromosomes, plasmids and phages of gram-positive bacteria (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.457008</id><title>Tools and applications for integrative analysis of DNA methylation in social insects (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.907678+00:00</updated><author><name>Claire Morandin</name></author><author><name>Volker P. Brendel</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA methylation is a common epigenetic signaling tool and an important biological process which is widely studied in a large array of species. The presence, level, and function of DNA methylation varies greatly across species. In insects, DNA methylation systems are reduced, and methylation rates are often low. Low methylation levels probed by whole genome bisulfite sequencing require great care with respect to data quality control and intepretation. Here we introduce BWASP/R, a reproducible, scalable workflow, that allows efficient, scalable, and entirely reproducible analyses of raw DNA methylation sequencing data. Consistent application of quality control filters and analysis parameters provides fair comparisons among different studies and an integrated view of all experiments on one species. We describe the capabilities of the &lt;monospace&gt;BWASP/R&lt;/monospace&gt; workflow by re-analyzing several publicly available social insect WGBS datasets, comprising 70 samples and cumulatively 147 replicates from four different species. We show that the CpG methylome comprises only about 1.5% of CpG sites in the honeybee genome and that the cumulative data are consistent with genetic signatures of site accessibility and physiological control of methylation levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Significance Statement&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNA methylation in the honeybee genome occurs occurs almost entirely at CpG sites. Methylation rates are small compared to rates in mammalian or plant genomes. De novo analysis of all published honeybee methylation studies and statistical modeling suggests that the CpG methylome consists of about only 300,000 sites. The development of a fully reproducible, scalable, portable workflow allows for easy accessible updates of integrative views of all current experiments. The integrated results for the honeybee are consistent with genetic determination of methylation site accessibility by yet uncharacterized sequence features and physiological control of methylation levels at those sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.457008" rel="alternate" title="Tools and applications for integrative analysis of DNA methylation in social insects (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456943</id><title>Multi view based imaging genetics analysis on Parkinson disease (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-23T08:02:16.907994+00:00</updated><author><name>Guglielmo Cerri</name></author><author><name>Manuel Tognon</name></author><author><name>Simone Avesani</name></author><author><name>Neil Oxtoby</name></author><author><name>Andre Altmann</name></author><author><name>Rosalba Giugno</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Longitudinal studies integrating imaging and genetic data have recently become widespread among bioinformatics researchers. Combining such heterogeneous data allows a better understanding of complex diseases origins and causes. Through a multi-view based workflow proposal, we show the common steps and tools used in imaging genetics analysis, interpolating genotyping, neuroimaging and transcriptomic data. We describe the advantages of existing methods to analyze heterogeneous datasets,  using Parkinson's Disease (PD) as a case study. Parkinson's disease is associated with both genetic and neuroimaging factors, however such imaging genetics associations are at an early investigation stage. Therefore it is desirable to have a  free and open source workflow that integrates different analysis flows  in order to recover potential genetic biomarkers in PD, as in other complex diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.19.456943" rel="alternate" title="Multi view based imaging genetics analysis on Parkinson disease (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>