<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.528626+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.454980</id><title>The structural coverage of the human proteome before and after AlphaFold (109 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.529021+00:00</updated><author><name>Eduard Porta-Pardo</name></author><author><name>Victoria Ruiz-Serra</name></author><author><name>Alfonso Valencia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The protein structure field is experiencing a revolution. From the increased throughput of techniques to determine experimental structures, to developments such as cryo-EM that allow us to find the structures of large protein complexes or, more recently, the development of artificial intelligence tools, such as AlphaFold, that can predict with high accuracy the folding of proteins for which the availability of homology templates is limited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we quantify the effect of the recently released AlphaFold database of protein structural models in our knowledge on human proteins. Our results indicate that our current baseline for structural coverage of 47%, considering experimentally-derived or template-based homology models, elevates up to 75% when including AlphaFold’s predictions, reducing the fraction of “dark proteome” from 22% to just 7% and the number of proteins without structural information from 4.832 to just 29.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, although the coverage of disease-associated genes and mutations was near complete before AlphaFold release (70% of ClinVar’s pathogenic mutations and 74% of oncogenic mutations), AlphaFold models still provide an additional coverage of 2% to 14% of these critically important sets of biomedical genes and mutations. We also provide several examples of disease-associated proteins where AlphaFold provides critical new insights. Overall, our results show that the sequence-structure gap of human proteins has almost disappeared, an outstanding success of direct consequences for the knowledge on the human genome and the derived medical applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.03.454980" rel="alternate" title="The structural coverage of the human proteome before and after AlphaFold (109 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.453756</id><title>LEVELNET: diving into the multiple layers of protein-protein physical interaction networks (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.529364+00:00</updated><author><name>Yasser Mohseni Behbahani</name></author><author><name>Paul Saighi</name></author><author><name>Flavia Corsi</name></author><author><name>Elodie Laine</name></author><author><name>Alessandra Carbone</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The complexity underlying protein-protein interaction (PPI) networks calls for the development of comprehensive knowledge bases organizing PPI-related data. The constant growth and high reliability of structural data make them a suitable source of evidence for the determination of PPI. We present LEVELNET, a fully-automated and scalable environment designed to integrate, explore, and infer protein interactions and non-interactions based on physical contacts and other PPI sources, including user-defined annotations. LEVELNET helps to break down the complexity of PPI networks by representing them as multi-layered graphs and allowing the selection of subnetworks and their direct comparison. LEVELNET proposes an interactive visualisation based on a user-friendly web interface. LEVELNET applications are multiple. It allows to explore PPIs of biological processes, identify co-localised partners, assess PPI predictions from computational or experimental sources, unravel cross-interactions, show and compare multiple PPI sources, and help creating PPI benchmarks with specific properties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;LEVELNET is freely available to the community at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lcqb.upmc.fr/levelnet/"&gt;http://www.lcqb.upmc.fr/levelnet/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.31.453756" rel="alternate" title="LEVELNET: diving into the multiple layers of protein-protein physical interaction networks (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455202</id><title>EnGRNT: Inference of gene regulatory networks using ensemble methods and topological feature extraction (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-15T16:11:33.529800+00:00</updated><author><name>Hakimeh Khojasteh</name></author><author><name>Mohammad Hossein Olyaee</name></author><author><name>Alireza Khanteymoori</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational methods to predict gene regulatory networks (GRNs) from gene expression data is a challenging task. Many machine learning methods have been developed, including supervised, unsupervised, and semi-supervised to infer gene regulatory networks. Most of these methods ignore the class imbalance problem which can lead to decreasing the accuracy of predicting regulatory interactions in the network. Therefore, developing an effective method considering imbalanced data is a challenging task. In this paper, we propose EnGRNT approach to infer GRNs with high accuracy that uses ensemble-based methods. The proposed approach, as well as the gene expression data, considers the topological features of GRN. We applied our approach to the simulated Escherichia coli dataset. Experimental results demonstrate that the appropriateness of the inference method relies on the size and type of expression profiles in microarray data. Except for multifactorial experimental conditions, the proposed approach outperforms unsupervised methods. The obtained results recommend the application of EnGRNT on the imbalanced datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.05.455202" rel="alternate" title="EnGRNT: Inference of gene regulatory networks using ensemble methods and topological feature extraction (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>