<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.648017+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474460</id><title>Protein interaction analysis of Plasmodium falciparum circumsporozoite protein variants with human immunoproteins explains RTS,S vaccine efficacy in Ghana (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.648411+00:00</updated><author><name>Cheikh Cambel Dieng</name></author><author><name>Colby T Ford</name></author><author><name>Anita T Lerch</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Huynh</name></author><author><name>Kovidh Vegesna</name></author><author><name>Jun-tao Guo</name></author><author><name>Daniel A Janies</name></author><author><name>Linda E. Amoah</name></author><author><name>Yaw Afrane</name></author><author><name>Eugenia Lo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The world's first malaria vaccine RTS,S provides only partial protection against Plasmodium falciparum infections. The explanation for such low efficacy is unclear. This study examined the associations of parasite genetic variations with binding affinity to human immunological proteins including human leukocyte antigen (HLA) and T cell receptors (TCR) involved in RTS,S-induced immune responses. Multiplicity of infections was determined by amplicon deep sequencing of merozoite surface protein 1 (PfMSP1). Genetic variations in the C-terminal of circumsporozoite protein (PfMSP1) gene were examined across 88 samples of P. falciparum collected from high and low transmission settings of Ghana. Binding interactions of PfMSP1 variants and HLA/TCR were analyzed using NetChop} and HADDOCK predictions. Anti-CSP IgG levels were measured by ELISA in a subset of 10 samples. High polyclonality was detected among P. falciparum infections. A total 27 CSP haplotypes were detected among samples. A significant correlation was detected between the CSP and MSP multiplicity of infection (MOI). No clear clustering of haplotypes was observed by geographic regions. The number of genetic differences in PfCSP between 3D7 and non-3D7 variants does not influence binding interactions to HLA/T cells nor anti-CSP IgG levels. Nevertheless, PfCSP peptide length significantly affects its molecular weight and binding affinity to the HLA. The presence of multiple non-3D7 strains among P. falciparum infections in Ghana impact the effectiveness of RTS,S. Longer PfCSP peptides may elicit a stronger immune response and should be considered in future version RTS,S. The molecular mechanisms of RTS,S cell-mediated immune responses related to longer CSP peptides warrants further investigations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474460" rel="alternate" title="Protein interaction analysis of Plasmodium falciparum circumsporozoite protein variants with human immunoproteins explains RTS,S vaccine efficacy in Ghana (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474397</id><title>Comparative analysis of Lysine and Arginine biosynthesis pathway in Deinococcus genomes (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.648766+00:00</updated><author><name>Sankar Mahesh</name></author><author><name>Deepa Sethi</name></author><author><name>Richa Priyadarshini</name></author><author><name>Ragothaman M Yennamalli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The members of the Deinococcaceae family have the ability to survive extreme environmental conditions. Deinococcus species have a complex cell envelope composed of L-ornithine containing peptidoglycan. Anabolism of L-ornithine is intrinsically linked to L-lysine and L-arginine biosynthetic pathways. To understand these two pathways, we analyzed the L-lysine and L-arginine pathways using 23 Deinococcus genomes, including D. indicus. We used BLAST-P based ortholog identification using D. radiodurans genes as the query. We identified some BLAST-P hits that shared the same functional annotation. We analyzed three (class I aminotransferase, acetyl-lysine deacetylase, and acetyl glutamate/acetyl aminoadipate kinase) from L-lysine biosynthesis pathway and three (bifunctional ornithine acetyltransferase or N-acetyl glutamate synthase protein, nitric oxide synthase-like protein, and Acetyl-lysine deacetylase) from L-arginine biosynthesis pathway. Two proteins showed certain structural variations. Specifically, [LysW]-lysine hydrolase protein sequence and structure level changes indicated changes in oligomeric conformation, which could likely be a result of divergent evolution. And, bifunctional ornithine acetyltransferase or N-acetyl glutamate synthase had its active site pocket positions shifted at the structural level and we hypothesize that it may not perform at the optimal level. Thus, we were able to compare and contrast different Deinococcus species indicating some genes occurring because of divergent evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.28.474397" rel="alternate" title="Comparative analysis of Lysine and Arginine biosynthesis pathway in Deinococcus genomes (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474495</id><title>DENA: training an authentic neural network model using Nanopore sequencing data of Arabidopsis transcripts for detection and quantification of N6-methyladenosine on RNA (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-03T07:25:28.648975+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuan Li</name></author><author><name>Hang Qin</name></author><author><name>Liang Ou</name></author><author><name>Jian Gao</name></author><author><name>Longxian Chen</name></author><author><name>Pei Hao</name></author><author><name>Jiawei Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Models developed using Nanopore direct RNA sequencing data from in vitro synthetic RNA with all adenosine replaced by N6-methyladenosine (m6A), are likely distorted due to superimposed signals from saturated m6A residues. Here, we develop a neural network, DENA, for m6A quantification using the sequencing data of in vivo transcripts from Arabidopsis. DENA identifies 90% of miCLIP-detected m6A sites in Arabidopsis, and obtains modification rates in human consistent to those found by SCARLET, demonstrating its robustness across species. We sequence the transcriptome of two additional m6A-deficient Arabidopsis, mtb and fip37-4, using Nanopore and evaluate their single-nucleotide m6A profiles using DENA.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.29.474495" rel="alternate" title="DENA: training an authentic neural network model using Nanopore sequencing data of Arabidopsis transcripts for detection and quantification of N6-methyladenosine on RNA (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>