<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.354678+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475838</id><title>Lightweight compositional analysis of metagenomes with FracMinHash and minimum metagenome covers (93 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.354785+00:00</updated><author><name>Luiz Carlos Irber</name></author><author><name>Phillip T Brooks</name></author><author><name>Taylor E Reiter</name></author><author><name>N Tessa Pierce-Ward</name></author><author><name>Mahmudur Rahman Hera</name></author><author><name>David Koslicki</name></author><author><name>C. Titus Brown</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The identification of reference genomes and taxonomic labels from metagenome data underlies many microbiome studies. Here we describe two algorithms for compositional analysis of metagenome sequencing data. We first investigate the FracMinHash sketching technique, a derivative of modulo hash that supports Jaccard containment estimation between sets of different sizes. We implement FracMinHash in the sourmash software, evaluate its accuracy, and demonstrate large-scale containment searches of metagenomes using 700,000 microbial reference genomes. We next frame shotgun metagenome compositional analysis as the problem of finding a minimum collection of reference genomes that "cover" the known k-mers in a metagenome, a minimum set cover problem. We implement a greedy approximate solution using FracMinHash sketches, and evaluate its accuracy for taxonomic assignment using a CAMI community benchmark. Finally, we show that the minimum metagenome cover can be used to guide the selection of reference genomes for read mapping. sourmash is available as open source software under the BSD 3-Clause license at github.com/dib-lab/sourmash/.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475838" rel="alternate" title="Lightweight compositional analysis of metagenomes with FracMinHash and minimum metagenome covers (93 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475254</id><title>Identifying and correcting repeat-calling errors in nanopore sequencing of telomeres (76 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.354873+00:00</updated><author><name>Kar-Tong Tan</name></author><author><name>Michael K. Slevin</name></author><author><name>Matthew Meyerson</name></author><author><name>Heng Li</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nanopore long-read genome sequencing is emerging as a potential approach for the study of genomes including long repetitive elements like telomeres. Here, we report extensive basecalling induced errors at telomere repeats across nanopore datasets, sequencing platforms, basecallers, and basecalling models. We found that telomeres which are represented by (TTAGGG)&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; and (CCCTAA)&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; repeats in many organisms were frequently miscalled (~40-50% of reads) as (TTAAAA)&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;, or as (CTTCTT)&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; and (CCCTGG)&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; repeats respectively in a strand-specific manner during nanopore sequencing. We showed that this miscalling is likely caused by the high similarity of current profiles between telomeric repeats and these repeat artefacts, leading to mis-assignment of electrical current profiles during basecalling. We further demonstrated that tuning of nanopore basecalling models, and selective application of the tuned models to telomeric reads led to improved recovery and analysis of telomeric regions, with little detected negative impact on basecalling of other genomic regions. Our study thus highlights the importance of verifying nanopore basecalls in long, repetitive, and poorly defined regions of the genome, and showcases how such artefacts in regions like telomeres can potentially be resolved by improvements in nanopore basecalling models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475254" rel="alternate" title="Identifying and correcting repeat-calling errors in nanopore sequencing of telomeres (76 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475728</id><title>Predicting patient treatment response and resistance via single-cell transcriptomics of their tumors (73 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.354939+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanju Sinha</name></author><author><name>Rahulsimham Vegesna</name></author><author><name>Saugato Rahman Dhruba</name></author><author><name>Wei Wu</name></author><author><name>D. Lucas Kerr</name></author><author><name>Oleg V. Stroganov</name></author><author><name>Ivan Grishagin</name></author><author><name>Kenneth D. Aldape</name></author><author><name>Collin M. Blakely</name></author><author><name>Peng Jiang</name></author><author><name>Craig J. Thomas</name></author><author><name>Trever G. Bivona</name></author><author><name>Alejandro A. Schäffer</name></author><author><name>Eytan Ruppin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Tailoring the best treatments to cancer patients is an important open challenge. Here, we build a precision oncology data science and software framework for &lt;underline&gt;PER&lt;/underline&gt;sonalized single-&lt;underline&gt;C&lt;/underline&gt;ell &lt;underline&gt;E&lt;/underline&gt;xpression-based &lt;underline&gt;P&lt;/underline&gt;lanning for &lt;underline&gt;T&lt;/underline&gt;reatments &lt;underline&gt;In On&lt;/underline&gt;cology (PERCEPTION). Our approach capitalizes on recently published matched bulk and single-cell transcriptome profiles of large-scale cell-line drug screens to build treatment response models from patients’ single-cell (SC) tumor transcriptomics. First, we show that PERCEPTION successfully predicts the response to monotherapy and combination treatments in screens performed in cancer and patient-tumor-derived primary cells based on SC-expression profiles. Second, it successfully stratifies responders to combination therapy based on the patients’ tumor’s SC-expression in two very recent multiple myeloma and breast cancer clinical trials. Thirdly, it captures the development of clinical resistance to five standard tyrosine kinase inhibitors using tumor SC-expression profiles obtained during treatment in a lung cancer patients’ cohort. Notably, PERCEPTION outperforms state-of-the-art bulk expression-based predictors in all three clinical cohorts. In sum, this study provides a first-of-its-kind conceptual and computational method that is predictive of response to therapy in patients, based on the clonal SC gene expression of their tumors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475728" rel="alternate" title="Predicting patient treatment response and resistance via single-cell transcriptomics of their tumors (73 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476228</id><title>Critical assessment of pan-genomics of metagenome-assembled genomes (52 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355039+00:00</updated><author><name>Tang Li</name></author><author><name>Yanbin Yin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Large scale metagenome assembly and binning to generate metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs) has become possible in the past five years. As a result, millions of MAGs have been produced and increasingly included in pan-genomics workflow. However, pan-genome analyses of MAGs may suffer from the known issues with MAGs: fragmentation, incompleteness, and contamination, due to mis-assembly and mis-binning. Here, we conducted a critical assessment of including MAGs in pan-genome analysis, by comparing pan-genome analysis results of complete bacterial genomes and simulated MAGs. Results: We found that incompleteness led to more significant core gene loss than fragmentation. Contamination had little effect on core genome size but had major influence on accessory genomes. The core gene loss remained when using different pan-genome analysis tools and when using a mixture of MAGs and complete genomes. Importantly, the core gene loss was partially alleviated by lowering the core gene threshold and using gene prediction algorithms that consider fragmented genes, but to a less degree when incompleteness was higher than 5%. The core gene loss also led to incorrect pan-genome functional predictions and inaccurate phylogenetic trees. Conclusions: We conclude that lowering core gene threshold and predicting genes in metagenome mode (as Anvio does with Prodigal) are necessary in pan-genome analysis of MAGs to alleviate the accuracy loss. Better quality control of MAGs and development of new pan-genome analysis tools specifically designed for MAGs are needed in future studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476228" rel="alternate" title="Critical assessment of pan-genomics of metagenome-assembled genomes (52 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475735</id><title>GoPeaks: Histone Modification Peak Calling for CUT&amp;Tag (38 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355096+00:00</updated><author><name>William M Yashar</name></author><author><name>Garth Kong</name></author><author><name>Jake VanCampen</name></author><author><name>Brittany M Smith</name></author><author><name>Daniel J Coleman</name></author><author><name>Lucia Carbone</name></author><author><name>Galip Gürkan Yardimci</name></author><author><name>Julia E Maxson</name></author><author><name>Theodore P Braun</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide mapping of the histone modification landscape is critical to understanding tran-scriptional regulation. Cleavage Under Targets and Tagmentation (CUT&amp;amp;Tag) is a new method for profiling the localization of covalent histone modifications, offering improved sensitivity and decreased cost compared with Chromatin Immunoprecipitation Sequencing (ChIP-seq). Here, we present GoPeaks, a peak calling method specifically designed for histone modification CUT&amp;amp;Tag data. GoPeaks implements a Binomial distribution and stringent read count cut-off to nominate candidate genomic regions. We compared the performance of GoPeaks against commonly used peak calling algorithms to detect H3K4me3, H3K4me1, and H3K27Ac peaks from CUT&amp;amp;Tag data. These histone modifications display a range of peak profiles and are frequently used in epigenetic studies. We found GoPeaks robustly detects genome-wide histone modifications and, notably, identifies H3K27Ac with improved sensitivity compared to other standard peak calling algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475735" rel="alternate" title="GoPeaks: Histone Modification Peak Calling for CUT&amp;Tag (38 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475870</id><title>Debiasing FracMinHash and deriving confidence intervals for mutation rates across a wide range of evolutionary distances (37 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355177+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahmudur Rahman Hera</name></author><author><name>N. Tessa Pierce-Ward</name></author><author><name>David Koslicki</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sketching methods offer computational biologists scalable techniques to analyze data sets that continue to grow in size. MinHash is one such technique that has enjoyed recent broad application. However, traditional MinHash has previously been shown to perform poorly when applied to sets of very dissimilar sizes. &lt;italic&gt;FracMinHash&lt;/italic&gt; was recently introduced as a modification of MinHash to compensate for this lack of performance when set sizes differ. While experimental evidence has been encouraging, FracMinHash has not yet been analyzed from a theoretical perspective. In this paper, we perform such an analysis and prove that while FracMinHash is not unbiased, this bias is easily corrected. Next, we detail how a simple mutation model interacts with FracMinHash and are able to derive confidence intervals for evolutionary mutation distances between pairs of sequences as well as hypothesis tests for FracMinHash. We find that FracMinHash estimates the containment of a genome in a large metagenome more accurately and more precisely when compared to traditional MinHash, and the confidence interval performs significantly better in estimating mutation distances. A python-based implementation of the theorems we derive is freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/KoslickiLab/mutation-rate-ci-calculator"&gt;https://github.com/KoslickiLab/mutation-rate-ci-calculator&lt;/ext-link&gt;. The results presented in this paper can be reproduced using the code at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/KoslickiLab/ScaledMinHash-reproducibles"&gt;https://github.com/KoslickiLab/ScaledMinHash-reproducibles&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475870" rel="alternate" title="Debiasing FracMinHash and deriving confidence intervals for mutation rates across a wide range of evolutionary distances (37 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476279</id><title>Benchmarking software to predict antibiotic resistance phenotypes in shotgun metagenomes using simulated data (26 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355237+00:00</updated><author><name>Emily F Wissel</name></author><author><name>Brooke M Talbot</name></author><author><name>Bjorn A Johnson</name></author><author><name>Robert A Petit</name></author><author><name>Vicki Hertzberg</name></author><author><name>Anne Dunlop</name></author><author><name>Timothy D Read</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The use of shotgun metagenomics for AMR detection is appealing because data can be generated from clinical samples with minimal processing. Detecting antimicrobial resistance (AMR) in clinical genomic data is an important epidemiological task, yet a complex bioinformatic process. Many software tools exist to detect AMR genes, but they have mostly been tested in their detection of genotypic resistance in individual bacterial strains. It is important to understand how well these bioinformatic tools detect AMR genes in shotgun metagenomic data. We developed a software pipeline, hAMRoaster (https://github.com/ewissel/hAMRoaster), for assessing accuracy of prediction of antibiotic resistance phenotypes. For evaluation purposes, we simulated a short read (Illumina) shotgun metagenomics community of eight bacterial pathogens with extensive antibiotic susceptibility testing profiles. We benchmarked nine open source bioinformatics tools for detecting AMR genes that 1) were conda or Docker installable, 2) had been actively maintained, 3) had an open source license, and 4) took FASTA or FASTQ files as input. Several metrics were calculated for each tool including sensitivity, specificity, and F1 at three coverage levels. This study revealed that tools were highly variable in sensitivity (0.25 - 0.99) and specificity (0.2 - 1) in detection of resistance in our synthetic FASTQ files despite similar databases and methods implemented. Tools performed similarly at all coverage levels (5x, 50x, 100x). Cohen’s kappa revealed low agreement across tools.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476279" rel="alternate" title="Benchmarking software to predict antibiotic resistance phenotypes in shotgun metagenomes using simulated data (26 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476034</id><title>CCPLS reveals cell-type-specific spatial dependence of transcriptomes in single cells (26 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355312+00:00</updated><author><name>Takaho Tsuchiya</name></author><author><name>Hiroki Hori</name></author><author><name>Haruka Ozaki</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cell-cell communications regulate internal cellular states of the cell, e.g., gene expression and cell functions, and play pivotal roles in normal development and disease states. Furthermore, single-cell RNA sequencing methods have revealed cell-to-cell expression variability of highly variable genes (HVGs), which is also crucial. Nevertheless, the regulation on cell-to-cell expression variability of HVGs via cell-cell communications is still unexplored. The recent advent of spatial transcriptome measurement methods has linked gene expression profiles to the spatial context of single cells, which has provided opportunities to reveal those regulations. The existing computational methods extract genes with expression levels that are influenced by neighboring cell types based on the spatial transcriptome data. However, limitations remain in the quantitativeness and interpretability: it neither focuses on HVGs, considers cooperation of neighboring cell types, nor quantifies the degree of regulation with each neighboring cell type.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we propose CCPLS (Cell-Cell communications analysis by Partial Least Square regression modeling), which isa statistical framework for identifying cell-cell communications as the effects of multiple neighboring cell types on cell-to-cell expression variability of HVGs, based on the spatial transcriptome data. For each cell type, CCPLS performs PLS regression modeling and reports coefficients as the quantitative index of the cell-cell communications. Evaluation using simulated data showed our method accurately estimated the effects of multiple neighboring cell types on HVGs. Furthermore, by applying CCPLS to the two real datasets, we demonstrate CCPLS can be used to extract biologically interpretable insights from the inferred cell-cell communications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The R package is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/bioinfo-tsukuba/CCPLS"&gt;https://github.com/bioinfo-tsukuba/CCPLS&lt;/ext-link&gt;. The data are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/bioinfo-tsukuba/CCPLS_paper"&gt;https://github.com/bioinfo-tsukuba/CCPLS_paper&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;haruka.ozaki@md.tsukuba.ac.jp&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476034" rel="alternate" title="CCPLS reveals cell-type-specific spatial dependence of transcriptomes in single cells (26 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476226</id><title>The minimizer Jaccard estimator is biased and inconsistent (22 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355376+00:00</updated><author><name>Mahdi Belbasi</name></author><author><name>Antonio Blanca</name></author><author><name>Robert S. Harris</name></author><author><name>David Koslicki</name></author><author><name>Paul Medvedev</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sketching is now widely used in bioinformatics to reduce data size and increase data processing speed. Sketching approaches entice with improved scalability but also carry the danger of decreased accuracy and added bias. In this paper, we investigate the minimizer sketch and its use to estimate the Jaccard similarity between two sequences. We show that the minimizer Jaccard estimator is biased and inconsistent, which means that the expected difference (i.e., the bias) between the estimator and the true value is not zero, even in the limit as the lengths of the sequences grow. We derive an analytical formula for the bias as a function of how the shared k-mers are laid out along the sequences. We show both theoretically and empirically that there are families of sequences where the bias can be substantial (e.g. the true Jaccard can be more than double the estimate). Finally, we demonstrate that this bias affects the accuracy of the widely used mashmap read mapping tool.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476226" rel="alternate" title="The minimizer Jaccard estimator is biased and inconsistent (22 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475696</id><title>Using syncmers improves long-read mapping (15 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355442+00:00</updated><author><name>Abhinav Dutta</name></author><author><name>David Pellow</name></author><author><name>Ron Shamir</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;As sequencing datasets keep growing larger, time and memory efficiency of read mapping are becoming more critical. Many clever algorithms and data structures were used to develop mapping tools for next generation sequencing, and in the last few years also for third generation long reads. A key idea in mapping algorithms is to sketch sequences with their minimizers. Recently, syncmers were introduced as an alternative sketching method that is more robust to mutations and sequencing errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we introduce parameterized syncmer schemes, and provide a theoretical analysis for multi-parameter schemes. By combining these schemes with downsampling or minimizers we can achieve any desired compression and window guarantee. We introduced syncmer schemes into the popular minimap2 and Winnowmap2 mappers. In tests on simulated and real long read data from a variety of genomes, the syncmer-based algorithms reduced unmapped reads by 20-60% at high compression while using less memory. The advantage of syncmer-based mapping was even more pronounced at lower sequence identity. At sequence identity of 65-75% and medium compression, syncmer mappers had 50-60% fewer unmapped reads, and ∼ 10% fewer of the reads that did map were incorrectly mapped. We conclude that syncmer schemes improve mapping under higher error and mutation rates. This situation happens, for example, when the high error rate of long reads is compounded by a high mutation rate in a cancer tumor, or due to differences between strains of viruses or bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475696" rel="alternate" title="Using syncmers improves long-read mapping (15 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476312</id><title>Probabilistic modeling of ambient noise in single-cell omics data (14 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355501+00:00</updated><author><name>Caibin Sheng</name></author><author><name>Rui Lopes</name></author><author><name>Gang Li</name></author><author><name>Sven Schuierer</name></author><author><name>Annick Waldt</name></author><author><name>Rachel Cuttat</name></author><author><name>Slavica Dimitrieva</name></author><author><name>Audrey Kauffmann</name></author><author><name>Eric Durand</name></author><author><name>Giorgio G. Galli</name></author><author><name>Guglielmo Roma</name></author><author><name>Antoine de Weck</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Droplet-based single-cell omics, including single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNAseq), single cell CRISPR perturbations (e.g., CROP-seq) and single-cell protein and transcriptomic profiling (e.g., CITE-seq) hold great promise for comprehensive cell profiling and genetic screening at the single cell resolution, yet these technologies suffer from substantial noise, among which ambient signals present in the cell suspension may be the predominant source. Current efforts to address this issue are highly specific to a certain technology, while a universal model to describe the noise across these technologies may reveal this common source thereby improving the denoising accuracy. To this end, we explicitly examined these unexpected signals and observed a predictable pattern in multiple datasets across different technologies. Based on the finding, we developed single cell Ambient Remover (scAR) which uses probabilistic deep learning to deconvolute the observed signals into native and ambient composition. scAR provides an efficient and universal solution to count denoising for multiple types of single-cell omics data, including single cell CRISPR screens, CITE-seq and scRNAseq. It will facilitate the application of single-cell omics technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476312" rel="alternate" title="Probabilistic modeling of ambient noise in single-cell omics data (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476125</id><title>MS1Connect: a mass spectrometry run similarity measure (14 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355592+00:00</updated><author><name>Andy Lin</name></author><author><name>Brooke L. Deatherage Kaiser</name></author><author><name>Janine R. Hutchison</name></author><author><name>Jeffrey A. Bilmes</name></author><author><name>William Stafford Noble</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Interpretation of newly acquired mass spectrometry data can be improved by identifying, from an online repos- itory, previous mass spectrometry runs that resemble the new data. However, this retrieval task requires comput- ing the similarity between an arbitrary pair of mass spectrometry runs. This is particularly challenging for runs acquired using different experimental protocols. We propose a method, MS1Connect, that calculates the simi- larity between a pair of runs by examining only the intact peptide (MS1) scans, and we show evidence that the MS1Connect score is accurate. Specifically, we show that MS1Connect outperforms several baseline methods on the task of predicting the species from which a given proteomics sample originated. In addition, we show that MS1Connect scores are highly correlated with similarities computed from fragment (MS2) scans, even though this data is not used by MS1Connect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.12.476125" rel="alternate" title="MS1Connect: a mass spectrometry run similarity measure (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475836</id><title>ProtFinder: finding subcellular locations of proteins using protein interaction networks (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355658+00:00</updated><author><name>Aayush Grover</name></author><author><name>Laurent Gatto</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein subcellular localization prediction plays a crucial role in improving our understanding of different diseases and consequently assists in building drug targeting and drug development pipelines. Proteins are known to co-exist at multiple subcellular locations which make the task of prediction extremely challenging. A protein interaction network is a graph that captures interactions between different proteins. It is safe to assume that if two proteins are interacting, they must share some subcellular locations. With this regard, we propose ProtFinder – the first deep learning-based model that exclusively relies on protein interaction networks to predict the multiple subcellular locations of proteins. We also integrate biological priors like the cellular component of Gene Ontology to make ProtFinder a more biology-aware intelligent system. ProtFinder is trained and tested using the STRING and BioPlex databases whereas the annotations of proteins are obtained from the Human Protein Atlas. Our model obtained an AUC-ROC score of 90.00% and an MCC score of 83.42% on a held-out set of proteins. We also apply ProtFinder to annotate proteins that currently do not have confident location annotations. We observe that ProtFinder is able to confirm some of these unreliable location annotations, while in some cases complementing the existing databases with novel location annotations. The source code for ProtFinder is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/UCLouvain-CBIO/ProtFinder"&gt;https://github.com/UCLouvain-CBIO/ProtFinder&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475836" rel="alternate" title="ProtFinder: finding subcellular locations of proteins using protein interaction networks (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475864</id><title>Inferring tumor-specific cancer dependencies through integrating ex-vivo drug response assays and drug-protein profiling (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355713+00:00</updated><author><name>Alina Batzilla</name></author><author><name>Junyan Lu</name></author><author><name>Jarno Kivioja</name></author><author><name>Kerstin Putzker</name></author><author><name>Joe Lewis</name></author><author><name>Thorsten Zenz</name></author><author><name>Wolfgang Huber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The development of cancer therapies may be improved by the discovery of tumor-specific molecular dependencies. The requisite tools include genetic and chemical perturbations, each with its strengths and limitations. Drug perturbations can be readily applied to primary cancer samples at a large scale, but mechanistic understanding of hits and further pharmaceutical development is often complicated by the fact that a small compound has a range of affinities to multiple proteins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To computationally infer the molecular dependencies of individual cancers from their ex-vivo drug sensitivity profiles, we developed a mathematical model that deconvolutes these data using measurements of protein-drug affinity profiles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our method, DepInfeR, correctly identified known dependencies, including EGFR dependence in Her2+ breast cancer cell line, FLT3 dependence in AML tumors with FLT3-ITD mutations and the differential dependencies on the B-cell receptor pathway in two major subtypes of chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL). Furthermore, our method uncovered new subgroup-specific dependencies, including a previously unreported dependence of high-risk CLL on Checkpoint kinase 1 (CHEK1). The method also produced a more accurate map of the molecular dependencies in a heterogeneous set of 117 CLL samples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability to deconvolute polypharmacological phenotypes into underlying causal molecular dependencies should increase the utility of high-throughput drug response assays for functional precision oncology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475864" rel="alternate" title="Inferring tumor-specific cancer dependencies through integrating ex-vivo drug response assays and drug-protein profiling (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.08.475501</id><title>OptiDiff: structural variation detection from single optical mapping reads (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355785+00:00</updated><author><name>Mehmet Akdel</name></author><author><name>Dick de Ridder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Detecting structural variation (SV) in eukaryotic genomes is of broad interest due to its often dramatic phenotypic effects, but remains a major, costly challenge based on DNA sequencing data. A cost-effective alternative in detecting large-scale SV has become available with advances in optical mapping technology. However, the algorithmic approaches to identifying SVs from optical mapping data are limited. Here, we propose a novel, open-source SV detection tool, OptiDiff, which employs a single molecule based approach to detect and classify homozygous and heterozygous SVs at coverages as low as 20x, showing better performance than the state of the art.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.08.475501" rel="alternate" title="OptiDiff: structural variation detection from single optical mapping reads (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476345</id><title>Griottes: a generalist tool for network generation from segmented tissue images (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355839+00:00</updated><author><name>Gustave Ronteix</name></author><author><name>Valentin Bonnet</name></author><author><name>Sebastien Sart</name></author><author><name>Jeremie Sobel</name></author><author><name>Elric Esposito</name></author><author><name>Charles N. Baroud</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Microscopy techniques and image segmentation algorithms have improved dramatically this decade, leading to an ever increasing amount of biological images and a greater reliance on imaging to investigate biological questions. This has created a need for methods to extract the relevant information on the behaviors of cells and their interactions, while reducing the amount of computing power required to organize this information. This task can be performed by using a network representation in which the cells and their properties are encoded in the nodes, while the neighborhood interactions are encoded by the links. Here we introduce &lt;monospace&gt;Griottes&lt;/monospace&gt;, an open-source tool to build the “network twin” of 2D and 3D tissues from segmented microscopy images. We show how the library can provide a wide range of biologically relevant metrics on individual cells and their neighborhoods, with the objective of providing multi-scale biological insights. The library’s capacities are demonstrated on different image and data types. This library is provided as an open-source tool that can be integrated into common image analysis workflows to increase their capacities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476345" rel="alternate" title="Griottes: a generalist tool for network generation from segmented tissue images (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476163</id><title>Multi-omic data helps improve prediction of personalised tumor suppressors and oncogenes (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355907+00:00</updated><author><name>Malvika Sudhakar</name></author><author><name>Raghunathan Rengaswamy</name></author><author><name>Karthik Raman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The progression of tumorigenesis starts with a few mutational and structural driver events in the cell. Various cohort-based computational tools exist to identify driver genes but require a large number of samples to produce reliable results. Many studies use different methods to identify driver mutations/genes from mutations that have no impact on tumour progression; however, a small fraction of patients show no mutational events in any known driver genes.  Current unsupervised methods map somatic and expression data onto a network to identify the perturbation in the network. Our method is the first machine learning model to classify genes as tumour suppressor gene (TSG), oncogene (OG) or neutral, thus assigning the functional impact of the gene in the patient. In this study, we develop a multi-omic approach, PIVOT (Personalised Identification of driVer OGs and TSGs), to train on experimentally or computationally validated mutational and structural driver events. Given the lack of any gold standards for the identification of personalised driver genes, we label the data using four strategies and, based on classification metrics, show gene-based labelling strategies perform best. We build different models using SNV, RNA, and multi-omic features to be used based on the data available. Our models trained on multi-omic data improved predictions compared to mutation and expression data, achieving an accuracy &amp;gt;0.99  for BRCA, LUAD and COAD datasets. We show network and expression-based features contribute the most to PIVOT. Our predictions on BRCA, COAD and LUAD cancer types reveal commonly altered genes such as TP53, and PIK3CA, which are predicted drivers for multiple cancer types. Along with known driver genes, our models also identify new driver genes such as PRKCA, SOX9 and PSMD4. Our multi-omic model labels both CNV and mutations with a more considerable contribution by CNV alterations. While predicting labels for genes mutated in multiple samples, we also label rare driver events occurring in as few as one sample. We also identify genes with dual roles within the same cancer type. Overall, PIVOT labels personalised driver genes as TSGs and OGs and also identifies rare driver genes. PIVOT is available at https://github.com/RamanLab/PIVOT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476163" rel="alternate" title="Multi-omic data helps improve prediction of personalised tumor suppressors and oncogenes (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476325</id><title>DeepGOZero: Improving protein function prediction from sequence and zero-shot learning based on ontology axioms (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.355967+00:00</updated><author><name>Maxat Kulmanov</name></author><author><name>Robert Hoehndorf</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Motivation: Protein functions are often described using the Gene Ontology (GO) which is an ontology consisting of over 50,000 classes and a large set of formal axioms. Predicting the functions of proteins is one of the key challenges in computational biology and a variety of machine learning methods have been developed for this purpose. However, these methods usually require significant amount of training data and cannot make predictions for GO classes which have only few or no experimental annotations. 
Results: We developed DeepGOZero, a machine learning model which improves predictions for functions with no or only a small number of annotations. To achieve this goal, we rely on a model-theoretic approach for learning ontology embeddings and combine it with neural networks for protein function prediction. DeepGOZero can exploit formal axioms in the GO to make zero-shot predictions, i.e., predict protein functions even if not a single protein in the training phase was associated with that function. Furthermore, the zero-shot prediction method employed by DeepGOZero is generic and can be applied whenever associations with ontology classes need to be predicted.
Availability: http://github.com/bio-ontology-research-group/deepgozero&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476325" rel="alternate" title="DeepGOZero: Improving protein function prediction from sequence and zero-shot learning based on ontology axioms (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475810</id><title>EagleImp: Fast and Accurate Genome-wide Phasing and Imputation in a Single Tool (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356023+00:00</updated><author><name>Lars Wienbrandt</name></author><author><name>David Ellinghaus</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reference-based phasing and genotype imputation algorithms have been developed with sublinear theoretical runtime behaviour, but runtimes are still high in practice when large genome-wide reference datasets are used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed &lt;italic&gt;EagleImp&lt;/italic&gt;, a software with algorithmic and technical improvements and new features for accurate and accelerated phasing and imputation in a single tool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We compared accuracy and runtime of &lt;italic&gt;EagleImp&lt;/italic&gt; with &lt;italic&gt;Eagle2, PBWT&lt;/italic&gt; and prominent imputation servers using whole-genome sequencing data from the 1000 Genomes Project, the Haplotype Reference Consortium and simulated data with more than 1 million reference genomes. &lt;italic&gt;EagleImp&lt;/italic&gt; is 2 to 10 times faster (depending on the single or multiprocessor configuration selected) than &lt;italic&gt;Eagle2/PBWT&lt;/italic&gt;, with the same or better phasing and imputation quality in all tested scenarios. For common variants investigated in typical GWAS studies, &lt;italic&gt;EagleImp&lt;/italic&gt; provides same or higher imputation accuracy than the &lt;italic&gt;Sanger Imputation Service, Michigan Imputation Server&lt;/italic&gt; and the newly developed &lt;italic&gt;TOPMed Imputation Server&lt;/italic&gt;, despite larger (not publicly available) reference panels. It has many new features, including automated chromosome splitting and memory management at runtime to avoid job aborts, fast reading and writing of large files, and various user-configurable algorithm and output options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the technical optimisations, &lt;italic&gt;EagleImp&lt;/italic&gt; can perform fast and accurate reference-based phasing and imputation for future very large reference panels with more than 1 million genomes. &lt;italic&gt;EagleImp&lt;/italic&gt; is freely available for download from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ikmb/eagleimp"&gt;https://github.com/ikmb/eagleimp&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475810" rel="alternate" title="EagleImp: Fast and Accurate Genome-wide Phasing and Imputation in a Single Tool (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476390</id><title>Integrative analysis of relative abundance data and presence-absence data of the microbiome using the LDM (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356079+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhengyi Zhu</name></author><author><name>Glen A. Satten</name></author><author><name>Yi-Juan Hu</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We previously developed LDM for testing hypotheses about the microbiome that performs the test at both the community level and the individual taxon level. LDM can be applied to relative abundance data and presence-absence data separately, which work well when associated taxa are abundant and rare, respectively. Here we propose an omnibus test based on LDM that allows simultaneous consideration of data at different scales, thus offering optimal power across scenarios with different association mechanisms. The omnibus test is available for the wide range of data types and analyses that are supported by LDM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and Implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The omnibus test has been added to the R package LDM, which is available on GitHub at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/yijuanhu/LDM"&gt;https://github.com/yijuanhu/LDM&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;yijuan.hu@emory.edu&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476390" rel="alternate" title="Integrative analysis of relative abundance data and presence-absence data of the microbiome using the LDM (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476214</id><title>The assembled Banana dihaploid mitochondrial genome is compact with a high number of gene copies (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356138+00:00</updated><author><name>Shruthy Priya Prakash</name></author><author><name>Vaidheki Chandrasekar</name></author><author><name>Selvi Subramanian</name></author><author><name>Rahamatthunnisha Ummar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Banana being a major food crop all around the world, attracts various research interests in crop improvement. In banana, complete genome sequences of &lt;italic&gt;Musa accuminata&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Musa balbisiana&lt;/italic&gt; are available. However, the mitochondrial genome is not sequenced or assembled. Mitochondrial (mt) genes play an important role in flower and seed development and in Cytoplasmic Male Sterility. Unraveling banana mt genome architecture will be a foundation for understanding inheritance of traits and their evolution. In this study, the complete banana mt genome is assembled from the whole genome sequence data of the &lt;italic&gt;Musa acuminata subsp. malaccensis&lt;/italic&gt; DH-Pahang. The mt genome sequence acquired by this approach was 409574 bp and it contains, 54 genes coding for 25 respiratory complex proteins 15 ribosomal proteins, 12 tRNA genes and two ribosomal RNA gene. Except atpB, rps11 and rps19 other genes are in multiple copies. The copy number is 12 in tRNA genes. In addition, nearly 25% tandem repeats are also present in it. These mt proteins are identical to the mt proteins present in the other members of AA genome and share 98% sequence similarity with &lt;italic&gt;M. balbisiana.&lt;/italic&gt; The C to U RNA editing is profoundly higher (87 vs 13%) in transcripts of &lt;italic&gt;M. balbisiana&lt;/italic&gt; (BB) compared to &lt;italic&gt;M. accuminata&lt;/italic&gt; (AA). The banana AA mitochondrial genome is tightly packed with 233 genes, with less rearrangements and just 5.3% chloroplast DNA in it. The maintenance of high copy number of functional mt genes suggest that they have a crucial role in the evolution of banana.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.13.476214" rel="alternate" title="The assembled Banana dihaploid mitochondrial genome is compact with a high number of gene copies (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475759</id><title>Multi-cancer classification; an analysis of neural network complexity (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356203+00:00</updated><author><name>James W. Webber</name></author><author><name>Kevin Elias</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cancer identification is generally framed as binary classification, normally discrimination of a control group from a single cancer group. However, such models lack any cancer-specific information, as they are only trained on one cancer type. The models fail to account for competing cancer risks. For example, an ostensibly healthy individual may have any number of different cancer types, and a tumor may originate from one of several primary sites. Pan-cancer evaluation requires a model trained on multiple cancer types, and controls, simultaneously, so that a physician can be directed to the correct area of the body for further testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Methods&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce novel neural network models to address multi-cancer classification problems across several data types commonly applied in cancer prediction, including circulating miRNA expression, protein, and mRNA. In particular, we present an analysis of neural network depth and complexity, and investigate how this relates to classification performance. Comparisons of our models with state-of-the-art neural networks from the literature are also presented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our analysis evidences that shallow, feed-forward neural net architectures offer greater performance when compared to more complex deep feed-forward, Convolutional Neural Network (CNN), and Graph CNN (GCNN) architectures considered in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusion&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results show that multiple cancers and controls can be classified accurately using the proposed models, across a range of expression technologies in cancer prediction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Impact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study addresses the important problem of pan-cancer classification, which is often overlooked in the literature. The promising results highlight the urgency for further research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475759" rel="alternate" title="Multi-cancer classification; an analysis of neural network complexity (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476464</id><title>MeShClust v3.0: High-quality clustering of DNA sequences using the mean shift algorithm and alignment-free identity scores (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356258+00:00</updated><author><name>Hani Z Girgis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: Tools for accurately clustering biological sequences are among the most important tools in computational biology. Two pioneering tools for clustering sequences are CD-HIT and UCLUST, both of which are fast and consume reasonable amounts of memory; however, there is a big room for improvement in terms of cluster quality. Motivated by this opportunity for improving cluster quality, we applied the mean shift algorithm in MeShClust v1.0. The mean shift algorithm is an instance of unsupervised learning. Its strong theoretical foundation guarantees the convergence to the true cluster centers. Our implementation of the mean shift algorithm in MeShClust v1.0 was a step forward; however, it was not the original algorithm. In this work, we make progress toward applying the original algorithm while utilizing alignment-free identity scores in a new tool: MeShClust v3.0. Results: We evaluated CD-HIT, MeShClust v1.0, MeShClust v3.0, and UCLUST on 22 synthetic sets and five real sets. These data sets were designed or selected for testing the tools in terms of scalability and different similarity levels among sequences comprising clusters. On the synthetic data sets, MeShClust v3.0 outperformed the related tools on all sets in terms of cluster quality. On two real data sets obtained from human microbiome and maize transposons, MeShClust v3.0 outperformed the related tools by wide margins, achieving 55%-300% improvement in cluster quality. On another set that includes degenerate viral sequences, MeShClust v3.0 came third. On two bacterial sets, MeShClust v3.0 was the only applicable tool because of the long sequences in these sets. MeShClust v3.0 requires more time and memory than the related tools; almost all personal computers at the time of this writing can accommodate such requirements. MeShClust v3.0 can estimate an important parameter that controls cluster membership with high accuracy. Conclusions: These results demonstrate the high quality of clusters produced by MeShClust v3.0 and its ability to apply the mean shift algorithm to large data sets and long sequences. Because clustering tools are utilized in many studies, providing high-quality clusters will help with deriving accurate biological knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.15.476464" rel="alternate" title="MeShClust v3.0: High-quality clustering of DNA sequences using the mean shift algorithm and alignment-free identity scores (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475465</id><title>Drug Contraindications in Comorbid Diseases: a Protein Interactome Perspective (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356350+00:00</updated><author><name>Kalyani B Karunakaran</name></author><author><name>Madhavi Ganapathiraju</name></author><author><name>Sanjeev Jain</name></author><author><name>Samir Brahmachari</name></author><author><name>Narayanaswamy Balakrishnan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Adverse drug reactions (ADRs) are leading causes of death and drug withdrawals and frequently co-occur with comorbidities. However, systematic studies on the effects of drugs in comorbidities are lacking. Drug interactions with the cellular protein-protein interaction (PPI) network give rise to ADRs. We selected 6 comorbid disease pairs, identified the drugs used in the treatment of the individual diseases A and B — 44 drugs in anxiety and depression, 128 in asthma and hypertension, 48 in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and heart failure, 58 in type 2 diabetes and obesity, 58 in Parkinson′s disease and schizophrenia, and 84 in rheumatoid arthritis and osteoporosis — and categorized them based on whether they aggravate the comorbid condition. We constructed drug target networks (DTNs) and examined their enrichment among genes in disease A/B PPI networks, expressed across 53 tissues and involved in ≈1000 pathways. To pinpoint the biological features characterizing the DTNs, we performed principal component analysis and computed the Euclidean distance between DTN component scores and feature loading values. DTNs of disease A drugs not contraindicated in B were affiliated with proteins common to A/B networks or uniquely found in the B network, similarly regulated common pathways, and disease-B specific pathways and tissues. DTNs of disease A drugs contraindicated in B were affiliated with common proteins or those uniquely found in the A network, differentially regulated common pathways, and disease A-specific pathways and tissues. Hence, DTN enrichment in pathways, tissues, and PPI networks of comorbid diseases will help identify drugs contraindications in comorbidities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475465" rel="alternate" title="Drug Contraindications in Comorbid Diseases: a Protein Interactome Perspective (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476308</id><title>MIA: An Open Source Standalone Deep Learning Application for Microscopic Image Analysis (5 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356420+00:00</updated><author><name>Nils Körber</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In recent years the amount of data generated by imaging techniques has grown rapidly along with increasing computational power and the development of deep learning algorithms. To address the need for powerful automated image analysis tools for a broad range of applications in the biomedical sciences, we present the Microscopic Image Analyzer (MIA). MIA combines a graphical user interface that obviates the need for programming skills with state-of-the-art deep learning algorithms for segmentation, object detection, and classification. It runs as a standalone, platform-independent application and is compatible with commonly used open source software packages. The software provides a unified interface for easy image labeling, model training and inference. Furthermore the software was evaluated in a public competition and performed among the top three for all tested data sets. The source code is available on &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/MIAnalyzer/MIA"&gt;https://github.com/MIAnalyzer/MIA&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.14.476308" rel="alternate" title="MIA: An Open Source Standalone Deep Learning Application for Microscopic Image Analysis (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475831</id><title>De novo protein structure prediction by incremental inter-residue geometries prediction and model quality assessment using deep learning (4 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-18T07:25:50.356473+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Liu</name></author><author><name>Guang-Xing He</name></author><author><name>Kai-Long Zhao</name></author><author><name>Gui-Jun Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The successful application of deep learning has promoted progress in protein model quality assessment. How to use model quality assessment to further improve the accuracy of protein structure prediction, especially not reliant on the existing templates, is helpful for unraveling the folding mechanism. Here, we investigate whether model quality assessment can be introduced into structure prediction to form a closed-loop feedback, and iteratively improve the accuracy of de novo protein structure prediction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this study, we propose a de novo protein structure prediction method called RocketX. In RocketX, a feedback mechanism is constructed through the geometric constraint prediction network GeomNet, the structural simulation module, and the model quality evaluation network EmaNet. In GeomNet, the co-evolutionary features extracted from MSA that search from the sequence databases are sent to an improved residual neural network to predict the inter-residue geometric constraints. The structure model is folded based on the predicted geometric constraints. In EmaNet, the 1D and 2D features are extracted from the folded model and sent to the deep residual neural network to estimate the inter-residue distance deviation and per-residue lDDT of the model, which will be fed back to GeomNet as dynamic features to correct the geometries prediction and progressively improve model accuracy. RocketX is tested on 483 benchmark proteins and 20 FM targets of CASP14. Experimental results show that the closed-loop feedback mechanism significantly contributes to the performance of RocketX, and the prediction accuracy of RocketX outperforms that of the state-of-the-art methods trRosetta (without templates) and RaptorX. In addition, the blind test results on CAMEO show that although no template is used, the prediction accuracy of RocketX on medium and hard targets is comparable to the advanced methods that integrate templates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RocketX web server are freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zhanglab-bioinf.com/RocketX"&gt;http://zhanglab-bioinf.com/RocketX&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;zgj@zjut.edu.cn&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.11.475831" rel="alternate" title="De novo protein structure prediction by incremental inter-residue geometries prediction and model quality assessment using deep learning (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>