<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.366009+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453379</id><title>AlphaPept, a modern and open framework for MS-based proteomics (57 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.366396+00:00</updated><author><name>Maximilian T. Strauss</name></author><author><name>Isabell Bludau</name></author><author><name>Wen-Feng Zeng</name></author><author><name>Eugenia Voytik</name></author><author><name>Constantin Ammar</name></author><author><name>Julia Schessner</name></author><author><name>Rajesh Ilango</name></author><author><name>Michelle Gill</name></author><author><name>Florian Meier</name></author><author><name>Sander Willems</name></author><author><name>Matthias Mann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In common with other omics technologies, mass spectrometry (MS)-based proteomics produces ever-increasing amounts of raw data, making their efficient analysis a principal challenge. There is a plethora of different computational tools that process the raw MS data and derive peptide and protein identification and quantification. During the last decade, there has been dramatic progress in computer science and software engineering, including collaboration tools that have transformed research and industry. To leverage these advances, we developed AlphaPept, a Python-based open-source framework for efficient processing of large high-resolution MS data sets. Using Numba for just-in-time machine code compilation on CPU and GPU, we achieve hundred-fold speed improvements while maintaining clear syntax and rapid development speed. AlphaPept uses the Python scientific stack of highly optimized packages, reducing the code base to domain-specific tasks while providing access to the latest advances in machine learning. We provide an easy on-ramp for community validation and contributions through the concept of literate programming, implemented in Jupyter Notebooks of the different modules. A framework for continuous integration, testing, and benchmarking enforces solid software engineering principles. Large datasets can rapidly be processed as shown by the analysis of hundreds of cellular proteomes in minutes per file, many-fold faster than the data acquisiton. The AlphaPept framework can be used to build automated processing pipelines using efficient HDF5 based file formats, web-serving functionality and compatibility with downstream analysis tools. Easy access for end-users is provided by one-click installation of the graphical user interface, for advanced users via a modular Python library, and for developers via a fully open GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453379" rel="alternate" title="AlphaPept, a modern and open framework for MS-based proteomics (57 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453747</id><title>ABlooper: Fast accurate antibody CDR loop structure prediction with accuracy estimation (23 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.366768+00:00</updated><author><name>Brennan Abanades</name></author><author><name>Guy Georges</name></author><author><name>Alexander Bujotzek</name></author><author><name>Charlotte M. Deane</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Antibodies are a key component of the immune system and have been extensively used as biotherapeutics. Accurate knowledge of their structure is central to understanding their function. The key area for antigen binding and the main area of structural variation in antibodies are concentrated in their six complementarity determining regions (CDRs), with the most variable being the CDR-H3 loop. The sequence and structure variability of CDR-H3 make it particularly challenging to model. Recently, deep learning methods have offered a step change in our ability to predict protein structures. In this work we present ABlooper, an end-to-end equivariant deep-learning based CDR loop structure prediction tool. ABlooper predicts the structure of CDR loops with high accuracy and provides a confidence estimate for each of its predictions. On the models of the Rosetta Antibody Benchmark, ABlooper makes predictions with an average H3 RMSD of 2.45Å, which drops to 2.02Å when considering only its 76% most confident predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453747" rel="alternate" title="ABlooper: Fast accurate antibody CDR loop structure prediction with accuracy estimation (23 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453671</id><title>MetaBinner: a high-performance and stand-alone ensemble binning method to recover individual genomes from complex microbial communities (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.367169+00:00</updated><author><name>Ziye Wang</name></author><author><name>Pingqin Huang</name></author><author><name>Ronghui You</name></author><author><name>Fengzhu Sun</name></author><author><name>Shanfeng Zhu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Binning is an essential procedure during metagenomic data analysis. However, the available individual binning methods usually do not simultaneously fully use different features or biological information. Furthermore, it is challenging to integrate multiple binning results efficiently and effectively. Therefore, we developed an ensemble binner, MetaBinner, which generates component results with multiple types of features and utilizes single-copy gene (SCG) information for k-means initialization. It then utilizes a two-step ensemble strategy based on SCGs to integrate the component results. Extensive experimental results over three large-scale simulated datasets and one real-world dataset demonstrate that MetaBinner outperforms other state-of-the-art individual binners and ensemble binners. MetaBinner is freely available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ziyewang/MetaBinner"&gt;https://github.com/ziyewang/MetaBinner&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453671" rel="alternate" title="MetaBinner: a high-performance and stand-alone ensemble binning method to recover individual genomes from complex microbial communities (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453649</id><title>Important Docking study of Structure of Plasmodium falciparum thioredoxin reductase-thioredoxin complex: the case of potent drug Telatinib, a small molecule angiogenesis inhibitor (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.367576+00:00</updated><author><name>Ivan Vito Ferrari</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last decades, malaria parasites have been rapidly developing resistance against antimalarial drugs, which underlines the need for novel drug targets. Thioredoxin reductase (TrxR) is crucially involved in redox homeostasis and essential for Plasmodium falciparum. In this communication, we report first time important Docking study by in Silico approach, using AutoDock Vina. After a selective analysis of over 300 drugs, processed with Pyrx (a Virtual Screening software into the active site of protein (ID PDB 4J56 Thioredoxin reductase 2 Chain A), we noticed excellent value of Binding Energy of Telatinib estimated by Pyrx software. These results are comparable to the crystallized ligand FAD (FLAVIN-ADENINE DINUCLEOTIDE) completed in the above-mentioned protein. Indeed, from the results of Autodock Vina, Telatinib an inhibitor of tyrosine kinases, has excellent a Binding affinity value, ca. −12 kcal/mol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453649" rel="alternate" title="Important Docking study of Structure of Plasmodium falciparum thioredoxin reductase-thioredoxin complex: the case of potent drug Telatinib, a small molecule angiogenesis inhibitor (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453736</id><title>Towards an integrative multi-omics workflow (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.367817+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Jeanneret</name></author><author><name>Stéphane Gazut</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The advent of high-throughput techniques has greatly enhanced biological discovery. Last years, analysis of multi-omics data has taken the front seat to improve physiological understanding. Handling functional enrichment results from various biological data raises practical questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose an integrative workflow to better interpret biological process insights in a multi-omics approach applied to breast cancer data from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) related to Invasive Ductal Carcinoma (IDC) and Invasive Lobular Carcinoma (ILC). Pathway enrichment by Over Representation Analysis (ORA) and Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) has been conducted with both features information from differential expression analysis or selected features from multi-block sPLS-DA methods. Then, comprehensive comparisons of enrichment results have been carried out by looking at classical enrichment analysis, probabilities pooling by Stouffer’s Z scores method and pathways clustering in biological themes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our work shows that ORA enrichment with selected sPLS-DA features and pathways probabilities pooling by Stouffer’s method lead to enrichment maps highly associated to physiological knowledge of IDC or ILC phenotypes, better than ORA and GSEA with differential expression driven features.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453736" rel="alternate" title="Towards an integrative multi-omics workflow (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453290</id><title>PCRMS: a database of predicted cis-regulatory modules and constituent transcription factor binding sites in genomes (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.368052+00:00</updated><author><name>Pengyu Ni</name></author><author><name>Zhengchang Su</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;More accurate and more complete predictions of &lt;italic&gt;cis&lt;/italic&gt;-regulatory modules (CRMs) and constituent transcriptional factor (TF) binding sites (TFBSs) in genomes can facilitate characterizing functions of regulatory sequences. Here, we developed a database PCRMS (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cci-bioinfo.uncc.edu"&gt;https://cci-bioinfo.uncc.edu&lt;/ext-link&gt;) that stores highly accurate and unprecedentedly complete maps of predicted CRMs and TFBSs in the human and mouse genomes. The web interface allows the user to browse CRMs and TFBSs in an organism, find the closest CRMs to a gene, search CRMs around a gene, and find all TFBSs of a TF. PCRMS can be a useful resource for the research community to characterize regulatory genomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453290" rel="alternate" title="PCRMS: a database of predicted cis-regulatory modules and constituent transcription factor binding sites in genomes (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.454001</id><title>Endorsement and Phylogenetic Analysis of some Fabaceae Plants based on DNA Barcoding gene MatK (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.368285+00:00</updated><author><name>Nader R. Abdelsalam</name></author><author><name>Mohamed E. Hasan</name></author><author><name>Samar M.A. Rabie</name></author><author><name>Houssam El-Din M.F. El-wakeel</name></author><author><name>Amera F. Zaitoun</name></author><author><name>Rehab Y. Ghareeb</name></author><author><name>Aly Z. Abdelsalam</name></author><author><name>Hesham M. Aly</name></author><author><name>Amira A. Ibrahim</name></author><author><name>Alaa A. Hemeida</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;DNA barcodes have been considered as a tool to facilitate species identification based on their simplicity and high-level accuracy compression to the complexity and subjective biases linked to morphological identification of taxa. MaturaseK gene “  MatK”  of the chloroplast is very crucial in the plant system which is involved in the group II intron splicing. The main objective of this current study is determining the relative utility of the “  MatK”  chloroplast gene for barcoding in fifteen legume trees by both single region and multiregional approaches. The chloroplast “  MatK”  gene sequences were submitted to GenBank and accession numbers (GenBank: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC602060"&gt;LC602060&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC602154"&gt;LC602154&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC602263"&gt;LC602263&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603347"&gt;LC603347&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603655"&gt;LC603655&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603845"&gt;LC603845&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603846"&gt;LC603846&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC603847"&gt;LC603847&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC604717"&gt;LC604717&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC604718"&gt;LC604718&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC605994"&gt;LC605994&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC604799"&gt;LC604799&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC605995"&gt;LC605995&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC606468"&gt;LC606468&lt;/ext-link&gt;, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="LC606469"&gt;LC606469&lt;/ext-link&gt;) were obtained with sequence length ranging from 730 to 1545 nucleotides. These DNA sequences were aligned with database sequence using PROMALS server  ,  Clustal Omega server and Bioedit program. Also,  the maximum likelihood and neighbor-joining algorithms for phylogenetic reconstruction using the MEGA-X program were employed. Overall, these results indicated that  the phylogenetic tree  analysis and the evolutionary distances of an individual dataset of each species were agreed with a phylogenetic tree of all each other consisting of two clades, the first clade comprising  (Enterolobium contortisiliquum, Albizia lebbek), Acacia saligna  ,  Leucaena leucocephala,  Dichrostachys Cinerea, (Delonix regia, Parkinsonia aculeata), (Senna surattensis, Cassia fistula, Cassia javanica)  and  Schotia brachypetala  were more closely to each other, respectively. The remaining four species of  Erythrina humeana, (Sophora secundiflora, Dalbergia Sissoo, Tipuana Tipu)  constituted the second clade. Therefore,  MatK  gene is considered promising a candidate for DNA barcoding in plant family Fabaceae and providing a clear relationship between the families. Moreover, their sequences could be successfully utilized in single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) or part of the sequence as DNA fragment analysis utilizing polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in plant systematic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.454001" rel="alternate" title="Endorsement and Phylogenetic Analysis of some Fabaceae Plants based on DNA Barcoding gene MatK (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453693</id><title>Hoslundia opposita and other Nigerian plants inhibit sickle hemoglobin polymerization and prevent erythrocyte sickling: a virtual screening-guided identification of bioactive plants. (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.368623+00:00</updated><author><name>Eric O. Olori</name></author><author><name>Olujide Oludayo Olubiyi</name></author><author><name>Chinedum Peace Babalola</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In sickle cell disease, a hereditary hemoglobinopathy, clinically observed disease presentations are the endpoint of a point mutation involving the substitution of glutamic acid with valine at the position 6 of the beta globin chain. With about 4.4 million people globally being affected, and another 43 million people bearing the sickle cell trait, several research efforts have been made to discover new and affordable treatment and possibly cure for the disease. Africa is endowed with a large flora population and traditional healers and citizens have over time depended on the use of herbs in folkloric medicine for different ailments including sickle cell disease (SCD). Such native knowledge has often formed the basis for different research exploration into the anti-sickling activities of selected African plants. These plants that have been so far investigated for their anti-sickling properties represent about 0.05 % of the 45,000 plant species enriching the flora landscape in Sub-Saharan Africa. Some of these have yielded potent anti-sickling profiles. In the current work we seek to achieve a more extensive search of the African plant diversity with anti-sickling properties: for this we have adopted a hybrid computational-cum-experimental protocol that employed computer-aided drug design (CADD) means for identifying plants with at least one constituent capable of interacting with the sickle hemoglobin, followed by extractive procedures and anti-sickling experiments for validating the predictions. Over two thousand (or 2,000) African natural products, representing over 200 plant species, were first virtually screened against the crystal structure of the dimerized human sickle hemoglobin. The natural products with the best computed sickle hemoglobin interaction energetics were found to belong to five plant species including Catharanthus roseus, Rauvolfia vomitoria, Hoslundia opposita, Lantana camara and Euphorbia hirta. The leaves of these plants were each collected subsequently and subjected to standard processing and extraction procedures. Using both HbSS polymerization inhibition and sickling reversal tests significant reductions in polymerization of erythrocyte hemolysate of the HbSS genotype were observed with the methanolic extracts of the plants, as well as sickling reversal levels of up to 68.50 % (H. opposita) was observed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453693" rel="alternate" title="Hoslundia opposita and other Nigerian plants inhibit sickle hemoglobin polymerization and prevent erythrocyte sickling: a virtual screening-guided identification of bioactive plants. (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453915</id><title>HyperChIP for identifying hypervariable signals across ChIP/ATAC-seq samples (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.368879+00:00</updated><author><name>Haojie Chen</name></author><author><name>Shiqi Tu</name></author><author><name>Chongze Yuan</name></author><author><name>Feng Tian</name></author><author><name>Yijing Zhang</name></author><author><name>Yihua Sun</name></author><author><name>Zhen Shao</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;With the reduction in sequencing costs, studies become prevalent that profile the chromatin landscape for tens or even hundreds of human individuals by using ChIP/ATAC-seq techniques. Identifying genomic regions with hypervariable ChIP/ATAC-seq signals across given samples is essential for such studies. In particular, the hypervariable regions (HVRs) across tumors from different patients indicate their heterogeneity and can contribute to revealing potential cancer subtypes and the associated epigenetic markers. We present HyperChIP as the first complete statistical tool for the task. HyperChIP uses scaled variances that account for the mean-variance dependence to rank genomic regions, and it increases the statistical power by diminishing the influence of true HVRs on model fitting. Applying it to a large pan-cancer ATAC-seq data set, we found that the identified HVRs not only provided a solid basis to uncover the underlying similarity structure among the involved tumor samples, but also led to the identification of transcription factors pertaining to the similarity structure when coupled with a motif-scanning analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.27.453915" rel="alternate" title="HyperChIP for identifying hypervariable signals across ChIP/ATAC-seq samples (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453642</id><title>Molecular Learning of a Soft-Disks Fluid (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.369169+00:00</updated><author><name>Luca Zammataro</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This work is based on the Equivalence between Molecular Dynamics and Neural Network. It provides learning proofs in a Lennard-Jones (LJ) fluid, presented as a network of particles having non-bonded interactions. I describe the fluid’s learning as the property of an order that emerges as an adaptation in establishing equilibrium with energy and thermal conservation. The experimental section demonstrates the fluid can be trained with logic-gates patterns. The work goes beyond Molecular Computing’s application, explaining how this model uses its intrinsic minimizing properties in learning and predicting outputs. Finally, it gives hints for a theory on real chemistry’s computational universality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.24.453642" rel="alternate" title="Molecular Learning of a Soft-Disks Fluid (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453685</id><title>SegmA: Residue Segmentation of cryo-EM density maps (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.369396+00:00</updated><author><name>Mark Rozanov</name></author><author><name>Haim J. Wolfson</name></author><content>&lt;label&gt;1&lt;/label&gt;&lt;title&gt;Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cryo-EM resolution revolution enables the development of algorithms for direct de-novo modelling of protein structures from given cryo-EM density maps. Deep Learning tools have been applied to locate structure patterns, such as rotamers, secondary structures and C&lt;italic&gt;α&lt;/italic&gt; atoms. We present a deep neural network (nicknamed SegmA) for the residue type segmentation of a cryo-EM density map. The network labels voxels in a cryo-EM map by the residue type (amino acid type or nucleic acid) of the sampled macromolecular structure. It also provides a visual representation of the density map by coloring the different types of voxels by their assgned colors. SegmA’s algorithm combines a rotation equivariant group convolutional network with a traditional U-net network in a cascade. In addition SegmA estimates the labeling accuracy and reports only labels assigned with high confidence. At resolution of 3&lt;italic&gt;Å&lt;/italic&gt; SegmAs accuracy is 80% for nucleotides. Amino acids which can be seen by eye, such as LEU, ARG and PHE, are detected by Segma with about 70% accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A web server of the application is under development at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dev.dcsh7cbr3o89e.amplifyapp.com"&gt;https://dev.dcsh7cbr3o89e.amplifyapp.com&lt;/ext-link&gt;. The SegmA open code is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Mark-Rozanov/SegmA_3A/tree/master"&gt;https://github.com/Mark-Rozanov/SegmA_3A/tree/master&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453685" rel="alternate" title="SegmA: Residue Segmentation of cryo-EM density maps (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453821</id><title>PEGR: a flexible management platform for reproducible epigenomic and genomic research (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.369628+00:00</updated><author><name>Danying Shao</name></author><author><name>Gretta D. Kellogg</name></author><author><name>Ali Nematbakhsh</name></author><author><name>Prashant Kuntala</name></author><author><name>Shaun Mahony</name></author><author><name>B. Franklin Pugh</name></author><author><name>William KM Lai</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reproducibility is a significant challenge in (epi)genomic research due to the complexity of experiments composed of traditional biochemistry and informatics. Recent advances have exacerbated this challenge as high-throughput sequencing data is generated at an unprecedented pace. Here we report on our development of a &lt;underline&gt;P&lt;/underline&gt;latform for &lt;underline&gt;E&lt;/underline&gt;pi-&lt;underline&gt;G&lt;/underline&gt;enomic &lt;underline&gt;R&lt;/underline&gt;esearch (PEGR), a web-based project management platform that tracks and quality controls experiments from conception to publication-ready figures, compatible with multiple assays and bioinformatic pipelines. It supports rigor and reproducibility for biochemists working at the wet bench, while continuing to fully support reproducibility and reliability for bioinformaticians through integration with the Galaxy platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453821" rel="alternate" title="PEGR: a flexible management platform for reproducible epigenomic and genomic research (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453903</id><title>3D Convolutional Neural Networks for Classification of Alzheimer's and Parkinson's Disease with T1-Weighted Brain MRI (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.369913+00:00</updated><author><name>Nikhil J. Dhinagar</name></author><author><name>Sophia I. Thomopoulos</name></author><author><name>Conor Owens-Walton</name></author><author><name>Dimitris Stripelis</name></author><author><name>Jose-Luis Ambite</name></author><author><name>Greg Ver Steeg</name></author><author><name>Daniel Weintraub</name></author><author><name>Philip Cook</name></author><author><name>Corey McMillan</name></author><author><name>Paul M. Thompson</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Parkinson's disease (PD) and Alzheimer's disease (AD) are progressive neurodegenerative disorders that affect millions of people worldwide. In this work, we propose a deep learning approach to classify these diseases based on 3D T1-weighted brain MRI. We analyzed several datasets including the Parkinson's Progression Markers Initiative (PPMI), an independent dataset from the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine (UPenn), the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI), and the Open Access Series of Imaging Studies (OASIS) dataset. PPMI and ADNI were partitioned to train (70%), validate (20%), and test (10%) a 3D convolutional neural network (CNN) for PD and AD classification. The UPenn and OASIS datasets were used as independent test sets to evaluate the model performance during inference. We also implemented a random forest classifier as a baseline model by extracting key radiomics features from the same T1-weighted MRI scans. The proposed 3D CNN model was trained from scratch for the classification tasks. For AD classification, the 3D CNN model achieved an ROC-AUC of 0.878 on the ADNI test set and an average ROC-AUC of 0.789 on the OASIS dataset. For PD classification, the proposed 3D CNN model achieved an ROC-AUC of 0.667 on the PPMI test set and an average ROC-AUC of 0.743 on the UPenn dataset. We also found that model performance was largely maintained when using only 25% of the training dataset. The 3D CNN outperformed the random forest classifier for both the PD and AD tasks. The 3D CNN also generalized better on unseen MRI data from different imaging centers. Our results show that the proposed 3D CNN model was less prone to overfitting for AD than for PD classification. This approach shows promise for screening of PD and AD patients using only T1-weighted brain MRI, which is relatively widely available. This model with additional validation could also be used to help differentiate between challenging cases of AD and PD when they present with similarly subtle motor and non-motor symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.26.453903" rel="alternate" title="3D Convolutional Neural Networks for Classification of Alzheimer's and Parkinson's Disease with T1-Weighted Brain MRI (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453696</id><title>Artificial Intelligence Resolves Kinetic Pathways of Magnesium Binding to RNA (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.370230+00:00</updated><author><name>Jan Neumann</name></author><author><name>Nadine Schwierz</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Magnesium is an indispensable cofactor in countless vital processes. In order to understand its functional role, the characterization of the binding pathways to biomolecules such as RNA is crucial. Despite the importance, a molecular description is still lacking since the transition from the water-mediated outer-sphere to the direct inner-sphere conformation is on the millisecond timescale and therefore out of reach for conventional simulation techniques. To fill this gap, we use transition path sampling to resolve the binding pathways and to elucidate the role of the solvent in the reaction. The results reveal that the molecular void provoked by the leaving phosphate oxygen of the RNA is immediately filled by an entering water molecule. In addition, water molecules from the first and second hydration shell couple to the concerted exchange. To capture the intimate solute-solvent coupling, we perform a committor analysis as basis for a machine learning algorithm that derives the optimal deep learning model from thousands of scanned architectures using hyperparameter tuning. The results reveal that the properly optimized deep network architecture recognizes the important solvent structures, extracts the relevant information and predicts the commitment probability with high accuracy. Our results provide a quantitative description of solute-solvent coupling which is ubiquitous for kosmotropic ions and governs a large variety of biochemical reactions in aqueous solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.25.453696" rel="alternate" title="Artificial Intelligence Resolves Kinetic Pathways of Magnesium Binding to RNA (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453477</id><title>Generative Adversarial Network augmented the gut microbiome-based health index by profoundly improved discrimination power (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.370433+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuxue Li</name></author><author><name>Gang Xie</name></author><author><name>Yuguo Zha</name></author><author><name>Kang Ning</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gut microbiome-based health index (GMHI) has been applied with success, while the discrimination powers of GMHI varied for different diseases, limiting its utility on a broad spectrum of diseases. In this work, a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) model is proposed to improve the discrimination power of GMHI. Built based on the batch corrected data through GAN (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI"&gt;https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI&lt;/ext-link&gt;), GAN-GMHI has largely reduced the batch effects, and profoundly improved the performance for distinguishing healthy individuals and different diseases. GAN-GMHI has provided results to support the strong association of gut microbiome and diseases, and indicated a more accurate venue towards microbiome-based disease monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAN-GMHI is publicly available on GitHub: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI"&gt;https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;ningkang@hust.edu.cn&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453477" rel="alternate" title="Generative Adversarial Network augmented the gut microbiome-based health index by profoundly improved discrimination power (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453588</id><title>Accelerated epigenetic aging and inflammatory/immunological profile (ipAGE) in patients with chronic kidney disease (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.370719+00:00</updated><author><name>Igor Yusipov</name></author><author><name>Elena Kondakova</name></author><author><name>Alena Kalyakulina</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Krivonosov</name></author><author><name>Nadezhda Lobanova</name></author><author><name>Maria Giulia Bacalini</name></author><author><name>Claudio Franceschi</name></author><author><name>Maria Vedunova</name></author><author><name>Mikhail Ivanchenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is defined by reduced estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR). This failure can be related to a phenotype of accelerated aging. In this work we considered 76 subjects with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) and 83 healthy controls. We evaluated two measures that can be informative of the rate of aging, i.e. whole blood DNA methylation using the Illumina Infinium EPIC array and plasma levels of a selection of inflammatory/immunological proteins using Multiplex Immunoassays. We demonstrated accelerated aging in terms of the most common epigenetic age estimators in CKD patients. We developed a new predictor of age based on inflammatory/immunological profile (ipAGE) and confirmed age acceleration in CKD patients. Finally, we evaluated the relationship between epigenetic age predictors and ipAGE and further identified the inflammatory/immunological biomarkers differentially expressed between cases and controls. In summary, our data show an accelerated aging phenotype in CKD patients sustained by inflammatory processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453588" rel="alternate" title="Accelerated epigenetic aging and inflammatory/immunological profile (ipAGE) in patients with chronic kidney disease (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453511</id><title>PatchPerPixMatch for Automated 3d Search of Neuronal Morphologies in Light Microscopy (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-29T07:34:31.371093+00:00</updated><author><name>Lisa Mais</name></author><author><name>Peter Hirsch</name></author><author><name>Claire Managan</name></author><author><name>Kaiyu Wang</name></author><author><name>Konrad Rokicki</name></author><author><name>Robert R. Svirskas</name></author><author><name>Barry J. Dickson</name></author><author><name>Wyatt Korff</name></author><author><name>Gerald M. Rubin</name></author><author><name>Gudrun Ihrke</name></author><author><name>Geoffrey W. Meissner</name></author><author><name>Dagmar Kainmueller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Studies of individual neurons in the Drosophila nervous system are facilitated by transgenic lines that sparsely and repeatably label respective neurons of interest. Sparsity can be enhanced by means of intersectional approaches like the split-GAL4 system, which labels the positive intersection of the expression patterns of two (denser) GAL4 lines. To this end, two GAL4 lines have to be identified as labelling a neuron of interest. Current approaches to tackling this task include visual inspection, as well as automated search in 2d projection images, of single cell multi-color flip-out (MCFO) acquisitions of GAL4 expression patterns. There is to date no automated method available that performs full 3d search in MCFO imagery of GAL4 lines, nor one that leverages automated reconstructions of the labelled neuron morphologies. To close this gap, we propose PatchPerPixMatch, a fully automated approach for finding a given neuron morphology in MCFO acquisitions of Gen1 GAL4 lines. PatchPerPixMatch performs automated instance segmentation of MCFO acquisitions, and subsequently searches for a target neuron morphology by minimizing an objective that aims at covering the target with a set of well-fitting segmentation fragments. Patch-PerPixMatch is computationally efficient albeit being full 3d, while also highly robust to inaccuracies in the automated neuron instance segmentation. We are releasing PatchPerPixMatch search results for ~30,000 neuron morphologies from the Drosophila &lt;italic&gt;hemibrain&lt;/italic&gt; in ~20,000 MCFO acquisitions of ~3,500 Gen1 GAL4 lines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Code&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Kainmueller-Lab/PatchPerPixMatch"&gt;https://github.com/Kainmueller-Lab/PatchPerPixMatch&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pppm.janelia.org"&gt;https://pppm.janelia.org&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453511" rel="alternate" title="PatchPerPixMatch for Automated 3d Search of Neuronal Morphologies in Light Microscopy (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>