<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.754204+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.450875</id><title>MSNovelist: De novo structure generation from mass spectra (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.755342+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael A. Stravs</name></author><author><name>Kai Dührkop</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Böcker</name></author><author><name>Nicola Zamboni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Structural elucidation of small molecules &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; from mass spectra is a longstanding, yet unsolved problem. Current methods rely on finding some similarity with spectra of known compounds deposited in spectral libraries, but do not solve the problem of predicting structures for novel or poorly represented compound classes. We present &lt;italic&gt;MSNovelist&lt;/italic&gt; that combines fingerprint prediction with an encoder-decoder neural network to generate structures &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; from fragment spectra. In evaluation, &lt;italic&gt;MSNovelist&lt;/italic&gt; correctly reproduced 61% of database annotations for a GNPS reference dataset. In a bryophyte MS&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; dataset, our &lt;italic&gt;de novo&lt;/italic&gt; structure prediction substantially outscored the best database candidate for seven features, and a potential novel natural product with a flavonoid core was identified. &lt;italic&gt;MSNovelist&lt;/italic&gt; allows predicting structures solely from MS&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; data, and is therefore ideally suited to complement library-based annotation in the case of poorly represented analyte classes and novel compounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.450875" rel="alternate" title="MSNovelist: De novo structure generation from mass spectra (25 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451268</id><title>DynaTMT: A user-friendly tool to process combined SILAC/TMT data (21 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.756769+00:00</updated><author><name>Kevin Klann</name></author><author><name>David Krause</name></author><author><name>Christian Münch</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The measurement of protein dynamics by proteomics to study cell remodeling has seen increased attention over the last years. This development is largely driven by a number of technological advances in proteomics methods. Pulsed stable isotope labeling in cell culture (SILAC) combined with tandem mass tag (TMT) labeling has evolved as a gold standard for profiling protein synthesis and degradation. While the experimental setup is similar to typical proteomics experiments, the data analysis proves more difficult: After peptide identification through search engines, data extraction requires either custom scripted pipelines or tedious manual table manipulations to extract the TMT-labeled heavy and light peaks of interest. To overcome this limitation, which deters researchers from using protein dynamic proteomics, we developed a user-friendly, browser-based application that allows easy and reproducible data analysis without the need for scripting experience. In addition, we provide a python package that can be implemented in established data analysis pipelines. We anticipate that this tool will ease data analysis and spark further research aimed at monitoring protein translation and degradation by proteomics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451268" rel="alternate" title="DynaTMT: A user-friendly tool to process combined SILAC/TMT data (21 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.08.451210</id><title>RESEPT: tissue architecture inference and visualization from spatially resolved transcriptomics (11 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.757441+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuzhou Chang</name></author><author><name>Fei He</name></author><author><name>Juexin Wang</name></author><author><name>Shuo Chen</name></author><author><name>Jingyi Li</name></author><author><name>Jixin Liu</name></author><author><name>Yang Yu</name></author><author><name>Li Su</name></author><author><name>Anjun Ma</name></author><author><name>Carter Allen</name></author><author><name>Yu Lin</name></author><author><name>Shaoli Sun</name></author><author><name>Bingqiang Liu</name></author><author><name>Jose Otero</name></author><author><name>Dongjun Chung</name></author><author><name>Hongjun Fu</name></author><author><name>Zihai Li</name></author><author><name>Dong Xu</name></author><author><name>Qin Ma</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present RESEPT, a deep-learning framework for characterizing and visualizing tissue architecture from spatially resolved transcriptomics by reconstructing and segmenting a transcriptome mapped RGB image. RESEPT can identify the tissue architecture, and represent corresponding marker genes and biological functions accurately. RESEPT also provides critical insights into the underlying mechanisms driving the complex tissue heterogeneities in Alzheimer's disease and glioblastoma.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.08.451210" rel="alternate" title="RESEPT: tissue architecture inference and visualization from spatially resolved transcriptomics (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451263</id><title>Efficient gradient boosting for prognostic biomarker discovery (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.758145+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaiqiao Li</name></author><author><name>Sijie Yao</name></author><author><name>Zhenyu Zhang</name></author><author><name>Biwei Cao</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. Wilson</name></author><author><name>Pei Fen Kuan</name></author><author><name>Ruoqing Zhu</name></author><author><name>Xuefeng Wang</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gradient boosting decision tree (GBDT) is a powerful ensemble machine learning method that has the potential to accelerate biomarker discovery from high-dimensional molecular data. Recent algorithmic advances, such as Extreme Gradient Boosting (XGB) and Light Gradient Boosting (LGB), have rendered the GBDT training more efficient, scalable and accurate. These modern techniques, however, have not yet been widely adopted in biomarkers discovery based on patient survival data, which are key clinical outcomes or endpoints in cancer studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we present a new R package &lt;bold&gt;Xsurv&lt;/bold&gt; as an integrated solution which applies two modern GBDT training framework namely, XGB and LGB, for the modeling of censored survival outcomes. Based on a comprehensive set of simulations, we benchmark the new approaches against traditional methods including the stepwise Cox regression model and the original gradient boosting function implemented in the package &lt;bold&gt;gbm&lt;/bold&gt;. We also demonstrate the application of &lt;bold&gt;Xsurv&lt;/bold&gt; in analyzing a melanoma methylation dataset. Together, these results suggest that &lt;bold&gt;Xsurv&lt;/bold&gt; is a useful and computationally viable tool for screening a large number of prognostic candidate biomarkers, which may facilitate cancer translational and clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;Xsurv&lt;/bold&gt; is freely available as an R package at: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/topycyao/Xsurv"&gt;https://github.com/topycyao/Xsurv&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at &lt;italic&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/italic&gt; online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.06.451263" rel="alternate" title="Efficient gradient boosting for prognostic biomarker discovery (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.08.451609</id><title>Identifying cellular-to-phenotype associations by elucidating hierarchical relationships in high-dimensional cytometry data (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-12T06:55:39.758481+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam S Chan</name></author><author><name>Wei Jiang</name></author><author><name>Emily Blyth</name></author><author><name>Jean Yee Hwa Yang</name></author><author><name>Ellis Patrick</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High-throughput single cell technologies hold the promise of discovering novel cellular relationships with disease and necessitate the use of effective analytical workflows. When manual gating is used to define cell types, the gating hierarchy can be used to identify cell types whose abundances change relative to a parent population. This strategy allows subtle changes to be observed that could be missed if small subsets were compared to all measured cells. However, typical analyses that employ unsupervised clustering overlook the valuable hierarchical structure present in cell type definitions by exclusively quantifying the proportions of cell type clusters relative to all cells. We present treekoR, a framework that facilitates multiple quantifications and comparisons of cell type proportions. Our results from twelve case studies reinforce the importance of quantifying proportions relative to parent populations in the analyses of cytometry data - as failing to do so can lead to missing important biological insights.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.08.451609" rel="alternate" title="Identifying cellular-to-phenotype associations by elucidating hierarchical relationships in high-dimensional cytometry data (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>