<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.753375+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450135</id><title>DeepMP: a deep learning tool to detect DNA base modifications on Nanopore sequencing data (87 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.753786+00:00</updated><author><name>Jose Bonet</name></author><author><name>Mandi Chen</name></author><author><name>Marc Dabad</name></author><author><name>Simon Heath</name></author><author><name>Abel Gonzalez-Perez</name></author><author><name>Nuria Lopez-Bigas</name></author><author><name>Jens Lagergren</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DNA Methylation plays a key role in a variety of biological processes. Recently, Nanopore long-read sequencing has enabled direct detection of these modifications. As a consequence, a range of computational methods have been developed to exploit Nanopore data for methylation detection. However, current approaches rely on a human-defined threshold to detect the methylation status of a genomic position and are not optimized to detect sites methylated at low frequency. Furthermore, most methods employ either the Nanopore signals or the basecalling errors as the model input and do not take advantage of their combination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present DeepMP, a convolutional neural network (CNN)-based model that takes information from Nanopore signals and basecalling errors to detect whether a given motif in a read is methylated or not. Besides, DeepMP introduces a threshold-free position modification calling model sensitive to sites methylated at low frequency across cells. We comprehensively benchmarked DeepMP against state-of-the-art methods on &lt;italic&gt;E. coli&lt;/italic&gt;, human and pUC19 datasets. DeepMP outperforms current approaches at read-based and position-based methylation detection across sites methylated at different frequencies in the three datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;DeepMP is implemented and freely available under MIT license at github.com/pepebonet/DeepMP&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;jose.bonet@irbbarcelona.org&lt;/email&gt; — &lt;email&gt;mandiche@kth.se&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.28.450135" rel="alternate" title="DeepMP: a deep learning tool to detect DNA base modifications on Nanopore sequencing data (87 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450324</id><title>PhenoExam: an R package and Web application for the examination of phenotypes linked to genes and gene sets (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.754078+00:00</updated><author><name>Alejandro Cisterna</name></author><author><name>Aurora González-Vidal</name></author><author><name>Daniel Ruiz</name></author><author><name>Jordi Ortiz</name></author><author><name>Alicia Gómez-Pascual</name></author><author><name>Zhongbo Chen</name></author><author><name>Mike Nalls</name></author><author><name>Faraz Faghri</name></author><author><name>John Hardy</name></author><author><name>Irene Díez</name></author><author><name>Paolo Maietta</name></author><author><name>Sara Álvarez</name></author><author><name>Mina Ryten</name></author><author><name>Juan A. Botía</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Gene set based phenotype enrichment analysis (detecting phenotypic terms that emerge as significant in a set of genes) can improve the rate of genetic diagnoses amongst other research purposes. To facilitate diverse phenotype analysis, we developed PhenoExam, a freely available R package for tool developers and a web interface for users, which performs: (1) phenotype and disease enrichment analysis on a gene set; (2) measures statistically significant phenotype similarities between gene sets and (3) detects significant differential phenotypes or disease terms across different databases. PhenoExam achieves these tasks by integrating databases or resources such as the HPO, MGD, CRISPRbrain, CTD, ClinGen, CGI, OrphaNET, UniProt, PsyGeNET, and Genomics England Panel App. PhenoExam accepts both human and mouse genes as input. We developed PhenoExam to assist a variety of users, including clinicians, computational biologists and geneticists. It can be used to support the validation of new gene-to-disease discoveries, and in the detection of differential phenotypes between two gene sets (a phenotype linked to one of the gene set but no to the other) that are useful for differential diagnosis and to improve genetic panels. We validated PhenoExam performance through simulations and its application to real cases. We demonstrate that PhenoExam is effective in distinguishing gene sets or Mendelian diseases with very similar phenotypes through projecting the disease-causing genes into their annotation-based phenotypic spaces. We also tested the tool with early onset Parkinson’s disease and dystonia genes, to show phenotype-level similarities but also potentially interesting differences. More specifically, we used PhenoExam to validate computationally predicted new genes potentially associated with epilepsy. Therefore, PhenoExam effectively discovers links between phenotypic terms across annotation databases through effective integration. The R package is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/alexcis95/PhenoExam"&gt;https://github.com/alexcis95/PhenoExam&lt;/ext-link&gt; and the Web tool is accessible at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://snca.atica.um.es/PhenoExamWeb/"&gt;https://snca.atica.um.es/PhenoExamWeb/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450324" rel="alternate" title="PhenoExam: an R package and Web application for the examination of phenotypes linked to genes and gene sets (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450340</id><title>HMMploidy: inference of ploidy levels from short-read sequencing data (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.754374+00:00</updated><author><name>Samuele Soraggi</name></author><author><name>Johanna Rhodes</name></author><author><name>Isin Altinkaya</name></author><author><name>Oliver Tarrant</name></author><author><name>François Balloux</name></author><author><name>Matthew C. Fisher</name></author><author><name>Matteo Fumagalli</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The inference of ploidy levels from genomic data is important to understand molecular mechanisms underpinning genome evolution. However, current methods based on allele frequency and sequencing depth variation do not have power to infer ploidy levels at low- and mid-depth sequencing data, as they do not account for data uncertainty. Here we introduce &lt;monospace&gt;HMMploidy&lt;/monospace&gt;, a novel tool that leverages the information from multiple samples and combines the information from sequencing depth and genotype likelihoods. We demonstrate that &lt;monospace&gt;HMMploidy&lt;/monospace&gt; outperforms existing methods in most tested scenarios, especially at low-depth with large sample size. &lt;monospace&gt;HMMploidy&lt;/monospace&gt; further allows for local inferences of ploidy change to detect within-chromosome variations. We apply &lt;monospace&gt;HMMploidy&lt;/monospace&gt; to sequencing data from the pathogenic fungus &lt;italic&gt;Cryptococcus neoformans&lt;/italic&gt; and retrieve pervasive patterns of polyploidy and aneuploidy, even when artificially downsampling the sequencing data. We envisage that &lt;monospace&gt;HMMploidy&lt;/monospace&gt; will have wide applicability to low-depth sequencing data from polyploid and aneuploid species.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450340" rel="alternate" title="HMMploidy: inference of ploidy levels from short-read sequencing data (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450493</id><title>Improved estimation of cell type-specific gene expression through deconvolution of bulk tissues with matrix completion (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.755234+00:00</updated><author><name>Weixu Wang</name></author><author><name>Jun Yao</name></author><author><name>Yi Wang</name></author><author><name>Chao Zhang</name></author><author><name>Wei Tao</name></author><author><name>Jiahua Zou</name></author><author><name>Ting Ni</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cell type-specific gene expression (CSE) brings novel biological insights into both physiological and pathological processes compared with bulk tissue gene expression. Although fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) and single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) are two widely used techniques to detect gene expression in a cell type-specific manner, the constraints of cost and labor force make it impractical as a routine on large patient cohorts. Here, we present ENIGMA, an algorithm that deconvolutes bulk RNA-seq into cell type-specific expression matrices and cell type fraction matrices without the need of physical sorting or sequencing of single cells. ENIGMA used cell type signature matrix generated from either FACS RNA-seq or scRNA-seq as reference, and applied matrix completion technique to achieve fast and accurate deconvolution. We demonstrated the superior performance of ENIGMA to previously published algorithms (TCA, bMIND and CIBERSORTx) while requiring much less running time on both simulated and realistic datasets. To prove its value in biological discovery, we applied ENIGMA to bulk RNA-seq from arthritis patients and revealed a pseudo-differentiation trajectory that could reflect monocyte to macrophage transition. We also applied ENIGMA to bulk RNA-seq data of pancreatic islet tissue from type 2 diabetes (T2D) patients and discovered a beta cell-specific gene co-expression module related to senescence and apoptosis that possibly contributed to the pathogenesis of T2D. Together, ENIGMA provides a new framework to improve the CSE estimation by integrating FACS RNA-seq and scRNA-seq with tissue bulk RNA-seq data, and will extend our understandings about cell heterogeneity on population level with no need for experimental tissue disaggregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.30.450493" rel="alternate" title="Improved estimation of cell type-specific gene expression through deconvolution of bulk tissues with matrix completion (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.450681</id><title>Knowledge-based antibody repertoire simulation, a novel allele detection tool evaluation and application (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.755524+00:00</updated><author><name>Xiujia Yang</name></author><author><name>Yan Zhu</name></author><author><name>Huikun Zeng</name></author><author><name>Sen Chen</name></author><author><name>Junjie Guan</name></author><author><name>Qi-Long Wang</name></author><author><name>Chunhong Lan</name></author><author><name>Deqiang Sun</name></author><author><name>Xueqing Yu</name></author><author><name>Zhenhai Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Detailed knowledge of the diverse immunoglobulin germline genes is critical for the study of humoral immunity. Hundreds of alleles have been discovered by analyzing antibody repertoire sequencing (Rep-seq or Ig-seq) data via multiple novel allele detection tools (NADTs). However, the performance of these NADTs through antibody sequences with intrinsic somatic hypermutations (SHMs) is unclear. Here, we developed a tool to simulate repertoires by integrating the full spectrum features of an antibody repertoire such as germline gene usage, junctional modification, position-specific SHM and clonal expansion based on 2152 high-quality datasets. We then systematically evaluated these NADTs using both simulated and genuine Ig-seq datasets. Finally, we applied these NADTs to 687 Ig-seq datasets and identified 43 novel alleles using defined criteria. Twenty-five alleles were validated through findings of other sources. In addition to the novel alleles detected, our simulation tool, the results of our comparison, and the streamline of this process may benefit further humoral immunity studies via Ig-seq.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.01.450681" rel="alternate" title="Knowledge-based antibody repertoire simulation, a novel allele detection tool evaluation and application (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450908</id><title>RAFFT: Efficient prediction of RNA folding pathways using the fast Fourier transform (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.755864+00:00</updated><author><name>vaitea opuu</name></author><author><name>Cyrille Merleau Nono Saha</name></author><author><name>Matteo Smerlak</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We propose a novel heuristic to predict RNA secondary structures. The algorithm is inspired by the kinetic partitioning mechanism, by which molecules follow alternative folding pathways to their native structure, some much faster than others. Similarly, our algorithm RAFFT generates an ensemble of concurrent folding pathways ending in multiple metastable structures for each given sequence; this is in contrast with traditional thermodynamic approaches, which are based on aim to find single structures with minimal free energies. When analyzing 50 predicted folds per sequence, we found near-native predictions (79% PPV and 81% sensitivity) for RNAs of length &amp;lt; 200 nucleotides, matching the performance of recent deep-learning-based structure prediction methods. Our algorithm also acts as a folding kinetic ansatz, which we tested on two RNAs: the coronavirus frameshifting stimulation element (CFSE) and a classic bi-stable sequence. For the CFSE, an ensemble of 68 distinct structures computed by RAFFT allowed us to produce complete folding kinetic trajectories, whereas known methods require evaluating millions of sub-optimal structures to achieve this result. For the second application, only 46 distinct structures were required to reproduce the kinetics, whereas known methods required a sample of 20,000 structures. Thanks to the efficiency of the fast Fourier transform on which RAFFT is based, these computations are efficient, with complexity O(L^2 log L).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.02.450908" rel="alternate" title="RAFFT: Efficient prediction of RNA folding pathways using the fast Fourier transform (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450404</id><title>Benchmarking supervised signature-scoring methods for single-cell RNA sequencing data in cancer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-05T07:27:44.756207+00:00</updated><author><name>Nighat Noureen</name></author><author><name>Zhenqing Ye</name></author><author><name>Yidong Chen</name></author><author><name>Xiaojing Wang</name></author><author><name>Siyuan Zheng</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Quantifying the activity of gene expression signatures is common in analyses of single-cell RNA sequencing data. Methods originally developed for bulk samples are often used for this purpose without accounting for contextual differences between bulk and single-cell data. More broadly, these methods have not been benchmarked. Here we benchmark four such supervised methods, including single sample gene set enrichment analysis (ssGSEA), AUCell, Single Cell Signature Explorer (SCSE), and a new method we developed, Jointly Assessing Signature Mean and Inferring Enrichment (JASMINE). Using cancer as an example, we show cancer cells consistently express more genes than normal cells. This imbalance leads to bias in performance by bulk-sample-based ssGSEA in gold standard tests and down sampling experiments. In contrast, single-cell-based methods are less susceptible. Our results suggest caution should be exercised when using bulk-sample-based methods in single-cell data analyses, and cellular contexts should be taken into consideration when designing benchmarking strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.29.450404" rel="alternate" title="Benchmarking supervised signature-scoring methods for single-cell RNA sequencing data in cancer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>