<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.740536+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460168</id><title>Random Forest Factorization Reveals Latent Structure in Single Cell RNA Sequencing Data (32 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.740936+00:00</updated><author><name>Boris M. Brenerman</name></author><author><name>Benjamin D. Shapiro</name></author><author><name>Michael C. Schatz</name></author><author><name>Alexis Battle</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA sequencing data contain patterns of correlation that are poorly captured by techniques that rely on linear estimation or assumptions of Gaussian behavior. We apply random forest regression to scRNAseq data from mouse brains, which identifies the co-regulation of genes within specific cellular contexts. By analyzing the estimators of the random forest, we identify several novel candidate gene regulatory networks and compare these networks in aged and young mice. We demonstrate that cell populations have cell-type specific phenotypes of aging that are not detected by other methods, including the collapse of differentiating oligodendrocytes but not precursors or mature oligodendrocytes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460168" rel="alternate" title="Random Forest Factorization Reveals Latent Structure in Single Cell RNA Sequencing Data (32 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460322</id><title>Variance of allele balance calculated from low coverage sequencing data infers departure from a diploid state (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.741339+00:00</updated><author><name>Kyle Fletcher</name></author><author><name>Rongkui Han</name></author><author><name>Diederik Smilde</name></author><author><name>Richard Michelmore</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polyploidy and heterokaryosis are common and consequential genetic phenomena that increase the number of haplotypes in an organism and complicate whole-genome sequence analysis. Allele balance has been used to infer polyploidy and heterokaryosis in diverse organisms using read sets sequenced to greater than 50x whole-genome coverage. However, Sequencing to adequate depth is costly if applied to multiple individuals or large genomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We developed VCFvariance.pl to utilize the variance of allele balance to infer polyploidy and/or heterokaryosis at low sequence coverage. This analysis requires as little as 10x whole-genome coverage and reduces the allele balance profile down to a single value, which can be used to determine if an individual has two or more haplotypes. This approach was validated on simulated, synthetic, and authentic read sets from an oomycete, fungus, and plant. The approach was deployed to ascertain the genome status of multiple isolates of &lt;italic&gt;Bremia lactucae&lt;/italic&gt; and &lt;italic&gt;Phytophthora infestans&lt;/italic&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;VCFvariance.pl is a Perl script available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kfletcher88/VCFvariance"&gt;https://github.com/kfletcher88/VCFvariance&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460322" rel="alternate" title="Variance of allele balance calculated from low coverage sequencing data infers departure from a diploid state (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.12.460001</id><title>DeepREAL: A Deep Learning Powered Multi-scale Modeling Framework Towards Predicting Out-of-distribution Receptor Activity of Ligand Binding (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.741656+00:00</updated><author><name>Tian Cai</name></author><author><name>Kyra Alyssa Abbu</name></author><author><name>Yang Liu</name></author><author><name>Lei Xie</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Drug discovery has witnessed intensive exploration of the problem of drug-target physical interactions over two decades, however, a strong drug binding affinity to a single target often fails to translate into desired clinical outcomes. A critical knowledge gap needs to be filled for correlating drug-target interactions with phenotypic responses: predicting the receptor activities or function selectivity upon the ligand binding (i.e., agonist vs. antagonist) on a genome-scale and for novel chemicals. Two major obstacles compound the difficulty on this direction: known data of receptor activity is far too scarce to train a robust model in light of genome-scale applications, and real-world applications need to deploy a model on data from various shifted distributions. To address these challenges, we have developed an end-to-end deep learning framework, DeepREAL, for multi-scale modeling of genome-wide receptor activities of ligand binding. DeepREAL utilizes self-supervised learning on tens of millions of protein sequences and pre-trained binary interaction classification to solve the data distribution shift and data scarcity problems. Extensive benchmark studies that simulate real-world scenarios demonstrate that DeepREAL achieves state-of-the-art performance in out-of-distribution settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.12.460001" rel="alternate" title="DeepREAL: A Deep Learning Powered Multi-scale Modeling Framework Towards Predicting Out-of-distribution Receptor Activity of Ligand Binding (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460213</id><title>The value of genotype-specific reference for transcriptome analyses (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.741958+00:00</updated><author><name>Wenbin Guo</name></author><author><name>Max Coulter</name></author><author><name>Robbie Waugh</name></author><author><name>Runxuan Zhang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;High quality transcriptome assembly using short reads from RNA-seq data still heavily relies upon reference-based approaches, of which the primary step is to align RNA-seq reads to a single reference genome of haploid sequence. However, it is increasingly apparent that while different genotypes within a species share “core” genes, they also contain variable numbers of “specific” genes that are only present a subset of individuals. Using a common reference may thus lead to a loss of genotype-specific information in the assembled transcript dataset and the generation of erroneous, incomplete or misleading transcriptomics analysis results. With the recent development of pan-genome information in many species, it is important that we understand the limitations of single genotype references for transcriptomics analysis. In this study, we quantitively evaluated the advantages of using genotype-specific reference genomes for transcriptome assembly and analysis using cultivated barley as a model. We mapped barley cultivar Barke RNA-seq reads to the Barke genome and to the cultivar Morex genome (common barley genome reference) to construct a genotype specific Reference Transcript Dataset (sRTD) and a common Reference Transcript Datasets (cRTD), respectively. We compared the two RTDs according to their transcript diversity, transcript sequence and structure similarity and the accuracy they provided for transcript quantification and differential expression analysis. Our evaluation shows that the sRTD has a significantly higher diversity of transcripts and alternative splicing events. Despite using a high-quality reference genome for assembly of the cRTD, we miss ca. 40% transcripts present in the sRTD and cRTD only has ca. 70% true assemblies. We found that the sRTD is more accurate for transcript quantification as well as differential expression and differential alternative splicing analysis. However, gene level quantification and comparative expression analysis are less affected by the source RTD, which indicates that analysing transcriptomic data at the gene level may be a reasonable compromise when a high-quality genotype-specific reference is not available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.14.460213" rel="alternate" title="The value of genotype-specific reference for transcriptome analyses (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460049</id><title>Convex-PLR – Revisiting affinity predictions and virtual screening using physics-informed machine learning (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-20T07:06:44.742283+00:00</updated><author><name>Maria Kadukova</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Chupin</name></author><author><name>Sergei Grudinin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Virtual screening is an essential part of the modern drug design pipeline, which significantly accelerates the discovery of new drug candidates. Structure-based virtual screening involves ligand conformational sampling, which is often followed by re-scoring of docking poses. A great variety of scoring functions have been designed for this purpose. The advent of structural and affinity databases and the progress in machine-learning methods have recently boosted scoring function performance. Nonetheless, the most successful scoring functions are typically designed for specific tasks or systems. All-purpose scoring functions still perform poorly on the virtual screening tests, compared to precision with which they are able to predict co-crystal binding poses. Another limitation is the low interpretability of the heuristics being used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We analyzed scoring functions’ performance in the CASF benchmarks and discovered that the vast majority of them have a strong bias towards predicting larger binding interfaces. This motivated us to develop a physical model with additional entropic terms with the aim of penalizing such a preference. We parameterized the new model using affinity and structural data, solving a classification problem followed by regression. The new model, called Convex-PL&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, demonstrated high-quality results on multiple tests and a substantial improvement over its predecessor Convex-PL. Convex-PL&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; can be used for molecular docking together with VinaCPL, our version of AutoDock Vina, with Convex-PL integrated as a scoring function. Convex-PL&lt;sup&gt;&lt;italic&gt;R&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Convex-PL, and VinaCPL are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://team.inria.fr/nano-d/convex-pl/"&gt;https://team.inria.fr/nano-d/convex-pl/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.13.460049" rel="alternate" title="Convex-PLR – Revisiting affinity predictions and virtual screening using physics-informed machine learning (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>