<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.418547+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445406</id><title>Pathway analysis in metabolomics: pitfalls and best practice for the use of over-representation analysis (47 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.419081+00:00</updated><author><name>Cecilia Wieder</name></author><author><name>Clément Frainay</name></author><author><name>Nathalie Poupin</name></author><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Mier</name></author><author><name>Florence Vinson</name></author><author><name>Juliette Cooke</name></author><author><name>Rachel PJ Lai</name></author><author><name>Jacob G Bundy</name></author><author><name>Fabien Jourdan</name></author><author><name>Timothy Ebbels</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Over-representation analysis (ORA) is one of the commonest pathway analysis approaches used for the functional interpretation of metabolomics datasets. Despite the widespread use of ORA in metabolomics, the community lacks guidelines detailing its best-practice use. Many factors have a pronounced impact on the results, but to date their effects have received little systematic attention in the field. We developed &lt;italic&gt;in-silico&lt;/italic&gt; simulations using five publicly available datasets and illustrated that changes in parameters, such as the background set, differential metabolite selection methods, and pathway database choice, could all lead to profoundly different ORA results. The use of a non-assay-specific background set, for example, resulted in large numbers of false-positive pathways. Pathway database choice, evaluated using three of the most popular metabolic pathway databases: KEGG, Reactome, and BioCyc, led to vastly different results in both the number and function of significantly enriched pathways. Metabolomics data specific factors, such as reliability of compound identification and assay chemical bias also impacted ORA results. Simulated metabolite misidentification rates as low as 4% resulted in both gain of false-positive pathways and loss of truly significant pathways across all datasets. Our results have several practical implications for ORA users, as well as those using alternative pathway analysis methods. We offer a set of recommendations for the use of ORA in metabolomics, alongside a set of minimal reporting guidelines, as a first step towards the standardisation of pathway analysis in metabolomics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Author summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metabolomics is a rapidly growing field of study involving the profiling of small molecules within an organism. It allows researchers to understand the effects of biological status (such as health or disease) on cellular biochemistry, and has wide-ranging applications, from biomarker discovery and personalised medicine in healthcare to crop protection and food security in agriculture. Pathway analysis helps to understand which biological pathways, representing collections of molecules performing a particular function, are involved in response to a disease phenotype, or drug treatment, for example. Over-representation analysis (ORA) is perhaps the most common pathway analysis method used in the metabolomics community. However, ORA can give drastically different results depending on the input data and parameters used. In this work, we have established the effects of these factors on ORA results using computational simulations applied to five real-world datasets. Based on our results, we offer the research community a set of best-practice recommendations applicable not only to ORA but also to other pathway analysis methods to help ensure the reliability and reproducibility of results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445406" rel="alternate" title="Pathway analysis in metabolomics: pitfalls and best practice for the use of over-representation analysis (47 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445440</id><title>Generative neural networks separate common and specific transcriptional responses (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.419767+00:00</updated><author><name>Alexandra J. Lee</name></author><author><name>Dallas L. Mould</name></author><author><name>Jake Crawford</name></author><author><name>Dongbo Hu</name></author><author><name>Rani K. Powers</name></author><author><name>Georgia Doing</name></author><author><name>James C. Costello</name></author><author><name>Deborah A. Hogan</name></author><author><name>Casey S. Greene</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide transcriptome profiling identifies genes that are prone to differential expression across contexts (“common DEGs”), as well as specific changes relevant to the experimental manipulation. Distinguishing common DEGs from those that are specifically changed in a context of interest will allow more efficient inference of relevant mechanisms and a more systematic understanding of the biological process under scrutiny. Currently, common changes can only be identified through the laborious manual curation of highly controlled experiments, an inordinately time-consuming and impractical endeavor. Here we pioneer a method for identifying common patterns using generative neural networks. This method produces a background set of transcriptomic experiments from which a gene and pathway-specific null distribution can be generated. By comparing the set of differentially expressed genes found in a target experiment against the background set, common results can easily be separated from specific ones. This “Specific cOntext Pattern Highlighting In Expression data” (SOPHIE) method is broadly applicable to new platforms or any species with a large collection of unannotated gene expression data. We apply SOPHIE to diverse datasets including human, including human cancer, and bacterial datasets. SOPHIE recapitulates previously described common DEGs, and our molecular validation indicates it detects highly specific, but low magnitude, biologically relevant, transcriptional changes. SOPHIE’s measure of specificity can complement log fold change activity generated from traditional differential expression analyses by, for example, filtering the set of changed genes to identify those that are specifically relevant to the experimental condition of interest. Consequently, these results can inform future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445440" rel="alternate" title="Generative neural networks separate common and specific transcriptional responses (33 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445506</id><title>On the sparsity of fitness functions and implications for learning (25 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.420288+00:00</updated><author><name>David H. Brookes</name></author><author><name>Amirali Aghazadeh</name></author><author><name>Jennifer Listgarten</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Fitness functions map biological sequences to a scalar property of interest. Accurate estimation of these functions yields biological insight and sets the foundation for model-based sequence design. However, the amount of fitness data available to learn these functions is typically small relative to the large combinatorial space of sequences; characterizing how much data is needed for accurate estimation remains an open problem. There is a growing body of evidence demonstrating that empirical fitness functions display substantial sparsity when represented in terms of epistatic interactions. Moreover, the theory of Compressed Sensing provides scaling laws for the number of samples required to exactly recover a sparse function. Motivated by these results, we study the sparsity of fitness functions sampled from a generalization of the NK model, a widely-used random field model of fitness functions. In particular, we present theoretical results that allow us to test the effect of the Generalized NK (GNK) model’s interpretable parameters—sequence length, alphabet size, and assumed interactions between sequence positions—on the sparsity of fitness functions sampled from the model and, consequently, the number of measurements required to exactly recover these functions. Further, we show that GNK fitness functions with parameters set according to protein structural contacts can be used to accurately approximate the number of samples required to estimate two empirical protein fitness functions, and are able to identify important higher-order epistatic interactions in these functions using only structural information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445506" rel="alternate" title="On the sparsity of fitness functions and implications for learning (25 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445595</id><title>nf-LO: A scalable, containerised workflow for genome-to-genome lift over (12 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.420536+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrea Talenti</name></author><author><name>James Prendergast</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The increasing availability of new genome assemblies often comes with an impaired amount of associated genomic annotations, limiting the range of studies that can be performed. A common workaround is to lift over annotations from better annotated genomes. However, generating the files required to perform a liftover is computationally and labour intensive and only a limited number are currently publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present nf-LO (nextflow-LiftOver), a containerised and scalable Nextflow pipeline that enables liftovers within and between any species for which assemblies are available. nf-LO will consequently facilitates data interpretation across a broad range of genomic studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445595" rel="alternate" title="nf-LO: A scalable, containerised workflow for genome-to-genome lift over (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445397</id><title>Self-Supervised Pretraining for Transferable Quantitative Phase Image Cell Segmentation (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.421186+00:00</updated><author><name>Tomas Vicar</name></author><author><name>Jiri Chmelik</name></author><author><name>Roman Jakubicek</name></author><author><name>Larisa Chmelikova</name></author><author><name>Jaromir Gumulec</name></author><author><name>Jan Balvan</name></author><author><name>Ivo Provaznik</name></author><author><name>Radim Kolar</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, U-Net-based method for robust adherent cell segmentation for quantitative phase microscopy image is designed and optimised. We designed and evaluated four specific post-processing pipelines. To increase the transferability to different cell types, non-deep learning transfer with adjustable parameters is used in the post-processing step. Additionally, we proposed a self-supervised pretraining technique using nonlabelled data, which is trained to reconstruct multiple image distortions and improved the segmentation performance by from 0.67 to 0.70 of Object-wise Intersection over Union. Moreover, we publish a new dataset of manually labelled images suitable for this task together with the unlabelled data for self-supervised pretraining.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Graphical Abstract&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="445397v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Highlights&lt;/title&gt;&lt;list list-type="bullet"&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four strategies for instance cell segmentation with U-Net were compared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specialised post-processing pipelines with tunable/optimizable parameters were designed for each segmentation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transferability to different cell types by optimisation of post-processing parameters was tested.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed self-supervised pretraining method improved both segmentation performance and transferability to different cell types.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;list-item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new manually labelled quantitative phase imaging dataset for cell segmentation with unlabelled data for self-supervised pretraining was created.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/list-item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445397" rel="alternate" title="Self-Supervised Pretraining for Transferable Quantitative Phase Image Cell Segmentation (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445658</id><title>Velodrome: Out-of-Distribution Generalization from Labeled and Unlabeled Gene Expression Data for Drug Response Prediction (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.421741+00:00</updated><author><name>Hossein Sharifi-Noghabi</name></author><author><name>Parsa Alamzadeh Harjandi</name></author><author><name>Olga Zolotareva</name></author><author><name>Colin C. Collins</name></author><author><name>Martin Ester</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Data discrepancy between preclinical and clinical datasets poses a major challenge for accurate drug response prediction based on gene expression data. Different methods of transfer learning have been proposed to address this data discrepancy. These methods generally use cell lines as source domains and patients, patient-derived xenografts, or other cell lines as target domains. However, they assume that they have access to the target domain during training or fine-tuning and they can only take labeled source domains as input. The former is a strong assumption that is not satisfied during deployment of these models in the clinic. The latter means these methods rely on labeled source domains which are of limited size. To avoid this assumption, we formulate drug response prediction as an out-of-distribution generalization problem which does not assume that the target domain is accessible during training. Moreover, to exploit unlabeled source domain data, which tends to be much more plentiful than labeled data, we adopt a semi-supervised approach. We propose Velodrome, a semi-supervised method of out-of-distribution generalization that takes labeled and unlabeled data from different resources as input and makes generalizable predictions. Velodrome achieves this goal by introducing an objective function that combines a supervised loss for accurate prediction, an alignment loss for generalization, and a consistency loss to incorporate unlabeled samples. Our experimental results demonstrate that Velodrome outperforms state-of-the-art pharmacogenomics and transfer learning baselines on cell lines, patient-derived xenografts, and patients and therefore, may guide precision oncology more accurately.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.25.445658" rel="alternate" title="Velodrome: Out-of-Distribution Generalization from Labeled and Unlabeled Gene Expression Data for Drug Response Prediction (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445360</id><title>CellMap: Characterizing the types and composition of iPSC-derived cells from RNA-seq data (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.422110+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhengyu Ouyang</name></author><author><name>Nathanael Bourgeois</name></author><author><name>Eugenia Lyashenko</name></author><author><name>Paige Cundiff</name></author><author><name>Patrick F. Cullen</name></author><author><name>Ravi Challa</name></author><author><name>Kejie Li</name></author><author><name>Xinmin Zhang</name></author><author><name>Fergal Casey</name></author><author><name>Sandi Engle</name></author><author><name>Baohong Zhang</name></author><author><name>Maria I. Zavodszky</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) derived cell types are increasingly employed as &lt;italic&gt;in vitro&lt;/italic&gt; model systems for drug discovery. For these studies to be meaningful, it is important to understand the reproducibility of the iPSC-derived cultures and their similarity to equivalent endogenous cell types. Single-cell and single-nucleus RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) are useful to gain such understanding, but they are expensive and time consuming, while bulk RNA-seq data can be generated quicker and at lower cost. &lt;italic&gt;In silico&lt;/italic&gt; cell type decomposition is an efficient, inexpensive, and convenient alternative that can leverage bulk RNA-seq to derive more fine-grained information about these cultures. We developed CellMap, a computational tool that derives cell type profiles from publicly available single-cell and single-nucleus datasets to infer cell types in bulk RNA-seq data from iPSC-derived cell lines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.445360" rel="alternate" title="CellMap: Characterizing the types and composition of iPSC-derived cells from RNA-seq data (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446070</id><title>Strategy for detecting off-target sites in genome-edited rice (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.422744+00:00</updated><author><name>Jumpei Narushima</name></author><author><name>Shinya Kimata</name></author><author><name>Yuh Shiwa</name></author><author><name>Takahiro Gondo</name></author><author><name>Satoru Akimoto</name></author><author><name>Keisuke Soga</name></author><author><name>Satoko Yoshiba</name></author><author><name>Kosuke Nakamura</name></author><author><name>Norihito Shibata</name></author><author><name>Kazunari Kondo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-editing using the CRISPR-Cas9 system can substantially accelerate crop breeding. Because off-target editing is the main problem with this system, a reliable method for comprehensively detecting off-target sites is required for the editing of food crop genomes. However, a method that accurately predicts off-target sites has not been established. In this study, we performed a SITE-Seq analysis to predict potential off-target sites. SITE-Seq is an unbiased method applicable for the in vitro detection of double-strand breaks (DSBs). To analyze SITE-Seq data, we developed a novel Galaxy system, which can perform simple and reproducible analyses without a command line operation. We conducted a SITE-Seq analysis of a rice genome modified by OsFH15 gRNA-Cas9, and identified 41 DSB sites in the annotated regions. Amplicon-sequencing revealed mutations at one off-target site in the genome-edited rice. The presence of an uncommon protospacer adjacent motif (NTG PAM) likely makes this off-target site difficult to identify using in silico methods. Of the six tested programs, only CRISPRdirect predicted this off-target site, but it also predicted 6,080 off-target sites in total. These results suggest the SITE-Seq method presented herein can efficiently predict off-target sites and is useful for assessing the safety of genome-edited food.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.28.446070" rel="alternate" title="Strategy for detecting off-target sites in genome-edited rice (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.444785</id><title>Automatic instance segmentation of mitochondria in electron microscopy data (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.423427+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke Nightingale</name></author><author><name>Joost de Folter</name></author><author><name>Helen Spiers</name></author><author><name>Amy Strange</name></author><author><name>Lucy M Collinson</name></author><author><name>Martin L Jones</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present a new method for rapid, automated, large-scale 3D mitochondria instance segmentation, developed in response to the ISBI 2021 MitoEM Challenge. In brief, we trained separate machine learning algorithms to predict (1) mitochondria areas and (2) mitochondria boundaries in image volumes acquired from both rat and human cortex with multi-beam scanning electron microscopy. The predictions from these algorithms were combined in a multi-step post-processing procedure, that resulted in high semantic and instance segmentation performance. All code is provided via a public repository.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.24.444785" rel="alternate" title="Automatic instance segmentation of mitochondria in electron microscopy data (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445915</id><title>Genetic Variation as a Long-Distance Modulator of RAD21 Expression in Humans (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.423906+00:00</updated><author><name>William Schierding</name></author><author><name>Julia A Horsfield</name></author><author><name>Justin M. O'Sullivan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutations and changes in expression in RAD21 are common across cancers types and outside of cancer can result in cohesinopathy. As such, exploration of variants that modify RAD21 enhancer activity, across the genome, may also provide insights into mechanisms by which distinct variants impact healthy human development and disease. We searched 42,953,834 genomic variants for a spatial-eQTL association with the transcription of RAD21. We identified 123 significant associations (FDR &amp;lt; 0.05), which are local (cis) or long-distance (trans) regulators of RAD21 expression. The 123 variants co-regulate a further seven genes, enriched for having Sp2 transcription factor binding sites in their promoter regions. The Sp2 transcription factor and six of the seven genes had previously been associated with cancer onset, progression, and metastasis. Our results suggest that genome-wide variation in non-coding regions impacts on RAD21 transcript levels in addition to other genes, which then could impact on oncogenesis and the process of ubiquitination. This identification of distant co-regulation of oncogenes represents a strategy for discovery of novel genetic regions which impact cancer onset and a potential for diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.445915" rel="alternate" title="Genetic Variation as a Long-Distance Modulator of RAD21 Expression in Humans (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.446060</id><title>RNA folding using quantum computers (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-05-31T08:45:04.424300+00:00</updated><author><name>Dillion M. Fox</name></author><author><name>Christopher M. MacDermaid</name></author><author><name>Andrea M. A. Schreij</name></author><author><name>Magdalena A. Zwierzyna</name></author><author><name>Ross C. Walker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The 3-dimensional fold of an RNA molecule is largely determined by patterns of intramolecular hydrogen bonds between bases. Predicting the hydrogen bonding network from the sequence, also referred to as RNA secondary structure prediction or RNA folding, is a nondeterministic polynomial-time (NP)-complete computational problem. The structure of the molecule is strongly predictive of its functions and biochemical properties, and therefore the ability to accurately predict the structure is a crucial tool for biochemists. Many methods have been proposed to efficiently sample possible secondary structure patterns. Classic approaches employ dynamic programming, and recent studies have explored approaches inspired by evolutionary algorithms. This work demonstrates leveraging quantum computing hardware to predict the secondary structure of RNA. A Hamiltonian written in the form of a Binary Quadratic Model (BQM) is derived to drive the system toward maximizing the number of base pairs while simultaneously maximizing the average length of the stems. An Adiabatic Quantum Computer (AQC) is compared to a Replica Exchange Monte Carlo (REMC) algorithm programmed with the same objective function, with the AQC being shown to be highly competitive at rapidly identifying low energy solutions. The method proposed in this study was compared to three algorithms from literature and was found to have the highest success rate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.27.446060" rel="alternate" title="RNA folding using quantum computers (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>