<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.108853+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459342</id><title>ELeFHAnt: A supervised machine learning approach for label harmonization and annotation of single cell RNA-seq data (59 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.109160+00:00</updated><author><name>Konrad Thorner</name></author><author><name>Aaron M. Zorn</name></author><author><name>Praneet Chaturvedi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Annotation of single cells has become an important step in the single cell analysis framework. With advances in sequencing technology thousands to millions of cells can be processed to understand the intricacies of the biological system in question. Annotation through manual curation of markers based on a priori knowledge is cumbersome given this exponential growth. There are currently ~200 computational tools available to help researchers automatically annotate single cells using supervised/unsupervised machine learning, cell type markers, or tissue-based markers from bulk RNA-seq. But with the expansion of publicly available data there is also a need for a tool which can help integrate multiple references into a unified atlas and understand how annotations between datasets compare. Here we present ELeFHAnt: &lt;italic&gt;Ensemble learning for harmonization and annotation of single cells&lt;/italic&gt;. ELeFHAnt is an easy-to-use R package that employs support vector machine and random forest algorithms together to perform three main functions: 1) &lt;italic&gt;CelltypeAnnotation&lt;/italic&gt; 2) &lt;italic&gt;LabelHarmonization&lt;/italic&gt; 3) &lt;italic&gt;DeduceRelationship&lt;/italic&gt;. &lt;italic&gt;CelltypeAnnotation&lt;/italic&gt; is a function to annotate cells in a query Seurat object using a reference Seurat object with annotated cell types. &lt;italic&gt;LabelHarmonization&lt;/italic&gt; can be utilized to integrate multiple cell atlases (references) into a unified cellular atlas with harmonized cell types. Finally, &lt;italic&gt;DeduceRelationship&lt;/italic&gt; is a function that compares cell types between two scRNA-seq datasets. ELeFHAnt can be accessed from GitHub at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/praneet1988/ELeFHAnt"&gt;https://github.com/praneet1988/ELeFHAnt&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459342" rel="alternate" title="ELeFHAnt: A supervised machine learning approach for label harmonization and annotation of single cell RNA-seq data (59 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459169</id><title>PHIST: fast and accurate prediction of prokaryotic hosts from metagenomic viral sequences (42 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.109375+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrzej Zielezinski</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Deorowicz</name></author><author><name>Adam Gudyś</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;PHIST (Phage-Host Interaction Search Tool) predicts prokaryotic hosts of viruses from their genomic sequences. It improves host prediction accuracy at species level over current alignment-based tools (on average by 3 percentage points) as well as alignment-free and CRISPR-based tools (by 14–20 percentage points). PHIST is also two orders of magnitude faster than alignment-based tools making it suitable for metagenomics studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GNU-licensed C++ code wrapped in Python API available at: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/refresh-bio/phist"&gt;https://github.com/refresh-bio/phist&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;andrzej.zielezinski@amu.edu.pl&lt;/email&gt;, &lt;email&gt;adam.gudys@polsl.pl&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at publisher Web site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459169" rel="alternate" title="PHIST: fast and accurate prediction of prokaryotic hosts from metagenomic viral sequences (42 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459728</id><title>MetaCoAG: Binning Metagenomic Contigs via Composition, Coverage and Assembly Graphs (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.109600+00:00</updated><author><name>Vijini Mallawaarachchi</name></author><author><name>Yu Lin</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Metagenomics binning has allowed us to study and characterize various genetic material of different species and gain insights into microbial communities. While existing binning tools bin metagenomics de novo assemblies, they do not make use of the assembly graphs that produce such assemblies. Here we propose MetaCoAG, a tool that utilizes assembly graphs with the composition and coverage information to bin metagenomic contigs. MetaCoAG uses single-copy marker genes to estimate the number of initial bins, assigns contigs into bins iteratively and adjusts the number of bins dynamically throughout the binning process. Experimental results on simulated and real datasets demonstrate that MetaCoAG significantly outperforms state-of-the-art binning tools, producing more high-quality bins than the second-best tool, with an average median F1-score of 88.40%. To the best of our knowledge, MetaCoAG is the first stand-alone binning tool to make direct use of the assembly graph information. MetaCoAG is available at https://github.com/Vini2/MetaCoAG.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459728" rel="alternate" title="MetaCoAG: Binning Metagenomic Contigs via Composition, Coverage and Assembly Graphs (29 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.458985</id><title>Spectrum graph-based de-novo sequencing algorithm MaxNovo achieves high peptide identification rates in collisional dissociation MS/MS spectra (29 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.109771+00:00</updated><author><name>Petra Gutenbrunner</name></author><author><name>Pelagia Kyriakidou</name></author><author><name>Frido Welker</name></author><author><name>Jürgen Cox</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We describe MaxNovo, a novel spectrum graph-based peptide de-novo sequencing algorithm integrated into the MaxQuant software. It identifies complete sequences of peptides as well as sequence tags that are incomplete at one or both of the peptide termini. MaxNovo searches for the highest-scoring path in a directed acyclic graph representing the MS/MS spectrum with peaks as nodes and edges as potential sequence constituents consisting of single amino acids or pairs. The raw score is a sum of node and edge weights, plus several reward scores, for instance, for complementary ions or protease compatibility. For search-engine identified peptides, it correlates well with the Andromeda search engine score. We use a particular score normalization and the score difference between the first and second-best solution to define a combined score that integrates all available information. To evaluate its performance, we use a human cell line dataset and take as ground truth all Andromeda-identified MS/MS spectra with an Andromeda score of at least 100. MaxNovo outperforms other software in particular in the high-sensitivity range of precision-coverage plots. We also identify incomplete sequence tags and study their statistical properties. Next, we apply MaxNovo to ion mobility-coupled time of flight data. Here we achieve excellent performance as well, except for potential swaps of the two amino acids closest to the C-terminus, which are not well resolved due to the low end of the mass range in MS/MS spectra in this dataset. We demonstrate the applicability of MaxNovo to palaeoproteomics samples with a Late Pleistocene hominin proteome dataset that was generated using three proteases. Interestingly, we did not use any machine learning in the construction of MaxNovo, but implemented expert domain knowledge directly in the definition of the score. Yet, it performs as good as or better than the leading deep learning-based algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.04.458985" rel="alternate" title="Spectrum graph-based de-novo sequencing algorithm MaxNovo achieves high peptide identification rates in collisional dissociation MS/MS spectra (29 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459270</id><title>Real age prediction from the transcriptome with RAPToR (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.110058+00:00</updated><author><name>Romain Bulteau</name></author><author><name>Mirko Francesconi</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Genome-wide gene expression profiling is a powerful tool for exploratory analyses, providing a high dimensional picture of the state of a biological system. However, uncontrolled variation among samples can obscure and confound the effect of variables of interest. Uncontrolled developmental variation is often a major source of unknown expression variation in developmental systems. Existing methods to sort samples from transcriptomes require many samples to infer developmental trajectories and only provide a relative pseudo-time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present RAPToR (&lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;R&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;eal &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;A&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;ge &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;P&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;rediction from &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;T&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;ranscriptome staging &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;o&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;n &lt;underline&gt;&lt;bold&gt;R&lt;/bold&gt;&lt;/underline&gt;eference), a simple computational method to estimate the absolute developmental age of even a single sample from its gene expression with up to minutes precision. We achieve this by staging samples on high-resolution reference developmental expression profiles we build from existing time series data. We implemented RAPToR for the most common animal model systems: nematode, fruit fly, zebrafish, and mouse, and demonstrate application for non-model organisms. We show how developmental variation discovered by RAPToR can be exploited to increase power to detect differential expression and to untangle the signal of perturbations of interest even when it is completely confounded with development. We anticipate our RAPToR post-profiling staging strategy will be especially useful in large scale single organism profiling because it eliminates the need for synchronization or for a tedious and potentially difficult step of accurate staging before profiling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459270" rel="alternate" title="Real age prediction from the transcriptome with RAPToR (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459763</id><title>clipplotr - a comparative visualisation and analysis tool for CLIP data (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.112076+00:00</updated><author><name>Anob M Chakrabarti</name></author><author><name>Charlotte Capitanchik</name></author><author><name>Jernej Ule</name></author><author><name>Nicholas Luscombe</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;CLIP technologies are now widely used to study RNA-protein interactions and many datasets are now publicly available. An important first step in CLIP data exploration is the visual inspection and assessment of processed genomic data on selected genes or regions and performing comparisons: either across conditions within a particular project, or incorporating publicly available data. However, the output files produced by data processing pipelines or preprocessed files available to download from data repositories are often not suitable for direct comparison and usually need further processing. Furthermore, to derive biological insight it is usually necessary to visualise CLIP signal alongside other data such as annotations, or orthogonal functional genomic data (e.g. RNA-seq). We have developed a simple, but powerful, command-line tool: clipplotr, which facilitates these visual comparative and integrative analyses with normalisation and smoothing options for CLIP data and the ability to show these alongside reference annotation tracks and functional genomic data. These data can be supplied as input to clipplotr in a range of file formats, which will output a publication quality figure. It is written in R and can both run on a laptop computer independently, or be integrated into computational workflows on a high-performance cluster. Releases, source code and documentation are freely available at: https://github.com/ulelab/clipplotr.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.10.459763" rel="alternate" title="clipplotr - a comparative visualisation and analysis tool for CLIP data (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459120</id><title>tascCODA: Bayesian tree-aggregated analysis of compositional amplicon and single-cell data (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.112966+00:00</updated><author><name>Johannes Ostner</name></author><author><name>Salomé Carcy</name></author><author><name>Christian L. Müller</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Accurate generative statistical modeling of count data is of critical relevance for the analysis of biological datasets from high-throughput sequencing technologies. Important instances include the modeling of microbiome compositions from amplicon sequencing surveys and the analysis of cell type compositions derived from single-cell RNA sequencing. Microbial and cell type abundance data share remarkably similar statistical features, including their inherent compositionality and a natural hierarchical ordering of the individual components from taxonomic or cell lineage tree information, respectively. To this end, we introduce a Bayesian model for &lt;bold&gt;t&lt;/bold&gt;ree-aggregated &lt;bold&gt;a&lt;/bold&gt;mplicon and &lt;bold&gt;s&lt;/bold&gt;ingle-&lt;bold&gt;c&lt;/bold&gt;ell &lt;bold&gt;co&lt;/bold&gt;mpositional &lt;bold&gt;d&lt;/bold&gt;ata &lt;bold&gt;a&lt;/bold&gt;nalysis (&lt;monospace&gt;tascCODA&lt;/monospace&gt;) that seamlessly integrates hierarchical information and experimental covariate data into the generative modeling of compositional count data. By combining latent parameters based on the tree structure with spike-and-slab Lasso penalization, &lt;monospace&gt;tascCODA&lt;/monospace&gt; can determine covariate effects across different levels of the population hierarchy in a data-driven parsimonious way. In the context of differential abundance testing, we validate &lt;monospace&gt;tascCODA&lt;/monospace&gt;’s excellent performance on a comprehensive set of synthetic benchmark scenarios. Our analyses on human single-cell RNA-seq data from ulcerative colitis patients and amplicon data from patients with irritable bowel syndrome, respectively, identified aggregated cell type and taxon compositional changes that were more predictive and parsimonious than those proposed by other schemes. We posit that tascCODA&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; constitutes a valuable addition to the growing statistical toolbox for generative modeling and analysis of compositional changes in microbial or cell population data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.06.459120" rel="alternate" title="tascCODA: Bayesian tree-aggregated analysis of compositional amplicon and single-cell data (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.452919</id><title>CardIAP: Calcium images analyzer web application (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.113694+00:00</updated><author><name>Ana Julia Velez Rueda</name></author><author><name>Agustín García Smith</name></author><author><name>Luis Alberto Gonano</name></author><author><name>Maria Silvina Fornasari</name></author><author><name>Gustavo Parisi</name></author><author><name>Leandro Matías Sommese</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ionic calcium (Ca2+) plays the role of the second messenger in eukaryotic cells associated with cellular functions of regulation of the cell cycle, such as transport, motility, gene expression, and metabolism (Permyakov and Kretsinger, 2009). The use of fluorometric techniques in isolated cells, loaded with Ca2+ sensitive fluorescent probes allows the quantitative measurement of dynamic events that occur in living, functioning cells. The Cardiomyocytes Images Analyzer Application (CardIAP) covers the need for tools to analyze and retrieve information from confocal microscopy images, in a systematic, accurate, and fast way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we present the CardIAP web app, an automated method for the identification of spatio-temporal patterns in a calcium fluorescence imaging sequence. Through this tool, users can analyze single or multiple Ca2+ transients from confocal line-scan images and obtain quantitative information on the dynamic response of the stimulated myocyte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our web application also allows the user the extraction of data on calcium dynamics in downloadable tables and plots, simplifying the calculation of the alternation and discordance indices and their classification. CardIAP could assist in studying the underlying mechanisms of anomalous calcium release phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;CardIAP is an open-source app, entirely developed in Python, which can be freely accessed and used at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cardiap.herokuapp.com/"&gt;http://cardiap.herokuapp.com/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.08.452919" rel="alternate" title="CardIAP: Calcium images analyzer web application (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459340</id><title>Atria: An Ultra-fast and Accurate Trimmer for Adapter and Quality Trimming (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.114079+00:00</updated><author><name>Jiacheng Chuan</name></author><author><name>Aiguo Zhou</name></author><author><name>Lawrence Richard Hale</name></author><author><name>Miao He</name></author><author><name>Xiang Li</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Next Generation Sequencing takes a dominant role in terms of output capacity and sequence length, adapters attached to the reads and low-quality bases hinder the performance of downstream analysis directly and implicitly, such as producing false-positive single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP), and generating fragmented assemblies. A fast trimming algorithm is in demand to remove adapters precisely, especially in read tails with relatively low quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Findings&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present a trimming program named Atria. Atria matches the adapters in paired reads and finds possible overlapped regions with a super-fast and carefully designed byte-based matching algorithm (&lt;italic&gt;O(n)&lt;/italic&gt; time with &lt;italic&gt;O(1)&lt;/italic&gt; space). Atria also implements multi-threading in both sequence processing and file compression and supports single-end reads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Atria performs favorably in various trimming and runtime benchmarks of both simulated and real data with other cutting-edge trimmers. We also provide an ultra-fast and lightweight byte-based matching algorithm. The algorithm can be used in a broad range of short-sequence matching applications, such as primer search and seed scanning before alignment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability &amp;amp; Implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Atria executables, source code, and benchmark scripts are available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cihga39871/Atria"&gt;https://github.com/cihga39871/Atria&lt;/ext-link&gt; under the MIT license.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459340" rel="alternate" title="Atria: An Ultra-fast and Accurate Trimmer for Adapter and Quality Trimming (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458844</id><title>Improve consensus partitioning via a hierarchical procedure (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-09-13T07:44:08.127200+00:00</updated><author><name>Zuguang Gu</name></author><author><name>Daniel Hübschmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Consensus partitioning is an unsupervised method widely used in high throughput data analysis for revealing subgroups and assigns stability for the classification. However, standard consensus partitioning procedures are weak to identify large numbers of stable subgroups. There are two main issues. 1. Subgroups with small differences are difficult to separate if they are simultaneously detected with subgroups with large differences. And 2. stability of classification generally decreases as the number of subgroups increases. In this work, we proposed a new strategy to solve these two issues by applying consensus partitionings in a hierarchical procedure. We demonstrated hierarchical consensus partitioning can be efficient to reveal more subgroups. We also tested the performance of hierarchical consensus partitioning on revealing a great number of subgroups with a DNA methylation dataset. The hierarchical consensus partitioning is implemented in the R package &lt;italic&gt;cola&lt;/italic&gt; with comprehensive functionality for analysis and visualizations. It can also automate the analysis only with a minimum of two lines of code, which generates a detailed HTML report containing the complete analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.03.458844" rel="alternate" title="Improve consensus partitioning via a hierarchical procedure (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>