<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.643811+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.17.452800</id><title>Causal inference using deep-learning variable selection identifies and incorporates direct and indirect causalities in complex biological systems (4 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.644577+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhenjiang Fan</name></author><author><name>Kate F Kernan</name></author><author><name>Panayiotis V Benos</name></author><author><name>Scott W Canna</name></author><author><name>Joseph A Carcillo</name></author><author><name>Soyeon Kim</name></author><author><name>Hyun Jung Park</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In complex diseases, causal structure learning across biological variables is critical to identify modifiable triggers or potential therapeutic agents. A limitation of existing causal learning methods is that they cannot identify indirect causal relations, those that would interact through latent mediating variables. We developed the first computational method that identifies both direct and indirect causalities, causal inference using deep-learning variable-selection (causalDeepVASE). To accurately identify indirect causalities and incorporate them with direct causalities, causalDeepVASE develops a deep neural network approach and extends a flexible causal inference method. In simulated and biological data of various contexts, causalDeepVASE outperforms existing methods in identifying expected or validated causal relations. Further, causalDeepVASE facilitates a systematic understanding of complex diseases. For example, causalDeepVASE uniquely identified a possible causal relation between IFNγ and creatinine suggested in a polymicrobial sepsis model. In future biomedical studies, causalDeepVASE can facilitate the identification of driver genes and therapeutic agents.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.17.452800" rel="alternate" title="Causal inference using deep-learning variable selection identifies and incorporates direct and indirect causalities in complex biological systems (4 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453379</id><title>AlphaPept, a modern and open framework for MS-based proteomics (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.645245+00:00</updated><author><name>Maximilian T Strauss</name></author><author><name>Isabell Bludau</name></author><author><name>Wen-Feng Zeng</name></author><author><name>Eugenia Voytik</name></author><author><name>Constantin Ammar</name></author><author><name>Julia Schessner</name></author><author><name>Rajesh Ilango</name></author><author><name>Michelle Gill</name></author><author><name>Florian Meier</name></author><author><name>Sander Willems</name></author><author><name>Matthias Mann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In common with other omics technologies, mass spectrometry (MS)-based proteomics produces ever-increasing amounts of raw data, making their efficient analysis a principal challenge. There is a plethora of different computational tools that process the raw MS data and derive peptide and protein identification and quantification. During the last decade, there has been dramatic progress in computer science and software engineering, including collaboration tools that have transformed research and industry. To leverage these advances, we developed AlphaPept, a Python-based open-source framework for efficient processing of large high-resolution MS data sets. Using Numba for just-in-time machine code compilation on CPU and GPU, we achieve hundred-fold speed improvements while maintaining clear syntax and rapid development speed. AlphaPept uses the Python scientific stack of highly optimized packages, reducing the code base to domain-specific tasks while providing access to the latest advances in machine learning. We provide an easy on-ramp for community validation and contributions through the concept of literate programming, implemented in Jupyter Notebooks of the different modules. A framework for continuous integration, testing, and benchmarking enforces solid software engineering principles. Large datasets can rapidly be processed as shown by the analysis of hundreds of cellular proteomes in minutes per file, many-fold faster than the data acquisiton. The AlphaPept framework can be used to build automated processing pipelines using efficient HDF5 based file formats, web-serving functionality and compatibility with downstream analysis tools. Easy access for end-users is provided by one-click installation of the graphical user interface, for advanced users via a modular Python library, and for developers via a fully open GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453379" rel="alternate" title="AlphaPept, a modern and open framework for MS-based proteomics (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453477</id><title>Generative Adversarial Network augmented the gut microbiome-based health index by profoundly improved discrimination power (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-07-26T19:57:11.645909+00:00</updated><author><name>Yuxue Li</name></author><author><name>Gang Xie</name></author><author><name>Yuguo Zha</name></author><author><name>Kang Ning</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Summary&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gut microbiome-based health index (GMHI) has been applied with success, while the discrimination powers of GMHI varied for different diseases, limiting its utility on a broad spectrum of diseases. In this work, a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) model is proposed to improve the discrimination power of GMHI. Built based on the batch corrected data through GAN (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI"&gt;https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI&lt;/ext-link&gt;), GAN-GMHI has largely reduced the batch effects, and profoundly improved the performance for distinguishing healthy individuals and different diseases. GAN-GMHI has provided results to support the strong association of gut microbiome and diseases, and indicated a more accurate venue towards microbiome-based disease monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAN-GMHI is publicly available on GitHub: &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI"&gt;https://github.com/HUST-NingKang-Lab/GAN-GMHI&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;ningkang@hust.edu.cn&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.07.23.453477" rel="alternate" title="Generative Adversarial Network augmented the gut microbiome-based health index by profoundly improved discrimination power (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>