<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.982587+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475279</id><title>Supervised dimensionality reduction for exploration of single-cell data by Hybrid Subset Selection - Linear Discriminant Analysis (45 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.983244+00:00</updated><author><name>Meelad Amouzgar</name></author><author><name>David R Glass</name></author><author><name>Reema Baskar</name></author><author><name>Inna Averbukh</name></author><author><name>Samuel C Kimmey</name></author><author><name>Albert G Tsai</name></author><author><name>Felix J Hartmann</name></author><author><name>Sean C Bendall</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell technologies generate large, high-dimensional datasets encompassing a diversity of omics. Dimensionality reduction enables visualization of data by representing cells in two-dimensional plots that capture the structure and heterogeneity of the original dataset. Visualizations contribute to human understanding of data and are useful for guiding both quantitative and qualitative analysis of cellular relationships. Existing algorithms are typically unsupervised, utilizing only measured features to generate manifolds, disregarding known biological labels such as cell type or experimental timepoint. Here, we repurpose the classification algorithm, linear discriminant analysis (LDA), for supervised dimensionality reduction of single-cell data. LDA identifies linear combinations of predictors that optimally separate a priori classes, enabling users to tailor visualizations to separate specific aspects of cellular heterogeneity. We implement feature selection by hybrid subset selection (HSS) and demonstrate that this flexible, computationally-efficient approach generates non-stochastic, interpretable axes amenable to diverse biological processes, such as differentiation over time and cell cycle. We benchmark HSS-LDA against several popular dimensionality reduction algorithms and illustrate its utility and versatility for exploration of single-cell mass cytometry, transcriptomics and chromatin accessibility data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475279" rel="alternate" title="Supervised dimensionality reduction for exploration of single-cell data by Hybrid Subset Selection - Linear Discriminant Analysis (45 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474883</id><title>SPITFIR(e): A supermaneuverable algorithm for restoring 2D-3D fluorescence images and videos, and background subtraction (16 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.983828+00:00</updated><author><name>Sylvain Prigent</name></author><author><name>Hoai-Nam Nguyen</name></author><author><name>Ludovic Leconte</name></author><author><name>Cesar Augusto Valades-Cruz</name></author><author><name>Bassam Hajj</name></author><author><name>Jean Salamero</name></author><author><name>Charles Kervrann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;While fluorescent microscopy imaging has become the spearhead of modern biology as it is able to generate long-term videos depicting 4D nanoscale cell behaviors, it is still limited  by the optical aberrations and the photon budget available in the specimen and to some extend to photo-toxicity. A direct consequence is the necessity to develop flexible and "off-road" algorithms in order to recover structural details and improve spatial resolution, which is critical when pushing the illumination to the low levels in order to limit photo-damages. Moreover, as the processing of very large temporal series of images considerably slows down the analysis, special attention must be paid to the feasibility and scalability of the developed restoration algorithms. To address these specifications, we present a very flexible method designed to restore 2D-3D+Time fluorescent images and subtract undesirable out-of-focus background. We assume that the images are sparse and piece-wise smooth, and are corrupted by mixed Poisson-Gaussian noise. To recover the unknown image, we consider a novel convex and non-quadratic regularizer Sparse Hessian Variation) defined as the mixed norms which gathers image intensity and spatial second-order derivatives. This resulting restoration algorithm named SPITFIR(e) (SParse fIT for Fluorescence Image Restoration) utilizes the primal-dual optimization principle for energy minimization and can be used to process large images acquired with varied fluorescence microscopy modalities. It is nearly parameter-free as the practitioner needs only to specify the amount of desired sparsity (weak, moderate, high).  Experimental results in lattice light sheet, stimulated emission depletion, multifocus microscopy, spinning disk confocal, and wide-field microscopy demonstrate the generic ability of the SPITFIR(e) algorithm to efficiently reduce noise and blur, and to subtract undesirable fluorescent background, while avoiding the emergence of deconvolution artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474883" rel="alternate" title="SPITFIR(e): A supermaneuverable algorithm for restoring 2D-3D fluorescence images and videos, and background subtraction (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475333</id><title>Comparing transmission reconstruction models with Mycobacterium tuberculosis whole genome sequence data (12 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.984356+00:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Sobkowiak</name></author><author><name>Kamila Romanowski</name></author><author><name>Inna Sekirov</name></author><author><name>Jennifer L Gardy</name></author><author><name>James Johnston</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Pathogen genomic epidemiology is now routinely used worldwide to interrogate infectious disease dynamics. Multiple computational tools that reconstruct transmission networks by coupling genomic data with epidemiological modelling have been developed. The resulting inferences are often used to inform outbreak investigations, yet to date, the performance of these transmission reconstruction tools has not been compared specifically for tuberculosis, a disease process with complex epidemiology that includes variable latency periods and within-host heterogeneity. Here, we carried out a systematic comparison of seven publicly available transmission reconstruction tools, evaluating their accuracy in predicting transmission events in both simulated and real-world &lt;italic&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/italic&gt; outbreaks. No tool was able to fully resolve transmission networks, though both the single-tree and multi-tree input implementations of TransPhylo identified the most epidemiologically supported transmission events and the fewest false positive links. We observed a high degree of variability in the transmission networks inferred by each approach. Our findings may inform the choice of tools in future tuberculosis transmission analyses and underscore the need for caution when interpreting transmission networks produced using probabilistic approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475333" rel="alternate" title="Comparing transmission reconstruction models with Mycobacterium tuberculosis whole genome sequence data (12 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474788</id><title>Unraveling membrane properties at the organelle-level with LipidDyn (11 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.984857+00:00</updated><author><name>Simone Scrima</name></author><author><name>Matteo Tiberti</name></author><author><name>Alessia Campo</name></author><author><name>Elisabeth Corcelle-Termeau</name></author><author><name>Delphine Judith</name></author><author><name>Mads Moller Foged</name></author><author><name>Knut Kristoffer Bundgaard Clemmens</name></author><author><name>Sharon Tooze</name></author><author><name>Marja Jäättelä</name></author><author><name>Kenji Maeda</name></author><author><name>Matteo Lambrughi</name></author><author><name>Elena Papaleo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cellular membranes are formed from many different lipids in various amounts and proportions depending on the subcellular localization. The lipid composition of membranes is sensitive to changes in the cellular environment, and their alterations are linked to several diseases, including cancer. Lipids not only form lipid-lipid interactions but also interact with other biomolecules, including proteins, profoundly impacting each other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations are a powerful tool to study the properties of cellular membranes and membrane-protein interactions on different timescales and at varying levels of resolution. Over the last few years, software and hardware for biomolecular simulations have been optimized to routinely run long simulations of large and complex biological systems. On the other hand, high-throughput techniques based on lipidomics provide accurate estimates of the composition of cellular membranes at the level of subcellular compartments. The community needs computational tools for lipidomics and simulation data effectively interacting to better understand how changes in lipid compositions impact membrane function and structure. Lipidomic data can be analyzed to design biologically relevant models of membranes for MD simulations. Similar applications easily result in a massive amount of simulation data where the bottleneck becomes the analysis of the data to understand how membrane properties and membrane-protein interactions are changing in the different conditions. In this context, we developed &lt;italic&gt;LipidDyn&lt;/italic&gt;, an &lt;italic&gt;in silico&lt;/italic&gt; pipeline to streamline the analyses of MD simulations of membranes of different compositions. Once the simulations are collected, &lt;italic&gt;LipidDyn&lt;/italic&gt; provides average properties and time series for several membrane properties such as area per lipid, thickness, diffusion motions, the density of lipid bilayers, and lipid enrichment/depletion. The calculations exploit parallelization and the pipelines include graphical outputs in a publication-ready form. We applied &lt;italic&gt;LipidDyn&lt;/italic&gt; to different case studies to illustrate its potential, including membranes from cellular compartments and transmembrane protein domains. &lt;italic&gt;LipidDyn&lt;/italic&gt; is implemented in Python and relies on opensource libraries. &lt;italic&gt;LipidDyn&lt;/italic&gt; is available free of charge under the GNU General Public License from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ELELAB/LipidDyn"&gt;https://github.com/ELELAB/LipidDyn&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474788" rel="alternate" title="Unraveling membrane properties at the organelle-level with LipidDyn (11 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474934</id><title>PDBspheres - a method for finding 3D similarities in local regions in proteins (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.985472+00:00</updated><author><name>Adam Zemla</name></author><author><name>Jonathan E. Allen</name></author><author><name>Dan Kirshner</name></author><author><name>Felice C. Lightstone</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present a structure-based method for finding and evaluating structural similarities in protein regions relevant to ligand binding. PDBspheres comprises an exhaustive library of protein structure regions (“spheres”) adjacent to complexed ligands derived from the Protein Data Bank (PDB), along with methods to find and evaluate structural matches between a protein of interest and spheres in the library. Currently, PDBspheres’ library contains more than 2 million spheres, organized to facilitate searches by sequence and/or structure similarity of protein-ligand binding sites or interfaces between interacting molecules. PDBspheres uses the LGA structure alignment algorithm as the main engine for detecting structure similarities between the protein of interest and library spheres. An all-atom structure similarity metric ensures that sidechain placement is taken into account in the PDBspheres’ primary assessment of confidence in structural matches. In this paper, we (1) describe the PDBspheres method, (2) demonstrate how PDBspheres can be used to detect and characterize binding sites in protein structures, (3) compare PDBspheres use for binding site prediction with seven other binding site prediction methods using a curated dataset of 2,528 ligand-bound and ligand-free crystal structures, and (4) use PDBspheres to cluster pockets and assess structural similarities among protein binding sites of the 4,876 structures in the “refined set” of PDBbind 2019 dataset. The PDBspheres library is made publicly available for download at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://proteinmodel.org/AS2TS/PDBspheres"&gt;https://proteinmodel.org/AS2TS/PDBspheres&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474934" rel="alternate" title="PDBspheres - a method for finding 3D similarities in local regions in proteins (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475090</id><title>Three million images and morphological profiles of cells treated with matched chemical and genetic perturbations (10 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.986158+00:00</updated><author><name>Srinivas Niranj Chandrasekaran</name></author><author><name>Beth A. Cimini</name></author><author><name>Amy Goodale</name></author><author><name>Lisa Miller</name></author><author><name>Maria Kost-Alimova</name></author><author><name>Nasim Jamali</name></author><author><name>John G Doench</name></author><author><name>Briana Fritchman</name></author><author><name>Adam Skepner</name></author><author><name>Michelle Melanson</name></author><author><name>John Arevalo</name></author><author><name>Juan C Caicedo</name></author><author><name>Daniel Kuhn</name></author><author><name>Desiree Hernandez</name></author><author><name>Jim Berstler</name></author><author><name>Hamdah Shafqat Abbasi</name></author><author><name>David E Root</name></author><author><name>Susanne E Swalley</name></author><author><name>Shantanu Singh</name></author><author><name>Anne E Carpenter</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;We present a new, carefully designed and well-annotated dataset of images and image-based profiles of cells that have been treated with chemical compounds and genetic perturbations. Each gene that is perturbed is a known target of at least two compounds in the dataset. The dataset can thus serve as a benchmark to evaluate methods for predicting similarities between compounds and between genes and compounds, measuring the effect size of a perturbation, and more generally, learning effective representations for measuring cellular state from microscopy images. Advancements in these applications can accelerate the development of new medicines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475090" rel="alternate" title="Three million images and morphological profiles of cells treated with matched chemical and genetic perturbations (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474935</id><title>ABRIDGE: An ultra-compression software for SAM alignment files (9 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.987014+00:00</updated><author><name>Sagnik Banerjee</name></author><author><name>Carson Andorf</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Advancement in technology has enabled sequencing machines to produce vast amounts of genetic data, causing an increase in storage demands. Most genomic software utilizes read alignments for several purposes including transcriptome assembly and gene count estimation. Herein we present, ABRIDGE, a state-of-the-art compressor for SAM alignment files offering users both lossless and lossy compression options. This reference-based file compressor achieves the best compression ratio among all compression software ensuring lower space demand and faster file transmission. Central to the software is a novel algorithm that retains non-redundant information. This new approach has allowed ABRIDGE to achieve a compression 16% higher than the second-best compressor for RNA-Seq reads and over 35% for DNA-Seq reads. ABRIDGE also offers users the option to randomly access location without having to decompress the entire file. ABRIDGE is distributed under MIT license and can be obtained from GitHub (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/sagnikbanerjee15/Abridge"&gt;https://github.com/sagnikbanerjee15/Abridge&lt;/ext-link&gt;) and docker hub. We anticipate that the user community will adopt ABRIDGE within their existing pipeline encouraging further research in this domain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.04.474935" rel="alternate" title="ABRIDGE: An ultra-compression software for SAM alignment files (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475257</id><title>GraphChainer: Co-linear Chaining for Accurate Alignment of Long Reads to Variation Graphs (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.987364+00:00</updated><author><name>Jun Ma</name></author><author><name>Manuel Cáceres</name></author><author><name>Leena Salmela</name></author><author><name>Veli Mäkinen</name></author><author><name>Alexandru I. Tomescu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Aligning reads to a variation graph is a standard task in pangenomics, with downstream applications in e.g., improving variant calling. While the vg toolkit (Garrison et al., Nature Biotechnology, 2018) is a popular aligner of short reads, GraphAligner (Rautiainen and Marschall, Genome Biology, 2020) is the state-of-the-art aligner of long reads. GraphAligner works by finding candidate read occurrences based on individually extending the best seeds of the read in the variation graph. However, a more principled approach recognized in the community is to co-linearly chain multiple seeds. We present a new algorithm to co-linearly chain a set of seeds in an acyclic variation graph, together with the first efficient implementation of such a co-linear chaining algorithm into a new aligner of long reads to variation graphs, GraphChainer. Compared to GraphAligner, at a normalized edit distance threshold of 40%, it aligns 9% to 12% more reads, and 15% to 19% more total read length, on real PacBio reads from human chromosomes 1 and 22. On both simulated and real data, GraphChainer aligns between 97% and 99% of all reads, and of total read length. At the more stringent normalized edit distance threshold of 30%, GraphChainer aligns up to 29% more total real read length than GraphAligner.
GraphChainer is freely available at https://github.com/algbio/GraphChainer&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475257" rel="alternate" title="GraphChainer: Co-linear Chaining for Accurate Alignment of Long Reads to Variation Graphs (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475205</id><title>Joint copy number and mutation phylogeny reconstruction from single-cell amplicon sequencing data (8 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.987646+00:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Sollier</name></author><author><name>Jack Kuipers</name></author><author><name>Niko Beerenwinkel</name></author><author><name>Koichi Takahashi</name></author><author><name>Katharina Jahn</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Reconstructing the history of somatic DNA alterations that occurred in a tumour can help understand its evolution and predict its resistance to treatment. Single-cell DNA sequencing (scDNAseq) can be used to investigate clonal heterogeneity and to inform phylogeny reconstruction. However, existing phylogenetic methods for scDNAseq data are designed either for point mutations or for large copy number variations, but not for both types of events simultaneously. Here, we develop COMPASS, a computational method for inferring the joint phylogeny of mutations and copy number alterations from targeted scDNAseq data. We evaluate COMPASS on simulated data and show that it outperforms existing methods. We apply COMPASS to a large cohort of 123 patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) and detect copy number alterations, including subclonal ones, which are in agreement with current knowledge of AML development. We further used bulk SNP array data to orthogonally validate or findings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475205" rel="alternate" title="Joint copy number and mutation phylogeny reconstruction from single-cell amplicon sequencing data (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475194</id><title>Genome-wide SNPs of vegetable leafminer, Liriomyza sativae: insights into the recent Australian invasion (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.987878+00:00</updated><author><name>Xuefen Xu</name></author><author><name>Tom L. Schmidt</name></author><author><name>Jiaxin Liang</name></author><author><name>Peter M. Ridland</name></author><author><name>Jessica Chung</name></author><author><name>Qiong Yang</name></author><author><name>Moshe Jasper</name></author><author><name>Paul A. Umina</name></author><author><name>Ary A. Hoffmann</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Liriomyza sativae&lt;/italic&gt;, the vegetable leafminer, is a serious agricultural pest originally from the Americas which has now colonized all continents except Antarctica. In 2015, &lt;italic&gt;L. sativae&lt;/italic&gt; arrived on the Australian mainland and established on the Cape York Peninsula in the northeast of the country. Here, we assessed genetic variation in &lt;italic&gt;L. sativae&lt;/italic&gt; based on genome-wide single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) generated by double-digest restriction-site associated DNA sequencing (ddRAD-seq) to uncover the potential origin(s) of this pest in Australia and contribute to reconstructing its global invasion history. Our principal component analyses (PCA) results suggested that Australian mainland populations were genetically close to populations from the Torres Strait and had connections to Bali and Papua New Guinea (PNG), whereas populations from Asia and Africa were more distantly related. Hawaii was genetically distinct from populations from Asia, Africa and Australia. Co-ancestry analyses pointed to signals of gene flow from the Torres Strait into the Australian mainland, while Indonesia/PNG were the likely sources of the initial invasion into the Torres Strait. Admixture analyses further revealed that &lt;italic&gt;L. sativae&lt;/italic&gt; from the Torres Strait had genetic diversity originating from multiple sources, which has now spread to the Australian mainland. The &lt;italic&gt;L. sativae&lt;/italic&gt; lineages from Asia/Africa appear closely related and may share co-ancestry. Isolation by distance (IBD) was found at a broad global scale, but not within small regions, suggesting human-mediated factors contribute to the local spread of this pest. Overall, our findings highlight the challenges in quarantine measures aimed at restricting the distribution of this global pest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475194" rel="alternate" title="Genome-wide SNPs of vegetable leafminer, Liriomyza sativae: insights into the recent Australian invasion (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475215</id><title>A Computational Method to Dissect Colonization Resistance of the Gut Microbiota against Pathogens (7 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.988157+00:00</updated><author><name>Shanlin Ke</name></author><author><name>Yandong Xiao</name></author><author><name>Scott T. Weiss</name></author><author><name>Xinhua Chen</name></author><author><name>Ciaran P. Kelly</name></author><author><name>Yang-Yu Liu</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The indigenous gut microbes have co-evolved with their hosts for millions of years. Those gut microbes play a crucial role in host health and disease. In particular, they protect the host against incursion by exogenous and often harmful microorganisms, a mechanism known as colonization resistance (CR). Yet, identifying the exact microbes responsible for the gut microbiota-mediated CR against a particular pathogen remains a fundamental challenge in microbiome research. Here, we develop a computational method --- Generalized Microbe-Phenotype Triangulation (GMPT) to systematically identify causal microbes that directly influence the microbiota-mediated CR against a pathogen. We systematically validate GMPT using a classical population dynamics model in community ecology, and then apply it to microbiome data from two mouse studies on C. difficile infection. The developed method will not only significantly advance our understanding of CR mechanisms but also pave the way for the rational design of microbiome-based therapies for preventing and treating enteric infections.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.06.475215" rel="alternate" title="A Computational Method to Dissect Colonization Resistance of the Gut Microbiota against Pathogens (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475154</id><title>GFAP: ultra-fast and accurate gene functional annotation software for plants (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.988415+00:00</updated><author><name>Dong Xu</name></author><author><name>Kangming Jin</name></author><author><name>Heling Jiang</name></author><author><name>Desheng Gong</name></author><author><name>Jinbao Yang</name></author><author><name>Wenjuan Yu</name></author><author><name>Yingxue Yang</name></author><author><name>Jihong Li</name></author><author><name>Weihua Pan</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sequence alignment is the basis of gene functional annotation for unknow sequences. Selecting closely related species as the reference species should be an effective way to improve the accuracy of gene annotation for plants, compared with only based on one or some model plants. Therefore, limited species number in previous software or website is disadvantageous for plant gene annotation. Here, we collected the protein sequences of 236 plant species with known genomic information from 63 families. After that, these sequences were annotated by pfam, Gene Ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) databases to construct our databases. Furthermore, we developed the software, Gene Annotation Software for Plants (GFAP), to perform gene annotation using our databases. GFAP, an open-source software running on Windows and MacOS systems, is an efficient and network independent tool. GFAP can search the protein domain, GO and KEGG information for 43000 genes within 4 minutes. In addition, GFAP can also perform the sequence alignment, statistical analysis and drawing. The website of https://gitee.com/simon198912167815/gfap-database provides the software, databases, testing data and video tutorials for users. GFAP contained large amount of plant-species information. We believe that it will become a powerful tool in gene annotation using closely related species for phytologists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.05.475154" rel="alternate" title="GFAP: ultra-fast and accurate gene functional annotation software for plants (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474134</id><title>EchinoDB: An update to the web-based application for genomic and transcriptomic data on echinoderms (6 tweets)</title><updated>2022-01-10T07:43:01.988784+00:00</updated><author><name>Varnika Mittal</name></author><author><name>Robert W. Reid</name></author><author><name>Denis Jacob Machado</name></author><author><name>Vladimir Mashanov</name></author><author><name>Daniel A. Janies</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Here we release a new version of EchinoDB (&lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://echinodb.uncc.edu"&gt;https://echinodb.uncc.edu&lt;/ext-link&gt;). EchinoDB is a database of genomic and transcriptomic data on echinoderms. The initial database consisted of groups of 749,397 orthologous and paralogous transcripts arranged in orthoclusters by sequence similarity. The new version of EchinoDB includes RNA-seq data of the brittle star &lt;italic&gt;Ophioderma brevispinum&lt;/italic&gt; and high-quality genomic assembly data of the green sea urchin &lt;italic&gt;Lytechinus variegatus&lt;/italic&gt;. In addition, we enabled keyword searches for annotated data and installed an updated version of Sequenceserver to allow BLAST searches. The data are downloadable in FASTA format. The first version of EchinoDB appeared in 2016 and was implemented in GO on a local server. The new version has been updated using R Shiny to include new features and improvements in the application. Furthermore, EchinoDB now runs entirely in the cloud for increased reliability and scaling. EchinoDB enjoys a user base drawn from the fields of phylogenetics, developmental biology, genomics, physiology, neurobiology, and regeneration. As use cases, we illustrate how EchinoDB is used in discovering pathways and gene regulatory networks involved in the tissue regeneration process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.03.474134" rel="alternate" title="EchinoDB: An update to the web-based application for genomic and transcriptomic data on echinoderms (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>