<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.979093+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463725</id><title>Mutagenesis-visualization: analysis of site saturation mutagenesis datasets in Python (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.982667+00:00</updated><author><name>Frank Hidalgo</name></author><author><name>Sage Templeton</name></author><author><name>Che Olavaria Gallegos</name></author><author><name>Joanne Wang</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Site saturation mutagenesis (SSM) experiments have been transformative in our study of protein function. Despite the rich data generated from such experiments, current tools for processing, analyzing, and visualizing the data offer only a limited set of static plots that are difficult to customize. Furthermore, usage of the tools requires extensive experience and programming. This slows the research process for those in the biological field who are unfamiliar with programming. Here, we introduce mutagenesis-visualization, a Python API for the creation of publication quality figures for SSM datasets which requires no prior Python or statistics experience. The plots can be rendered as native matplotlib objects (easy to stylize) or as Plotly objects (interactive graphs). Additionally, the software offers the possibility to visualize the datasets on Pymol. Availability and implementation: The software can be installed from PyPI or GitHub using the pip package manager and is compatible with Python ≥ 3.8. The documentation can be found at readthedocs and the source code can be found on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.08.463725" rel="alternate" title="Mutagenesis-visualization: analysis of site saturation mutagenesis datasets in Python (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.462574</id><title>Deep learning-based tumor microenvironment segmentation is predictive of tumor mutations and patient survival in non-small-cell lung cancer (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.983165+00:00</updated><author><name>Łukasz Rączkowski</name></author><author><name>Iwona Paśnik</name></author><author><name>Michał Kukiełka</name></author><author><name>Marcin Nicoś</name></author><author><name>Magdalena A Budzinska</name></author><author><name>Tomasz Kucharczyk</name></author><author><name>Justyna Szumiło</name></author><author><name>Paweł Krawczyk</name></author><author><name>Nicola Crosetto</name></author><author><name>Ewa Szczurek</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that tumor microenvironment (TME) and gene mutations are the main determinants of progression of the deadliest cancer in the world - lung cancer - their interrelations are not well understood. Digital pathology data provide a unique insight into the spatial composition of the TME. Here, we generated 23,199 image patches from 55 hematoxylin-and-eosin (H&amp;amp;E)-stained lung cancer tissue sections and annotated them into 9 different tissue classes. Using this dataset, we trained a deep neural network and used it to segment 467 lung cancer H&amp;amp;E images downloaded from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) database. We used the segmented images to compute human interpretable features reflecting the heterogeneous composition of the TME, and successfully utilized them to predict patient survival (c-index 0.723) and cancer gene mutations (largest AUC 73.5% for PDGFRB). Our approach can be generalized to different cancer types to inform precision medicine strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.09.462574" rel="alternate" title="Deep learning-based tumor microenvironment segmentation is predictive of tumor mutations and patient survival in non-small-cell lung cancer (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.462986</id><title>Stochastic variational variable selection for high-dimensional microbiome data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-10-11T10:10:02.987009+00:00</updated><author><name>Tung Dang</name></author><author><name>Kie Kumaishi</name></author><author><name>Erika Usui</name></author><author><name>Shungo Kobori</name></author><author><name>Takumi Sato</name></author><author><name>Yusuke Toda</name></author><author><name>Yuji Yamasaki</name></author><author><name>Hisashi Tsujimoto</name></author><author><name>Yasunori Ichihashi</name></author><author><name>Hiroyoshi Iwata</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Background&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rapid and accurate identification of a minimal-size core set of representative microbial species plays an important role in the clustering of microbial community data and interpretation of the clustering results. However, the huge dimensionality of microbial metagenomics data sets is a major challenge for the existing methods such as Dirichlet multinomial mixture (DMM) models. In the framework of the existing methods, computational burdens for identifying a small number of representative species from a huge number of observed species remain a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We proposed a novel framework to improve the performance of the widely used DMM approach by combining three ideas: (i) We extended the finite DMM model to the infinite case, via the consideration of Dirichlet process mixtures and estimate the number of clusters as a random variables. (ii) We proposed an indicator variable to identify representative operational taxonomic units that substantially contribute to the differentiation among clusters. (iii) To address the computational burdens of the high-dimensional microbiome data, we proposed are a stochastic variational inference, which approximates the posterior distribution using a controllable distribution called variational distribution, and stochastic optimization algorithms for fast computation. With the proposed method named stochastic variational variable selection (SVVS), we analyzed the root microbiome data collected in our soybean field experiment and the human gut microbiome data from three published data sets of large-scale case-control studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Conclusions&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;SVVS demonstrated a better performance and significantly faster computation than existing methods in all cases of testing data sets. In particular, SVVS is the only method that can analyze the massive high-dimensional microbial data with above 50,000 microbial species and 1,000 samples. Furthermore, it was suggested that microbial species selected as a core set played important roles in the recent microbiome studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.10.04.462986" rel="alternate" title="Stochastic variational variable selection for high-dimensional microbiome data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>