<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.856915+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456196</id><title>Over 1000 tools reveal trends in the single-cell RNA-seq analysis landscape (63 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.857381+00:00</updated><author><name>Luke Zappia</name></author><author><name>Fabian J Theis</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Recent years have seen a revolution in single-cell technologies, particularly single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq). As the number, size and complexity of scRNA-seq datasets continue to increase, so does the number of computational methods and software tools for extracting meaning from them. Since 2016 the scRNA-tools database has catalogued software tools for analysing scRNA-seq data. With the number of tools in the database passing 1000, we take this opportunity to provide an update on the state of the project and the field. Analysis of five years of analysis tool tracking data clearly shows the evolution of the field, and that the focus of developers has moved from ordering cells on continuous trajectories to integrating multiple samples and making use of reference datasets. We also find evidence that open science practices reward developers with increased recognition and help accelerate the field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.13.456196" rel="alternate" title="Over 1000 tools reveal trends in the single-cell RNA-seq analysis landscape (63 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456127</id><title>The Molecular Subtyping Resource (MouSR): a user-friendly tool for rapid biological discovery from human or mouse transcriptional data (35 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.857626+00:00</updated><author><name>Baharak Ahmaderaghi</name></author><author><name>Raheleh Amirkhah</name></author><author><name>James Jackson</name></author><author><name>Tamsin RM Lannagan</name></author><author><name>Kathryn Gilroy</name></author><author><name>Sudhir B Malla</name></author><author><name>Keara L Redmond</name></author><author><name>Tim Maughan</name></author><author><name>Simon Leedham</name></author><author><name>Andrew S Campbell</name></author><author><name>Owen J Sansom</name></author><author><name>Mark Lawler</name></author><author><name>Philip D Dunne</name></author><author><name> </name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Generation of transcriptional data has dramatically increased in the last decade, driving the development of analytical algorithms that enable interrogation of the biology underpinning the profiled samples. However, these resources require users to have expertise in data wrangling and analytics, reducing opportunities for biological discovery by “wet-lab” users with a limited programming skillset. Although commercial solutions exist, costs for software access can be prohibitive for academic research groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To address these challenges, we have developed an open source and user-friendly data analysis platform for on-the-fly bioinformatic interrogation of transcriptional data derived from human or mouse tissue, called “MouSR”. This internet-accessible analytical tool, &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mousr.qub.ac.uk/"&gt;https://mousr.qub.ac.uk/&lt;/ext-link&gt;, enables users to easily interrogate their data using an intuitive “point and click” interface, which includes a suite of molecular characterisation options including QC, differential gene expression, gene set enrichment and microenvironmental cell population analyses from RNA-Seq. Users are provided with adjustable options for analysis parameters to generate results that can be saved as publication-quality images. To highlight its ability to perform high quality data analysis, we utilise the MouSR tool to interrogate our recently published tumour dataset, derived from genetically engineered mouse models and matched organoids, where we rapidly reproduced the key transcriptional findings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MouSR online tool provides a unique freely-available option for users to perform rapid transcriptomic analyses and comprehensive interrogation of the signalling underpinning transcriptional datasets, which alleviates a major bottleneck for biological discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456127" rel="alternate" title="The Molecular Subtyping Resource (MouSR): a user-friendly tool for rapid biological discovery from human or mouse transcriptional data (35 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456144</id><title>Applying Machine Learning to Classify the Origins of Gene Duplications (19 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.857865+00:00</updated><author><name>Michael T.W. McKibben</name></author><author><name>Michael S. Barker</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Nearly all lineages of land plants have experienced at least one whole genome duplication (WGD) in their history. The legacy of these ancient WGDs is still observable in the diploidized genomes of extant plants. Genes originating from WGD-paleologs-can be maintained in diploidized genomes for millions of years. These paleologs have the potential to shape plant evolution through sub- and neofunctionalization, increased genetic diversity, and reciprocal gene loss among lineages. Current methods for classifying paleologs often rely on only a subset of potential genomic features, have varying levels of accuracy, and often require significant data and/or computational time. Here we developed a supervised machine learning approach to classify paleologs from a target WGD in diploidized genomes across a broad range of different duplication histories. We collected empirical data on syntenic block sizes and other genomic features from 27 plant species each with a different history of paleopolyploidy. Features from these genomes were used to develop simulations of syntenic blocks and paleologs to train a gradient boosted decision tree. Using this approach, Frackify (Fractionation Classify), we were able to accurately identify and classify paleologs across a broad range of parameter space, including cases with multiple overlapping WGDs. We then compared Frackify with other paleolog inference approaches in six species with paleotetraploid and paleohexaploid ancestries. Frackify provides a way to combine multiple genomic features to quickly classify paleologs while providing a high degree of consistency with existing approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456144" rel="alternate" title="Applying Machine Learning to Classify the Origins of Gene Duplications (19 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456081</id><title>MetaProFi: A protein-based Bloom filter for storing and querying sequence data for accurate identification of functionally relevant genetic variants (14 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.858005+00:00</updated><author><name>Sanjay Kumar Srikakulam</name></author><author><name>Sebastian Keller</name></author><author><name>Fawaz Dabbaghie</name></author><author><name>Robert Bals</name></author><author><name>Olga V. Kalinina</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Technological advances of next-generation sequencing present new computational challenges to develop methods to store and query these data in time- and memory-efficient ways. We present MetaProFi (https://github.com/kalininalab/metaprofi), a Bloom filter-based tool that, in addition to supporting nucleotide sequences, can for the first time directly store and query amino acid sequences and translated nucleotide sequences, thus bringing sequence comparison to a more biologically relevant protein level. Owing to the properties of Bloom filters, it has a zero false-negative rate, allows for exact and inexact searches, and leverages disk storage and Zstandard compression to achieve high time and space efficiency. We demonstrate the utility of MetaProFi by indexing UniProtKB datasets at organism- and at sequence-level in addition to the indexing of Tara Oceans dataset and the 2585 human RNA-seq experiments, showing that MetaProFi consumes far less disk space than state-of-the-art-tools while also improving performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456081" rel="alternate" title="MetaProFi: A protein-based Bloom filter for storing and querying sequence data for accurate identification of functionally relevant genetic variants (14 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455589</id><title>Optimizing Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) using Machine Learning (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.858157+00:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas J. Cordaro</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Kavran</name></author><author><name>Michael Smallegan</name></author><author><name>Megan Palacio</name></author><author><name>Nickolaus Lammer</name></author><author><name>Tyler S. Brant</name></author><author><name>Vanessa DuMont</name></author><author><name>Naiara Doherty Garcia</name></author><author><name>Suzannah Miller</name></author><author><name>Tara Jourabchi</name></author><author><name>Sara L. Sawyer</name></author><author><name>Aaron Clauset</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Despite substantial standardization, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) experiments frequently fail. Troubleshooting failed PCRs can be costly in both time and money. Using a crowdsourced data set spanning 290 real PCRs from six active research laboratories, we investigate the degree to which PCR success rates can be improved by machine learning. While human designed PCRs succeed at a rate of 55-64%, we find that a machine learning model can accurately predict reaction outcome 81% of the time. We validate this level of improvement by then using the model to guide the design and predict the outcome of 39 new PCR experiments. In addition to improving outcomes, the model identifies 15 features of PCRs that researchers did not optimize well compared to the learned model. These results suggest that PCR success rates can easily be improved by 17-26%, potentially saving millions of dollars and thousands of hours of researcher time each year across the scientific community. Other common laboratory methods may benefit from similar data-driven optimization effort.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455589" rel="alternate" title="Optimizing Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) using Machine Learning (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455694</id><title>LoFTK: a framework for fully automated calculation of predicted Loss-of-Function variants (9 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.858347+00:00</updated><author><name>A. Alasiri</name></author><author><name>K. J. Karczewski</name></author><author><name>B. Cole</name></author><author><name>B. Loza</name></author><author><name>J. H. Moore</name></author><author><name>S. W. van der Laan</name></author><author><name>F. W. Asselbergs</name></author><author><name>B. J. Keating</name></author><author><name>J. van Setten</name></author><content>&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Motivation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loss-of-Function (LoF) variants in human genes are important due to their impact on clinical phenotypes and frequent occurrence in the genomes of healthy individuals. Current approaches predict high-confidence LoF variants without identifying the specific genes or the number of copies they affect. Moreover, there is a lack of methods for detecting knockout genes caused by compound heterozygous (CH) LoF variants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Results&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have developed the Loss-of-Function ToolKit (LoFTK), which allows efficient and automated prediction of LoF variants from both genotyped and sequenced genomes. LoFTK enables the identification of genes that are inactive in one or two copies and provides summary statistics for downstream analyses. LoFTK can identify CH LoF variants, which result in LoF genes with two copies lost. Using data from parents and offspring we show that 96% of CH LoF genes predicted by LoFTK in the offspring have the respective alleles donated by each parent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Availability and implementation&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;LoFTK is an open source software and is freely available to non-commercial users at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/CirculatoryHealth/LoFTK"&gt;https://github.com/CirculatoryHealth/LoFTK&lt;/ext-link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Contact&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;email&gt;j.vansetten@umcutrecht.nl&lt;/email&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Supplementary information&lt;/title&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at &lt;italic&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/italic&gt; online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455694" rel="alternate" title="LoFTK: a framework for fully automated calculation of predicted Loss-of-Function variants (9 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455997</id><title>Sciviewer enables interactive visual interrogation of single-cell RNA-Seq data from the Python programming environment (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.858521+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan Kotliar</name></author><author><name>Andres Colubri</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Visualizing two-dimensional (2D) embeddings (e.g. UMAP or tSNE) is a key step in interrogating single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-Seq) data. Subsequently, users typically iterate between programmatic analyses (e.g. clustering and differential expression) and visual  exploration (e.g. coloring cells by interesting features) to uncover biological signals in the data. Interactive tools exist to facilitate visual exploration of embeddings such as performing differential expression on user-selected cells. However, the practical utility of existing tools is limited because they do not support rapid movement of data and results to and from the programming environments where the bulk of data analysis takes place, interrupting the iterative process. Here, we present the Single-cell Interactive Viewer (Sciviewer), a tool that overcomes this limitation by allowing interactive visual interrogation of embeddings from within Python. Beyond differential expression analysis of user-selected cells, Sciviewer implements a novel method to identify genes varying locally along any user-specified direction on the embedding. Sciviewer enables rapid and flexible iteration between interactive and programmatic modes of scRNA-Seq exploration, illustrating a useful approach for analyzing high-dimensional data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.455997" rel="alternate" title="Sciviewer enables interactive visual interrogation of single-cell RNA-Seq data from the Python programming environment (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455803</id><title>Pout2Prot: an efficient tool to create protein (sub)groups from Percolator output files (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.858689+00:00</updated><author><name>Tim Van Den Bossche</name></author><author><name>Kay Schallert</name></author><author><name>Pieter Verschaffelt</name></author><author><name>Bart Mesuere</name></author><author><name>Dirk Benndorf</name></author><author><name>Lennart Martens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;The protein inference problem is complicated in metaproteomics due to the presence of homologous proteins from closely related species. Nevertheless, this process is vital to assign taxonomy and functions to identified proteins of microbial species, a task for which specialized tools such as Prophane have been developed. We here present &lt;italic&gt;Pout2Prot&lt;/italic&gt;, which takes Percolator Output (.pout) files from multiple experiments and creates protein (sub)group output files (.tsv) that can be used directly with Prophane. &lt;italic&gt;Pout2Prot&lt;/italic&gt; offers different grouping strategies, allows distinction between sample categories and replicates for multiple files, and uses a weighted spectral count for protein (sub)groups to reflect (sub)group abundance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;Pout2Prot&lt;/italic&gt; is available as a web application at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pout2prot.ugent.be"&gt;https://pout2prot.ugent.be&lt;/ext-link&gt; and is installable via pip as a standalone command line tool and reusable software library. All code is open source under the Apache License 2.0 and is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/compomics/pout2prot"&gt;https://github.com/compomics/pout2prot&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;sec&gt;&lt;title&gt;Logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;fig id="ufig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"&gt;&lt;graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="455803v1_ufig1" position="float" orientation="portrait" /&gt;&lt;/fig&gt;&lt;/sec&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455803" rel="alternate" title="Pout2Prot: an efficient tool to create protein (sub)groups from Percolator output files (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456006</id><title>Position-dependent Codon Usage Bias in the Human Transcriptome (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.858931+00:00</updated><author><name>Kaavya Subramanian</name></author><author><name>Nathan Waugh</name></author><author><name>Cole Shanks</name></author><author><name>David A Hendrix</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;All life depends on the reliable translation of RNA to protein according to complex interactions between translation machinery and RNA sequence features. While ribosomal occupancy and codon frequencies vary across coding regions, well-established metrics for computing coding potential of RNA do not capture such positional dependence. Here, we investigate &lt;italic&gt;position-dependent codon usage bias (PDCUB)&lt;/italic&gt;, which dynamically accounts for the position of protein-coding signals embedded within coding regions. We demonstrate the existence of PDCUB in the human transcriptome, and show that it can be used to predict translation-initiating codons with greater accuracy than other models. We further show that observed PDCUB is not accounted for by other common metrics, including position-dependent GC content, consensus sequences, and the presence of signal peptides in the translation product. More importantly, PDCUB defines a spectrum of translational efficiency supported by ribosomal occupancy and tRNA adaptation index (tAI). High PDCUB scores correspond to a tAI-defined translational ramp and low ribosomal occupancy, while low PDCUB scores exhibit a translational valley and the highest ribosomal occupancy. Finally, we examine the relationship between PDCUB intensity and functional enrichment. We find that transcripts with start codons showing the highest PDCUB are enriched for functions relating to the regulation of synaptic signaling and plasticity, as well as skeletal, heart, and nervous-system development. Furthermore, transcripts with high PDCUB are depleted for functions related to immune response and detection of chemical stimulus. These findings lay important groundwork for advances in our understanding of the regulation of translation, the calculation of coding potential, and the classification of RNA transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456006" rel="alternate" title="Position-dependent Codon Usage Bias in the Human Transcriptome (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456038</id><title>MetaLogo: a generator and aligner for multiple sequence logos (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.859218+00:00</updated><author><name>Yaowen Chen</name></author><author><name>Zhen He</name></author><author><name>Yahui Men</name></author><author><name>Guohua Dong</name></author><author><name>Shuofeng Hu</name></author><author><name>Xiaomin Ying</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Sequence logos are used to visually display sequence conservations and variations. They can indicate the fixed patterns or conserved motifs in a batch of DNA or protein sequences. However, most of the popular sequence logo generators can only draw logos for sequences of the same length, let alone for groups of sequences with different characteristics besides lengths. To solve these problems, we developed MetaLogo, which can draw sequence logos for sequences of different lengths or from different groups in one single plot and align multiple logos to highlight the sequence pattern dynamics across groups, thus allowing users to investigate functional motifs in a more delicate and dynamic perspective. We provide users a public MetaLogo web server (http://metalogo.omicsnet.org), a standalone Python package (https://github.com/labomics/MetaLogo), and also a built-in web server available for local deployment. Using MetaLogo, users can draw informative, customized, aesthetic, and publishable sequence logos without any programming experience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456038" rel="alternate" title="MetaLogo: a generator and aligner for multiple sequence logos (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455616</id><title>OTUs clustering should be avoided for defining oral microbiome (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.859471+00:00</updated><author><name>Alba Regueira-Iglesias</name></author><author><name>Lara Vazquez-Gonzalez</name></author><author><name>Carlos Balsa-Castro</name></author><author><name>Triana Blanco-Pintos</name></author><author><name>Victor Manuel Arce</name></author><author><name>Maria Jose Carreira</name></author><author><name>Inmaculada Tomas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This in silico investigation aimed to: 1) evaluate a set of primer pairs with high coverage, including those most commonly used in the literature, to find the different oral species with 16S rRNA gene amplicon similarity/identity (ASI) values ≥97%; and 2) identify oral species that may be erroneously clustered in the same operational taxonomic unit (OTU) and ascertain whether they belong to distinct genera or other higher taxonomic ranks.
Thirty-nine primer pairs were employed to obtain amplicon sequence variants (ASVs) from the complete genomes of 186 bacterial and 135 archaeal species. For each primer, ASVs without mismatches were aligned using BLASTN and their similarity values were obtained. Finally, we selected ASVs from different species with an ASI value ≥97% that were covered 100% by the query sequences. For each primer, the percentage of species-level coverage with no ASI≥97% (SC-NASI≥97%) was calculated.
Based on the SC-NASI≥97% values, the best primer pairs were OP_F053-KP_R020 for bacteria (65.05%), KP_F018-KP_R002 for archaea (51.11%), and OP_F114-KP_R031 for bacteria and archaea together (52.02%). Eighty percent of the oral-bacteria and oral-archaea species shared an ASI≥97% with at least one other taxa, including Campylobacter, Rothia, Streptococcus, and Tannerella, which played conflicting roles in the oral microbiota. Moreover, around a quarter and a third of these two-by-two similarity relationships were between species from different bacteria and archaea genera, respectively. Furthermore, even taxa from distinct families, orders, and classes could be grouped in the same cluster. 
Consequently, irrespective of the primer pair used, OTUs constructed with a 97% similarity provide an inaccurate description of oral-bacterial and oral-archaeal species, greatly affecting microbial diversity parameters. As a result, clustering by OTUs impacts the credibility of the associations between some oral species and certain health and disease conditions. This limits significantly the comparability of the microbial diversity findings reported in oral microbiome literature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455616" rel="alternate" title="OTUs clustering should be avoided for defining oral microbiome (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.14.456366</id><title>Scoring Protein Sequence Alignments Using Deep Learning (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.859653+00:00</updated><author><name>Bikash Shrestha</name></author><author><name>Badri Adhikari</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Background: A high-quality sequence alignment (SA) is the most important input feature for accurate protein structure prediction. For a protein sequence, there are many methods to generate a SA. However, when given a choice of more than one SA for a protein sequence, there are no methods to predict which SA may lead to more accurate models without actually building the models. In this work, we describe a method to predict the quality of a protein's SA. Methods: We created our own dataset by generating a variety of SAs for a set of 1,351 representative proteins and investigated various deep learning architectures to predict the local distance difference test (lDDT) scores of distance maps predicted with SAs as the input. These lDDT scores serve as indicators of the quality of the SAs. Results: Using two independent test datasets consisting of CASP13 and CASP14 targets, we show that our method is effective for scoring and ranking SAs when a pool of SAs is available for a protein sequence. With an example, we further discuss that SA selection using our method can lead to improved structure prediction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.14.456366" rel="alternate" title="Scoring Protein Sequence Alignments Using Deep Learning (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455982</id><title>Refining Bulk Segregant Analyses: Ontology-Mediated Discovery of Flowering Time Genes in Brassica oleracea (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.859852+00:00</updated><author><name>Rutger A. Vos</name></author><author><name>Carin A. M. van der Veen-van Wijk</name></author><author><name>M. Eric Schranz</name></author><author><name>Klaas Vrieling</name></author><author><name>Peter G. L. Klinkhamer</name></author><author><name>Frederic Lens</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Bulk segregant analysis (BSA) can help identify quantitative trait loci (QTLs), but this may result in substantial bycatch of functionally irrelevant genes. Here we develop a Gene Ontology-mediated approach to zoom in on specific markers implicated in flowering time from among QTLs identified by BSA of the giant woody Jersey kale phenotyped in four bulks of flowering onset.

Our BSA yielded tens of thousands of candidate genes. We reduced this by two orders of magnitude by focusing on genes annotated with terms contained within relevant subgraphs of the Gene Ontology. A further enrichment test led to the pathway for circadian rhythm in plants. The genes that enriched this pathway are attested from previous research as regulating flowering time. Some of these genes were also identified as having functionally significant variation compared to Arabidopsis.

We validated and confirmed our ontology-mediated results through a more targeted, homology-based approach. However, our ontology-mediated approach produced additional genes of putative importance, showing that the approach aids in exploration and discovery. We view our method as potentially applicable to the study of other complex traits and therefore make our workflows available as open-source code and a reusable Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.455982" rel="alternate" title="Refining Bulk Segregant Analyses: Ontology-Mediated Discovery of Flowering Time Genes in Brassica oleracea (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456153</id><title>Distinguishing and employing sister species of fish in assessment of stream quality (6 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.860071+00:00</updated><author><name>Fred Van Dyke</name></author><author><name>Benjamin W. van Ee</name></author><author><name>Seth Harju</name></author><author><name>Joshua W. Budi</name></author><author><name>Thomas B. Sokolowski</name></author><author><name>Brian Keas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Biological indicators (bioindicators) can be individual species or species groups used to assess habitat quality. Unfortunately, conservationists often lack information on species distribution, how to differentiate between similar species, and environmental conditions associated with the presence of a species. We addressed these problems using two “sister” species of fish, the Mottled Sculpin (&lt;italic&gt;Cottus bairdii&lt;/italic&gt;) and the Slimy Sculpin (&lt;italic&gt;Cottus cognatus&lt;/italic&gt;), as stream quality indicators in the Manistee River watershed in the Huron-Manistee National Forests in Michigan, USA. We determined the abundance and distribution of these species and related their presence to concurrent in-stream measurements of temperature, dissolved oxygen, pH, conductivity, turbidity, and stream quality score based on macroinvertebrate diversity. To be certain of identification, we sequenced the Cytochrome c Oxidase Subunit I (CO1) molecular marker for specimens and used it as a DNA barcode to determine a specimen’s species. Cladistic analyses of CO1 unambiguously supported recognition of Mottled Sculpin and Slimy Sculpin as distinct species, confirming initial 87.5% correct identification using morphological characteristics, with uncertainty limited to juvenile fish. Field determinations increased to 100% correct identification as investigators gained more experience. Both species were most abundant in headwater regions, decreased downstream, and were sympatric at several locations. Mottled Sculpin were more likely to be found at stream locations with lower conductivity, pH, and stream quality scores, whereas Slimy Sculpin presence was more strongly associated higher levels of DO and lower levels of turbidity. Such findings are important because Mottled Sculpin are a designated management indicator species of the US Forest Service in the Huron-Manistee National Forests, but may be ineffective as a habitat quality indicator when used alone. Concurrent use of Mottled Sculpin and Slimy Sculpin as a management indicator sister-species complex could allow sufficient landscape coverage to permit habitat assessment if species-specific differences in environmental tolerances are precisely determined.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456153" rel="alternate" title="Distinguishing and employing sister species of fish in assessment of stream quality (6 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455609</id><title>A Systematic Comparison of Differential Analysis Methods for CyTOF Data (5 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.860236+00:00</updated><author><name>Lis Arend</name></author><author><name>Judith Bernett</name></author><author><name>Quirin Manz</name></author><author><name>Melissa Klug</name></author><author><name>Olga Lazareva</name></author><author><name>Jan Baumbach</name></author><author><name>Dario Bongiovanni</name></author><author><name>Markus List</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Cytometry techniques are widely used to discover cellular characteristics at single-cell resolution. Many data analysis methods for cytometry data focus solely on identifying subpopulations via clustering and testing for differential cell abundance. For differential expression analysis of markers between conditions, only few tools exist. These tools either reduce the data distribution to medians, discarding valuable information, or have underlying assumptions that may not hold for all expression patterns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we systematically evaluated existing and novel approaches for differential expression analysis on real and simulated CyTOF data. We found that methods using median marker expressions compute fast and reliable results when the data is not strongly zero-inflated. Methods using all data detect changes in strongly zero-inflated markers, but partially suffer from overprediction or cannot handle big datasets. We present a new method, CyEMD, based on calculating the Earth Mover’s Distance between expression distributions that can handle strong zero-inflation without being too sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we developed CYANUS, a user-friendly R Shiny App allowing the user to analyze cytometry data with state-of-the-art tools, including well-performing methods from our comparison. A public web interface is available at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://exbio.wzw.tum.de/cyanus/"&gt;https://exbio.wzw.tum.de/cyanus/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.09.455609" rel="alternate" title="A Systematic Comparison of Differential Analysis Methods for CyTOF Data (5 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456096</id><title>A practical framework RNMF for the potential mechanism of cancer progression with the analysis of genes cumulative contribution abundance (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.860409+00:00</updated><author><name>Zhenzhang Li</name></author><author><name>Haihua Liang</name></author><author><name>Shaoan Zhang</name></author><author><name>Wen Luo</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Mutational signatures can reveal the mechanism of tumorigenesis. We developed the RNMF software for mutational signatures analysis, including a key model of cumulative contribution abundance (CCA) which was designed to highlight the association between genes and mutational signatures. Applied it to 1073 esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC) and found that APOBEC signatures (SBS2* and SBS13*) mediated the occurrence of PIK3CA E545k mutation. Furthermore, we found that age signature is strongly linked to the TP53 R342* mutation. In addition, the CCA matrix image data of genes in the signatures New, SBS3* and SBS17b* were helpful for the preliminary evaluation of shortened survival outcome. In a word, RNMF can successfully achieve the correlation analysis of genes and mutational signatures, proving a strong theoretical basis for the study of tumor occurrence and development mechanism and clinical adjuvant medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.12.456096" rel="alternate" title="A practical framework RNMF for the potential mechanism of cancer progression with the analysis of genes cumulative contribution abundance (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456002</id><title>Data and Diversity Driven Development of a Shotgun Crystallisation Screen using the Protein Data Bank (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.860595+00:00</updated><author><name>Gabriel Abrahams</name></author><author><name>Janet Newman</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Protein crystallisation has for decades been a critical and restrictive step in macro-molecular structure determination via X-ray diffraction. Crystallisation typically involves a multi-stage exploration of the available chemical space, beginning with an initial sampling (screening) followed by iterative refinement (optimisation). Effective screening is important for reducing the number of optimisation rounds required, reducing the cost and time required to determine a structure. Here, we propose an initial screen (Shotgun II) derived from analysis of the up-to-date Protein Data Bank (PDB) and compare it with the previously derived (2014) Shotgun I screen. In an update to that analysis, we clarify that the Shotgun approach entails finding the crystallisation conditions which cover the most diverse space of proteins by sequence found in the PDB - which can be mapped to the well known Maximum Coverage problem in computer science. With this realisation we are able to apply a more effective algorithm for selecting conditions, such that the Shotgun II screen outperforms the Shotgun I screen both in protein coverage and quantity of data input. Our data demonstrates that the Shotgun I screen, compared with alternatives, has been remarkably successful over the seven years it has been in use, indicating that Shotgun II is likely to be a highly effective screen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.11.456002" rel="alternate" title="Data and Diversity Driven Development of a Shotgun Crystallisation Screen using the Protein Data Bank (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455835</id><title>"Devil's stairs", Poisson's Statistics, and Patient Sorting via Variabilities for Oxygenation: All from Arterial Blood Gas Data (3 tweets)</title><updated>2021-08-16T11:16:22.860830+00:00</updated><author><name>Gennady P. Chuiko</name></author><author><name>Yevhen S. Darnapuk</name></author><author><name>Olga V. Dvornik</name></author><author><name>Yaroslav M. Krainyk</name></author><author><name>Olga M. Yaremchuk</name></author><author><name>Anastasiia Diadenko</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;This report deals with arterial oxygen saturation (SaO2) for healthy adults. A comparably small data set (20 persons) holds 3-minute records of SaO2. The sample rate was 200 Hz. The charts have the looks of a "devil's stairs." A few (from 1 to 10) detectable oxygenation levels form the stair's treads, more or less long. "The risers" have two types (up and down), and all have virtually the same height, about 1 %. The inter-level shifts  ( 0 to 42 switches per record) turned out a rare event at the actual sample rate. The number of switchings meets the Poisson distribution. There were found three visibly varied intensities for the switch-overs within the data set. Histograms also show the co-existing of no fewer than three subsets into the data set. The subsets differ by the intensity of switch-overs, amounts of possible levels, relative frequencies of most probable levels (modes), etcetera. In short, those all are diverse variability quantifiers. The higher variability subset has about 25 %, the lower one - 45%.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.455835" rel="alternate" title="&quot;Devil's stairs&quot;, Poisson's Statistics, and Patient Sorting via Variabilities for Oxygenation: All from Arterial Blood Gas Data (3 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>