<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>https://front-matter.io/</id><title>Popular BioRxiv bioinformatics preprints posted in the last week</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.693830+00:00</updated><author><name>Martin Fenner</name><email>martin@front-matter.io</email></author><link href="https://front-matter.io" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://front-matter.io/bioinformatics/feed.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446934</id><title>eggNOG-mapper v2: Functional Annotation, Orthology Assignments, and Domain Prediction at the Metagenomic Scale (64 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.694212+00:00</updated><author><name>Carlos P. Cantalapiedra</name></author><author><name>Ana Hernández-Plaza</name></author><author><name>Ivica Letunic</name></author><author><name>Peer Bork</name></author><author><name>Jaime Huerta-Cepas</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Even though automated functional annotation of genes represents a fundamental step in most genomic and metagenomic workflows, it remains challenging at large scales. Here, we describe a major upgrade to eggNOG-mapper, a tool for functional annotation based on precomputed orthology assignments, now optimized for vast (meta)genomic data sets. Improvements in version 2 include a full update of both the genomes and functional databases to those from eggNOG v5, as well as several efficiency enhancements and new features. Most notably, eggNOG-mapper v2 now allows: (i) de novo gene prediction from raw contigs, (ii) built-in pairwise orthology prediction, (iii) fast protein domain discovery, and (iv) automated GFF decoration. eggNOG-mapper v2 is available as a standalone tool or as an online service at &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://eggnog-mapper.embl.de"&gt;http://eggnog-mapper.embl.de&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.03.446934" rel="alternate" title="eggNOG-mapper v2: Functional Annotation, Orthology Assignments, and Domain Prediction at the Metagenomic Scale (64 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.02.446710</id><title>Tatajuba ― Exploring the distribution of homopolymer tracts (33 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.694534+00:00</updated><author><name>Leonardo de Oliveira Martins</name></author><author><name>Samuel Bloomfield</name></author><author><name>Emily Stoakes</name></author><author><name>Andrew Grant</name></author><author><name>Andrew J. Page</name></author><author><name>Alison E. Mather</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Length variation of homopolymeric tracts, which induces phase variation, is known to regulate gene expression leading to phenotypic variation in a wide range of bacterial species. There is no specialised bioinformatics software which can, at scale, exhaustively explore and describe these features from sequencing data. Identifying these is non-trivial as sequencing and bioinformatics methods are prone to introducing artefacts when presented with homopolymeric tracts due to the decreased base diversity. We present tatajuba, which can automatically identify potential homopolymeric tracts and their putative phenotypic impact, allowing for rapid investigation. We use it to detect all tracts in two separate datasets, one of &lt;italic&gt;Campylobacter jejuni&lt;/italic&gt; and one of three &lt;italic&gt;Bordetella&lt;/italic&gt; species, and to highlight those tracts that are polymorphic across samples. With this we confirm homopolymer tract variation with phenotypic impact found in previous studies and additionally find many more with potential variability. The software is written in C and is available under the open source license GNU GPL version 3 from &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/quadram-institute-bioscience/tatajuba"&gt;https://github.com/quadram-institute-bioscience/tatajuba&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.02.446710" rel="alternate" title="Tatajuba ― Exploring the distribution of homopolymer tracts (33 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446559</id><title>AltumAge: A Pan-Tissue DNA-Methylation Epigenetic Clock Based on Deep Learning (16 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.694805+00:00</updated><author><name>Lucas Paulo de Lima Camillo</name></author><author><name>Louis R Lapierre</name></author><author><name>Ritambhara Singh</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Several age predictors based on DNA methylation, dubbed epigenetic clocks, have been created in recent years. Their accuracy and potential for generalization vary widely based on the training data. Here, we gathered 143 publicly available data sets from several human tissues to develop AltumAge, a highly accurate and precise age predictor based on deep learning. Compared to Horvath’s 2013 model, AltumAge performs better across both normal and malignant tissues and is more generalizable to new data sets. Interestingly, it can predict gestational week from placental tissue with low error. Lastly, we used deep learning interpretation methods to learn which methylation sites contributed to the final model predictions. We observed that while most important CpG sites are linearly related to age, some highly-interacting CpG sites can influence the relevance of such relationships. We studied the associated genes of these CpG sites and found literary evidence of their involvement in age-related gene regulation. Using chromatin annotations, we observed that the CpG sites with the highest contribution to the model predictions were related to heterochromatin and gene regulatory regions in the genome. We also found age-related KEGG pathways for genes containing these CpG sites. In general, neural networks are better predictors due to their ability to capture complex feature interactions compared to the typically used regularized linear regression. Altogether, our neural network approach provides significant improvement and flexibility to current epigenetic clocks without sacrificing model interpretability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446559" rel="alternate" title="AltumAge: A Pan-Tissue DNA-Methylation Epigenetic Clock Based on Deep Learning (16 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446540</id><title>Signal-based optical map alignment (10 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.694992+00:00</updated><author><name>Mehmet Akdel</name></author><author><name>Henri van de Geest</name></author><author><name>Elio Schijlen</name></author><author><name>Irma M.H. van Rijswijck</name></author><author><name>Eddy J. Smid</name></author><author><name>Gabino Sanchez-Perez</name></author><author><name>Dick de Ridder</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;In genomics, optical mapping technology provides long-range contiguity information to improve genome sequence assemblies and detect structural variation. Originally a laborious manual process, Bionano Genomics platforms now offer high-throughput, automated optical mapping based on chips packed with nanochannels through which unwound DNA is guided and the fluorescent DNA backbone and specific restriction sites are recorded. Although the raw image data obtained is of high quality, the processing and assembly software accompanying the platforms is closed source and does not seem to make full use of data, labeling approximately half of the measured signals as unusable. Here we introduce two new software tools, independent of Bionano Genomics software, to extract and process molecules from raw images (OptiScan) and to perform molecule-to-molecule and molecule-to-reference alignments using a novel signal-based approach (OptiMap). We demonstrate that the molecules detected by OptiScan can yield better assemblies, and that the approach taken by OptiMap results in higher use of molecules from the raw data. These tools lay the foundation for a suite of open-source methods to process and analyze high-throughput optical mapping data. The Python implementations of the OptiTools are publicly available through &lt;ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bif.wur.nl/"&gt;http://www.bif.wur.nl/&lt;/ext-link&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446540" rel="alternate" title="Signal-based optical map alignment (10 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446382</id><title>Micro-Meta App: an interactive software tool to facilitate the collection of microscopy metadata based on community-driven specifications (8 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.695318+00:00</updated><author><name>Alex Rigano</name></author><author><name>Shannon Ehmsen</name></author><author><name>Serkan Utku Ozturk</name></author><author><name>Joel Ryan</name></author><author><name>Alexander Balashov</name></author><author><name>Mathias Hammer</name></author><author><name>Koray Kirli</name></author><author><name>Karl Bellve</name></author><author><name>Ulrike Boehm</name></author><author><name>Claire M. Brown</name></author><author><name>James J. Chambers</name></author><author><name>Robert A. Coleman</name></author><author><name>Andrea Cosolo</name></author><author><name>Orestis Faklaris</name></author><author><name>Kevin Fogarty</name></author><author><name>Thomas Guilbert</name></author><author><name>Anna B. Hamacher</name></author><author><name>Michelle S. Itano</name></author><author><name>Daniel P. Keeley</name></author><author><name>Susanne Kunis</name></author><author><name>Judith Lacoste</name></author><author><name>Alex Laude</name></author><author><name>Willa Ma</name></author><author><name>Marco Marcello</name></author><author><name>Paula Montero-Llopis</name></author><author><name>Glyn Nelson</name></author><author><name>Roland Nitschke</name></author><author><name>Jaime A. Pimentel</name></author><author><name>Stefanie Weidtkamp-Peters</name></author><author><name>Peter J. Park</name></author><author><name>Burak Alver</name></author><author><name>David Grunwald</name></author><author><name>Caterina Strambio-De-Castillia</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;For the information content of microscopy images to be appropriately interpreted, reproduced, and meet FAIR (Findable Accessible Interoperable and Reusable) principles, they should be accompanied by detailed descriptions of microscope hardware, image acquisition settings, image pixel and dimensional structure, and instrument performance. Nonetheless, the thorough documentation of imaging experiments is significantly impaired by the lack of community-sanctioned easy-to-use software tools to facilitate the extraction and collection of relevant microscopy metadata. Here we present &lt;bold&gt;Micro-Meta App&lt;/bold&gt;, an intuitive open-source software designed to tackle these issues that was developed in the context of nascent global bioimaging community organizations, including &lt;bold&gt;B&lt;/bold&gt;io&lt;bold&gt;I&lt;/bold&gt;maging &lt;bold&gt;N&lt;/bold&gt;orth &lt;bold&gt;A&lt;/bold&gt;merica (BINA) and &lt;bold&gt;QUA&lt;/bold&gt;lity Assessment and &lt;bold&gt;REP&lt;/bold&gt;roducibility in &lt;bold&gt;Li&lt;/bold&gt;ght &lt;bold&gt;Mi&lt;/bold&gt;croscopy (QUAREP-LiMi), whose goal is to improve reproducibility, data quality and sharing value for imaging experiments. The App provides a user-friendly interface for building comprehensive descriptions of the conditions utilized to produce individual microscopy datasets as specified by the recently proposed 4DN-BINA-OME tiered-system of Microscopy Metadata model. To achieve this goal the App provides a visual guide for a microscope-user to: 1) interactively build diagrammatic representations of hardware configurations of given microscopes that can be easily reused and shared with colleagues needing to document similar instruments. 2) Automatically extracts relevant metadata from image files and facilitates the collection of missing image acquisition settings and calibration metrics associated with a given experiment. 3) Output all collected Microscopy Metadata to interoperable files that can be used for documenting imaging experiments and shared with the community. In addition to significantly lowering the burden of quality assurance, the visual nature of Micro-Meta App makes it particularly suited for training users that have limited knowledge of the intricacies of light microscopy experiments. To ensure wide-adoption by microscope-users with different needs Micro-Meta App closely interoperates with &lt;bold&gt;MethodsJ2&lt;/bold&gt; and &lt;bold&gt;OMERO.mde&lt;/bold&gt;, two complementary tools described in parallel manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446382" rel="alternate" title="Micro-Meta App: an interactive software tool to facilitate the collection of microscopy metadata based on community-driven specifications (8 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446671</id><title>Identifying strengths and weaknesses of methods for computational network inference from single cell RNA-seq data (7 tweets)</title><updated>2021-06-07T06:25:57.695940+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Stone</name></author><author><name>Sunnie Grace McCalla</name></author><author><name>Alireza Fotuhi Siahpirani</name></author><author><name>Viswesh Periyasamy</name></author><author><name>Junha Shin</name></author><author><name>Sushmita Roy</name></author><content>&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) offers unparalleled insight into the transcriptional programs of different cellular states by measuring the transcriptome of thousands individual cells. An emerging problem in the analysis of scRNA-seq is the inference of transcriptional gene regulatory networks and a number of methods with different learning frameworks have been developed. Here we present a expanded benchmarking study of eleven recent network inference methods on six published single-cell RNA-sequencing datasets in human, mouse, and yeast considering different types of gold standard networks and evaluation metrics. We evaluate methods based on their computing requirements as well as on their ability to recover the network structure. We find that while no method is a universal winner and most methods have a modest recovery of experimentally derived interactions based on global metrics such as AUPR, methods are able to capture targets of regulators that are relevant to the system under study. Based on overall performance we grouped the methods into three main categories and found a combination of information-theoretic and regression-based methods to have a generally high performance. We also evaluate the utility of imputation for gene regulatory network inference and find that a small number of methods benefit from imputation, which further depends upon the dataset. Finally, comparisons to inferred networks for comparable bulk conditions showed that networks inferred from scRNA-seq datasets are often better or at par to those from bulk suggesting that scRNA-seq datasets can be a cost-effective way for gene regulatory network inference. Our analysis should be beneficial in selecting algorithms for performing network inference but also argues for improved methods and better gold standards for accurate assessment of regulatory network inference methods for mammalian systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.01.446671" rel="alternate" title="Identifying strengths and weaknesses of methods for computational network inference from single cell RNA-seq data (7 tweets)"/><category term="Bioinformatics"/><published>2021-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published></entry></feed>